ANDREW HUBERMAN: Welcome
to the Huberman Lab podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor
of neurobiology
and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today we are
discussing happiness.
We're going to discuss
the science of happiness,
because indeed, there are
excellent laboratories that
have worked for many decades
to try and understand
what is this thing
that we call happiness
and what brings us happiness
in the short and long term.
In fact, we could probably
point to happiness
as one of the most sought-after
states or commodities,
or emotions.
Whatever you want to
call it, happiness
is what many people are seeking
in work, in relationships,
and in general.
And yet most of us can't
really define exactly what
happiness is or means for us.
We can point to
certain experiences,
we can try and describe our
states of mind and body,
but most people recognize
the feeling when we have it,
and we certainly recognize the
feeling of not being happy.
Whether or not that means
simply not being happy
as the absence of happiness
or all-out depression.
Now one of the key problems in
trying to understand happiness
and, indeed, the science
and psychology of happiness
is that it does indeed
involve other similar things.
Things like joy, and
gratitude, and meaning.
And indeed, many scientists
and psychologists
have argued for
many, many decades
about what happiness really is.
Now we can come up with
so-called operational
definitions of happiness.
Operational definitions are
basically agreed-upon terms
or agreed-upon
definitions and conditions
that will define something
such as happiness.
Much in the same way
that we can all probably
come up with an operational
definition of milk.
But of course, milk can be
cow's milk, it can be oat milk,
it can be soy milk,
et cetera, et cetera.
So too, something
like happiness can
be micro-divided and sliced
and diced into as many things
as we decide.
Today we are really going to
focus on three main things.
First, we are going to define
happiness as a brain state
and as a state of mind and body.
We're going to take a look at
what the science says about all
of that.
Second, we are going to talk
about tools and practices
for placing ourselves
into states of happiness.
And while for most of
us, we think of happiness
as something that only arrives
through the acquisition
of some goal or some thing
external to us, and of course,
that is true.
There is also something
called synthetic happiness
or synthesized happiness
which turns out
to be at least as powerful and
perhaps even more powerful.
Now I'll just say
right off the bat
that I'm not going to tell
you that all you have to do
is sit in a chair and
imagine being happy
in order to feel happy.
Synthesize happiness actually
involves some very concrete
steps that have been defined by
excellent labs in psychology,
so we're going to talk
about synthesize happiness
as it relates to what you can
do to obtain happy states more
readily or more frequently.
And then, third, we're
going to talk about some
of the misconceptions or what
I would call the contradictions
of happiness research.
And what I mean by
that is most of you
have probably heard about
the general conditions
for obtaining happiness.
And they always
seem to circle back
to some of the same basic
features of get great sleep,
have great social connection,
pursue meaning, don't focus
to any overextend on
things like pursuing money
because there are indeed
these studies that
show that the amount of
money that people make
does not necessarily scale
directly with happiness.
We'll talk about those studies
in some detail a little bit
later.
And while all of
that literature is
very powerful and
informative, there
is what I see as
a contradiction.
Which is for instance, that for
many of us, including myself,
especially in the
years when I was
in graduate school
and a postdoc,
there were times in which
pursuing and being involved
in work and pursuing
degrees and finding
meaning in my vocation
actually separated me
from the opportunity
to have quite
as many social connections,
or quite as much sleep,
or quite as much exercise, or
even quite as much sunshine,
for that matter.
So all of the things that we're
told that we need in order
to access happiness
on a regular basis
oftentimes contradict
with the pressures
and the requirements
of not just daily life
but in building a
life that allows
us to have the kind of
resources that we need in order
to have things like quality
social connection, and the time
and opportunity to get regular
exercise and great nutrition,
et cetera, et cetera.
So, again, while this
isn't necessarily
a complaint with any
of the research out
of the fields of
psychology on happiness,
it is important
that we acknowledge
these contradictions that
exist in the discussion
around happiness.
In particular, the
popular discussions
around the science of happiness.
So today, what we are
going to arrive at,
what you will
finish this episode,
with is a set of tools and a
framework for understanding
the pursuit of happiness
in the short and long-term
as it relates to the
research from psychology
but also the neuroscience.
And my goal today is really
to try and place that all
into a structured
framework so that you
can know where you are in
your journey or the landscape
around happiness in your
pursuit of happiness.
And what I won't
tell you is that you
need to abandon
all goals in terms
of pursuing money,
career, et cetera,
and simply focus
on relationships.
But we will talk
about what constitutes
an excellent social bond or
even in excellent conversation.
There's excellent research
that points to the fact
that even rather shallow
connections, that
is, connections between people
that you happen to just see
in the hallway on
a regular basis,
not even requiring
close bonds of any kind,
can be built into close
bonds that can deliver
a tremendous amount of feeling
and genuine social connection
provided certain
conditions are met.
So today, again, it's
really about understanding
the science of happiness,
understanding the mechanisms
underlying what
we call happiness.
And providing you a
framework by which
you can pursue and
achieve happiness not just
as a long-term goal and not
just as a day-to-day goal
of little micro exercises
of gratitude, et cetera,
but rather as a way to
think about happiness
as a state that you have
control over, at least
in terms of your
ability to access
what I would call
the algorithms that
enable us or open the
opportunity to experience
happiness.
Now before we begin
today's episode,
I'd like to talk about a very
specific tool that applies yes
to our pursuit of
happiness but actually
to our pursuit of everything,
including quality sleep
and ongoing
motivation, et cetera.
I've talked many, many
times before on this podcast
and on other podcasts,
and on social media
about the critical
value of getting
regular bright light, ideally
sunlight, in your eyes
within the first hour of waking.
Or if the sun isn't out when
you wake up in the morning,
to turn on a lot of
bright artificial lights
and then get
sunlight in your eyes
for anywhere from
5 to 20 minutes,
depending on how cloudy it is
in the early part of the day.
Absolutely outsized
effects mood and focus
during the day and
quality of sleep at night.
Now there's another
sort of central tenet
of getting great sleep
and improving mood
and focus throughout the day.
And that's to avoid
bright artificial light
exposure to your eyes between
the hours of about 10 PM
to 4:00 AM.
Now leaving shift workers aside,
and we have an entire episode
devoted to shift work, most
people are asleep at night
and awake during the day.
And you would be wise to
avoid exposure of your eyes
to bright artificial light
between the hours of 10:00
PM and 4:00 AM.
If you're going to use
screens or artificial lights,
dim them down as far as you can.
Now there are several studies
that point to the fact
that one of the major
issues with getting
bright light in your eyes
between the hours of 10:00
PM and 4:00 AM is that
it has a negative impact
on the so-called dopaminergic or
dopamine circuits of the brain
and body, which can
enhance depression.
That is lead to ongoing
lower mood and affect.
So that's a reason
to dim the lights
or avoid bright lights
between 10:00 PM and 4:00 AM.
However, I and many others
need to use artificial light
and screens sometimes, even
between the hours of 10:00
PM and midnight or even
midnight to 3:00 AM,
depending on what's going
on in my life or your life.
That may include you as well.
Now it turns out that
there are powerful ways
to offset some, not all, but
some of the negative effects
of viewing artificial lights
between the hours of 10:00
PM and 4:00 AM.
And one of the most
powerful ways to do that
is to simply adjust
the overall brightness
of your artificial
lighting throughout the day
and in the evening.
So one of the issues nowadays
that we're really facing
is that people are simply not
getting enough bright light
in their eyes from sunlight
or from other sources
during the daytime,
and they're getting
far too much bright
light in their eyes
largely from artificial sources,
of course, in the evening
and at night.
Not just from 10 PM
to 4:00 AM, but also
in the evening hours from 6 to
10 PM and so on and so forth.
So a very simple yet
powerful solution
that supported by peer-reviewed
research in humans
is to try and make your
indoor working and/or home
environment during the
day as bright as possible.
Now, if you can achieve that
through direct sunlight,
terrific.
If you can get outside a lot
during the daytime, terrific.
But many people simply cannot.
But most people do have some
windows in their environment.
I realize some don't
but, most people do.
And as a consequence,
most people
are using rather dim artificial
lighting indoors during the day
and then very bright
artificial lighting
indoors in the evening, and
at night, that's a problem.
And if you think about
it, logically, you
want to do the exact reverse.
So it's been shown
that if you simply
increase the amount of
bright artificial light
that you were exposed to
during the day, and remember
this is not an excuse to not get
your morning sunlight viewing,
but in addition to that, to make
your indoor artificial lights
very bright, bright,
bright, bright, bright
throughout the day.
And then much dimmer from the
hours of 6:00 PM until bedtime.
Or if you can't do
that, then maybe as soon
as you get home from about
8:00 PM until bedtime.
And then dim them way,
way down between 10:00
PM and 4:00 AM or off entirely.
That's going to be
a far better pattern
for your sleep-wake
cycles, focus, mood, et
cetera than what
most people do, which
is to have a few windows
in their indoor working
environment during the day and
keep the indoor lights rather
dim at a time when they
need more photons, more
light energy.
And then in the evening,
when they get home
because it's dark
outside, they tend
to turn the lights
much brighter.
You actually want
to do the reverse.
Now there's an even
simpler solution,
which is to get some bright
sunlight in your eyes
right around the time of sunset.
It doesn't have to
be exactly at sunset,
it could be in the late
afternoon and evening.
But it's been shown now
in studies on humans,
and I'll provide a
link to at least one
of those studies,
that by getting
some bright light in your
eyes, ideally from sunlight,
in the late afternoon
and evening.
And, of course, the timing will
vary depending on time of year
and where you are
located on the planet.
But facing the
sun around sunset,
you don't actually have
to see the sun cross down
below the horizon,
but facing the sun
around that time for anywhere
from 5 to 10 minutes or even
less, even two to
five minutes, can
adjust the
sensitivity of neurons
in your retina that communicate
light information to the brain
and make it such that in
the evening when you use
artificial lights, they
aren't going to have as much
of a detrimental effect
on your dopamine system
and for impairing your sleep.
So the idea is as much bright
light, ideally from sunlight
but also from artificial
sources, from the time
you wake up in the
morning until the evening.
Maybe around 6:00 or 7:00.
Maybe in the summer
months, a little bit later.
And then really try and
get as little bright light
in your eyes as you can in the
evening and nighttime hours.
And ideally, you would also get
some sunlight exposure right
around the time of sunset
or in the late afternoon.
Go outside, take
your sunglasses off.
Don't try and do this through a
windshield or through a window.
It will not work.
You have to get outside.
If you're under an
overhang, at least
try and get some direct sunlight
in your eyes at that time.
And that will adjust
the sensitivity
of your retina such that
bright artificial lights
or artificial lights
of any kind that you're
exposed to in the evening and
in the late hours of the night
won't have as much of
a detrimental effect.
That said, if you
go to the bathroom
in the middle of the night,
try and keep the lights dim.
Many people have asked
whether or not, for instance,
a nightlight or a flashlight
is going to have as much
of a negative effect.
This is very straightforward.
If you think about it, if you
shine a light at something,
you can see into
your environment.
If you've ever been
camping or you've
walked with a flashlight,
you can see things around you
that you wouldn't
otherwise, of course.
But if you were to shine
that light in your eyes,
it would be far brighter.
So yes, of course, if you get
up in the middle of the night
and you can use your phone
flashlight to illuminate
the environment that you're
in so that you can safely
go to where you need to
go and then back to bed,
that's going to be far better
than turning on the lights
or, of course, shining
light in your eyes, right.
So the idea is bright,
bright, bright in the morning
and throughout the day.
And as dim and dark
as possible at night.
And that afternoon light
viewing provides, sort of,
what I call a Netflix
inoculation that
will allow you to adjust
your retinal sensitivity
and give you a little bit
more flexibility in terms
of allowing some
nighttime light exposure
without the detrimental effects.
Now I realize today's
episode is about happiness,
it's not about
sunlight or dopamine.
And yet, as we'll
talk about more
in just a moment, if you're
not optimizing your sleep
and if you are using or
being exposed to light rather
at the wrong times of
the day/night cycle,
that is going to make it
very hard for the other sorts
of practices that
relate to happiness
to have their full impact.
So the backdrop, where I would
say the kind of landscape
of your chemicals
and your hormones,
is powerfully controlled by not
just the brightness of light
but the timing of light
and your exposure to light.
In particular, your exposure
to light to your eyes
is something that you have
a lot of control over.
You don't have absolute control,
but you have a lot of control
over.
And it's been proven that
even these small steps, which
are completely cost-free.
They require just a
few minutes of time,
but no purchase a
product or anything else
can allow you to greatly
adjust your neurochemistry
and your hormones in the
direction of better mood,
better sleep, and happiness.
Before we begin, I'd
like to emphasize
that this podcast is separate
from my teaching and research
roles at Stanford.
It is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science-related tools
for the general public.
In keeping with
that theme, I'd like
to thank the sponsors
of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Thesis.
Thesis makes custom nootropics.
And as I've said many times
before on this podcast,
I am not a fan of
the word nootropics
because it means smart drugs.
And frankly, there are no
specific neural circuits
in the brain or body for
being quote-unquote smart.
Thesis understands
this, and they've
developed custom nootropics
that are designed
to bring your brain and
body into the state that's
ideal for what you
need to accomplish.
They use the highest
quality ingredients,
things like
phosphatidylserine, alpha GPC,
many ingredients
that I've talked
about before on this podcast
and that I happen to use myself.
I've been using Thesis
for over a year now,
and I can confidently say
that their nootropics have
been a game changer.
For me, I like their
nootropic for clarity.
I used that before
cognitive work often.
And I like their
nootropic for energy.
And I often used
that before workouts.
In particular, workouts
that are especially intense.
To get your own personalized
nootropic starter kit,
go online to
takethesis.com/huberman.
Take their 3-minute
quiz, and these
will send you four
different formulas
to try in your first month.
Again that's
takethesis.com/huberman.
And use the code
Huberman at checkout
to get 10% off your first box.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data
from your blood and DNA
to help me better
understand your body
and help you meet
your health goals.
I've long been a believer in
getting regular blood work done
for the simple reason that
many of the factors that impact
your immediate and
long-term health
can only be analyzed with
a quality blood test.
One of the problems with a
lot of blood tests and DNA
tests out there, however,
is that you get information
back about lipids and
levels of hormones
and levels of metabolic
factors and so on,
but you don't know what to
do with that information.
InsideTracker has a very
easy-to-use online site where
you can monitor your levels.
And you can click on
any specific marker,
any specific hormone,
or metabolic factor,
and it will tell you the
behavioral tools, for instance,
exercise, the nutrition tools,
and the supplementation-based
tools that you can
use in order to bring
those numbers into
the appropriate ranges
for your immediate and
long-term health goals.
If you'd like to
try InsideTracker,
you can visit
insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off any of
InsideTracker's plan.
Again that's
insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Helix Sleep.
Helix makes
mattresses and pillows
that are of the absolute
highest quality.
I started sleeping on a Helix
mattress well over a year ago,
and it's been the best
sleep that I've ever had.
One of the things that makes
Helix mattresses so unique
is that they match the
design of the mattress
to your unique sleep needs.
So, for instance, if you
go on to their website,
you can take a brief quiz.
It's only takes about
two or three minutes.
And you'll answer
questions like do
you tend to run hot or
cold throughout the night.
Or whether or not you sleep
on your back, your side,
or your stomach, or
maybe you don't know.
Regardless, they will match you
to the custom mattress that's
ideal for your sleep needs.
For me that was the
dusk D-U-S-K mattress.
Which, for me, was not
too firm, not too soft,
and was ideal for
my sleep patterns.
You take the quiz,
and you'll find out
what mattress is ideal
for your sleep patterns.
So if you're interested in
upgrading your mattress,
go to helixsleep.com/huberman,
take their brief sleep quiz,
and they'll match you to
a customized mattress.
And you'll get up to $200 off
any mattress order and two
free pillows.
They have a 10-year warranty.
And you get to try
out the mattress
for 100 nights risk-free.
Again, if you're
interested, you can go
to helixsleep.com/huberman for
up to $200 off and two free
pillows.
Let's talk about happiness.
This thing that everybody seems
to want, and yet not everybody
can agree on what exactly
it is or how to get it.
Now I want to start by quoting
a previous guest on the Huberman
Lab podcast.
And that is a colleague of mine
at Stanford School of Medicine,
Dr. Karl Deisseroth, who's both
a bioengineer and a clinician.
That is, he's a psychiatrist
who spends a lot of his time
both running a laboratory
and seeing patients,
human patients, of course.
And I once was at
a meeting where
I heard Karl say something
to the extent of we
don't know what
other people feel.
In fact, most of the
time, we don't even
really know how we feel.
And while that
statement was meant
to report several different
things about the way
that the brain
works and emotions,
et cetera, one of the things
that he was emphasizing,
and I know he was emphasizing
it because he confirmed
this for me, was the
fact that language.
Things like the word
happiness, or joy, or meaning,
or pleasure, or delight,
are actually not
very precise when it comes to
describing our brain and body
states.
So, for instance, if I tell
you I'm feeling pretty happy.
I know what that means for
me, at least in this moment,
but you don't really
know whether or not
it means the same thing as what
pretty happy means for you.
If I say I'm extremely
happy and I have a big grin.
I have a grin on my face that I
can't seem to wipe off my face.
Well, then, you might get a
sense of how much happier I
am than pretty happy.
But it's still hard to calibrate
my level of internal state
or happiness, and the
same is true for you
and for everybody else.
And it's important for
us to acknowledge this
because at this point
in human history, 2022,
we don't really
have a measurement
like body temperature or
heart rate or heart rate
variability or even a way
to measure neurochemicals
in the brain and body
that give us anything
better than a crude correlate
or an estimate, at best,
of what happiness is.
So that's really important to
understand and to keep in mind
throughout this episode.
It doesn't mean that we cannot
have a strong data-driven
conversation about happiness
and what brings us to a state
of happiness.
But it's very important to
understand that language is not
an ideal and maybe even
a deficient tool in terms
of describing our emotions and
our states of mind and body.
Now equally important
is to understand
that while we do have
neurotransmitters,
that is, the chemicals
that are released between
neurons, nerve cells
that allow neurons
to communicate, things
like glutamate and gaba,
for instance.
And we have what are
called modulators.
These are chemicals
also released
by neurons that impact the
electrical firing and chemical
release of other neurons.
Things like serotonin, and
dopamine, and acetylcholine,
and epinephrine.
Neuromodulators and
neurotransmitters
are always present in a
cocktail in our brain and body.
That is, they are present
in different ratios
and at different levels.
So we need to completely
discard with the idea
that any one neurotransmitter
or any one neuromodulator
is solely responsible
for a state of happiness
or for a lack of state of
happiness, for that matter.
That said, it is true
that for people that
tend to have lower baseline
levels of, for instance,
dopamine, their
levels of happiness,
or we should say their
self-reported levels
of happiness, tend to
be lower than for those
that have greatly elevated
baseline levels of dopamine.
Now, this can be
best appreciated
at the extremes
where, for instance,
in conditions like
Parkinson's disease
or other conditions where
people's levels of dopamine
in their brain is
severely depleted.
Mind you, we also see this
in drug-addicted individuals
that are in a withdrawal state
because they're trying to quit
or they don't have access to the
drug that normally stimulates
release of dopamine.
Think the cocaine addict
who can't get cocaine.
Or the methamphetamine
addict that
can't or is trying to avoid
taking methamphetamine.
Or the Parkinson's patient
who has fewer dopamine
neurons because
they degenerated.
Those individuals do tend
to be more depressed.
They tend to have lower affect.
They are less happy.
At least, that's how they report
themselves to be emotionally.
And that's what we observe when
we look at them behaviorally
in terms of the amount of
smiling, the amount of energy
they seem to have.
At the opposite extreme.
And while still focusing
on the kind of pathology
of neurotransmitter and
neuromodulator systems,
an individual who is in
a manic phase of bipolar
will tend to have very
elevated levels of dopamine.
And those people will
talk a mile a minute,
and they won't require sleep.
And at least to them, every
idea is an exciting idea and one
that they want to pursue.
We did an entire episode about
bipolar depression, A.K.A.
Bipolar disorder.
So if you'd like to learn
more about that, please
check out that episode.
That and all other
episodes of the podcast,
of course, you can find it
hubermanlab.com in all formats.
But the point here is
that very low levels
are very high levels of
dopamine are correlated
with certain states of,
for instance, low happiness
or the absence of happiness.
We could even call it
depression in some cases.
Or extreme happiness
or even euphoria.
Sometimes even
inappropriate euphoria,
as is the case with
bipolar depression
or sometimes called bipolar
mania or bipolar disorder.
Now, of course, there's a range
in between depressed and manic.
And most people, fortunately
reside somewhere in that range.
And it is indeed a continuum.
And I think it's safe to
say that levels of dopamine
probably do correlate
with levels of happiness.
But there is no
one single chemical
nor chemical signature, that is,
no specific recipe of two parts
dopamine, to one part
serotonin, to one part
acetylcholine that we can
say equates to happiness.
Indeed there's now
tremendous controversy
as to whether or not,
for instance, having
lower levels of
serotonin is actually
the cause of depression
or merely correlates
with depression or maybe
doesn't even correlate
with depression, at all.
This became especially
controversial
because, in the last year,
the so-called serotonin
hypothesis of depression has
been called into question.
And indeed, it does seem to be
the case that for individuals
that are depressed,
their levels of serotonin
can sometimes be normal.
However, and this is
an important however,
that does not mean that
administering drugs
that increase levels of
serotonin in depressed people
does not sometimes
and indeed often help
ameliorate some
of their symptoms.
And I should mention that many
of the selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors.
So-called SSRIs such
as Prozac and Zoloft,
et cetera, are still
considered excellent treatments
for conditions like OCD
and so on and so forth.
But what I'm trying to do is
make two important points.
First of all, that language
is not a great indicator
of internal state.
Especially when trying to
understand other people's
internal state.
And that is especially true
for things like happiness.
And that there is
no one chemical
signature of happiness.
There's no one neural
modulator or combinations
of neuromodulators
that we can say
is the cocktail for happiness.
But, and it's a very
important, but when
levels of dopamine
and serotonin tend
to be chronically
low for an individual
below their typical
baseline, they
will, yes, tend to
be lower in affect
and have lower mood and less
episodes of happiness per day,
per week, per month,
per year, et cetera.
Conversely, when an
individual has elevations
in dopamine and
serotonin levels,
in particular dopamine levels
and the other so-called
catecholamines, which include
epinephrine and norepinephrine.
So the catecholamines are
dopamine, epinephrine,
and norepinephrine.
They're all very
similar biochemically.
They all lead to states of
elevated motivation, energy,
and so on.
When those chemicals are
elevated above baseline,
people do tend to have elevated
sense of mood and well-being,
and in particular
sense of possibility
about what they
can do in the world
and what the world
can offer them.
So we need to acknowledge
those two features of language
and neurochemistry as we
wade into the discussion
about the psychology
of happiness.
And, in particular, about
the controlled experiments
that have been done in
excellent laboratories focused
on the psychology of happiness
and what brings happiness
and what does not.
There have been some excellent
studies on happiness.
And these come in
two forms generally.
One form of these
studies is individuals
come into a laboratory.
They participate in an
experiment over the course
of a day or months.
And then, data are
collected analyzed,
and the papers are submitted,
and published, and discussed.
The other form is so-called
longitudinal study.
Where individuals come
into the laboratory,
and they are studied over
a very long period of time.
Ranging from months to years
and sometimes even decades.
And then, the variables of
age, life circumstances,
and other factors can be
incorporated into the data.
And typically, there
are multiple papers,
there's data published
throughout the longitudinal
study, or sometimes
it's just one paper
at the end of the
longitudinal study.
Let's talk about one of
the more famous and perhaps
the longest-running
longitudinal study on happiness.
This is a study that was
initiated or conceived
in 1938 at Harvard University.
The so-called Harvard
Happiness Project.
Some of you probably
heard about this.
It involved Harvard
College sophomores
and other individuals who were
incorporated into this study
as well.
It's a study that initially
had more than a couple
of hundred subjects.
But because some have
either dropped out and not
been able to be contacted and
monitored over time or died,
or for whatever reason,
are no longer participating
in the study, they're very
few of these individuals left.
And yet there's tremendous
power to a study like this.
It's such an impressive study,
and we're all so grateful
that laboratories
at Harvard decided
to initiate and continue
this study because it
is one of the few studies,
perhaps the study that
has allowed us to understand
happiness in our species
over a very long period of time.
Like any study,
it's not perfect.
It didn't include a
lot of matching by sex
or matching by
vocation, or matching
by income and background.
And back then, there was
also a lot less discussion
about trauma and
histories around trauma,
as well as positive
episodes in people's lives.
Nonetheless, there's a lot of
power in a study like this.
And there are some
very basic takeaways,
some of which you may have heard
before but some of which may be
surprising those
of you who haven't.
So one of the key
things about the study
is people in the
study, at least those
who still have intact memory,
which many of them do,
are able to think
back on not just
their previous year or week but
10 years ago, 20 years ago, 50
years ago and compare
what makes them happy
at one age versus another age.
A number of things have
emerged from that conversation.
So I just want to discuss
some of the highlight points
then we'll get into
a little bit more
of the nitty-gritty of the data.
First of all, it's been
discussed many, many times
that the total amount of
income that an individual makes
or has, and again, this
could be income from work,
or it could be money
that they inherited,
does not seem to directly relate
to their level of happiness.
Now a lot of people take
that point and think,
oh, money doesn't matter.
Other people hear that point
and think to themselves,
yeah, right, easy to say
if you have a lot of money.
We'll talk about the
interpretation of those data
in just a few minutes.
But I do want to
earmark that finding.
Because I agree that while
money or total resources itself
does not predict happiness
in any kind of direct way,
that is not the
same thing as saying
having very few resources will
make you happier, of course.
I don't think anyone
would imagine that.
But it also tends to overlook
an important point, which
is something that I certainly
have learned to appreciate
in my life and something
that I especially appreciated
when I was a student
and post-doc, which
is the following.
People will say money
can't buy happiness.
And we'll talk about the buy
aspect of that in a moment.
And indeed, that's true.
If you look at this
longitudinal study or you
look at other
studies that are done
on a more short-term basis.
Once people get past a
certain level of income
relative to their cost of
living, the amount of happiness
does not scale with that income.
That is, for every
additional $1,000 or $10,000
that they earn,
they don't report
being that much happier
on a daily basis.
Now that said, I venture the
argument that while money truly
cannot buy happiness, it
absolutely can buffer stress.
And in particular,
it can buffer stress
in the form of the
ability to purchase or pay
for goods and services,
and in particular services.
You're not going to tell
me that having children
doesn't involve some
increase in the demands
on your life, less
sleep, and more demands.
And it certainly is
the case that if you
can hire help to clean.
You can hire nannies
if that's your thing.
You can hire help to assist
with babysitting or even night
nurses if you're having trouble
sleeping that will literally
allow you to sleep while
they take care of your child
in the middle of the night.
Often give excellent care.
One hopes excellent care.
That that won't offset
some of the stress
associated with lack of sleep.
So there are a million
different examples
one could give of this, but
I certainly experienced this
during graduate school.
In fact, I experience both
sides of the equation here.
I made very little money
as a graduate student.
I had essentially no savings
when I started graduate school,
and I made very little money.
The amount doesn't
matter at this point,
but I could just barely
afford rent and my food.
I actually opted to live in the
laboratory a lot of the time.
And by doing that,
I had more money
to spend on other things
that were important to me.
Now I did not have a
family at the time,
and so I was able to do that.
Something that not
everyone can do.
But I made very little
money, but at the same time,
I was in laboratory
all the time,
and that's where I wanted to be.
And so my level of
stress was actually
pretty low because
I was investing
all my time and energy
into the very thing
that I knew would eventually
help bring me more resources.
When I moved from being a
graduate student to a postdoc,
for instance.
A postdoc is generally a
three to five-year period.
It's sort of like
residency in medicine,
where you're no
longer taking courses,
but you continue to do research.
In fact, entire new
lines of research
and prior to getting
a professorship.
My income went up slightly,
went up by about 30% to 40%.
But because of where I moved
and because of the times,
my cost of living went way,
way up and I was extremely
stressed.
So it wasn't my
absolute income, it
was my absolute income
relative to my cost of living.
The other thing that
one needs to consider
when considering income versus
cost of living is there's
also this notion of peer group.
And we're going to talk
more about social bonds
and connections later.
But one thing that
I noticed when
I moved from being a
graduate student to a postdoc
was I was a graduate student in
a small town where I had access
if I chose to participate
in most, if not all,
of the social gatherings because
they were all very low cost.
People tended to aggregate
at the farmer's market
on Saturday.
Most people wouldn't even
purchase anything, at least not
the graduate students
wouldn't purchase anything.
It was just a
place to aggregate.
People sometimes play
pickup games of soccer
or just hang out
have a cup of coffee.
There was a volleyball
game on Fridays.
Sometimes people would go
out to eat that evening,
which of course, costs
money, et cetera,
but it was relatively
low cost of living.
And social connections and
peer group interactions
were all generated around
the same fairly low-cost
activities.
When I transitioned to being
a postdoc, I made more money,
but cost of living went up.
But in addition to
that, my peer group
tended to want to engage in
the same kinds of activities
that people in that larger
city were engaged in.
So peer group has a tremendously
powerful influence on
whether or not we gauge
the amount of money
that we have as bringing
us happiness or not.
And that really speaks to
the critical importance
of social interactions
and certain kinds
of social interactions,
in particular.
Now, if any of that was unclear,
what I'm basically saying is
it's not just about being
able to pay your rent.
It's also about
being able to access
the kinds of social interactions
that you deem are quote-unquote
correct for you at
that stage of life
and in the place where
you happen to be living.
Because if you can meet all
the demands of costs of rent
and paying your power
bill and food, et cetera,
but you are socially
isolated because your peer
group, or those around you
that you want to engage with,
are engaging in activities that
you either don't have time for,
literally, because
you're doing other things
or that you don't have the
financial resources for,
then that can actually
severely impact this rating
of what we call happiness.
Why am I parsing
this so finally?
Well, I'm parsing and finally
because I think that most of us
have heard the outcome of
this study from Harvard
or the more short-term
studies, also many of which
are from Harvard.
We'll talk about the
just phenomenal work
from Dan Gilbert's laboratory
and other laboratories who have
focused on issues like these.
And I certainly don't
want to take anything away
from those results.
They're very powerful
and important results
that really point over
and over to the fact
that people's happiness does not
necessarily scale with income.
In fact, it tends not
to past a certain level,
and yet I think
we'd be remiss, I
think actually it
would be inappropriate
for me to say that the amount
of income that one makes
is not important.
Because if the amount of
money that you happen to have
or are making does
not allow you to meet
your basic needs of shelter,
health care, et cetera.
And/or doesn't
allow you to access
the kind of social interactions
that can renew and reset
or, I would say,
directly enhance
the kind of neurotransmitter
systems and hormones
that lead us to feel that
we are happy in our life
and we're having quality
social connections, well then
that's very stressful.
And this brings me back to
the statement I made earlier,
which is, indeed, money
cannot buy happiness,
but it certainly
can buffer stress.
And one of the ways
that it buffers stress
is by allowing options
of different kinds
of social interactions.
Options of different
types of recreation
that one can engage in to access
new forms of social interaction
and so on and so on.
So we need to be a little bit
careful or at least nuanced
about this statement that
money can't buy happiness
and that the data support
the fact that wealth
doesn't determine happiness.
I think there is a truth
to that but there's
another side to that, I think
is less often acknowledged
and that certainly
I've experienced
and that I think many of
you out there have probably
experienced as well.
One other major finding of
the Harvard longitudinal
study on happiness, as well
as shorter-term studies
on happiness, is
that much as you've
heard, perhaps that no
one on their deathbed
says they wish they had
worked more, well indeed,
the total amount of time
that one spends working
does not seem to
determine one's happiness.
And yet I also want to earmark
that result as one that we need
to parse a bit more carefully.
Because work, last
time I checked
and certainly for me,
is the way typically
that people earn an income.
And as we just talked
about a moment ago,
income is often a way
that people have access
to or provide access
for their family
to things like
recreation that opens up
the opportunity for more
social connection, right.
So we have to be careful with
how we interpret these blanket
statements that have become
very popular that money doesn't
determine happiness and that
the amount that you work
isn't going to
determine happiness.
It certainly is the case
that if you earn more money
from working more and
that money is devoted
to things that bring
more opportunities
for social connection
or for buffering stress
in other areas of your
life, including health care,
care for your children,
care for yourself,
recreation, other things
that you enjoy, well then
I think it's a little bit naive
to assume that work itself is
somehow counter to happiness.
Which, of course, it isn't.
And it especially isn't if we
combine that feature of work
with another important feature
of the human psyche, which
is this notion of meaning.
Now in the
not-too-distant future,
we will do an episode of
this podcast on meaning
and what constitutes meaning
in a given endeavor, work
or otherwise.
But much of the psychology of
the last century, and still
today, focuses on this
feature of meaning
as a critical one in terms
of what makes us happy
and what doesn't make us happy,
certainly in the long term.
And I can certainly
say for myself
that learning and teaching, and
doing research in my laboratory
brings me tremendous feeling
of meaning and happiness.
Some people consider
their work simply
a way to gain a paycheck,
and other people
find that they would do the
very work they do regardless of
whether or not they were paid.
In fact, many people will do
volunteer work and other forms
of work for zero money.
So this idea that
money isn't important
or that work is not as
important as we deem it to be,
that also needs to be
considered from a number
of different perspectives.
And again, by no
means am I trying
to undermine the data of
these impressive studies, both
the longitudinal and
short-term studies,
but I think we do have to be
cautious in our discussion
of results like these
because the internet is
replete with conversations
about the big factors that
determine happiness.
It's going to be social
connection, not income.
It's going to be
the amount of time
that you are able to have open
thinking and creativity, which
I think is an essential feature
of happiness, by the way.
Physical health.
In particular, one's
ability to stay mobile
and to be able to access
the kind of daily activities
that one needs to
accomplish unassisted
is a strong correlate of
happiness and so on and so on.
And, of course, there are
the basic physiology factors.
The things that feed back
onto our overall feelings
of well-being.
And I've talked
about these before,
and we'll just put these
quickly into a bin.
You can think of this
as a toolkit of things
that you and everyone really
should be constantly trying
to access, if not optimize, on
a regular basis because they
raise the tide or
what I would call
the buoyancy of
your overall system,
meaning your brain and body.
And that would be getting
sufficient deep sleep at least
80% of the nights of your life.
And ideally, the remaining
20% you're not getting deep
sleep or as much of it
because of positive events.
Quality nutrition.
Quality social interactions.
And we will define that
a little bit better.
In fact, we will define that
in a lot of detail later
in this episode and
actually how to get better
at creating quality
social interactions,
even very brief
social interactions.
So we have sleep,
we have nutrition,
we have social interactions.
We have purposeful
work, whether or not
it's paid work or non-paid work.
And, of course, there
are things like exercise
and maybe relationships to
pets and things of that sort.
And there are a
few others as well.
All of those are known to
increase your overall state
of well-being, that
puts you in a position
to access more meaning
and happiness, et cetera.
But for most
people, I think it's
fair to say that
earning a living.
And earning a living by working
is the typical way in which
we spend most of our time.
So I think we need to
put a special bracket
around those activities.
And it's something we will
return to a little bit
later in terms of trying to
understand how periods of life
in which there are big
or extensive work demands
or extensive family
demands on us
are indeed compatible
with states of happiness
or frequent states of happiness
and how better to access those.
Rather than simply say
money isn't important
or the amount of time at
work really isn't important.
That's not what people are
going to pay attention to.
In fact, I don't know how
I will feel on my deathbed.
How could I?
Human beings are pretty
good about understanding
how they feel in the present.
If not describing it, they
are pretty good at feeling it
if they have any sense
of internal state.
That is interception.
And you could have some idea
of how you feel in a moment.
We're pretty good about
describing our past feelings,
at least in broad
contour, but we are not
very good at projecting how
we will feel in the future.
And in fact, that's
a theme that's
going to come up
again and again today.
Nonetheless, what we do know on
the basis of really solid data
are that certain aspects
of our well-being
tend to change
across our lifespan.
Now lifespan is
something that we
need to consider from
also a bit of nuance
because humans are indeed
living longer and longer.
And if we look at
the data on happiness
across the lifespan dated maybe
30 or 40 years back or even
20 years ago, it is
consistently described
in that literature as a
so-called u-shaped function.
Where people in their 20s
report being very, very happy,
but as time goes on and they
acquire more responsibility.
So typically, getting
married and having
children in their mid to late
20s and 30s and into their 40s.
Having more work
demands, et cetera,
happiness tends to be
rated lower and lower,
at least in those
previous studies.
And then happiness tended
to increase as people
approach their 50s and 60s.
And they tended to retire,
and their work demands
were shed from
them, and they were
able to enjoy the small things
of life despite the fact
that, in general, I
would say almost always
people's health is not as
vigorous when they're 70
as it is when they're 20.
There are exceptions
to that, of course.
Of course, you can adjust the
rate of cognitive and physical
decline.
But in general,
people in their 20s
feel more physically
and mentally vigorous
than they do in their
60s and 70s, in general.
That u-shaped function
that I just described still
holds true today,
but of course, there
have been some major shifts
to the general life stages
and when people undergo
those life stages.
For instance, many people are
getting married much later.
Many people are opting
to not have children.
In fact, if you look at the data
on whether or not people have
children or not and how
that relates to happiness,
everyone will tell you that
their kids are their greatest
source of joy, at least most
people will tell you that
and are a tremendous
source of happiness.
It's obvious.
Kids are delightful, and
raising kids while hard
is a wonderful experience.
If you look at the
ratings of happiness
among people that elected to not
have children versus those that
had, most people
who have children
report their overall
levels of happiness
as lower than that of people
who opt not to have children.
Now there are a lot of ways
to interpret those findings.
And by no means am I encouraging
people to not have children.
That's a issue that you have
to resolve for yourself,
of course.
But we could imagine,
for instance,
that people who opt
not to have children
have more income to devote
to things more focused
on themselves or their partner
or other aspects of their life.
We don't know if that's
the underlying reason.
We could perhaps
conclude that people
who opt not to have children
are getting more sleep
on a regular basis or have
more time for exercise
or the other sorts of
things that elevate
states of mood and well-being.
Again we do not know
what the underlying
reasons are for this finding.
But it does seem that
despite most every parent
reporting that their kids are
their greatest source of joy
and quote-unquote
happiness in life
that people who opt not to have
children are at least as happy
or report being at least
as happy or even happier
than those that opt
to have children.
And, of course, I
want to be very clear
that I'm not trying to
settle any arguments about
whether or not people
should have children or not.
I happen to find children
and animals delightful.
And I'm always happy when
people opt to have children
provided they are taking
good care of their children
or doing their very best to take
good care of their children.
So that's my stance.
But of course,
you're all entitled
to your own stance on this.
There are also the
general arguments
that people like to have
about whether or not
the population of the Earth will
be sustained or not sustained
based on current birth
rates, et cetera.
Indeed many areas of the world,
birth rates are going down.
It is actually
something that just
as a perhaps point
of interest has
been studied from the somewhat
unusual but logical perspective
of whether or not child diapers
are selling at the same rate
as they were some years ago and
whether or not adult diapers
for the elderly are being sold
at the same rate or greater.
If you think about it is one
indirect measure of whether
or not people are living longer
and/or opting to have children.
Definitely in discussion
for another time,
probably for another
podcast entirely.
I'd like to take a quick
break and acknowledge
one of our sponsors
Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens,
now called AG1, is
a vitamin-mineral
probiotic drink
that covers all of your
foundational nutritional needs.
I've been taking Athletic
Greens since 2012,
so I'm delighted that they're
sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I started
taking Athletic Greens,
and the reason I still take
Athletic Greens once or usually
twice a day, is that it
gets me the probiotics
that I need for gut health.
Our gut is very important.
It's populated by
gut microbiota that
communicate with the brain, the
immune system, and basically
all the biological
systems of our body
to strongly impact our
immediate and long-term health.
And those probiotics
and Athletic Greens
are optimal and vital
for microbiotic health.
In addition, Athletic
Greens contains a number
of adaptogens,
vitamins, and minerals
that make sure that all of my
foundational nutritional needs
are met.
And it tastes great.
If you'd like to
try Athletic Greens,
you can go to
athleticgreens.com/huberman,
and they'll give you five
free travel packs that make it
really easy to mix up
Athletic Greens while
you're on the road, in the
car, on the plane, et cetera.
And they'll give you a year
supply of vitamin D3K2.
Again that's
athleticgreens.com/huberman
to get the five free travel
packs and the year supply
of vitamin D3K2.
So this u-shaped function
of people being happier
earlier in life
and then reporting
feeling far less happy
and then happiness
returning to them, that is,
the rising of the u again
in their later years, is
something that I do believe
should be repeated
in modern times.
And repeated in a way that
takes into account that you
might be shifted to the right.
That is, I am certainly
aware that people are
tending to get married later.
Many are opting to
not have children.
So, for instance, the
question arises whether or not
that u-shaped curve
should have a bump down
at the bottom of
the u among those
that opt not to have children.
Because the argument was made in
the discussion of those papers
that the reason why
happiness is lower
when people are in
their 30s, 40s, and 50s
is because they're devoting more
time to raising their children
and devoting more time to work.
I would hope people
would enjoy their work,
but not everybody really
enjoys their work.
And many people, even if
they do enjoy their work
and they find
meaning in it, still
find it stressful,
which certainly
can run counter to happiness.
Nowadays, you could imagine
that because a number of people
are opting perhaps to work
less or to not have children
or both, where they
find tremendous meaning
from their work
that there would be
a bump at the bottom of that
u among those that decided to
simply not take on these
additional responsibilities.
That would be an
interesting test,
I think, of whether or not the
total load of responsibility
is really what's correlating
with reported happiness or not.
Now one very consistent
finding that has absolutely
stood the test of time, and
it's kind of an interesting one.
It's a little bit of a
pop psychology finding,
but I think it points to
something interesting that we
will return to
again and again is
that people tend
to report feeling
lower levels of happiness,
believe it or not,
on their birthday.
And the argument for why
this is the following.
That typically, we
go through our year
not comparing ourselves to
our peers terribly much.
We might do that
a little bit more
when we're in elementary
school, high school, et cetera.
We're sort of age match,
maybe even college as well.
But an evaluation of ourselves
to our age-match peers
is not typically something
that we do on a daily basis.
Whereas on our birthday,
we get a snapshot
of where we are in the arc of
time, or at least in our life.
And many people report feeling
rather low on their birthday
because they use that as
a benchmark or a window
into the things that they
have not accomplished.
The things that,
despite being age blank,
they still haven't accomplished.
And so that's interesting
because what it really
points to is two things.
One the extent to which much
of our feelings of happiness
are relative, in particular,
relative to our peers.
So there's that
social aspect again.
And the fact that
most of the time, we
are not very good at
orienting ourselves
in the longer arc of time.
We're pretty good
at knowing where
we are in the arc of a
day, or the arc of a week,
or the arc of a month, or even
a year, but that most of us
are not very good at
reflecting on where
we are in our life arc.
And, of course, most
of us don't know
how long we will
live anyway, but we
do have some general sense.
I mean, very few people
live past the age of 100.
Many people live to be 70 or 80.
And again, life span
is extending as far
as we know from year to year.
But, in general, people report
that on their birthdays.
And I should say these
are for birthdays
aged 25 or later, at
least in the studies
I was able to access.
I don't think that a
lot of three-year-olds
sit around comparing themselves
to other three-year-olds
and how well they're
doing or 12-year-olds.
You can imagine some people
might do that at 18, et cetera.
But it's really by the
mid-20s that people
start evaluating
themselves to their peers
in terms of life progression
and so-called milestones.
It's been argued that that's
one of the reasons why people
report lower affect,
lower levels of happiness
on their birthday.
Something that's a little
bit counterintuitive.
And, of course, there
are things that are
anti-correlated with happiness.
I'd be remiss if I didn't
mention a few of these.
That's longitudinal study,
the Harvard happiness project
has reported, for
instance, that people that
are chronic smokers of
nicotine and chronic
consumers of alcohol, in
particular alcoholics.
That is, people who
suffer from alcoholism
or what sometimes is called
alcohol use disorder that
is strongly anti-correlated
with happiness.
And I should also mention
that the family members,
and in particular,
the romantic partners
of people who are chronic
smokers and the partners
alcohol users, often
will report lower
levels of happiness.
Especially if they
themselves are not
chronic smokers or regular
consumers of alcohol.
So we've done episodes on
nicotine in particular,
and that touched on
smoking, of course.
And we've done an
episode on alcohol
and the effects of
alcohol on health.
Again, you can find
those at hubermanlab.com.
This study from the
Harvard happiness project
really has strong
data supporting
the fact that avoiding
being a nicotine smoker.
There are positive health
effects of nicotine
that are discussed in
the episode nicotine.
But being a-- but smoking
nicotine, in particular,
is counterproductive for
people's at least self-reported
happiness and certainly
overall health.
I think there's zero question
that smoking increases
cancers of different kinds.
And that alcohol consumption.
And in particular, alcohol
consumption beyond two
drinks per week.
Two drinks being the
typical volume of a beer,
a glass of wine or
cocktail, et cetera,
is detrimental for
various aspects of health.
And, of course, there
are other things
that you could imagine would
relate to a lack of happiness.
For instance, a major trauma.
Physical or emotional trauma.
That could include the loss
of a major relationship,
a death of a close one.
Being the victim of a violent
crime and things of that sort.
And yet it's been argued, in
fact, strongly argued that when
you look at people's levels
of happiness after a trauma,
that if you wait
about a year or so,
sometimes is even as
short as three months
after a trauma, that
people self-reported levels
of happiness are not
significantly lower than they
were prior to the trauma.
Now I very much want to
highlight, underline, and bold
and asterisks that
statement as one
that we really need
to explore carefully.
Because there are other data
that strongly point to the fact
that major life
traumas can severely
disrupt one sense of
happiness and well-being.
And I think as long as we're
going to have this discussion,
we should point to a useful
definition of trauma.
And the definition
that I'll paraphrase
is one that was supplied by a
former guest on the Huberman
Lab podcast, Dr. Paul Conti,
who's a psychiatrist who's
written a book called Trauma.
I personally think it's the
best book on trauma and tools
for alleviating trauma.
It's incredibly thorough, easy
to read, and well-informed.
And here again,
I'm paraphrasing,
but Dr. Conti describes trauma
as something that fundamentally
changes the way that our
brain and body function
in a way that makes
other aspects of living
more challenging.
Again, an event, either
emotional or physical,
or both, that fundamentally
changes the way
that our brain and/or
body, our nervous system,
and other organs function
in a way that prevents us
from enjoying daily activities.
And that could even be
ongoing distraction.
Traumas can create
rumination, or they
can create obsessive thought,
or they can create dissociation.
Any number of different things.
Again check out that
episode with Dr. Paul Conti
if you'd like to learn
more about trauma
and how it manifests.
But the idea that's
been put forth
by a number of researchers
in the field of happiness
that three months after
a major trauma, people
aren't reported that they
are feeling any less happy
than before the trauma,
that was surprising to me.
So I went into this
literature a bit more deeply.
One of the basis of that
general line of thinking
is a-- what I consider a now
classic and very important
and frankly excellent
talk that was
given by Professor Dan Gilbert
on the science of happiness.
You can find this on YouTube.
I say a classic one because
it was done some years ago.
It's received millions of views.
And one of the points that
he makes in that talk which
is grounded in
research carried out
by his laboratory and other
laboratories is that--
he poses a question.
He says you know,
let's do a quiz.
Would you rather be someone
who wins the lottery
and he shows a picture
of somebody who just won,
I think it was several
hundreds of millions of dollars
in the lottery, or was
recently made paraplegic lost
use of their legs?
And then goes on to
state that one year
after people have
won the lottery,
this major monetary windfall
versus have become paraplegic
is that their self-reported
levels of happiness
are the same.
Which I think is
incredibly surprising.
I heard this, and I immediately
thought of an experience
that I've had where I
teach a course at Stanford
School of Medicine on
neural regeneration.
And it's actually a course
that I attended some years
ago when I was a
post-doc at Stanford,
so well over a decade ago.
And we had-- excuse me.
We had an individual
come into the course.
This was an older gentleman.
So older meaning he
was in his early 70s.
And he had become paraplegic
fairly late in life
from a cycling accident.
And he was and is
an expert in what
it is to become a
paraplegic, of course,
because he had that experience,
but also because he spends
a lot of his time doing
volunteer work with people who
have become paraplegic
and have become paraplegic
at different ages.
And what he described to me
was that the overall outcomes
for people that are
rendered paraplegic
in terms of their mental health
and their physical well-being
and their management
of general life skills
scales with how early
they had that injury
and how long they had
the use of their limbs.
So it's not straightforward.
When I heard this result
described by Dr. Dan Gilbert,
that winning the lottery
and becoming paraplegic
basically don't impact
your levels of happiness
to any different degree when
people look back a year later,
I was pretty surprised
given my experience
of hearing this
lecture at Stanford.
So I thought, wow,
from what I understand.
Indeed, there are people
who are rendered paraplegic
and manage that
transition very easily.
It doesn't seem to disrupt
their feelings of well-being,
et cetera, but for
other people, it
can be severely disrupting
to their sense of well-being
and so on and so forth.
I went back and
examined these data.
And in fact, a
subsequent talk, it's
actually a podcast that
was given by Dr. Dan
Gilbert some years later.
So this would be
just a few years ago.
I think in 2019-- there
is a specific date
in which it was recorded
but just a few years ago.
And indeed, he corrects
himself in that podcast.
What he says is that he
misspoke in that earlier talk.
That the difference in
self-reported levels
of happiness for those that
have been rendered paraplegic
for versus those who've won the
lottery is not as great as one
would expect.
I think most people would expect
that being rendered paraplegic
would make people
far less happy.
That's the expectation,
I think, anyway.
And that people would
win the lottery,
at least for some
period of time,
would be far happier
than they were
prior to winning the lottery.
And especially given the
tremendous amount of money.
And again, the fact that
money can't buy happiness,
but that money does
indeed enable the ability
to buffer stress
provided people were
responsible with
that money and just
didn't blow it or spend
it all right away.
That they could start
to afford things
that they couldn't afford, not
just in terms of luxury items
but also the
ability to hire help
that would free up time that
would allow them to do anything
from travel that they couldn't
access before to meditate
if that was something that they
didn't have time to do before.
And so on and so forth.
So the result quote
unquote that winners
of the lottery and
recent paraplegics
have the same levels of
happiness is actually not true.
At least according to the
author of the original study.
Now what he did not point to is
the degree to which that is not
true, but he did point to
the direction of the result.
And the fact that people who are
rendered paraplegic, in fact,
are reporting
themselves as less happy
than they were prior
to their injury.
And certainly that their
levels of happiness
are lower than those that
simply won the lottery
hundreds of millions of
dollars, which I think
is the more intuitive result.
And so I think it's important
to be aware of that discrepancy
because it's something
that was lost
in the communication
around those results
the first time around.
And indeed, Dan Gilbert
is an excellent scientist
and was quite good about trying
to correct the narrative.
I myself, as a podcaster
who puts information
on the internet, know that
the challenges of correcting
narratives, especially of things
that came out some time ago,
we always attempt to
do this as best we
can, but not everyone that
saw that first video will
necessarily hear the discussion
that has happened subsequently.
So my hope is that Dr. Gilbert
will interpret me communicating
this now not as an
attempt to criticize him
but rather as an attempt
to praise his willingness
to try and correct the
narrative to be more accurate.
So to be very clear about what
this study did and didn't show.
And here, I'm going to
combine these results
with other studies
that I was able to find
that explored
similar phenomenon.
So major trauma, for instance.
Not necessarily becoming
paraplegic but traumas
of a different sort,
emotional traumas.
When you look at the whole
of those data, at least,
my read is that when people win
the lottery or acquire wealth
through inheritance, some
form of wealth acquisition
that is sudden and that wasn't
preceded by a specific effort
to gain that wealth, right.
Buying a lottery ticket
is a pretty quick thing.
Inheritance is something
that you simply
get by virtue of who you are,
not necessarily by effort.
Well, that led to increases
in self-reported happiness
compared to prior to the
inheritance of the lottery win,
but it wasn't as
substantial as you
might imagine if
you are approaching
the notion of
happiness simply from,
well, more money
equals more happiness.
And while it is true that people
who are rendered paraplegic
or who undergo psychological
traumas or physical traumas
of any various kind
are, and frankly,
are remarkably
resilient in many cases.
They can still manage to
go about life and work
and engage in
relationships, et cetera.
There is a visible decrease
in overall levels of happiness
and well-being,
in particular, if
the psychological
and physical trauma
renders their nervous system
different in a way that
impacts other major areas of
life and enjoyment for them.
And that's certainly true
one year out from the trauma.
So the point is that
we do need to reframe
this idea that whether or
not you win the lottery
or become paraplegic or
suffer some major trauma,
your levels of
happiness are going
to be the same three
months or a year later.
I don't think that's accurate.
And in fact, Dr. Dan
Gilbert emphasized
that that's not accurate
even in that initial study.
And I think it's
an important thing
to frame because that's
such a popular notion.
Or that that idea
combined with the idea
that increased earnings
don't make us happy
combined with the idea that
we are happy early in life
but then as more demands arise
in life, we become less happy,
and then we become happy again.
And that idea is
we already explored
is not necessarily true.
Frankly, I knew a lot
of teenagers and people
in their early 20s that
are pretty unhappy who
then become happier later as
they acquire more resources.
Sometimes distance,
let's be honest,
sometimes distance from
our family of origin
makes us more happy,
sometimes less so.
It's highly individual.
So I think those general themes
that we've heard over and over,
while they have merit and
they certainly stand up
in some of the more
powerful longitudinal
and short-term studies, there
is nuance, and in some cases,
there are now additional
data that are causing us
to revise those understandings.
Now there is an
important point, or I
should say the important
point, that we can really
credit Dan Gilbert and others
in the field of psychology with
and that we owe them a
great debt of gratitude
for is that we do
have far more control
over our levels of happiness
than we might think.
And many of the
things that reside
at that level of control.
That is, the things that we can
do and think and say and access
don't come from external things.
They don't come necessarily
from the acquisition of material
goods, but rather
there are things
that we can do that can allow
us to so-called synthesize
happiness.
And I think this is
one of the great gifts
of modern psychology is that--
Dan Gilbert and others, the
Harvard happiness project,
work at Yale and elsewhere.
There are excellent labs working
on happiness all over the US
and all over the world, frankly.
One of the great gifts
that they've supplied us
in the form of data
is that there really
are things that we can all
do and think and access
to allow ourselves to
so-called synthesize happiness.
Now, this notion of
synthesizing happiness,
or synthetic happiness
as it's sometimes called,
can sometimes ruffle
people's feathers a bit.
Because people immediately
flip to the idea
that, oh, you're
just going to tell
me to be grateful for what
I have or to just navel
gaze or just to
imagine that I'm happy.
But that's really not
what synthetic happiness
is about at all.
Synthetic happiness
actually has to do
with some really important
larger principles about the way
that our emotional
system and the way
that the reward systems of
our brain really function.
And they point to
important concepts
that we're going to now discuss.
Things like the hedonic
set point, for instance.
Or the dopamine
system of anticipation
of rewards versus receiving
words just as a brief insight
into that.
Our anticipation of
something positive
oftentimes leads to
greater increases
in the sorts of
neurochemicals that
support a state of
happiness and well-being
then the actual
acquisition of the thing
that we're trying to obtain.
And this goes back
to a theme I've
discussed a few times
before in this podcast,
in particular with my colleague
at Stanford School of Medicine,
Dr. Anna Lembke, who wrote the
fabulous book Dopamine Nation.
If you're interested in
dopamine and addiction,
in particular, that's
a wonderful clear,
and extremely informative read.
And if you're interested
in dopamine more
generally, not just in
the states of addiction
but in everyday life and
in pursuit and motivation,
The Molecule of More is an
excellent book related to that.
And as I mentioned
earlier, we have
this episode on dopamine
motivation and drive.
The notion of
synthetic happiness
is not simply about
imagining happiness,
or thinking about happiness
or anticipating happiness.
To some extent, it is,
but it relates to a number
of other important themes.
But it is grounded
very thoroughly
in the neurobiology
of dopamine rewards.
And I'll talk about some of that
neurobiology in a few moments.
But I want to take
a couple of minutes
and talk about what
synthetic happiness is
and what some of
the conditions are
for allowing us to
access the state
of so-called
synthetic happiness.
And I want to point
out at the outset
that synthetic happiness, while
it might sound synthetic A.K.A.
false, it's anything but.
It actually turns out to be
among the more and perhaps
the more potent
form of happiness
that we can all access.
And this is where themes
related to our control
over our own
internal state really
become not only valid
but very powerful.
So, for instance, Dr.
Dan Gilbert and others
have explored how opportunity
and choice, that is, freedom
can and can't lead to
states of happiness.
And the results of those studies
are very solid and, frankly,
very surprising.
Until you understand the
results, and once you do,
I think you will immediately
see areas of your own life
that you can start to
access more happiness, again
genuine happiness,
simply by framing
certain choices in
a particular way
and maybe even by
eliminating choices.
Now I'd like to focus
on the research aimed
at understanding what increases
our levels of happiness.
And I'd like to frame this
under the umbrella of two
major themes.
The first theme is
so-called natural happiness.
Natural happiness is the sort
of happiness that most of us
are familiar with.
So the kind of
happiness that we expect
to have if we, for
instance, complete a degree.
Hopefully, a degree in a topic
meaningful and interesting
to us but a degree nonetheless.
Or we find a mate.
Hopefully, a mate that we
enjoy spending time with.
Or, for instance, making a
certain income or finding
work that we enjoy
on a regular basis.
All of those are
forms of happiness
that, from a very early
time in development,
we are taught exist.
For instance, even
when we are very young,
we are told that our
birthday is coming
and that we are going
to get presents,
and those presents
are going to be
focused on knowledge of
things that we already enjoy.
So if you're a little
kid, and you like trucks,
or you're a little kid
and you like dolls,
you can sort of expect that
those gifts will bring you
some level of joy or happiness.
And while that's a
small child example,
that general notion
of natural happiness
is, of course, one that
persists into adolescence,
into young adulthood,
and into adulthood.
And we quite understandably
come to associate
this feeling of joy or happiness
with the receiving of things
or the acquisition of
things, whether by effort,
by gift, by inheritance,
or some other form.
So that's natural happiness.
And yet, as I mentioned
a little bit earlier,
there's also this notion
of synthetic happiness.
And some of the more interesting
and exciting research
in the fields of psychology
and, in fact, neuroscience
point to this idea of
synthetic happiness
as at least as powerful
a source of happiness
as natural happiness.
Again, at least as powerful
and perhaps even more powerful.
And of course, one has to take a
slightly different view of what
happiness is in order to accept
this idea that we can create
happiness for ourselves,
but that doesn't mean
that the whole notion
of synthetic happiness
is merely a passive
one where all we
do is sit back and imagine being
happy and then we are happy.
For better or for worse,
our nervous systems
and our neurochemistry
simply don't work that way.
In fact, synthetic
happiness has almost always
been understood as
something that we
have to put some effort
toward achieving.
But, and this is an
important thing to point out,
synthetic happiness
also requires
that certain situational
or environmental conditions
be met.
A good example of this is some
of the work by Gillian Mandich,
or I should say Dr.
Gillian Mandich, who's
done some interesting work on
the conditions for creating
happiness within our mind and
in our overall state of being.
And she's been involved in a
number of different studies.
But one of the ones that I
found particularly interesting
is one in which they explored
different types of music
and other aspects of
environmental settings.
So you bring subjects
to the laboratory
play them different
types of music.
There are, in fact,
certain aspects of music
that can create different
states of mind sadness,
happiness, anticipation.
In fact, there are
certain patterns of music
that can reliably induce
anticipation of the fear
and anxiety base type.
So, for instance,
think the movie Jaws.
If you recall, for those
of you who have seen Jaws,
there's this ongoing
theme music any time
the shark might be present in
the water or in a given scene.
That essentially goes [HUMMING]
Now for the musicians
out there, this
has basis in things
like tritones and things
that are understood
from the mathematics
and the musical side.
And from the
neuroscience side, are
known to create a neural
state of anticipation.
Yeah, a neural state
of anticipation
and not necessarily
a positive one.
And indeed, there are
other patterns of music
that involve up tones.
Think some of the music
that's typically been used
in cartoons of various sorts.
There's a long history of this.
Indeed there's a
whole literature
of psychological and now even
a smaller but still interesting
literature on the
neuroscience of how
certain patterns
of music can induce
a state of joy and joyful
anticipation, in particular.
A lot of those patterns
of music are incorporated
into so-called happy
cartoons and Disney movies
and things of that sort.
In any case, Dr. Mandich and
others have explored how music,
in particular, but other
features of the environment can
or cannot induce
states of happiness.
And the basic takeaway
from those studies
is that while having a
certain environmental sound,
musical tone, or visual feature
to a given space, a room,
is necessary for a
state of happiness,
it is not alone sufficient.
What is required is that
individuals not only
be placed into an
environment that
contains music or visual items
or a combination of music
and visual items that
can induce states
of joy or happiness or
positive anticipation,
but that they also are given
some sort of instruction
or instruction manual as
how to synthesize happiness
inside of that environment.
This is important
because what this
says is that our ability to
create states of happiness
is dependent on our environment
but also requires effort
from us.
That also makes sense as to why
when we are under conditions
of deprivation.
So it could be
social deprivation
or financial deprivation.
Or even for people that are
very sensitive to whether.
There are a certain number
of individuals, about 30%
of people, who report feeling
very, very low under conditions
where the sky is overcast.
Especially if it's been
overcast for a number of days.
The so-called seasonal
affective depression.
Those individuals,
by the way, can often
receive tremendous
benefits in terms
of elevating their mood if they
make an effort to get sunlight.
And if they can't get sunlight,
artificial light of the sort
that we talked about earlier.
But in any case,
there are a number
of people that are profoundly
negatively influenced
by the lack of positive
visual and auditory cues
in their environment.
But for most people,
we are in what
I would call a
dynamic relationship
with our environment.
Our environment has
an effect on our mood.
But the research
indicates that we also
need to make some sort of
effort toward being happy.
Now effort toward being
happy is a very vague term.
So let's better
define what that is.
In the case of Dr.
Mandich's work,
this took the form of
doing so-called happiness
inventories, right.
That can be focusing on things
that one is grateful for,
things that they
particularly enjoy.
This is somewhat of a
gratitude-type practice
but includes some
other features as well
that are more focused
on the things that
bring you meaning and actually
engaging in the things
that bring you meaning.
So if you're trying
to think about how
to improve your levels
of happiness, what
this research essentially
says is that you would
be smart to try and adjust
your home environment,
adjust your work environment
so that it is cheerful to you.
Maybe that means a plant.
For me, in my laboratory,
one of the things
that was really critical
that I had as a postdoc
and in my own laboratory when
I first started my lab was I
love aquaria.
So I had multiple fish tanks.
In fact, people in my laboratory
were always rolling their eyes.
Why do we have to have all these
fish tanks with all these--
I like freshwater tanks,
not saltwater tanks,
for reasons that
aren't interesting
for this discussion.
But freshwater tanks with discus
fish, for instance, to me,
are just beautiful.
They make me happy.
I just enjoy them.
Music is a complicated
thing in laboratories
because it's a shared space.
So headphones are the
general requirement.
But having either silence
if you love silence.
And I happen to like
working in silence
or listening to
certain forms of music.
I do also use the 40
Hertz binaural beats.
Or I particularly like listening
to Glenn Gould while I work
or listening to whale
song, believe it or not,
while I work because it doesn't
have any structure that I
can follow.
I don't speak whale,
and so I can't follow.
But it sort of fills the space
in a way that I find pleasant.
And I've put substantial
amounts of effort
into making my laboratory
spaces and my office
spaces, my workspaces,
nice places to be.
Now I had no
knowledge of this work
from Dr. Mandich and others
at the time when I did that.
But what I found was
that over the years,
I was challenged in maintaining
a kind of elevated mood
while working in a laboratory,
not because I didn't thoroughly
enjoy the work, I love doing
experiments with my hands,
and I loved being in lab, but
at least the labs that I was
in as a graduate student
and post-doc there
were no windows so I wasn't
getting adequate sunshine.
The windows that we
didn't open, so I
wasn't getting a lot of fresh
air, and so on and so forth.
So I've personally
found it very valuable
to create an environment
both at work and at home
that I find aesthetically
pleasant, at least in some way
or another.
And I realize people
have varying levels
of control over their
aesthetic environment.
Certainly, the
auditory environment
can be controlled nowadays
through the use of headphones
if you're allowed to use those.
So, for instance, using music
or using background sound
that you find very
pleasant combined
with a concerted
effort on your part
to create states of happiness
by hopefully doing work that's
meaningful to you or at least is
leading to meaningful outcomes.
We'll talk a little
bit more about that.
But these happiness
inventories also
turn out to be interesting and
important sources of creating
so-called synthetic happiness.
And we'll also talk
about other ways
that one can create elevated
levels of synthetic happiness.
And I realize the word
synthetic probably
draws up connotations
of false happiness
or contrived happiness.
I wish instead of calling
it synthetic happiness.
They had called it
self-created or self-directed
happiness or something of
that sort because then it
wouldn't sound as false.
Because it's simply not false.
It leads to the
same, as far as we
know, identical neurochemical
and psychological states
of happiness as
natural happiness.
And might even be
more persistent
than natural happiness.
It certainly, is more
under our control.
But the key point
is that environment
and self-directed work at
being happy are both important,
and they interact
with one another.
So if you're somebody who
has a hard time synthesizing
happiness through
any of the methods
that we talk about today, don't
consider yourself deficient.
It could very well be that the
environment that you're in,
social environment or
physical environment,
or auditory environment,
is simply not
conducive to
synthesizing happiness.
And for that reason,
I think the work
of Gillian Mandich and
colleagues and others
in the field is tremendously
important because it removes us
from this pressure to
just synthesize happiness
from within despite
our circumstances.
I think many of us have heard
of the incredible stories
of people like Viktor
Frankl or Nelson Mandela who
were stripped of
their freedom and yet
managed to maintain some
sense of positive anticipation
or at least some
sense of identity
that allowed them to still
access forms of happiness.
Those are highly unique
situations, of course.
And they speak to the
power of the human psyche
for synthesizing happiness
and certainly for synthesizing
a sense that there might
be a future and to live
into that future.
In their cases, incredibly
impressive ways.
But I think for most everybody,
the environment that we're in
has a powerful
impact on our mood.
And some people
more than others.
I know people that are perfectly
happy with blank walls.
No pictures on the walls.
Other people
benefit tremendously
from having photos or plants
in their environment and so on.
You really have to determine
what's needed for you
and do your best
to try and place
those things into
your environment,
or rather, place yourself
into an environment that
is conducive to you
synthesizing your happiness.
In fact, the
powerful interaction
between our environment
and our own ability
to generate certain
kinds of emotions
is well established
not just for happiness
but for things like gratitude.
So, for instance, there's a
classic study from AMES A-M-E-S
in 2004 that was
focused on gratitude.
And we've had an episode
on gratitude before.
The basic takeaway
of that episode
is that it turns out
receiving gratitude
is a more powerful
stimulus for the release
of neurochemicals and activation
of brain areas associated
with so-called
prosocial behaviors
and feelings of well-being,
including happiness.
But also observing stories in
the form of movies or books
or other narratives of
other people receiving help
is also a very powerful
stimulus for gratitude.
Also, giving gratitude
is very powerful but not
as powerful as receiving
gratitude, at least
that's what the research
says, or observing
powerful exchanges of gratitude
between other individuals.
What the study
from AMES showed is
that gratitude as a state
of mind and as an emotion
does not exist in a vacuum.
It's not independent
of our surroundings.
So, for instance,
just writing down
all the things you're
grateful for while it
has some positive impact,
the impact of that
or receiving gratitude
or observing gratitude
is far more potent, right.
Bigger increases in
happiness and feelings
of well-being and indeed
neurochemicals and activation
of brain areas associated
with happiness and well-being
when there's a reciprocity.
When the person receiving
understands something
about the person
that's giving to them
and understands that the
person is giving genuinely,
for instance.
So there's an
environmental interaction.
It's not just about
receiving, it's
receiving from somebody that you
know genuinely wants to give.
And likewise, for the
giver in that equation,
the feelings of
well-being are far greater
when the person
receiving whatever
it is money, food, assistance
in some form or another.
Could be physical
assistance, et cetera.
When the giver has knowledge
that the person receiving it
genuinely needed the thing
that they are receiving.
So the important finding within
the research, again and again,
is that happiness doesn't
exist in a vacuum.
It's partially our
own responsibility
to synthesize happiness.
You know, I was told that many
times you're like happiness
is in your head.
Well, yes, indeed,
it's in your head,
but it's also dependent
on interactions
with your environment.
Physical environment and
social environment, and so on.
Likewise, gratitude is something
that we can create inside of us
right through gratitude
lists and appreciation,
or we can give both
powerful sources
of evoking neurochemical changes
associated with gratitude
and happiness and well-being.
But it, too, doesn't
exist in a vacuum.
There's a much greater
positive effect
when we have knowledge about
why the giver is giving us
something or that
the person receiving
something is going to benefit
tremendously from receiving it.
So I'm highlighting
this because I
think that when we hear
about synthetic happiness,
there's a kind of automatic
erasing of context
that tends to occur.
And in fact, if you were to
peruse the various videos
online or papers that exist
on PubMed around happiness
and synthetic happiness,
in particular,
you would come away
with the impression
that synthetic happiness
is just something
that we're supposed to
snap our fingers in access
or perhaps do very
specific things in access.
But while that is true,
context really matters.
And I think that's
an important point.
Much in the same way
that the point needs
to be made that while money
doesn't buy happiness,
money can buffer stress
and certainly offer
opportunities that can
provide opportunities
for more happiness.
So I think we are starting to
arrive at a general theme here,
which is that nothing related
to our mood exists in isolation.
And in fact, that leads
me to a discussion
of one of the major
scientific findings
in the realm of what sorts
of mindsets and behaviors
can, in fact, lead to happiness.
And this is a paper that
was published in 2008.
Even though that might
seem like a while ago,
it forms the basis for a
large amount of literature
that followed.
It's a very
interesting literature.
This is work from Elizabeth
Dunn and colleagues
and was published in
the Journal Science.
Which, again, is one of the sort
of three apex journals, Nature,
Science, Cell, I always say
is sort of the Super Bowl, NBA
championships, and Stanley
Cup of scientific publishing--
very, very stringent in
terms of the number of papers
they let in.
Very few, that is.
And the title of this
paper makes fairly obvious
what the paper is about.
The title of the paper
is "spending money
on others promotes happiness".
And I know a number of you
probably hear that title
and think, oh boy, here we go.
He's going to tell us that
giving away all our money
is going to make us happier
than receiving money.
And I promise you, that is not
what I'm going to tell you.
But nonetheless, this is
a very interesting study,
and it's one that I
think that we really
ought to pay attention to.
Because what the
study is based on
is the fact that income,
provided one's income
meets a certain
level of basic needs,
indeed has been shown to
have only a weak effect
on overall happiness.
OK?
So quoting from the paper
in the first paragraph,
quote "income has a reliable
but surprisingly weak
effect on happiness
within nations".
Within nations just
mean they looked
at this in not just
the United States,
but a number of other
places, as well.
"Particularly once
basic needs are met."
OK, so if that's the
case, then what aspects
of money and having money
are related to happiness?
Certainly, there are people
who have a lot of money who
are very happy.
Certainly, there are people
who have very little money
who are very happy.
And of course, the
reverse is also true.
There are plenty of people
who don't have very much money
who are unhappy,
and in fact, there
are people who have a lot of
money who are very unhappy.
A point that whenever
it's made often
leads those with less money
to kind of roll their eyes,
because the assumption is more
money does increase happiness.
And in fact, it doesn't.
And later, we'll get back to
this idea of whether or how one
acquired their money has
any impact on whether
or not that money increases
their happiness or not.
Let's kind of earmark
that for later.
In the meantime, let's
talk a little bit more
about the findings
in this paper.
This paper is
interesting, because what
it did is it explored something
called prosocial spending.
Prosocial spending
is a phenomenon
where people are taking
a certain portion
of their income, and they
are giving it to others.
Often for causes or for
things that they think
are important to see
happen in the world
or change in the world.
That could be a hungry
individual having access
to food or medical care.
It could be for
environmental causes.
It could be for animal wellness.
It could be for any number
of different things.
It could even be
giving somebody money
so that they can buy themselves
a gift or giving somebody money
and not having any understanding
or expectation of what they're
going to do with the money.
Again, one of the central
themes around gratitude
is that while
receiving is great,
giving is also great in terms of
increasing sense of well-being.
And one of the more
important features to that
is when we give, either
in the form of words
or in the form of
resources, knowledge
that the person
receiving benefits
from that in some
real way, greatly
increases the
chance that there's
an increase in happiness for the
giver, as well as the receiver.
Again, that's a note
about gratitude,
but not an insignificant one
as it relates to the study.
So what the study found was
that higher prosocial spending
was associated
with significantly
greater happiness.
This was a very statistically
significant effect.
And they found that the
effects of income and prosocial
spending were independent
and similar in magnitude.
Independent and
similar in magnitude.
I'll explain what
that means for those
of you that might be confused
by that statement in just
a moment.
Whereas, quote, "personal
spending remained
unrelated to happiness".
So what this study
basically found
was if people are allotted
a certain amount of money
to give away, and one
adjusts for overall income,
and this is
important, because you
could imagine that for some
individual giving away $2,000
might represent a
significant portion
of their yearly
or monthly income.
And for another individual it
might represent a tiny fraction
of their income.
But when you adjust for
income level, what you find
is that people who
gave away money
benefited tremendously in
terms of their own increase
in happiness.
In fact, quote, "employees who
devoted more of their bonuses
to prosocial spending,
that is giving way
more money, experience greater
happiness after receiving
the bonus, and the manner in
which they spent that bonus was
a more important predictor
of their happiness
than the size of
the bonus itself".
This was an actual
experiment they ran
with real income, real money.
I'm going to read
that again just
to make sure it hits
home, because I found
this to be really impactful.
"Employees who devoted a
greater fraction of their bonus
to prosocial spending, that is
giving away money to others,
experienced greater happiness
after receiving the bonus.
And the manner in
which they spent
that bonus was a more important
predictor of their happiness
than the size of
the bonus itself."
So the actual bonus, the
receiving of the money,
led to greater increases in
happiness if they gave it away.
And the act of giving
it away itself,
led to greater
increases in happiness
than receiving the bonus.
So it's a twofer,
as you might say.
So the takeaway from this
study and studies like it,
I think is pretty obvious that
to the extent that we can.
And again, when I say to
the extent that we can,
this means whatever
percentage of our own income
that we can afford to give away,
or if we don't have income,
the percentage of our effort.
I mean this is about money,
but it's also about effort.
We can help others, right?
You can serve in food kitchens,
you can do community gardening,
you can pick up trash, you
can do any number of things.
You can assist a
neighbor with child care
or you can assist a neighbor
who is physically less
able to retrieve their
paper, et cetera, et cetera.
The point is that
giving resources,
certainly in the form of money,
but also in the form of effort
and time, is immensely
beneficial for synthesizing
our own happiness.
That is for the
giver, us, to increase
our levels of happiness.
But the degree of increase
in our own happiness
is proportional in
some way to the extent
to which the person receiving
actually needed that help
and registers that help.
Excellent research
also points to the fact
that another potent
way to synthesize
happiness, that is to create
genuine states of happiness
in ourselves, is to leverage
the so-called focus system.
Or rather, I should say to
de-emphasize the tendency
of our minds to wander.
There's an excellent paper
on this, also published
in the Journal Science.
This is now a classic paper.
I talked a little bit about it
in the episode on meditation,
but for those of you
that did or perhaps
didn't hear that episode, I
just want to briefly touch
on a few aspects of the paper.
And in particular, a few aspects
of the paper that I didn't talk
about previously.
And the title of
this paper, again,
is a very
straightforward in terms
of telling you what it's about.
And that is, "A wandering
mind is an unhappy mind"
by Killingsworth and Gilbert.
This paper was published
in Science in 2010,
and we will provide
a link to the paper.
This is frankly, a
very interesting paper.
This paper involved
several subjects,
or I should say,
2,250 adult subjects.
And what they were
able to do was
to contact these
subjects while they
were going about living
their daily lives
and ask them both
what they were doing
and what they were feeling.
Some additional questions
that they asked them,
but they were able to
establish whether or not
people were watching television
or doing housework or working
on a home computer or resting or
listening to music, et cetera,
in their natural environment.
So this is outside
the laboratory.
And they were able to
assess to what extent
those people were happy
or unhappy or neutral,
or had some other
emotional state at the time
when they were engaging in any
number of different activities.
And they assessed whether or
not those individuals were also
focused on or focused away
from whatever activity they
were engaging in.
And the takeaways from
this study are many,
but for sake of today's
discussion, what
I think is especially
interesting
is that regardless
of whether or not
people were engaging in
activities that they enjoyed
or not, the tendency for their
mind to wander from an activity
predicted lower
levels of happiness
than if they tended to be
focused on the activity
they were engaged in.
Now that itself
should be surprising.
I mean, what that says
is that even if somebody
was engaged in activity
like cleaning their house
or doing homework or reading
something that they weren't
enjoying, if they were focused
on what they were doing,
they tended to report as happier
than if their mind was drifting
elsewhere.
Now this also points to the
idea that perhaps our minds
drift to unpleasant thoughts
more than pleasant thoughts.
But they also addressed
that in the study.
Point I'd like to
make here is quote
"although people's
minds were more
likely to wander
to pleasant topics
than to unpleasant topics"
and there the difference
is pretty significant.
People's minds tended to
wander to pleasant topics
about 43% of the time as
opposed to unpleasant topics
about 27% of the time.
Or to neutral topics and the
remaining 31% of samples.
"People were no
happier when thinking
about pleasant topics than
about their current activity".
Think about that.
"People were no
happier than when
thinking about pleasant things
then their current activity".
In fact, the mere focus
on what they were doing
was more powerful
than anything else,
even if they didn't enjoy
what they were doing.
So they go on here to say, quote
"although negative moods are
known to cause mind
wandering, I now
see strongly suggested that
mind wandering was generally
the cause, the
cause, and not merely
the consequence of unhappiness."
So there are a lot of
aspects of this study that
are worth going into.
But the major takeaway, or the
one that perhaps we should all
be most concerned with,
is that when we are not
focused on what we
are doing, we tend
to be far less happy
than when we are
focused on what we are doing.
Even if what we are
doing is something
that we don't deem
very pleasant.
And certainly, if we
are engaged in something
that we consider very pleasant
and we are very focused on,
well then our levels of
happiness are the highest.
That's sort of obvious.
But what this really speaks
to is the tremendous power
of building our ability to
focus on what we're doing.
And to stay present
to what we are doing.
Now this whole notion
of staying present
is one that itself is a
little bit complicated.
And in the episode on meditation
I talked a little bit about
whether or not it's
beneficial to be
present to our
internal state, or that
is our inter receptive state.
Our feelings of our heart
rate and how full or empty
our gut feels or our state of
being from our skin inward,
or whether or not
we should focus
on being present to things in
our immediate surroundings.
Both our versions
of being quote,
unquote "present"
as you can imagine.
But in the one case,
we're focused internally,
in the other we're
focused externally,
and of course, most
of the time it's
some combination of the two.
But what this study
really says is
that any practice that can
powerfully impact our ability
to remain present in the
activity we are engaged in,
could even be a
phone call, could
be texting for that matter,
could be social media
for that matter, right?
We're not placing judgment
on the activity here.
In fact, what we're
really talking about
is the enormous happiness
increasing value
of being present to what
we're doing regardless
of what we are doing.
And a practice that's known to
be beneficial for increasing
our ability to focus
is, among other things,
a short meditation practice.
In fact, work from Wendy
Suzuki's lab at NYU,
again, Wendy's been a
guest on this podcast.
Her laboratory has
shown that even
a very brief meditation
of about 13 minutes,
and this would be the
sort of quote unquote
"classic" type of
meditation of eyes
closed, focusing
on one's breathing.
Even a very brief meditation
of just 13 minutes
or so done consistently,
so ideally, every day.
But I have to imagine that
even if you skip a day,
there are still benefits.
That sort of
meditation can greatly
enhance one's ability to focus.
In her studies,
that was also shown
that sort of brief meditation
could also greatly enhance
mood and sleep and
various aspects
of cognitive performance.
And work from my laboratory,
in collaboration with Dr. David
Spiegel at Stanford,
department of psychiatry
has shown that even briefer
meditations of even just five
minutes per day can have fairly
outsized positive effects
on a number of different
parameters, as well.
Those very brief
types of meditations,
because they really are
focusing and more accurately,
I should say,
refocusing exercises.
When you do that sort of
activity of closing your eyes
and forcing yourself
to focus and refocus
on your breath and
internal state,
that is directing your
perception inward.
Or if you choose, you
could deliberately
focus your perception
on some external object
or sound, for that matter.
When one does that, the circuits
of the brain involved in focus
dramatically improve.
That is they rewire and
increase their ability for you
to achieve focus.
Many of us have heard about
meditation, many of us
think about meditation as
a "mindfulness" exercise.
Mindfulness in quotes, because
that itself needs definition.
But I prefer to view
meditations of the sort
that I just described
as perceptual or focus
based training, which is
really what the data point to.
Notions around consciousness
and states of mind
are very hard to define, but
it's very clear that even
a 5 minute a day or ideally,
an up to a 13 minute a day
meditation can greatly
increase our ability to focus.
And based on the
findings in this paper,
"A wandering mind is an unhappy
mind" also make it very clear
that the ability to
refocus again and again
and again on what we're
doing throughout our day,
regardless of what
we're doing, can
have a very dramatic, in fact,
a statistically significant
increase on our levels
of overall happiness.
So what else does
the research tell us
we can do to increase our
levels of genuine happiness?
Well, it's very clear based
on the longitudinal study
from Harvard, as well
as the Yale happiness
project and the work of
numerous laboratories in the US
and elsewhere, that
quality social connection
is extremely powerful
in terms of its ability
to increase our
levels of happiness.
What is quality
social connection?
Quality social connection
falls into a number
of different bins.
This can be romantic connection,
this can be friendship,
this can even be
coworker or just
daily superficial
interaction type connections.
That's surprising
to a lot of people,
because I think a lot of people
hear quality social connection
and they think
deep conversation.
But it's very clear
from the research
that oftentimes our
conversations with people
that we are closest to are
actually quite shallow.
If you think about it, if you've
been in a romantic relationship
or a friendship for a
long period of time,
or maybe even a sibling
relationship or other family
relationship, much of
what you talk about
is fairly superficial
or fairly trivial.
In fact, it's often a
sharing of the trivial day
to day things between two
people or through groups
of people that
leads to the feeling
that people are really
connected to one another.
In particular, if it's involving
shared experiences of any kind,
good or bad.
So there's an extensive
literature on social connection
and how to build
social connection.
This certainly
should be the topic
of a full episode
of this podcast
in the not too distant future.
But because social connection
can have such a powerful impact
on our states of happiness
and overall well-being,
I want to emphasize a few
features of social connection
that I think most people
might not appreciate.
Once again, when we hear
quality social connection,
I think most of us tend to
think about deep, meaningful
conversation or long walks
on the beach or camping trips
together or travel together.
And while all of those
certainly qualify
as wonderful opportunities
for social connection,
opportunities for
quality social connection
are certainly not limited to
those kinds of interactions.
In fact, I can recall times
in my graduate career,
so this would be times when I
was living in the laboratory.
Because that was a significant
portion of my graduate years.
And one of the more important
social connections for me
was the staff that worked there
in the wee hours of the night
and that came in very
early in the morning.
So one of the more regular
social connections I had is I
would brush my teeth in
the hallway bathroom.
And there was no one else
really around at that time,
except for the
janitors that tended
to leave early in the morning.
They had worked a good
portion of the night.
Or that were arriving
very early in the day.
And the fact that I would
see them on a regular basis
and maybe exchange a few
words about their work
or their families or the
holidays, actually for me,
became very meaningful.
In part, because my social
connections at the time
were really limited to
only social connections
that I had in the
context of work.
Now some people might look
at my schedule at that time
and look at my life at
that time and say, well,
that was very unhealthy.
You were lacking in
certain number of ways.
But frankly, looking
back, and at the time,
and I know this because
I journaled at the time,
I was exceedingly
happy, at least
for that stage of my life.
At that stage of
my life, I wanted
to be focused primarily on
doing experiments and immersing
myself in my
scientific training.
And for me, the even seemingly
insignificant interactions
of talking to the
janitor in the morning
or some of the other regular
staff was not insignificant.
In fact, for me it
was very significant.
And over the holidays when
their hours were reduced,
I actually missed
them quite a lot.
And even as I talk
about this, I can
recall the feelings
of well-being
of just seeing familiar faces.
And that brings up an
important point, which
is there's quite extensive
literature pointing to the fact
that when we see faces,
especially faces in the morning
and in the late afternoon,
there is a positive impact
on the emotional circuitry.
Or I should say, the
circuitry of the brain that
underlies emotional well-being.
And that shouldn't
come as surprising.
We as old world primates,
much like other primates,
are very dependent on faces
and facial expressions
in terms of registering
our own place in life
and our emotional state.
Now the origins
of this are many.
In particular, we
have a brain area,
it's actually called
the fusiform face gyrus.
This is an area
of the brain that
was largely
discovered by a woman
by Nancy Kanwisher at MIT.
And the Kanwisher lab
has done extensive work
showing that this
brain area that's
dedicated to the processing
of faces, and not just faces
in real life, but faces
on computer screens
and elsewhere, are
intimately tied
to areas of the brain that are
associated with emotionality.
That's actually a work
from another laboratory,
Dorsal's laboratory at
Caltech, now at Uc Berkeley,
has shown that this
face processing
area in the brain in both
non-human primates and primates
is directly linked to
the areas of our brain
that associate with
anxiety and fear.
But also, areas
of the brain that
are associated with well-being.
So it comes as no
surprise that when
we see faces, in
particular, friendly faces,
even if we have just brief
interactions with those faces,
and even if no
words are exchanged,
that creates the
sense of social bond.
And it creates a sense
of predictability.
And I raise this again because
I think a lot of people
think that social
connection always
has to come in the form of
close friendships, which
of course are wonderful.
Or close romantic relationships,
which of course, are wonderful.
Or close family relationships,
But as we'll soon discuss
in our model of happiness,
or how to achieve
happiness based
on the scientific
literature in a few minutes,
social connection can and
should come in various forms.
And when I say
various forms, I mean
forms of brief interaction,
more superficial interaction,
and forms of deeper interaction.
All of those are relevant
to our states of happiness.
And there's research to
support that daily interactions
with somebody at a cafe or
just a brief hello or a smile.
Provided that we
are both present,
or we make the effort to be
present to those interactions,
however brief they are,
can have a positive effect
on people's overall well-being.
And not just in that
moment, but consistently.
Evidenced by the
fact, I think, that
when I look back on
those years of working
long hours in the laboratory and
essentially restricting myself
either to exercising,
sleeping, eating or working.
Again, that's what I wanted
at that stage of my life.
Certainly, not the way
I live my life now.
But that's what I wanted
that stage of my life.
That even those
seemingly insignificant
social interactions
were important to me
and had a potent
impact on increasing
my level of happiness.
And frankly, still do.
And I feel that right now.
That said, I think all of us
can appreciate the immense value
of social connection that is of
the more long lasting, and for
lack of a better
word, richer type,
whether or not that is with
siblings or with parents
or with friends or
with romantic partners.
For that reason, I want
to emphasize a little bit
about what
constitutes connection
and what constitutes
social connection.
There are basically two
forms of social connection
that have been studied
and I'll review both,
as it relates to increasing
our levels of happiness.
And the first one is
presence and eye contact,
and the second is
physical contact.
So in terms of presence
and eye contact
there's been a lot
of studies about
whether or not people
exchange direct eye contact
during conversation or not,
dictating whether or not
each individual in
that interaction
feels as if they
had a connection.
Now again, keep in mind that
while we think of connection
as relating to some deep
or meaningful conversation,
and oftentimes that
can be the case.
Think for instance, an excellent
therapist patient relationship.
Or an excellent
romantic relationship.
Or an excellent friendship
where you really feel
heard and understood, or
at least to the extent
that people are
willing to explore
certain topics with you.
You're willing to hear
them and listen really
carefully for what
they're saying,
and they're willing to hear and
listen to what you're saying
in an attempt to understand.
That certainly can enhance
the sense of social connection
leading to what people would
call social bonds leading
to increased happiness.
But eye contact is also known
to be an important feature.
The thing about eye
contact is that most people
assume that a lot
of eye contact,
and in fact,
ongoing eye contact,
is critical to a
sense of connection.
And in fact, that's
not the case.
There's a recent paper that I
find really interesting that
was published in
Proceedings of the National
Academy of Sciences in 2021.
The title of this
paper is "Eye contact
marks the rise and fall
of shared attention
in conversation".
I find this paper interesting
for a number of reasons.
First of all, my laboratory
works on internal states
and vision, so it
relates directly
to the work that
my laboratory does.
But also, that it
violates what I thought
was a general rule of
social connection, which
is this idea that two people
needed to be focused on one
another, that is
looking at one another
directly and fairly consistently
throughout a conversation
in order for the feeling
of connection to emerge.
But it turns out
that's not the case.
And in fact, just to give
you the takeaway and then
I'll flesh it out a little bit
with some data, eye contact,
or I should say mutual
eye contact, so two people
registering the presence of the
other person looking at them.
You're looking at me
and I'm looking at you.
If you're watching
this on YouTube,
then perhaps we are actually
doing this at that moment.
And if you're
listening, just know
that I'm looking
directly into the camera
as I'm saying this
at this moment.
If we were to be looking
directly at one another,
that, it turns out,
signals the next step,
which is that it's very likely
that we will each both look
away.
And that turns out to
be a way in which we set
and reset attention continually
during conversation.
So again, I really
like this study
because of the high fidelity.
The high temporal precision.
That is, the precision
over time at which they
looked at eye contact and
engagement of attention
between individuals.
And they did this by looking
at things like pupil size
and of course
where the eyes were
looking and so on and so forth.
The basic takeaway of this
study was the following.
And here I'm quoting
from the study.
Quote "Rather than
maximizing shared attention,
good conversation
may require shifts
in and out of shared states
accompanied by eye contact".
So what this basically
says is that when
two people are
involved in a very,
let's call it an
intimate conversation,
but the word intimate
should not be misconstrued
to mean something about
intimacy or sexual intimacy
or physical intimacy.
Just a conversation
in which both people
feel present to the
conversation and focused
on that conversation and that
conversation and its contents
only.
The tendency is for people
to take turns talking,
although sometimes,
depending on the individuals
they might interrupt
more or less.
Again, interrupting can
be a sign of interest,
it doesn't always have
to be rude, by the way.
But they're sharing information.
Hopefully, about a common
topic or set of topics.
They will at some moment
look at one another.
That's what the study shows.
And that after briefly
gazing directly at one
another, attention peaks,
and then they will look away,
and attention will get reduced.
And then the
conversation consists
of a series of focusing back
on one another with their eyes,
and then focusing off,
focusing on and focusing off.
And those mutual
eye contact moments
actually predict the
breaking of attention.
So it's this ramping up
of attention and braking
of attention.
Ramping of attention and
braking of attention.
I think these are important
results because they violate
this stereotype or assumption
that deep social connection
of the sort leading
to happiness always
involves ongoing eye
contact or ongoing focus.
Just as with meditation, just
as with any activity, frankly,
we undergo shifts in
attention and focus.
That is focus ramps up and
then it breaks, and then
it re-engages.
It ramps up it breaks,
and then it re-engages.
And that, it turns
out, is the basis
of in-depth connected
conversation.
So for those of you that
are interested in creating
social connection
in any context,
and in particular for sake
of increasing happiness,
because it's very clear
that social connections,
even if they are fairly
superficial social connections,
can increase our
sense of happiness.
Seeing faces is important.
Ideally, faces in person,
although I suppose these days,
over Zoom or over other
screen type medium
would be a close second.
But the point is that if you
want to increase happiness
you need to have quality
social connections.
And if you want to have
quality social connections
you need to be
present and engage
in those social connections.
And that requires a viewing
of each other's faces,
ideally, which is not to say
that a phone call or text
exchange can't be meaningful.
But that faces are really
the most powerful way
to engage in social contact.
And that eye contact, not
consistent eye contact,
but eye contact of the sort
that builds up and then breaks
and builds up and breaks
across the interaction
is going to be the best way
that we are aware of to feel
that one had a real connection.
This should also
remove any pressure
that you might feel to
constantly look at somebody
or to be completely eyes
open staring at them
without blinking or diverting
your attention at any point
during a conversation.
This also frankly,
is an opportunity
where if somebody says, hey,
you're not paying attention
because you look away,
that you may actually
be engaging in what is
the more typical form
of healthy connection.
I talked about this long ago
on an episode about focus.
It turns out when
we are listening
very intently to
somebody and trying
to remember the information
they're telling us,
we will often close our eyes.
And that's not a form of lack
of attention, that's actually
a form of attending in.
Because we have so much of
our brain devoted to vision.
When 40% of our brain
is devoted to vision
in some way or another,
when we close our eyes,
we can actually devote
more attentional resources
to remembering the specifics
of what people are telling us.
But again, please don't
go through conversations
with your eyes closed
the entire time.
I think that would certainly
not be conducive to building
social connection.
So we know that faces are
important for social connection
as it relates to
synthetic happiness.
And we know that eye contact is
really important for building
social connection.
Physical contact
is also important
for social connection.
And not just romantic or
sexual type connection.
In fact, there is a form
of physical connection
that is present
in other primates.
In fact, it's present as far
as we know, in all mammals.
And is also very much a feature
of the human nervous system.
And that's something
called allogrooming.
I have to imagine that
most people probably
haven't heard of allogrooming.
The reason I'm
bringing up alogrooming
is that it stems from a
fairly extensive literature
about the prosocial,
pro happiness
effects of pets on humans.
In fact, if you want
to read up on this,
there is a paper out of Yale
University on this topic
that was published in 2018.
The title of the paper is
"The influence of interactions
with dogs on affect", OK
emotion, "anxety and arousal
in children".
And it references
some other studies
that were performed on humans.
And the basic takeaway is
that these so-called AAAs,
animal assisted activities,
represent a really potent way
to increase people,
including children's feelings
of well-being.
Now what's interesting
about this to me
is that dogs
themselves don't really
have to do much except be
present in the room in order
for these positive effects, that
is, the reductions in anxiety,
increases in happiness,
et cetera, to occur.
And in fact, they can
be very, very brief.
As they describe in the
paper, "brief unstructured
interactions with
an unfamiliar dog",
so you don't even
need to know this dog,
"after exposure to a moderate
stressor showed higher positive
affect relevant to participants
who received a soothing object
or waited for the
same amount of time."
So just even seeing a dog
for a brief amount of time
has been shown to reduce
stress and improve happiness,
or I should say,
increase feelings
of happiness
overall then a child
receiving a soothing object.
Which was, at least for me, a
little bit counterintuitive.
I would have thought
that children receiving
a soothing object
would have been
the more powerful stimulus.
But in fact, it wasn't, at
least not in this study.
The real question I think we
should be asking ourselves
is, what is it about
interactions with others
and with other animals
that could potentially
have this prosocial
happiness enhancing effect?
And the reason I
raise this is also
because I think many people
are interested in either owning
or having interactions with
pets as a way to improve
their feelings of well-being.
And I say having
interactions with because I
myself am a good example
of somebody who wasn't
always able to have pets.
So when I was a graduate
student in a postdoc,
I very much wanted a dog.
Very, very, very
much wanted a dog.
In fact, there was a rule
in my family at some point
that I wasn't allowed to talk
about dogs anymore because I
was talking about all
the breeds of dogs.
Going to dog breeders,
examining different breeds,
going to the pound, et cetera.
The point was that I was
obsessed with getting a dog,
but I knew I wasn't in a good
position to own a dog yet.
I didn't have the finances, I
didn't have the correct living
situation and so on.
Eventually, I did
own a dog, of course.
But at the time I couldn't.
So what I would do is every
Sunday I would go to a place
where they fostered dogs
and they needed dog walkers.
And I would walk their dog.
I would also walk
my neighbor's dogs.
I didn't charge them for it.
In fact, I felt like I was
being paid by getting time
with those dogs.
And in fact, I put an ad
at that time on Craigslist
that I would walk
people's dogs for free,
and only a few people
took that seriously.
But of the ones that did,
I had a great little cadre
of dog owners that would allow
me to take their dogs out
and I was super happy.
It just made me
very, very happy.
And I really enjoyed it.
And frankly, it was a
great opportunity for me
to also get to the various dog
breeds and the different dog
temperaments and to learn a bit
about my ability to interact
with dogs in a certain way.
I actually got to be a
pretty good dog walker.
Unfortunately, later
I got a bulldog.
And it turns out
no matter how good
a dog walker you are, Bulldogs
just simply don't like to walk.
In fact, if you've ever
walked up to a bulldog
and you've offered to
scratch or pet that dog,
you'll notice that
Bulldogs love that.
And I would argue, having
been a bulldog owner,
that they like it because it's
an opportunity for them to stop
moving.
But that's more about
the bulldog than what
I'm about to tell
you next, which
is this principle of
so-called allogrooming.
Allogrooming is a
pattern of behavior
that's observed in essentially
all mammals but very strongly
in nonhuman primates
and primates,
where individuals within a
species touch one another.
And this is non-sexual touch.
So this would be someone
brushing somebody else's hair
or combing their hair or even
using a lint roller on them,
for instance.
Or someone grooming
somebody else.
Now typically, one needs
to have an established
relationship with this person.
So it could be a professional
type relationship
where this is a barber
cutting somebody's
hair or a hairdresser cutting
or styling somebody's hair.
It could be somebody
giving someone
a manicure or a pedicure.
Could be somebody doing skin
care or massage for somebody
in a professional context.
Or it could be two
people who have agreed
that it is appropriate
for the context
and for the relationship
for one person
to be grooming somebody else.
Can even, believe it or not
there's literature on this,
can even extend into
the realm of people
sort of cleaning and
picking off other people.
Now when we see
this in primates,
it seems like a very cute and
sort of almost understandable
behavior.
We can see these
pictures online.
If you look them up, you can
just look up allogrooming
and you'll see vast
number of pictures
of for instance, baboons
picking little things out
of each other's hair.
Or grooming and kind of
perusing one another,
to find things,
presumably parasites
or like little bits
of plants or something
like that they want
to remove from them.
Allogrooming is
known to stimulate
a certain category of neurons
called the C tactile fibers.
These are a particular category
of so-called sensory neurons
that innervate our skin.
So these are literally like
little endings of neurons,
little wires that
end up in the skin,
that when they are
touched lightly
tend to create a
feeling of well-being
in the person that's
being touched.
Again, this is
consensual touch that's
very context appropriate.
But it's known to
increase levels
of oxytocin, a kind of hormone
slash neurotransmitter.
It's both, really.
That is known to evoke
feelings of bond.
Or of feeling bonded to
somebody or something.
And for many people
we hear about oxytocin
and we think about the bond
between parent and child,
in particular mother
and infant where it's
been most extensively studied.
Or between two members
of a romantic couple.
But if you look at the
literature on allogrooming,
what you find is that when
humans groom one another,
the increases in oxytocin
that are experienced
are at least on par with and in
fact, more often, more dramatic
in response to allogrooming
than in response
to other forms of touch.
So the point here
is that allogrooming
is a prosocial
behavior that tends
to associate with
and promote feelings
of well-being and happiness.
And this is not
a trivial effect.
If you look at the brain imaging
data or other forms of data
on this, allogrooming
is a very powerful form
of bonding between individuals
that's completely nonverbal.
In fact, most often it
doesn't involve eye contact.
I suppose two people could
be looking at one another
grooming one another,
but typically, this
is done from the
side or from behind.
Why did I bring up
the paper on pets?
Well it turns out that
when humans stroke dogs,
or brush their
dogs or stroke cats
or brush their cats,
et cetera, that
is a form of human to
animal allogrooming.
And it's one in which
both the pet and the human
receive huge
increases in oxytocin
and other related neurochemicals
that make us feel bonded.
I bring this up because
the Harvard longitudinal
study on happiness,
and many, many others,
if not hundreds of other
studies on happiness,
point to the importance of
quality social connection.
You hear this over
and over again.
People on their
deathbeds don't say
they wish they had worked more.
People on their deathbeds
talk about the richness
of social connections
or the wish
that they had invested
more in social connections.
I think a lot of people
think of social connections
only in terms of travel with
or conversation with others.
But much of what we perceive
as deep social connections
also involves physical contact.
And that's something
that's deeply rooted
in our evolutionary biology.
And it's present both in us
and in non-human primates.
And it's clear
that we can engage
in these kinds of pro-social,
non verbal, non eye contact
type behaviors through things
like non-sexual tactile
touch, a.k.a.
allogrooming.
So we've been talking about a
number of the different things
that one can do in order to
increase levels of happiness.
And certainly,
before we conclude
today, I'm going to
touch back into not just
synthetic happiness and the
various things we can do,
such as prosocial
spending, allogrooming,
social connection, et cetera.
But also things
related to happiness
that involve focus on vocation
and work and pursuit of goals.
Because as I mentioned
at the beginning,
those are also
critical to increasing
our state of happiness,
and certainly
our state of security
and the feeling
that we can provide for
ourselves and perhaps
for others, as well.
So we will talk about that.
But I think it's also
important to talk
about this notion of
choice and choices,
and whether or not having
a lot of freedom to choose
or limited freedom in choosing
what we do and what we get,
and what we are able
to pursue in life,
how that relates to
both natural happiness
and synthetic happiness.
Dan Gilbert and
others have explored
this issue of freedom
of choice and how
it relates to happiness.
And there I must
say, the findings
are incredibly counterintuitive.
But very, very well supported
by all of their data.
I'm going to summarize a large
amount of those studies at once
by saying the following.
Dan's laboratory and
other laboratories
have done experiments
where they give people
a series of options.
And one of the more
classic examples, they
give people the opportunity
to rate a number
of different
paintings or pictures
in ascending or descending
order of preference.
In other words,
they're deciding which
ones they like most which
ones they like least.
Then what's interesting
is the experimenter
will vary the
extent to which they
have to stick to that choice.
So this could be
sticking to the choice
by receiving that
painting to take home.
Or in another
experiment, it was having
to make a choice
between giving up
one photograph that they,
the research subject took,
or another photograph
that they took.
One of the photographs
was going to go off
to a publication, another one
they could keep for themselves.
And the conditions
in that experiment
were either that you
had to make the decision
and it was final, that is,
you could keep one and rate
your decision, or
you could keep one
and then you had the
opportunity to swap out
that picture for the other
one at some later time.
In other words, these
experiments really
weren't about rating pictures,
they were really about
whether or not constraining
your choice, meaning
forcing somebody
to make a choice
and stick to that choice, led
to greater levels or lesser
levels of happiness and
satisfaction with that choice.
And what they find
consistently is
that when people have an
ongoing set of choices
it leads to reduced
levels of happiness.
Now that might come as
surprising to many of you,
but I want to be clear
about what this means.
This is not to say that having a
lot of choices of what you like
most leads to lesser happiness.
And that having fewer
choices about things
you do, or objects you
acquire, et cetera,
leads to greater happiness.
What this set of
experiments really points to
is that when we make a
choice, if we are forced
to stick to that
choice we tend to be
far happier with that
choice than if we maintain
the option to change our mind.
The results of these experiments
are extremely informative,
I believe, in terms of
understanding our real life
happiness.
That is, happiness
outside the laboratory.
But I think they are
often misunderstood
as meaning that if we
have a lot of choices
we tend to be less happy than
if we have fewer choices.
That is not the case.
Having freedom of
choice is terrific.
And actually, correlates with
elevated levels of happiness.
But once we make
our choice, it's
clearly the case that
killing all other choices
or having all other
options killed
for us increases our
satisfaction with the choice
that we've made.
Whereas, leaving doors open,
leaving options open greatly
diminishes our sense
of satisfaction.
This has been exported to any
number of different domains.
So this has been exported to
the domain of making choices
about what college to go to or
what partner to select in life.
In every one of
those instances, we
see that our happiness
with our choice
is very much related
to that choice
being either the only one or
one of very few other options.
There are a number of different
ways to interpret this.
Through the lens
of neuroscience we
might say that the
prefrontal cortex,
the area of the brain that's
involved in decision making
and evaluating
different options,
is an area of the brain
that's vital, frankly,
to our evolution as human
beings and to our daily life
and to our whole life.
It is, of course,
the thing that allows
us to evaluate different rule
sets, to change rule sets,
to switch contexts and to
create meaning, et cetera.
To interpret what's
good what's bad.
But it's also a
fairly costly process,
meaning it's very
metabolically demanding.
And there's an entire
literature related
to what's called ego depletion.
This is certainly a topic
for a future podcast.
But ego depletion essentially
says that if I have you
attend very intensely to a
given task, for instance,
asking you to count
backwards from 1,000 to 0
in increments of 13.
And then have you
switch about halfway
through, that's hard
for a lot of people.
If I have you do that,
then your ability
to suppress impulsive behavior
and to do a hard cognitive
or physical task immediately
after that is actually
suppressed.
This so-called ego depletion.
It relates to a number
of different things,
but it certainly
relates to engagement
of the prefrontal
cortex, which is
very metabolically demanding.
So evaluating choices and
doing computation of numbers
or attending to
things with your mind
and forcing yourself
to focus intensely
is metabolically demanding.
And that's a limited
resource that
can be reset by things like
sleep and non sleep deep rest
or idle time or letting
your mind wander.
In that case a
positive mind wandering
to allow your brain to
reset its ability to focus.
But the other thing
that it does is
it impacts the reward
circuitry of the brain,
the so-called dopamine reward
circuitry and other reward
circuitry of the brain.
And here I'm painting
with a broad brush.
But it essentially divides
them such that for instance,
if a given choice of
a let's say a partner
or maybe buying ourselves
an article of clothing,
not that I want to compare
selection of a life partner
to selection of an
article of clothing.
But just to give
multiple examples.
Might give us, and here
it's arbitrary units, x
units of dopamine increase.
Well, if we buy that
article of clothing or we
select that life
partner, and then
we emerge from the
store or the wedding
and we are focused on what
we purchased for ourselves,
our choice, or our life partner
choice, and only that, well
then there's a certain amount of
neurochemical reward associated
with that.
And happiness and well-being.
But it's also very
clear that if we
leave those choices, the store
or our wedding for instance,
or a life with somebody for
a moment, even just mentally,
and start thinking
about the other options
that we might
entertain as possible.
If those are still open to
us in reality or in our mind,
well then our reward circuitry
becomes fractured in a way.
Not physically fractured,
but less attention
is devoted to the reward
circuitry associated
with our choice.
And as a consequence, instead
of it being x units of dopamine,
it's x divided by however
many other choices
we might have available to
us in our mind or in reality.
So instead of, and again,
these are arbitrary units,
but instead of a certain
amount of reward,
it's a certain amount
of reward divided
by the number of
other options that we
might be considering as
alternatives to what we chose.
And I think this is a
very important aspect
of understanding how limiting
our choices after we've
made them is a
vital part of what
we call synthetic happiness.
In fact, we could
even go so far as
to say that focusing on
the choices we've made
and really investing in
those choices as good ones,
or great ones, and
really trying to limit
our thinking to the
choices that we've
made once we've
made them is perhaps
also important to our
natural happiness.
Because it's so inextricably
entwined with what
we think of as a good life.
And what I mean by that
is if we are constantly
in a mode of evaluative
decision making,
even after we've
made a decision,
we are not neurochemically
nor psychologically able
to extract the feelings
of happiness associated
with the choice that we made.
So we've talked about a
number of different dimensions
of happiness, both in synthetic
and natural happiness.
And some of the more
counterintuitive aspects
of happiness.
For instance, that
people tend to adjust
their levels of happiness not
regardless but often in spite
of their life circumstances.
But as we emphasized earlier
in the episode, that is not
to say, at least the
research does not directly
support the idea that
a major trauma or loss
won't impact our happiness.
In fact, it tends to.
And that's why it's
important that people access
resources and work devoted
to overcoming trauma, which
certainly exists out there.
And of course, there are
the longitudinal studies
in short term studies showing
that income level and material
things don't necessarily scale
with happiness, and vise versa.
And yet, we also acknowledged
early in the episode
that while indeed money
can't buy happiness,
it can buffer stress.
And while work doesn't
necessarily bring happiness,
per se, work can bring
a tremendous feeling
of meaning and resources
which can then put you
into context in which things
like prosocial contact
and enhanced bonds and
caretaking of others and of you
can be enhanced.
So it would be unfair
and in fact, inaccurate,
to simply view happiness
through the lens of money
doesn't matter, it's all
about social connection.
And so on and so forth.
Absolutely, social
connection is important,
which is why we spent some
minutes talking about some
of the ways to enhance
social connection
both with other human
beings and other animals,
and them with us.
I think there's a opportunity
here to take the research
on happiness, the research
on the neuroscience of what
happiness and gratitude and
prosocial connection tells us,
and to combine it into a
bit of a model or a toolkit,
if you will.
And I think indeed, this
will be a toolkit in one
of our future toolkit episodes,
likely merged with the toolkit
on gratitude, which
we haven't done yet.
And perhaps even we will do an
entire episode on social bonds
and how to enhance or
build social bonds.
Or at least what the
science tells us about that.
If we take a step
back and we look
at the concept of happiness,
we can make a couple
of absolute statements.
That is, statements that I
think very few people, if any,
would contest.
First of all, there's no
single molecule or chemical
associated with happiness,
but that the chemical milieu
of the brain and body
is important for setting
the stage or the
opportunity for happiness.
Hence, why there are treatments
aimed at alleviating depression
or mania that target certain
neurochemical systems
and hormone systems.
Happiness, at least the
way I'm framing it today,
has essentially two components.
One is meaning.
That is, what sort of meaning
do certain types of interactions
or behaviors, could be work,
could be social interactions,
et cetera, carry for us?
And nested in that is this
concept of connection.
And we talked a bit about
tools for enhancing connection.
Things like eye contact, but
not constant eye contact.
Things like being very
present to a conversation
or an activity that
you're engaging in.
Remember, we talked
about the paper,
"A Distracted Mind
is an Unhappy Mind"?
The paper published in Science.
And we talked about the study,
also published in Science
in which giving money, but
also knowing how that money has
positively impacted
others, leads
to this feeling of pro-social
connection and happiness
in the giver and
in the receiver.
And I should mention
again that it's not
just the giving of money but
also the giving of effort
and time and attention that
can have similar effects.
So we have meaning
and connection,
and a number of different
ways to access those.
And then we have
this access that I'm
referring to as
performance and resources.
And I'm talking about
performance and resources
as it relates to
natural happiness, not
synthetic happiness,
but natural happiness.
Because we would be
wrong, I believe,
if we were to say that
income doesn't matter.
I think it's fair to say,
based on the research,
that income matters.
And income that can cover
costs of living plus that
includes some buffer.
And what do I mean by buffer?
I mean buffer to the anxiety
that circumstances might change
is important.
Now that's going to vary
from person to person.
Meaning some people
will be perfectly happy
making $1 more than their
absolute cost of living
every month.
Other people will require
a more substantial buffer
in order to protect them against
the negative psychological
effects of worrying about
for instance, inflation.
Or worrying that they
might lose their job.
And this is why I think
most people recommend
having, if possible, some
buffer in their bank account
that could cover two or
three or maybe even six
or maybe even 12 months
of living expenses
were they to lose
their job or something
catastrophic happened to them.
So if we're going to
talk about happiness,
I think it's only fair, only
accurate, and frankly, only
respectful to talk about
living requirements and cost
of living requirements.
That includes this
sort of buffer.
And that buffer to
anxiety is going
to vary depending on how
anxious somebody gets
about the possibility
of catastrophic things
happening to them, like
losing their job or their rent
going up or doubling.
And here, I'm talking
about hypotheticals.
But I think we all know
people and perhaps ourselves
have experienced those
kinds of circumstances.
So when we talk about
happiness we absolutely
need to think about resources.
And we also need to
think about performance.
I think we would be completely
inaccurate if we simply
said, oh, any work
leading to any outcomes.
Any effort, regardless
of whether or not
it gets you an A in
school or an F in school
isn't going to impact
your happiness.
I don't think anyone
would agree with that.
And yet if you look at
the major takeaways,
at least as they are
communicated typically
in the public sphere around
the longitudinal and short term
studies of happiness,
the takeaway generally
is more focused on
social connection
and how money is not important.
I don't think anyone that's
saying that actually means
that income that can cover
your expenses plus some buffer
isn't important.
But it's often not stated.
So if we were to come up with a
general model of happiness that
includes various tools
for how to increase
our levels of happiness,
I think it's only
fair to include both natural
and synthetic forms of happiness
and to pursue both natural
and synthetic happiness.
Just to remind you,
natural happiness
is the kind of happiness
that we associate
with obtaining something,
either by effort
or because it was given to us.
Although, I definitely want
to highlight the fact that
receiving things that don't
require much reward in order
to receive them over
time can be detrimental
to our dopamine system.
That's an important aside.
The other form of happiness
is the form of happiness
that we call
synthetic happiness.
Which is, for instance,
focusing on social connection.
And we talked about ways
to do that as a means
to enhance your happiness.
Again, the language, the
name synthetic happiness
implies something
kind of artificial.
But frankly, genuine social
connection is genuine.
There's nothing
artificial about it
or synthetic about it, is
that you can synthesize it
through action, through
deliberate action.
Likewise, being focused
or encouraging yourself.
Working on being focused on
whatever activities you happen
to be engaged in,
positive or negative,
is known to increase
your levels of happiness.
Again, this is a form
of synthetic happiness.
You're not obtaining
anything new or additional
as a consequence of this.
It's entirely internal.
There's no external reward.
There isn't more
money that arrives
with this or a better grade.
Although, I would
make the argument
that if you are
present to the work
you're doing in any context,
physical or mental work,
it's very likely
that you are going
to perform better at that work.
So we have natural happiness
and synthetic happiness.
And both of them require
our attention and effort.
And in fact, if we
were to draw a link
between natural and
synthetic happiness,
it really is this
concept of presence,
of really being focused
on what we're doing,
that's most likely to lead
to the outcomes that we want.
Both externally, in terms of
receiving monetary rewards
or grades, or
praise, or whatever
it is that you happen to
be pursuing out there,
resources of some kind.
And presence, and
striving to be present
when in the pursuit of so-called
synthetic happiness in the form
of social connection or in
the form of really focusing
on the choice that
you've made and making
the best of that choice,
especially since you
made that choice in a way that
you deemed best at the time.
Well, that also is known to
increase your overall levels
of happiness.
So if an ability to focus
and attend to things deeply
is really what's most important,
and really acts as the greatest
lever for both natural
and synthetic happiness,
well then, tools like a 5 minute
daily meditation or a 13 minute
day meditation, as
well as tools that
allow us to get excellent
sleep every night.
Which, of course, sets the basis
for attention during the day.
If you've ever had a
poor night's sleep then
you are very familiar
with how hard it
is to focus the following day.
At least for long
periods of time.
But building our
capacity to focus
through a focusing exercise,
which again, is often
called meditation, but
is really simply just
a focusing and
perceptual exercise.
That's going to create
an outsized effect
on all the aspects,
all the behaviors
that we know feed into
creating natural and synthetic
happiness.
And so it's really fair
to say that our ability
to attend and focus really
equates to happiness.
So as is often typical
of this podcast,
today we've talked a lot
about the various aspects
of the science of happiness,
including the different forms
of happiness and tools to
access those different forms
of happiness.
If you're learning from
and/or enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to
our YouTube channel.
That's a terrific zero
cost way to support us.
In addition, please
subscribe to the podcast
on both Spotify and Apple.
And on both Spotify
and Apple, you
have the opportunity to leave
us up to a five star review.
If you have questions
or suggestions
about topics and
guests you'd like
me to include on the
Huberman Lab podcast,
please put those in the
comment section on YouTube.
I do read all the comments.
In addition, please
check out the sponsors
mentioned at the beginning
of today's episode.
That's the best way to
support this podcast.
The Huberman Lab also has
a zero cost newsletter
that you can access.
It includes summaries
of podcast episodes,
as well as summaries
of various protocols
for mental health, physical
health and performance.
You can sign up
for the newsletter
by going to Hubermanlab.com,
going to the menu,
and look for the Neural
Network newsletter sign up.
You just provide your
email, and I assure you,
we do not share your
email with anybody.
And again, it's
completely zero cost.
Again, go to Hubermanlab.com and
sign up for the Neural Network
newsletter.
And if you're not already
following us on social media,
we are Huberman
Lab on Instagram,
Huberman Lab on Twitter and
Huberman Lab on Facebook.
And at all of those sites I
provide science and science
related tools for mental
health, physical health
and performance.
Some of which overlap
with information
covered on the
Huberman Lab podcast.
But often, which is distinct
from information covered
on the Huberman Lab podcast.
So again, that's Huberman
Lab on Instagram, Twitter,
and Facebook.
Once again, thank
you for joining me
for today's discussion about the
science of happiness and tools
for increasing your happiness.
And as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[MUSIC PLAYING]