- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast.
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
[bright music]
I'm Andrew Huberman, and I'm
a professor of neurobiology
and ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
Today, we are discussing cannabis,
also referred to as marijuana.
Cannabis includes many different compounds
that have profound impact
on the brain and body,
so while many of you have
probably heard of THC,
there are also compounds
in cannabis such as CBD,
and of course there are different types
or strains of cannabis,
including sativa strains
and indica strains
and hybrid strains, and believe it or not,
nowadays, there is also
an entire literature,
meaning a scientific
and medicinal literature
about type one, type two
and type three strains.
I'll explain what all of
that is and how they work.
I'll talk about some of
the medicinal applications
of different strains of cannabis
and combinations of cannabis strains,
as well as some of the
potential health hazards
of cannabis use.
I want to emphasize that any
discussion about cannabis
has to be framed within the context
that the legality of
cannabis varies tremendously
depending on where you are in the world,
so depending on which country you're in
and even which state you're in
or which area within a country,
possessing and using and
certainly selling cannabis
can be either highly
illegal or entirely legal
or decriminalized or largely overlooked.
You, of course, are obligated to know
what those local laws are for you,
where you live and where you travel.
With that said, today's discussion
really will include a full picture
as to where cannabis and the various
and even very specific
compounds within cannabis
can be extremely useful in
the treatment of some ailments
and where certain compounds in cannabis
can be extremely dangerous for
certain individuals to use,
in particular, individuals
that have preexisting,
genetic propensity for psychosis.
That theme is going to
come up again and again,
but we are also going to talk
about the role of cannabis
in anxiety and depression,
both positive and negative effects.
We'll talk about sex differences
in terms of women versus men
and how they react
differently to cannabis,
and I would be entirely remiss
if I didn't include a
conversation about cannabis,
meaning THC, CBD, hybrid
strains, et cetera
in creativity and different
modes of thinking,
because as many of you probably know
or at least have heard about,
cannabis can impact the way that we think,
the types of memory systems we can access
and what's called convergent
and divergent thinking,
which is one way of conceptualizing
what is commonly referred
to as creativity.
So today's discussion is going to include
a lot of information,
but I promise to make it clear
and accessible to all of you,
regardless of whether or
not you have a background
in biology or not,
and today's discussion
will also be quite nuanced.
You'll find me routinely reading
directly from specific research papers,
something that of course we
always do on this podcast,
but today I'm really going to dig
into some of the finer points
of the methodology in papers
and some of the statistics that were used
and the specific populations
of people that were studied,
because as it turns out,
there are instances that we will discuss
in which the use of cannabis
can be immensely beneficial
to one group and yet can
be entirely detrimental
to another group, even
at equivalent dosages
and depending on a number
of different factors,
so we will discuss what those factors are.
Just to give you a brief overview
of the kind of structure I'm
going to put on today's episode,
we will review of course,
cannabis and its various forms.
I'll talk about some of the biology,
but we are going to really
drill into how dosage,
that is the concentration
of THC relative to CBD,
impacts whether or not cannabis
is going to have one effect or another.
We will also talk about
the frequency of use,
daily use, multiple times per day use,
weekly use or monthly or occasional use.
We will also talk about
different professions
and how some people may have
a little bit more leeway
in terms of whether or not
they decide to use cannabis
or any of its various component
chemical constituents,
that is CBD or THC, et cetera.
And for other professions,
it might be entirely inappropriate
because of the particular
kinds of cognitive tasks
those professions demand.
We will also talk about
genetic predisposition,
again, sex differences, hormone effects,
and I will also touch on what I think
is the most important variable
in determining whether or not cannabis
is right or wrong for
you, and that is your age
at which you are considering starting
or continuing use or ceasing use.
What I can assure you is that
by the end of today's podcast,
you will have a quite thorough
understanding of cannabis,
how it works, what it does,
what its potential benefits can be,
what its potential hazards are,
and whether or not it's right for you
and the people that you know.
I'm excited to announce that
the Huberman Lab Podcast
has now launched a premium channel.
The purpose of the premium
channel is severalfold.
First of all, I will be
hosting regular AMAs,
Ask Me Anythings, where
you can ask me anything,
and I will provide answers in depth
to your specific questions about science
and science related
tools for mental health,
physical health and performance.
Now, there is a nominal
cost to the premium channel.
It's $10 per month, or you can
pay $100 for the entire year.
I should mention, however,
that a significant portion of the funds
raised through the premium channel
are going to support not just
the "Huberman Lab Podcast,"
which we will continue to
release every Monday on schedule
of zero cost to all consumers' content
on mental health, physical
health and performance,
but proceeds from the premium channel
will also be used to fund research,
in particular research
done on human beings,
so not animal models, but on human beings,
which I think we all agree is a species
that we are most interested in.
And, we are going to
specifically fund research
that is aimed toward
developing further protocols
for mental health, physical
health and performance,
and those protocols will be distributed
through all channels, not
just the premium channel,
but through all channels,
Huberman Lab Podcast and
other media channels.
So the idea here is to
give you information
to your burning questions in depth
and allow you the opportunity
to support the kind of research
that provides those kinds of
answers in the first place.
Now, an especially exciting
feature of the premium channel
is that the Tiny Foundation
has generously offered
to do a dollar-for-dollar match
on all funds raised for research
through the premium channel.
So this is a terrific way
that they're going to amplify
whatever funds come in
through the premium channel
to further support research for science
and science-related tools
for mental health, physical
health and performance.
If you'd like to sign up
for the Huberman Lab premium channel,
again, there's a cost of $10 per month
or you can pay $100 upfront
for the entire year.
That will give you access to all the AMAs.
You can ask questions and get
answers to your questions,
and you'll of course get
answers to all the questions
that other people ask as well.
There will also be some premium content,
such as transcripts of the AMAs
and various transcripts and protocols
of Huberman Lab Podcast episodes
and not found elsewhere.
And again, you'll be supporting research
for mental health, physical
health and performance.
You can sign up for the premium channel
by going to hubermanlab.com/premium,
again, that's hubermanlab.com/premium.
Before diving into all of that,
I'd like to highlight a new,
what I think is a very useful
and zero cost resource.
This resource is what's
called Non-Sleep Deep Rest
or NSDR protocol.
I've talked many times before
on the Huberman Lab Podcast
about Non-Sleep Deep Rest, AKA, NSDR.
NSDR is sort of an umbrella term
for a variety of different practices,
so these are behavioral practices
that allow you to direct
your brain and body
into a particular state,
and most typically,
that state is one of deep relaxation,
but also one in which you
can access your bodily
and brain systems for teaching yourself
how to relax in real
time and how to recover
some of the sleep that you
may not be getting at night,
and to restore levels of dopamine
in particular areas of the
brain that are involved
in motivation and cognitive
and motor control.
Basically, NSDR is a
wonderfully restorative tool.
This has been demonstrated
many times over now
through quality peer-reviewed science,
and there are neurochemical benefits,
and there are physical benefits,
and there are certainly
psychological benefits.
I highly recommend NSDR to anybody
that has trouble falling asleep
or that wakes up in
the middle of the night
and needs to get better
at falling back asleep,
as well as to anyone out
there that has issues
with anxiety or
self-regulation of any kind.
And if you don't have any of those issues,
it's also immensely beneficial
just as a restorative
for leaning back into
focused work of any kind.
Now, a number of people have reached out
about finding NSDR protocols,
and there are a number
of different good ones
out there floating around.
I've decided to put a
zero-cost NSDR script
out there on the internet
for people to access,
so you can find it by going to YouTube
and simply put my last
name, 'Huberman' and 'NSDR'
into the search function.
This is a YouTube channel
that's hosted by Virtusan,
which has a terrific
app that includes NSDR
and a number of other health
and wellness protocols,
but they've been quite generous
in hosting a 10 minute NSDR, read by me.
This NSDR is distinct from,
although I should say,
similar to yoga nidra,
which some of you are familiar with.
This NSDR is different than yoga nidra
in the sense that it
doesn't have intentions.
There's no mystical component,
and I describe a little bit of the science
and why specific components
of the NSDR are included,
things like long exhale breathing,
I talk about perceptual shifts
and how to move from thinking and planning
to pure sensation.
If none of that makes sense right now,
it'll make total sense after
listening to the NSDR script.
Again, it's a 10 minute
NSDR script, read by me.
You can do this first thing in
the morning when you wake up,
especially if you didn't
get enough sleep that night,
and you're feeling a little bit fatigued,
and you need to lean into
the day with full vigor.
You could do it at any
point during the day
or if you wake up in
the middle of the night.
Again, this is a zero-cost
resource for you.
You can find it by going to YouTube,
put my last name in and NSDR.
I encourage you to try
it, and if you like it
or frankly, if you don't,
you can just put that
in the comment section there on YouTube,
and I've put it there as
a free resource to you,
so that you can benefit
from the research-backed,
peer-reviewed studies that point to NSDR
as a very useful practice.
Before we begin, I'd like to
emphasize that this podcast
is separate from my teaching
and research roles at Stanford.
It is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring zero-cost to consumer information
about science and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Levels.
Levels is a program that lets you see
how different foods affect your health
by giving you real-time
feedback on your diet
using a continuous glucose monitor.
One of the most important factors
in your immediate and long-term health
is how well you're
managing your blood glucose
or blood sugar.
I started using Levels about a year ago
as a way to see how different foods
and different lifestyle factors
were impacting my blood glucose levels.
So for instance, it allowed
me to see how different foods
and particular macronutrients
and combinations of macronutrients
would either peak or trough my blood sugar
or keep my blood sugar steady.
It also allowed me to see how working out
with weights or running, how
that impacted my blood glucose.
So for me, it was a fascinating
experiment unto myself
as to how my meal schedule, the
specific foods I was eating,
different combinations of
food, as I mentioned before,
and exercise were combining to regulate
this thing that we call blood sugar
and that's so vital to our health.
I think anyone that tries Levels will find
that you learn an immense
amount about what you're doing
and what you ought to be doing differently
in order to optimize your
immediate feelings of wellbeing
and your health trajectory.
If you're interested in
learning more about Levels
and trying a CGM yourself,
go to levels.link/huberman,
that's levels.link, L-I-N-K, /huberman.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Thesis.
Thesis makes custom nootropics
that are designed for
your particular needs.
I am not a fan of the word nootropics,
because nootropics
literally means smart drugs
or smart drug, and frankly,
as a neuroscientist,
I know and every other
neuroscientist knows
that there is no neural circuit
or chemical in the brain for being smart.
There are, for instance,
neural circuits and chemicals
that increase your ability to focus
or your ability to task switch.
Thesis understands this and therefore,
has designed custom nootropics that vary
and are tailored to you
so that, for instance,
if you want to achieve focus and clarity
for one particular type of work,
there is a Nootropic for that.
Or if you'd like to have more
energy and have more focus,
there's a different Nootropic for that.
If you'd like to get your own personalized
nootropics starter kit,
you can go online to
takethesis.com/huberman,
take that three minute quiz,
and Thesis will send you
four different formulas
to try in your first month,
and then they'll work with you and iterate
to find the best formulas
for you to take ongoing.
Again, that's takethesis.com/huberman
and use the code 'huberman' at checkout
to get 10% off your first box.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I've long been a believer in
getting regular blood work done
for the simple reason
that many of the factors
that impact your immediate
and long-term health
can only be analyzed with
a quality blood test.
With a lot of blood tests and
DNA tests out there, however,
an issue is you get information back
about lipids and hormones, et cetera,
but you don't know what to
do with that information.
With InsideTracker, they
have a personalized platform
that makes interpreting your data
and then acting on that
data very straightforward
and very directed toward
specific protocols.
What I mean by that is
you'll get information back
about hormone levels
and metabolic factors,
lipids, et cetera, and then you can look
to nutritional changes,
supplementation changes,
exercise protocol changes
and other lifestyle features
that combine or work on their own
to start to try and shift those numbers
into the range that's appropriate for you.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can visit insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off any of InsideTracker plans.
Just use the code 'huberman' at checkout.
Again, that's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off and use the
code 'huberman' at checkout.
On many episodes of the
Huberman Lab Podcast,
we talk about supplements.
While supplements aren't
necessary for everybody,
many people derive
tremendous benefit from them,
things like enhancing sleep
and the depth of sleep,
or for enhancing focus
and cognitive ability,
or for enhancing energy or
adjusting hormone levels
to optimal range for you.
The Huberman Lab Podcast
is now partnered with
Momentous Supplements.
We partnered with Momentous
for a number of important reasons.
First of all, the quality
of their ingredients
is exceptional, it's
really second to none.
Second of all, they ship internationally,
and that was important to us,
because a number of you reside
outside of the United States.
Third, we've worked with
Momentous very closely
to develop single-ingredient formulations.
Now, this turns out to be very important,
because if you're going
to take supplements,
you want to know what's
working for you and what isn't.
And of course, you want to
optimize the cost efficiency
and the biological efficiency
of those supplements.
To find the supplements we discuss
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
you can go to livemomentous spelled O-U-S,
livemomentous.com/huberman,
and I should just mention that the library
of those supplements is
constantly expanding.
Again, that's livemomentous.com/huberman.
Let's talk about cannabis,
and when we refer to cannabis,
we are indeed referring to
marijuana or the marijuana plant.
Now, cannabis plants
come in different strains
or different varieties,
and those different strains
are indeed different genetic strains.
So just as animals and humans
have different genetic backgrounds,
and they can be crossed to one another
to yield further genetic
variation in the offspring,
plants can be hybridized to one another
in various ways through grafting
or through the use of different
types of seed combinations,
et cetera, in order to
generate different strains.
There are also naturally
occurring differences
in the strains of plants,
and the cannabis plant is no exception.
So for instance, in the context
of the discussion about cannabis
and its medicinal uses
and recreational uses,
we need to distinguish
between the sativa variety,
the indica variety, a
variety called ruderalis
that's not often discussed,
and hybrids of sativa,
indica and ruderalis.
Before diving into the
different strains of cannabis
and how they impact the brain embody,
both similarly and differently,
I want to emphasize
that the cannabis plant
contains a number of different
psychoactive compounds.
Now, the most powerful of
those compounds is THC.
The technical name for it is
delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol.
But THC, as I'll refer to it,
is just one of the psychoactive
and biologically active
compounds within cannabis plants.
There's also CBD, which
is technically referred to
as cannabidiol, and cannabidiol, CBD,
is known to be used for
things like pain management,
anxiety management and
other medicinal purposes.
We will talk about the efficacy
of CBD for those purposes,
as well as some of, believe it or not,
some of the dangers of CBD,
depending on where it's sourced
and the dosage, et cetera.
So we've got THC, CBD and
also CBN or cannabinol.
CBN is less often discussed.
You're going to hear a lot less
about CBN containing products out there,
CBN containing medicines,
but it is relevant to today's discussion,
so it will come up a bit.
Now, I will be sure to
provide more specificity
to what I'm about to say,
but very broadly speaking,
THC is largely responsible
for the psychoactive effects of cannabis,
that is the changes in mood,
the changes in bodily state
and sensation, et cetera.
Whereas CBD and to some extent,
CBN, have profound effects
on the brain and body,
but they don't tend to
give people the sensation
of altered perception,
altered mood, et cetera.
Some people might say they are
not the component of cannabis
that, quote unquote, gets you high,
although today, we will really drill into
what the high itself represents
in terms of chemical
systems in the brain body.
And what we will soon learn is that
what we think of as being
high actually includes
a number of different changes
in the brain and body,
some of which can be
best explained by CBD,
not by THC, which runs counter
to what most people out
there know and believe.
So broadly speaking, we
have THC, CBD and CBN.
But I want to point out
that the cannabis plant
has over 70, seven-zero,
70 different psychoactive compounds,
many of which still have not been studied
in isolation and in detail.
So there's a big future
of research for cannabis
and for THC and THC-related
psychoactive compounds,
as well as for CBD and CBN.
Today we're mainly going to focus
on THC and CBD, as I mentioned before.
I should also point out
that the cannabis plant
has over 400 biologically
active compounds.
So these are biologically active compounds
that may or may not have
psychoactive properties,
that may or may not be useful
for pain relief, et cetera.
Again, there is a vast
landscape for exploration
of the cannabis plant and of
hemp for what they include
that could be beneficial
to us or detrimental to us,
so again, a lot more work to do.
Today, we're going to really
try and stay on target
with what we already know
and where there are
certain exciting mysteries
or intriguing mysteries
about what we ought to explore more.
I will certainly highlight those.
Let's go back to the different strains
of the cannabis plant,
sativa, indica and ruderalis
and explore how each of those
differentially impacts the brain and body,
because therein I think
we can start to learn
a lot about this incredible plant
that is the cannabis plant.
And whether or not you
are a user of cannabis
or whether or not you are
entirely opposed to cannabis use,
understanding how cannabis works
in the brain and body, itself,
is absolutely fascinating
and can teach you a lot about
how your brain and body work
at a basic level and
can tell you a lot about
how your brain and body will
react to different life events
and how your mood is
established and stabilized,
and how your appetite is
established and stabilized
and so on.
So we have the three
major strains of cannabis,
sativa, indica and ruderalis.
And for sake of today's conversation,
we can pretty much cross off ruderalis.
It's not often consumed,
and components of ruderalis
are not often consumed
for medicinal or recreational purposes.
Let's focus on sativa and indica.
People will consume the
sativa variety of cannabis
either by edible or by smoking cannabis,
or they will consume the
indica variety of cannabis,
again by edible or by smoking cannabis,
or sometimes they will take
it in a transdermal form
or a sublingual form.
There are a bunch of different ways
to get the cannabis into the body,
but there's a clear distinction
between sativa and indica
that actually shows up first
in the structure of the plant.
At their extremes, meaning
in a pure strain of sativa,
it tends to be a taller
plant, a longer stock,
believe it or not,
and actually the length of the
leaves is quite a bit longer,
whereas the indica plant tends
to be more short and stout.
And, for those aficionados out there,
I'm sure you know a lot of
the other specific features
of sativa versus indica,
but already what we're talking
about is the same plant,
cannabis, with two very
different morphologies or shapes.
You might say, "Well, why is
this interesting or important
"to how it affects me
or affects other people
"for medicinal or recreational purposes?"
Well, it turns out that even
though they are the same plant,
these two different genetic varieties,
because of the way that they grow
and the way they capture sunlight
and the way, believe it or
not, that the different plants
within that strain
interact with one another,
'cause believe it or not,
plants are interacting with one another,
they actually bring different elements
of the psychoactive compounds
to different components
within the leaves and the so-called buds.
The takeaway is that when consumed,
and when I say consumed,
I want to be very clear,
I don't necessarily just
mean oral consumption
or eating cannabis sativa by edible,
I also mean smoking it,
and that could be...
people will, just like with tobacco,
the way that they bring
the psychoactive components
into their bloodstream and
into their brain and body
is to essentially heat the dried leaves
of the cannabis plant.
Then the heat liberates some
of the psychoactive components
that when inhaled into the lungs,
because the lungs include
a lot of vasculature,
a lot of basically blood
vessels and capillaries,
that the psychoactive components
are actually directly absorbed
from the lungs into the bloodstream,
and they can cross into the bloodstream
and permeate throughout the body
and cross the so-called
blood brain barrier.
So in other words, burning
the plant liberates the smoke
that contains the psychoactive compounds,
and those are inhaled into the lungs
and then get into the brain and body
and act on the brain and body.
And the major effect of sativa varieties
are to create a high, if you will,
and I'm putting this in air quotes
for those of you that are listening,
but to also act as a stimulant.
The sativa varieties tend to make people
feel invigorated, somewhat alert.
It doesn't tend to be
as much of a sedative
as some of the other varieties.
Some people report
heightened sense of focus
or heightened sense of creativity.
We'll talk a little bit later on
as to whether or not they actually
are achieving heightened
levels of focus and creativity,
or whether or not they
just perceive themselves
to have heightened levels
of focus and creativity.
The sativa varieties tend to make people
feel a little bit less susceptible
to pain and noxious stimuli,
which are basically stimuli
that you don't like.
So the sativa varieties are
often prescribed or are used
in the recreational context
for pain management and relief.
Basically, the sativa variety is known
to include a head biased effect.
So here, we're talking
about subjective effects,
and of course these will vary
from one individual to the next.
Some people will smoke cannabis sativa
or ingest cannabis sativa orally
and will feel an entirely
different array of effects,
but most people, the majority of people
experience a head-centered
high, alertness, focus
and a sense that they're more creative.
Contrast that with the
indica varieties of cannabis,
and when people smoke or eat
or ingest indica varieties,
the psychoactive components of indica,
and again, this is pure indica,
so not hybridized with sativa
at all, but just pure indica,
tend to lead to more full-bodied effects.
People report feeling more
complete, full-body relaxation,
more of a sedative effect.
Indica cannabis is often prescribed
and/or used recreationally
in order to achieve a state of sleep
or to help relieve anxiety,
so less of a stimulant effect.
And we will talk about why,
literally, the underlying neural circuits
that lead to the sativa
variety causing more
of a elevated mood and a
head high, if you will,
and the indica variety as being
more full body relaxation.
One of the ways to
remember the distinction
between the effects of cannabis
sativa and cannabis indica
was relayed to me by a friend
who actually was a chronic,
meaning every day, all
day, consumer of marijuana.
He basically smoked marijuana for 20 years
before quitting about
four or five years ago,
and he said that indica
is often referred to
as 'in-da-couch,' meaning
laid back in the couch.
And that can help you remember
that the indica varieties of cannabis
do tend to be more
sedative in their effects.
Okay, so there's sativa
and there's indica,
and then now there are hybrid strains.
So marijuana growers and
people who specialize
in creating novel varieties
of the cannabis plant,
again, I'm using the words
cannabis and marijuana
more or less interchangeably here,
they are very good at
creating new strains of plant
that might be 25% sativa and
75% indica or vice versa,
or 50/50 or 90/10.
Essentially, what's happening nowadays
is that through plant biology,
plant genetics, I should say,
growers are getting quite efficient
at creating a variety of different strains
of the marijuana plant that
give rise to very nuanced
and distinct effects on brain and body.
In fact, so much so, that
there's now a new nomenclature,
a new language emerging around cannabis
and the development of
novel strains of cannabis
for medicinal and/or
recreational purposes.
And while this might
sound a little bit medical
or a little bit clinical to
some people, believe it or not,
this is the nomenclature
that is now typically used.
People still refer to the sativa,
indica and hybrid strains,
but there's now also a description
of so-called type one, type
two and type three strains
for any given sativa,
indica or hybrid strain.
Okay, so just to put this
clearly in your mind,
you've got sativa varieties,
that is pure sativa varieties.
You have indica varieties,
again, pure indica,
and then you have hybrid varieties,
and beneath each of those,
you have type one, type
two and type three strains
of indica, sativa or hybrid varieties.
What are type one, type
two and type three?
Well, type one, type two
and type three strains
are strains that have varying amounts
or ratios of THC to CBD.
So for instance, type one strain,
so for instance, you could
have a pure sativa, type one,
or a type one pure sativa
or a type one indica.
Those are going to have
the greatest amount
of THC relative to CBD.
And I really want to emphasize this,
understanding the ratio of THC to CBD
can help explain a lot
or even predict a lot
about how a given strain of
cannabis will impact somebody.
For instance, because THC
is largely responsible
for the typical psychoactive
components of cannabis,
so what I mean here is, if
somebody's ingesting sativa,
and it routinely makes
them feel more energized,
elevates their mood,
it gives them a heightened
sense of creativity,
if that's what they experience,
and they're taking a
type one version of that,
that means that it's quite rich
in THC and very little CBD.
However, if they were to take
a type one version of sativa,
and it feels far too strong,
like too much energy,
or they felt like they were
too much in their head,
nowadays, there are strains of sativa
that have been genetically engineered,
and I don't mean by an
engineer tinkering away
with gene engineering in
a CRISPR creating mutes,
but literally by hybridizing,
crossing different plants to one another,
creating in a natural context,
the same way plants in the outside world
would sometimes hybridize to one another,
creating a variety
that's perhaps type two,
which is going to have
less THC and more CBD,
or a type three, which is
going to be very high CBD
and very little THC,
and the same is also true
for the indica varieties.
So I want to make sure that
everyone understands this,
because it becomes very important
for understanding the biology of cannabis
and predicting positive versus
negative effects of cannabis.
Sativa has this stimulant-like effect
and tends to be more of
a head high, if you will.
Indica tends to be more full-body,
then lead to more in-da-couch,
as I refer to it before,
pun intended, deep relaxation,
reduce insomnia, et cetera.
Now, within each of
those sativa and indica,
you have type one, type
two and type three,
and that has everything
to do with how much THC,
which is the dominant
psychoactive compound,
versus CBD, which has other
effects, mainly on the body,
but not so much on the brain
and modes of thinking and mood, et cetera,
how much THC versus CBD is present.
And again, type one is THC dominant,
type two, equal ratios, if
you will, of THC and CBD,
and type three tend to be high CBD.
Okay, so already we've got
some categorization here
that hopefully isn't overwhelming to you,
but this turns out to
be extremely important
if you want to understand
how cannabis works
and predict the effects of cannabis.
I'd like to take a quick break
and acknowledge one of our
sponsors, Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens, now called AG1,
is a vitamin mineral probiotic drink
that covers all of your
foundational nutritional needs.
I've been taking Athletic
Greens since 2012,
so I'm delighted that they're
sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I started
taking Athletic Greens,
and the reason I still
take Athletic Greens,
once are usually twice a day,
is that it gets to me the probiotics
that I need for gut health.
Our gut is very important.
It's populated by gut microbiota
that communicate with the
brain, the immune system,
and basically all the
biological systems of our body
to strongly impact our
immediate and long-term health,
and those probiotics in Athletic Greens
are optimal and vital
for microbiotic health.
In addition, Athletic
Greens contains a number
of adaptogens, vitamins and minerals
that make sure that all of my foundational
and nutritional needs are
met, and it tastes great.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman,
and they'll give you
five free travel packs
that make it really easy
to mix up Athletic Greens
while you're on the road,
in the car, on the plane, et cetera,
and they'll give you a year's
supply of vitamin D3 K2.
Again, that's athleticgreens.com/huberman
to get the five free travel packs
and the year's supply of vitamin D3 K2.
Okay, so somewhat surprisingly,
we're going to set aside cannabis.
We're going to take what we
know about sativa, indica,
type one, type two, type
three, CBD, et cetera,
and we're just going to set
that aside for a moment.
Why would we do that?
Well, we have to ask ourselves,
why would any of these plants,
why would any of these
compounds, THC, CBD,
sativa, indica, et cetera,
why would any of that have
any effect on us at all?
And this discussion
that we're about to have
very much resembles the discussion
that we had on a previous
episode about nicotine,
because as many of you know,
nicotine is a commonly used substance.
In fact, if we were to look
at the three most commonly used drugs,
alcohol will be at the top of the list.
Many billions of people
regularly use alcohol
or occasionally use alcohol.
Many billions of people also use nicotine.
It's the second most consumed
drug, so more than 1 billion
and probably closer to 2
billion people consume nicotine,
and then the third most consumed drug
is cannabis in one form or another.
And many of you are probably shouting,
"What about caffeine?
What about caffeine?"
Well, in the context of drugs,
and in particular, addictive drugs,
caffeine doesn't quite rise to the list,
but if we were to look at caffeine
and include it in that list,
caffeine would be above all of those.
But the most commonly
used drugs are alcohol,
second after that is
nicotine and then cannabis.
Nicotine, as some of you may know,
if you listen to the episode on nicotine,
but even if you didn't,
nicotine comes from the tobacco plant,
and there are a few other
plants that include nicotine,
and typically it's brought
into the brain and body
by smoking tobacco, dipping tobacco,
snuffing tobacco or vaping nicotine.
Nicotine exists in the outside world
in these plants, the tobacco plants,
but the reason it has
an effect on the body
is that there are so-called
nicotinic receptors in the body.
Now, those nicotinic receptors
were named after nicotine,
the compound, but they
existed in the brain and body,
not because of the existence
of a tobacco plant,
but because there are
other chemicals in the body
that naturally occur, namely acetylcholine
that bind the nicotine receptor.
Those chemicals, such as acetylcholine,
that bind the nicotinic
receptor in your brain and body
create an enhanced sense of
focus, et cetera, et cetera.
But, nicotine from tobacco
binds that same receptor,
but with much greater affinity,
and therefore also
creates a state of focus,
but a much greater one than we
can achieve without nicotine.
So you can see the nicotine episode
if you want to learn more about that.
In a very similar way, all
of our brains and bodies,
from the time that we are
conceived, believe it or not,
very shortly after conception,
if we want to be accurate,
very early conception,
when you were in the womb,
and still now, if you're
listening to this,
you have what are called
cannabinoid receptors,
because you also have
endogenous cannabinoids.
What do we mean by that?
You have receptors, which
are like little parking spots
that are present on cells
in your brain and body,
and what we call a ligand,
which is basically just a
chemical that's released,
parks in that receptor
and causes a number of
different biological effects.
Cannabis contains compounds
that also bind to those receptors,
but here I want to make a
really clear distinction.
We have what are called
endogenous ligands,
those just mean chemicals from within us
that we make naturally,
even if we never go
near the cannabis plant
or any other source of cannabis,
we have chemicals that are created in us
that park in those receptors
and cause biological effects
on mood, on perception,
on the immune system,
on hunger, et cetera,
again, without ever going
anywhere near cannabis,
we have these endogenous cannabinoids.
So endogenous cannabinoids
are floating around in us,
or I should say, they are released in us
in particular ways,
bind to these receptors
and cause changes in
mood, appetite, et cetera.
They have many different
effects on the brain and body,
and we'll talk about those.
But just like with nicotine,
there are substances in the outside world,
in this case, cannabis
contains these substances,
so things like THC and like
CBD, that when ingested
by smoking or vaping
or by ingesting edibles
also will park in those same receptors,
the cannabinoid receptors and
lead to biological effects.
Now, it's a little bit misleading,
because we call them cannabinoid receptors
as if they were there to bind cannabis,
or just like we call
the nicotine receptors,
nicotinic receptors, it makes
it seem as if they were there
in order to bind nicotine from tobacco,
but that's not the way our
brains and bodies evolved.
Our brains and bodies
evolved for these receptors
to make use of chemicals
that exist within us,
called again, endogenous chemicals,
and those endogenous chemicals
lead to certain effects,
as I mentioned before.
The key thing here,
if you haven't understood
anything I've set up until now,
please understand this, the key thing is
that THC and CBD and the
other components of cannabis
bind to those receptors,
those endogenous cannabinoid receptors,
the ones that we naturally
make, with much greater affinity
and exert a vastly
greater potency and effect
on mood and perception, et cetera,
than do our endogenous cannabinoids.
Another analogy that one could take
in order to understand this
would be hormones, like
testosterone and estrogen.
Many people, I would say all people,
make testosterone and
estrogen to varying degrees.
It's going to depend on whether
or not you're male, female,
your age, whether or not
you've gone through puberty,
et cetera, et cetera,
but let's just take
testosterone for example.
There's testosterone
circulating in your body.
That's true if you're male or female,
and there are receptors
called androgen receptors,
we could even call them
testosterone receptors.
And the testosterone
binds to those receptors
and has effects on cells.
It causes hair growth, changes the voice.
It can affect libido.
It affects all sorts of
things in the brain and body,
depending on which organ and
tissue you're talking about.
But of course,
there are people that take
synthetic testosterone
or derivatives of testosterone,
and some of those derivatives,
for instance, in the
body building community
and the sports community,
they will take things like Dianabol.
These are modified
versions of testosterone
that can bind to the testosterone receptor
with much greater affinity,
or I should say the androgen receptor
and have supra physiological effects,
effects that would
essentially never be seen
from testosterone that was endogenously,
excuse me, endogenously
released within the body.
We could say the same thing for estrogen.
There are estrogen receptors,
they bind estrogen,
but if someone were to
take synthetic estrogen
or to ingest a plant compound
that contains various
estrogenic compounds,
and those plants
certainly exist out there,
they can have supra physiological effects
on those receptors.
Why am I telling you this?
Well, many people believe
that because cannabis,
marijuana is a plant, and
plants grow out of the ground,
and they're naturally occurring,
and because we have receptors in our body
that are there without
the need to engineer them
from some external source,
they're in our genome.
They're program for it, and
we're born with these things,
and we keep these our entire life.
Many people mistakenly think,
ah, these plant compounds
are safer for us or better for us,
or are somehow appropriate
for us to ingest,
but that's simply not true,
and here, I'm not saying
that cannabis is always
a bad idea for people.
There are certain populations
and certain people
for which it can be relatively
safe recreationally,
that's the truth, and
there are other populations
for which it can be downright dangerous,
recreationally or medicinally.
And of course, there
are medicinal purposes
that are being explored, and
we'll talk more about that.
But this is vital to understand,
because I think that when we hear,
"Oh, it's from a plant, it's natural,"
and then you also have
a receptor for these,
endogenous cannabinoid receptors,
and therefore, the marriage of those two,
the coming together of the
chemical THC or CBD or both
with these receptors is
somehow supposed to happen
as if this was a purpose
of having these receptors,
but it's simply not the case.
In the same way that
the nicotinic receptors
are not there because
nicotine is good for us,
they're there because there are compounds
that exist within us that are good
to bind to those receptors
from time to time.
Now, here's the key thing about,
I guess today, I'm saying
there are a lot of key things,
but here's another key thing
about understanding cannabis
and the way that it works,
which is that THC and CBD,
when they're brought
into the brain and body
by smoking or edible, et cetera,
they bind to those receptors,
those endogenous cannabinoid receptors,
and they tap into the same systems
that your endogenous
cannabinoids would tap into,
the ones that affect mood and energy
and creativity and relaxation, et cetera,
but they do so with thousand
fold greater potency.
And as a consequence of that,
your endogenous cannabinoids
are outcompeted.
They really get no opportunity
to interact with those receptors.
And understanding that,
can lead to a very clear
understanding of why, for instance,
when people use cannabis
to relieve anxiety,
or they use cannabis to
enter a certain brain state
for creativity or to enter sleep,
why a dependence on
cannabis starts to emerge.
Because if they don't ingest cannabis,
and again, ingest could
mean smoke to bring THC in,
or CBD in, or ingest
orally or even transdermal
or tincture or one of the other varieties,
if they don't do that,
then what happens is
not only are the receptors not
stimulated to the same degree
or with the same potency
that they normally are,
but the endogenous cannabinoids
can no longer have their effect,
so people experience
heightened levels of anxiety,
disrupted mood, disrupted
brain state, and so on.
Now, again, I want to be very clear
that I'm not trying to
paint a picture of cannabis
as all bad or even partially bad.
What I want to do today is give you
as much information I can
as to how cannabis works,
how its different component parts work,
how the different types of cannabis work,
and point to some of
the valid medicinal uses
and some of the recreational uses,
and then lay out the landscape for you
as to who is really most at risk
in terms of psychoactive components,
immune components and so on and so forth,
so that you can make the
most informed choice for you.
I am not here to tell you
what to do or what not to do.
As I like to say, do as you wish,
I mean, don't do as you wish
if it harms other people or yourself,
but do as you wish, but
know what you're doing,
so that's really my goal here.
So as we begin to dive
further into the biology,
I think you'll start to
get a clearer picture
of why cannabis is so
effective in some context,
but also why it can create
such massive suffering
in other contexts because of the way
that it out-competes your own natural
endogenous cannabinoid systems.
So let's talk about those
endogenous cannabinoid systems,
what they are and how they work,
because that will give us a lens
into what the higher
potency or maximum impact
of the various cannabis
plant varieties and strains
in THC and CBD and so forth,
how and why those work.
So what are the endogenous cannabinoids,
these chemical substances
that everybody makes?
You make them, I make them.
You've been making them basically
from the time that you were conceived,
and you are going to make them
until the time that you die.
Whether or not they have the impact
and the biological functions
that I'm about to describe
will depend a lot on whether or not
you are using your own
endogenous cannabinoids
to park in those receptors
that you also have
from birth until death,
or whether or not you are
tickling those receptors
or strongly activating those receptors
using some external source like
cannabis and THC, et cetera.
The two main endogenous cannabinoids
that we want to consider are anandamide,
which we will refer to
as EAE, so anandamide,
and another one, which
is arachidonoyl-glycerol,
arachidonoyl-glycerol, which
we will abbreviate 2-AG.
So let's just take EAE and
2-AG, lump them together
and talk about the
endogenous cannabinoids,
just to make it simple.
But if you want to do the
deep dive on anadamide
versus 2-AG, please be my guest.
The endogenous cannabinoids
are released from neurons.
What are neurons? Neurons are nerve cells.
And nerve cells should be
conceptualized like this.
You have presynaptic neurons
and postsynaptic neurons.
Presynaptic neurons basically
contain little vesicles,
little bubbles full of neurotransmitter,
which are chemicals,
and when neurons are
stimulated electrically,
and that could be from a thought,
it could be from the desire to move,
it could be because of a drug,
it could be because you're hungry,
the relevant neurons will vomit
out or will fuse, as we say,
those little packets, those little bubbles
of neurotransmitter into the gap
between the pre and postsynaptic neuron,
and we call that a synaptic
cleft or the synapse.
It's a little gap, a little space,
and the neurotransmitter
flows across that synapse,
and some of it will park
in the little parking spots
that we call receptors on
the postsynaptic neuron side.
Depending on which neurotransmitter it is,
and a bunch of other things
not worth going into right now,
the parking of that chemical
and those neurotransmitter receptors
will either cause that neuron
on the postsynaptic side
to itself, release
neurotransmitter elsewhere,
or it will quiet it down,
so-called excitation and inhibition.
That's kind of neuro
transmission in a nutshell.
If you don't understand it, no big deal.
It's not going to prevent you
from understanding today's discussion.
If you understand even a small fraction
of what I've just said,
then it's going to allow you to understand
not just today's discussion,
but a lot of neuroscience
with a lot more nuance and
depth of understanding.
The key thing to know about
the endogenous cannabinoids
is that unlike most neurotransmitters,
they are released from
the postsynaptic side.
So what happens is neurotransmitter goes
from presynaptic neuron
to postsynaptic neuron,
but under certain conditions,
the postsynaptic neuron,
itself, releases a chemical,
and that chemical goes backward,
what we call retrogradely,
to the presynaptic neuron,
binds to receptors there
and changes the probability
that the presynaptic neuron
will release neurotransmitter.
Put simply, endogenous cannabinoids
tend to decrease the probability
that a neuron will
release neurotransmitter.
They're a break on the system.
They're a way of shutting
down the communication
between neurons, regulating it,
not to make it completely quiet,
but to adjust the levels
with a lot of nuance.
Now, the other thing that the
endogenous cannabinoids do
is a mind bender, because
we're talking about cannabis,
and a commonly known feature
of cannabis and marijuana consumption
is disruptions in short-term memory,
and there is essentially zero debate
as to whether or not that occurs,
and we'll talk about the
mechanisms a little bit later.
And yet, endogenous cannabinoids,
the chemicals that you naturally release
from these postsynaptic neurons
that travel retrogradely back
to the presynaptic neuron,
actually can lead to
strengthening of connections
between the presynaptic neuron
and the postsynaptic neuron
through a process called
long-term potentiation, or LTP.
They can also cause
what's called depression of communication
between a presynaptic neuron
and a postsynaptic neuron.
Long-term depression has nothing to do
with depression as a psychological
state or as a illness.
Long-term potentiation
and long-term depression
simply refer to the probability
that one neuron will be able
to stimulate and activate another neuron.
And, as I just told you,
the endogenous cannabinoids
can either turn up the dial
or turn down the dial.
They can either increase the probability
or decrease the probability
that a given connection between neurons
will function more or will function less.
So if you think about the
communication between neurons
as crosstalk, as a conversation,
well, the endogenous cannabinoids
can dictate whether or not
that conversation is likely
to occur or not to occur.
Think of them as either putting someone
at the top of your text
chain in your phone,
which would be long-term potentiation,
or essentially blocking their number,
which would essentially
be long-term depression.
So, if you're getting the impression
that the endogenous cannabinoids
are working in a number of different ways,
and it's not very
straightforward, you're right.
In fact, that's the message
that I'd like you to take away.
The endogenous cannabinoids
are sometimes increasing
neuronal communication.
This can lead to increases in mood
or increases in the likelihood
that someone will talk a certain way
or behave a certain way
or feel a certain way.
That can also lead to decreases
in synaptic transmission,
that is communication between neurons,
in ways that will make
somebody's mood lower,
or will make them less
hungry or more hungry.
And, here's the really key thing,
there are two kinds of
endogenous cannabinoid receptors,
referred to as CB1 and CB2,
and we can say with confidence that CB1
is highly enriched in the nervous system,
and especially within the brain.
It's found not everywhere,
but almost everywhere in the brain
and elsewhere in the nervous system,
so spinal cord and other
aspects of the nervous system.
CB2, the cannabinoid receptor, CB2
is largely located in
the tissues of the body,
including the immune system, the liver,
even the genitals, et cetera.
So what this means is that
the endogenous cannabinoids
are having these sorts of effects
on neurons that I talked about,
but they are also having
effects on immune cells,
on reproductive organs, on liver,
on digestion, on hunger, et cetera,
through mechanisms that are divorced
from the function of the
nervous system of neurons.
Now, in reality, no system
of the brain and body
is divorced from the nervous system,
because the nervous system
is controlling everything.
It is really the master controller,
and everything's feeding
back to the nervous system,
so it's a two way street.
But the simple way to think
about it is CB1 receptors
are mainly in the nervous system,
and CB2 receptors are mainly in the body
and endogenous cannabinoids,
again, EAE, anandamide,
and 2-AG, arachidonoyl-glycerol,
are impacting CB1 and CB2 receptors.
Today we're mainly going to
talk about CB1 receptors,
'cause they are the ones
that are responsible
for most of the familiar
effects of cannabis,
but the key takeaway at this
point is to really understand
that the major effects of
your endogenous cannabinoids
on these receptors in this
particular CB1 are very nuanced.
It depends on context,
depends on which neurons.
It's sometimes increasing
communication between neurons,
sometimes decreasing it, and
then along comes cannabis,
and that cannabis, again,
can arrive by smoking,
by vaping, by edible.
And cannabis contains THC and CBD
that potently bind the CB1 receptor,
and now the effects of the CB1 receptor
being occupied by THC or
being occupied by CBD,
are not very nuanced.
In fact, they are very predictable
and especially important is to understand
that they are so strong, and
they park in that receptor
with such affinity, with
such force and precision
and stubbornness and refusal
to leave that receptor
that they completely outcompete
the endogenous cannabinoid system.
In fact, they leave the
endogenous cannabinoid system
essentially dysfunctional,
which, in some cases,
may be a good thing, but in most cases,
is going to lead to
problems of various kinds,
and we'll talk about
what sorts of problems.
And again, I feel obligated to say,
this is not me saying don't
ingest cannabis or THC or CBD.
That's not what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is if
you evaluate the potency
that is in technical terms,
it would be the affinity
with which these compounds,
THC and CBD and CBN, bind to
these endogenous receptors,
that would be like a howitzer
gun, like a cannon going off,
as compared to endogenous cannabinoid,
whether or not it's EAE or 2-AG,
which is more like a cap
gun level of activation,
at least in this analogy.
So now you have what at
least I would like to think
is a fairly complete understanding
of the different varieties of cannabis,
at least at a broad sweep,
and the different biological
effects that they can have,
at least in terms of the major receptors
and in retrograde signaling,
et cetera, et cetera.
Now, let's take a step
back into the real world
and evaluate or think about
what happens when somebody smokes cannabis
or ingests cannabis by way of edible
or tincture or something of that sort.
Cannabis is very fast to
enter the bloodstream.
In fact, within 30 seconds,
it's going to enter the brain
and permeate throughout
the brain and body.
That's very, very fast.
I mean, when you contrast that
with something like
alcohol or even nicotine,
depending on how the
nicotine is delivered,
that is a very fast
delivery of the psychoactive
and biologically active compound,
which in this case is THC and CBD
and probably some other things as well.
So within 30 seconds,
it reaches the brain and bodily tissues,
and within 30 to 60 minutes,
it's going to reach
its peak concentrations
and have its peak biological effects.
Those aren't always the same thing,
but in the case of cannabis,
again here I'm using
cannabis as an umbrella term
for THC and CBD, the
effects are going to peak
at about 30 to 60 minutes
after bringing those compounds
into the body in some way or another.
And the effects tend to last
anywhere from three to four hours,
although there's some variation on that,
depending on individual metabolism,
whether or not somebody is
familiar with the compound,
believe it or not,
psychologically familiar,
but also biologically familiar,
or whether or not it's a first time use
or occasional use and so on.
THC and CBD and other
components of cannabis
are highly what we call lipophilic.
That is, they have an affinity toward,
and they can actually pass
through fatty tissues.
Now, every cell in your
body, but especially neurons,
have a double layer of
fat on their outside.
And of course, when people hear "fat,"
they always think, ooh, fat's bad.
Most of the world seems to
want to lose fat or bodily fat.
Here we're talking about
the fatty membrane,
the barrier around each tissue,
in this case we're talking
particularly about neurons.
And THC and CBD and the
other components of cannabis
are highly lipophilic,
so they can get into
essentially all cells just
simply by flowing into them.
They will also remain in
those cells for a long time.
So, I know that a number of people,
depending on whether
or not they get tested
for work or for sport or otherwise
for cannabis or CBD and THC,
don't take this as a strict number,
but typically, if one ingests CBD or THC,
smokes cannabis, ingests
by orally, et cetera,
doesn't matter, it's going
to stay in that fatty tissue
and can be detected for at
least as long as 80 days
after ingestion, and
there's a whole industry
as to how to accelerate the clearance,
and I should just tell you
that just losing bodily fat
isn't going to eliminate
it from your system,
maybe partially in those fat cells,
but certainly intravisceral
fat and other fatty tissue
that's in around the brain and body
is going to harbor that THC
molecule and the CBD molecule
for quite a long while, at least 80 days.
So, if someone smokes cannabis
or they ingest cannabis,
it very rapidly gets into the bloodstream,
and the components that are psychoactive
get into the bloodstream
and are immediately able to
access neurons and other cells
and start having these effects
of parking at those endogenous
cannabinoid receptors
and impacting the
signaling between neurons,
which leads to the subjective
effects of cannabis,
including THC and CBDs,
so let's talk about
what those different
subjective effects are.
Again, this is going to vary
depending on whether or not
people are ingesting sativa
varieties of cannabis,
just to remind you, those
tend to be elevated mood,
alertness, talkativeness.
People who take sativa varieties
tend to talk a lot more
than they would otherwise.
Again, there are exceptions to this,
of course there are exceptions.
I'm sure there are people
out there shouting,
although I guess if
you're the quiet people
who don't talk too much,
you're probably not shouting,
or if you're not, you're
not doing on sativa,
Joe contended, but in any
event, there are exceptions,
but there are also general rules.
And the sativas tend to
make people's mood elevated,
energetic, again, this sort of head high,
and indica varieties
tend to do the opposite.
more of a sedative, relaxant, et cetera.
Why and how would they do that?
Well, without going into
an extensive deep dive
into the different
neurotransmitter systems
of the brain and body,
what we know for sure
is that CB1 receptors are present
on an enormous number of different neurons
in brain structures in neural circuits,
so that the sativa varieties
that act as a stimulant,
making people feel happy,
'cause in general, they
do tend to elevate mood,
at least at certain dosages, talkative,
tend to make people feel
like they have ideas
that are interesting, that
they might want to share,
tend to narrow their context,
so we tend to increase focus.
This is something that's not
often discussed about cannabis,
but especially the sativa varieties
can increase people's level
of focus to particular things,
something they're watching
or something they're doing
or music, it allows them to
narrow their sense of focus.
That's going to occur by
activation of CB1 receptors
in the so-called prefrontal cortex,
which is just behind the forehead,
and the prefrontal cortex
acts as a strong modulator
of so-called limbic
circuitry and other circuitry
that is more stress oriented.
The way to think about the
stress and limbic circuitry,
such as the amygdala, which
many people have heard about,
is that they aren't really
circuits for fear and stress.
They are circuits that
are constantly evaluating
one's own internal state,
heart rate, et cetera,
and what's happening
externally, and, sorry to say,
but the default of those
systems is to detect danger,
so threat detection systems.
And then the prefrontal
cortex largely acts
as a brake on those systems,
so like the reins pulling
back on a steed of horses
that would otherwise just take off.
And so, the sativa varieties
tend to increase CB1 activation
in the prefrontal cortex
and in other circuitry
that then leads to an
overall reduction in stress,
because of the way that
prefrontal circuitry
can reduce activation or the amygdala.
Now that, of course, does not explain
why some people become very
stressed and very paranoid
when they smoke sativa varieties
or other varieties of cannabis
or ingest other varieties of cannabis.
We'll talk about the paranoid
effect and why that occurs
and who might predict
that would occur to them
in a little bit.
But I just want to give you a
sense of how this is working,
because as I mentioned before,
THC and/or CBD are going
to bind that CB1 receptor,
let's say in prefrontal cortex,
the neurons of the prefrontal
cortex, it's going to bind there,
and then they'll be a retrograde signaling
back to the presynaptic neuron,
and in the case of prefrontal cortex,
what's happening is it's
increasing transmission,
increasing the release of neurotransmitter
in the prefrontal cortex.
However, at the same time,
the very same THC and CBD that
was brought into the system
is binding the very same type
of receptors, CB1 receptors,
in other brain structures,
such as the amygdala
and causing retrograde signaling
back to the presynaptic
neurons in the amygdala,
but it's quieting the
activation of those neurons,
so this is interesting.
We have the same
compounds, THC and/or CBD,
brought into the body and brain,
binding the same receptors, in
this case the CB1 receptors,
but depending on where
those receptors are located
and which brain areas we're referring to,
they are either causing
heightened levels of alertness
and activation of
systems that are designed
to make you talkative and
alertness and mood, et cetera,
focus, or they're causing
suppression of those circuitries.
So we have kind of a seesaw effect here
where the same compound is
increasing mood and alertness
and focus in the prefrontal cortex
and is decreasing stress
and threat detection
in the amygdala, and that's
one of the reasons why,
especially the sativa
varieties of cannabis,
allow people to enter
these states of focus,
some might even say flow,
although I don't want to go
into what flow states really are.
That's for a different discussion,
and it's very poorly defined as it is.
And I certainly don't want
to give people the impression
that cannabis increases flow states,
because that's not always the case,
and certainly most often is
not going to be the case.
But the idea here is that this
molecule comes into our brain
and is shifting everything
towards a state of focus,
elevated mood of heightened
sense of importance
about whatever it is that
we happen to be doing.
And now of course, whatever
we could happen to be doing
could be writing a song, writing poetry,
communicating with somebody,
but it could also be something as trivial
as watching cartoons or watching a movie,
which is not trivial in its own right,
but in terms of thinking
about the creative aspects
or the creativity stimulating
aspects of cannabis,
not productivity oriented.
So narrowed focus, elevated mood,
more relaxed and yet energetic,
that's the major effects
of the sativa varieties,
except, and this is a really big boldface,
triple underlined 'except,'
except in some individuals,
depending on dosage,
but also depending on
preexisting neural circuitry
and propensity for anxiety,
some people ingest or
smoke sativa varieties,
and regardless of whether
or not it's a type one,
type two or type three variety,
regardless of the ratio
between THC and CBD,
people will experience
intense anxiety and paranoia.
Now, how do you predict
who will experience intense
anxiety and paranoia
and who will experience
intense relaxation, focus
and sense of creativity from ingesting
or smoking a type one, type
two or type three sativa?
Well, there is no way to predict that,
and there's a lot of what
I would call street lore
or dorm room lore or not peer reviewed,
but peer discussed
among friends and people
and acquaintances lore out
there that what one needs to do
is simply smoke more, or just ingest more.
You hear that, "Oh, well listen,
if it makes you paranoid,
"you simply need to use more,"
that is absolutely categorically false.
Everything we know about the
way that THC and CBD work
is that they tend to potentiate,
that is increase the effects
of these different systems
at given synapses and in different areas
of the brain and body.
That is, if someone
experiences paranoia or anxiety
from a given strain of the marijuana plant
or from ingesting an
edible in a particular way
or a particular kind of edible,
that person is very likely
to experience the same effect
every time they ingest
that strain or variety.
This is part of what's led
to this enormous industry.
I mean, there are a number
of different reasons,
but this is part of what's
led to this enormous industry
of highly customized cannabis
where people will spend some time
really seeking out the
different strains of cannabis
and hybrids of cannabis
that work best for them
and work best for them
in particular context.
I wish I could tell you
that if you are a person
who is between 5' 7" and 6' tall,
and you have blue eyes or brown eyes,
that the sativa varieties are
going to be right for you,
or that sativa varieties are
going to give you panic attacks,
I can't do that.
The only way to determine it would be
to actually experience ingesting
those or smoking those,
which is certainly also
not what I'm suggesting.
That's up to you.
I'm not telling you what
to do or what not to do,
but there are no good predictors.
In fact, if you look in the literature,
it is not at all clear that people
who have a heightened level of anxiety
when they do not smoke cannabis
will experience cannabis
as less paranoia inducing
or more relaxing.
That's simply not the case.
Now, what we can say for sure
is that general categories of effects,
such as increased focus
and reduced anxiety
are largely due to activation of areas
like the prefrontal cortex.
Now, unlike other compounds
like nicotine or alcohol
or neurotransmitter systems like dopamine,
when we talk about the cannabinoid system,
and I say effects, biological
effects, psychoactive effects,
I want you to keep in mind always,
please, please, please keep in mind
that those effects can be varied
and often opposite in direction,
so let's just give an example of that.
I just mentioned that when
people smoke or or eat sativa,
that it tends to lead to one specific set,
or generally leads to one
specific set of effects,
heightened focus, mood, et cetera.
Whereas when they ingest or
smoke indica and its components,
again, we're still
talking about THC and CBD
in varying ratios, but now
indica cannabis, and you say,
"Well, why would it improve
the transition time to sleep?"
Or at least give people the impression
that it improves the
transition time to sleep.
We'll talk about what indica actually does
for sleep in a little bit,
but indica also tends
to suppress activation
of the amygdala and threat
detection centers in the brain,
again, binding the same CB1 receptors
in those retrograde signaling mechanisms
that I talked about before,
but it also tends to shut
down the hippocampus,
an area of the brain
associated with memory,
which is why indica
varieties lead to pronounced,
or I should say profound
defects in short-term memory
and sometimes in long-term memory as well,
if it's consumed over
long periods of time.
We'll talk about short, medium
and long-term consumption,
occasional consumption going forward.
So what I'd like you to take away
from this component of the
discussion is first of all,
the mechanism of action
by which cannabis impacts
the brain and body,
but in particular the brain,
is going to be through CB1 receptors,
and those CB1 receptors can
lead to either an acceleration
or a brake on particular
biological mechanisms.
And there are going to be a constellation
of different accelerations and braking
of different neural systems
in the brain and body,
depending on whether or
not people ingest sativa
or indica or some hybrid strain.
And perhaps most importantly,
even if you didn't understand anything
that I've said about the biology
of these different
strains in the receptors,
please do understand that
there is no way to predict
what the effect of a given
strain will be on an individual.
There has been extensive exploration
as to whether or not people
who are so called mellower
or more anxious or any number
of different personality dimensions
will respond in one way or the other,
but, in fact, there is no way to tell.
Layer on top of that the
fact that dosing THC and CBD
can be fairly straightforward
in the form of edibles,
because there can be, at least
if it's a controlled source,
a defined number of milligrams of THC,
a defined number of milligrams of CBD.
That's true for ingestibles.
It's much harder to gauge that
from the smokeable forms of cannabis,
especially if those
smokeable forms of cannabis
are obtained through sources
where there isn't a lot
of clear information
about the total amount
of THC in that product.
Now, this is all changing
quite a lot nowadays
because of the commercialization
of of THC and CBD products
and cannabis in a number
of different areas,
including in the United States.
But still, many people
are ingesting cannabis,
THC, CBD through sources
where they don't really know
how much they're bringing
into their system.
And so, whether or not someone
gets incredible anxiety
relief, enhanced sense of mood
and focus and wellbeing,
pain relief, et cetera,
or whether or not they have
full blown panic attacks,
et cetera, is very hard to predict
based on dosage information alone.
Now, of course, we can
create broad categories,
and we are going to talk about studies
that create broad categories
of low dose, moderate dose,
and high dose. frequent
use and infrequent use,
but unlike alcohol, unlike nicotine,
we can't really point to
specificity of X amount of alcohol,
grams of alcohol per week, which is safe,
or X amount of alcohol, which is not safe.
And so I know a lot of people
out there are wondering,
how often can they smoke cannabis,
or how often can they eat
cannabis or THC or CBD
in any number of its different
forms and products, safely?
Well, we have to really
define what 'safely' means,
and we have to really acknowledge
that there's a pretty
loose set of controls
over what one is bringing
into their brain and body
as they ingest THC and CBD,
but even under conditions in
which it's very controlled,
it's very hard to predict
what those effects will be.
So before moving into specifics
of taking cannabis or not taking cannabis,
who should, who shouldn't,
what the medicinal purposes are
and what some of the newer,
exciting data point to,
I just briefly want to make a list,
and I promise very briefly,
I know I'm not often concise,
but I do try to be thorough for your sake.
I want to make a very brief list
of the different brain areas
that are impacted by THC and CBD
and why THC and CBD have
the various effects they do.
When somebody smokes or ingests cannabis,
doesn't matter what the
THC or CBD ratio is,
if they experience deficits in memory,
and that's almost always
present, that's going to be
because of reductions
in electrical activity
within this brain region
we call the hippocampus.
Hippocampus means seahorse.
It's shaped like a seahorse.
Anatomists like to name things
after what things look like,
but hippocampus memory, memory is reduced,
in particular short-term memory.
That's true regardless of whether or not
one is using sativa indica or some hybrid.
In general, the prefrontal
cortex is going to be activated
by the sativa varieties, which
is going to increase thinking
and narrowly constrain
focus to some activity,
and that's more commonly associated
with the sativa varieties.
The indica varieties,
as I mentioned before,
tend to lead to a suppression of activity
in prefrontal cortex, believe it or not,
and turn off thinking and planning.
This is why indica
varieties are often used
for relaxation and for promoting sleep.
Regardless of whether or not
sativa or indica variety,
and again, regardless of
the ratio of THC to CBD,
there is a general
suppression of neural circuits
within the so-called basal
ganglia and cerebellum.
Basal ganglia and cerebellum
are areas of the brain
that are involved in action
planning and withholding action,
so that would be the basal ganglia,
so-called go, no go circuitry,
and the cerebellum, which
is involved in balance,
but also motor planning
and motor sequencing.
This is why people who smoke marijuana,
regardless of the strain,
will tend to be less physically mobile.
Other common effects are
reddening of the eyes,
dryness of the mouth,
that's actually caused by
the same general mechanism,
which is a reduction in
the secretion of saliva
and of tears and lubrication of the eyes
from the lacrimal glands of the eyes
because of the presence of largely CB2,
but also CB1 receptors in
the mouth and on the eyes.
And there tends to be,
especially with certain
strains of cannabis,
increase in appetite, so-called munchies,
and that has everything to do
with very, very high density
of CB1 receptors in the hypothalamus,
and in particular areas
of the hypothalamus,
like the arcuate nucleus
other areas as well, of course,
that have tons of CB1
receptors, bind THC and CBD
and activate the neurons that
strongly stimulate appetite
through two mechanisms, one
is a cognitive mechanism
of creating a preoccupation with food
in anticipation of taste,
as well as the experience of taste.
So the narrowing of focus
to what you want to go eat.
You really crave, I dunno, pizza.
It seems to be high fat,
high carbohydrate foods,
but really crave pizza
and narrowing of focus,
so that you're not thinking
about anything else,
but also signaling from
the hypothalamus to the gut
to neurons within the stomach, itself,
that regulate blood sugar,
so there are strong effects
on blood sugar of THC and CBD
that generally lead to
increases in appetite,
so two parallel mechanisms,
one within the brain,
one within the body, increasing appetite,
so there's an array of different effects.
And as I mentioned before,
CB1 receptors are present
all over the nervous system
in the brain, the spinal cord.
In fact, the presence of CB1
receptors in the spinal cord
largely explains the fact that
THC and CBD, to some extent,
although it's not very well studied,
can provide some pain relief.
I say some, because a
lot of people perceive
or believe that they
experience more pain relief
from cannabis than they actually do.
It actually has a lot to
do with a perceptual shift
to basically focusing on other things,
but there does seem to
be some antinociceptive,
meaning anti pain effects of
cannabis, THC in particular,
and that is exerted largely
through effects on CB1 receptors
in neurons of the spinal cord.
So a broad array of
effects are taking place,
regardless of what strain you take
and whether or not you eat the cannabis
or you smoke the cannabis.
And the broad array of effects
can be explained by the fact
that that retrograde signaling
can lead to activation
or suppression of activity
in various neurons.
So now I'd like to take a step back
from the biology of
cannabis and THC and CBD
and all the signaling
and receptors, et cetera,
and really just focus on cannabis use,
and wherever possible,
I will point to the specific
strains that have been studied
and the ratios of THC to CBD,
but I have to say that unfortunately,
most studies of marijuana, of cannabis,
while they have been very careful
to detail the amount of THC,
low dose, medium dose, or high dose,
and actually getting very specific,
right down to the number of milligrams
or even how much
circulating THC is present
after somebody smokes a
joint or ingests cannabis,
most studies have not distinguished
between sativa and indica strains.
And that's unfortunate,
because in the real world,
people are distinguishing
between sativa and indica strains
in their patterns of
use and what they prefer
and what they don't prefer,
or even what they prefer
to smoke during the day
or ingest during the day versus night.
Believe it or not, there are people
who are using certain
strains during the day
and other strains at night,
but the science is yet
to catch up to that,
or I should say, more accurately,
the general public and the
themes that are emerging
and the practices that are
emerging around cannabis,
especially in states where it's
decriminalized or legalized,
are occurring at such a rapid rate
that there's absolutely no way
that the science could keep up.
This is a naturally occurring experiment,
not to say that it's natural,
like people should do it,
but it's an experiment
that's happening in real time
in the real world, much
faster than controlled studies
within university laboratories
and other laboratories can keep up.
So at this point, I think it's
appropriate to ask ourselves,
why do people even use cannabis?
What are they trying to achieve?
Is it always about not feeling pain?
Is it always about reducing anxiety?
Well, sometimes it is,
but oftentimes people are using cannabis
in order to achieve a particular state.
And we could use a broad brush and say,
"Well, they just like being high,"
but while that may be true
in a lot of circumstances,
and I have to believe it actually is true
there are a lot of people who use cannabis
in a very directed way, or
they get, quote unquote, high,
in order to achieve states
that to them are particularly attractive,
and one such state is
a state of creativity.
And this brings us to a broader theme,
which is, does cannabis
increase creativity?
And if so, is it the THC, the CBD,
what's the appropriate ratio
or the best ratio for
accessing creativity?
This is an interesting and
important discussion, I believe,
because creativity is one
of the more sought after
and more elusive states
that humans can experience.
And yet, if you look at human evolution,
you look at our progression
in terms of technology development
and culture and music
and poetry, et cetera,
we really can look to
creativity as the state
that fostered so much of that evolution.
So whether or not you're into technology,
or you're into art or music,
whether or not you're just somebody
who wants to expand their understanding
or their experience of life in some way,
creativity is a
fundamentally important state
to try and access and to
try and access regularly
and to try and tap into,
in order to eventually produce something,
in order to create something of meaning
that exists not just
in that creative state,
but to yourself after that
creative state has gone away,
so the painting that you
paint in the creative state
hopefully is a painting
that still inspires
and has impact after you
exit that creative state
and that will inspire others,
and this could be true
for any number of different
things, not just painting.
So does cannabis increase creativity?
The short answer is, it depends.
First of all, we need
to define creativity.
Here we are, thinking as scientists,
if not already scientists,
and there are basically
two modes of thinking
that are associated with creativity,
and they don't completely
explain creativity.
But if you look in the research,
the psychology research and
the neuroscience research,
you'll hear about convergent thinking
and divergent thinking.
Convergent thinking is taking loose ideas
and kind of braiding them together,
finding a common thread, synthesizing,
and organizing those different ideas
into some common or specific framework
in order to get or create
some specific outcome.
So convergent thinking is
basically the person in the room
who's listening to all the
ideas and taking them all in.
Maybe it's a panel of, how should we
get a certain product out to market?
Or what are the different motifs
that we should include
in a piece of music?
Or what should we do
in terms of rearchitecting
a given physical space?
Taking in those different opinions,
those different ideas
from different people,
and then synthesizing them and coming up
with one or a small
subset of coherent ideas
that incorporate some or all
of the ones that they heard,
so that's convergent thinking.
It doesn't have to involve a
panel of people talking to you.
I use that as an example
of what goes on inside your own head
when you are engaging
in convergent thinking.
You're thinking, well,
so and so said this,
and I think that, and
you're braiding them through
and trying to get some common themes,
some common vector to emerge from that.
Divergent thinking, on the other hand,
is best described as brainstorming.
It's exploring ideas
and continuing to move
into the variation and
the vastness of ideas
in hopes of eventually
being able to converge
on some novel idea or framework.
So these are similar and related,
but typically the creativity process
involves first brainstorming
and divergent thinking,
and then in order to arrive at something,
to actually create
something, the verb 'create,'
not just thinking about
what you might create,
which occurs during divergent thinking,
but actually creating
something, a specific painting,
a specific song, a specific
body of literature,
a specific scientific project
or experiment and so on,
that usually involves convergent thinking.
Now these can be explored
in the laboratory,
and they can be explored
in the laboratories
through sets of different
types of questionnaires
or even tasks that you
can give human subjects,
and this has been done extensively
and across the entire body of data,
and by that I mean,
literally hundreds of studies
that have explored the relationship
between particular neuro
circuits and neurochemicals,
convergent and divergent thinking.
We can arrive at a principle,
and the principle involves a molecule
that many of you have heard
about before, which is dopamine.
Dopamine is a neuromodulator.
It's involved in motivation,
and it tends to direct our attention
to things outside of us, but
it's also closely related
to convergent thinking
and divergent thinking
and to the creative process.
And therefore, it should
come as no surprise
that diseases of the
nervous system, excuse me,
such as bipolar disorder,
which we've done in episode
all about bipolar disorder
or schizophrenia or mood disorders
that impact the levels of dopamine,
either make it way, way too
high or way, way too low,
strongly impact whether or
not people will be creative.
And I think the short takeaway
that makes the most sense
in terms of framing this,
and we covered this on the
episode on bipolar disorder,
sometimes called bipolar
depression, is that in professions
where there's a lot of creativity required
in order to succeed, so
again, musicians, composers,
artists, et cetera, you tend
to find more manic depression,
and manic depression,
at least in the manic states,
the hyperactive states,
are correlated with
elevated levels of dopamine.
Likewise, it has been seen over
and over throughout history
that individuals that have
mild forms of schizophrenia,
or even full-blown schizophrenia,
many famous painters for
instance, or musicians,
they are known to have
elevated levels of dopamine,
and they are quite creative.
Now, that doesn't mean
everybody who's creative
has elevated levels of dopamine,
although it's likely that
their levels of dopamine
are at least not diminished,
and it doesn't mean
that non-creative people
have low levels of dopamine,
so don't get carried away
with the interpretation here.
But the point is this,
dopamine levels strongly
relate to the probability
that you can engage in convergent
and divergent thinking,
and they do so in the following way.
When dopamine levels are high,
divergent thinking is more likely.
That is, when people
have a lot of dopamine
circulating in their system,
they tend to be very
expansive with their ideas,
they tend to brainstorm a lot,
they tend to be comfortable
and even want to,
or reflexively throw out a lot of ideas
so that sometimes even
seem a little disconnected.
Some people might think of this
as attention deficit, but it's not.
It's really the idea of
throwing out disparate ideas.
You hear sometimes, you
throw things against the wall
and see what sticks, that's
a obviously an analogy,
but people are throwing lots
of things against the wall
and seeing what stick,
and then seeing how the things
that stick fit together,
that's divergent thinking,
and elevations in dopamine
tend to increase divergent thinking.
However, they tend to do this
in an inverted U-shape way.
For those of you either
watching on YouTube,
I'm just drawing a hump, obviously,
and for those of you listening,
just imagine a U, the shape of a letter U,
and then just flip it upside
down, so it looks like a bump.
Turns out that when dopamine
levels are very low,
there's a low probability
of divergent thinking.
When dopamine levels are
high, as I mentioned before,
there's a high level or
probability of divergent thinking.
But when dopamine levels
go very, very high,
then there's again, a reduction
in divergent thinking.
In other words, there's a sweet spot
of elevated dopamine
for divergent thinking.
And again, divergent thinking
is critical for the creativity process,
because creativity by definition
is taking a novel set of ideas
and arranging them in a particular way,
or taking existing ideas and
arranging them in a novel way
that then you eventually converge
on some new product, new
idea, new song, et cetera.
Now, convergent thinking follows
a very different pattern.
When dopamine levels are high,
convergent thinking is not very likely.
And when dopamine levels are low,
convergent thinking is very likely.
So here, using arguably
a very reductionist view,
we're looking at all of this
thing we're calling creativity
through a very neurosciencey
reductionist lens,
we can say this.
The creative process
involves going into a state
where you're willing to
consider a lot of options,
many of which seem distantly
or not even connected to one another,
and dopamine facilitates
that divergent thinking state
in which you are perfectly happy
and in fact, experience a
joy, or elation, a comfort
and a pleasure in organizing
all these different ideas
that to anyone else might
seem not that related.
But when your dopamine
levels are elevated,
these all seem like great ideas
and that maybe there
are connections there.
You're not accepting all
of them as true and valid
and interesting in combining
them, but there's this idea
that it's worth entertaining
the possibility,
at least for moments.
And then, as dopamine levels drop,
there is the process
of convergent thinking,
which is taking options
down off the wall saying,
"No, no, that doesn't fit with that,
"that doesn't fit with that,
"but ah, that fits with
that, and that can work.
"That feels right or sounds
right or looks right."
That's the creativity process.
And so, I think this is not just important
for understanding cannabis,
which we'll get back to in a moment,
but it's important for
understanding creativity
and brain states in general.
Brain states are not, as we would say,
a square wave function.
You don't just drop into
a trench of creativity.
Creativity is not an
event, it's a process.
And what I'm telling you
is that it's a process
that involves divergent thinking
and consideration of a
lot of different ideas.
That's correlated with high
but not too high dopamine.
And then, one has to
transition into a state
of convergent thinking,
which is really honing in
on the ideas that seem to have validity
or that could have validity
and getting rid of everything else,
and that's associated with low dopamine.
It's more about logical
implementation and consideration
as opposed to thinking about
and considering everything.
So let's now return to the question
of whether or not cannabis
and its different components
increase creativity.
And when you look at
the literature on this,
you find studies that very
clearly point to a yes,
it increases creativity,
and it's not surprising,
therefore, that cannabis can
increase dopamine transmission,
that is dopamine levels,
in certain brain areas,
in particular brain areas
involved in thinking and planning.
So cannabis increases
dopamine in these areas.
Elevated dopamine increases
divergent thinking,
and divergent thinking is
associated with creativity,
and there are studies
that support the idea
that cannabis can increase creativity.
However, there are at
least as many studies
that say that cannabis does
not increase creativity,
that cannabis increases
consideration of multiple ideas,
perhaps through elevation of
dopamine and related systems,
but that ultimately the
ideas that converge from that
are not truly creative ideas,
at least they don't meet the criteria
for creative brainstorming
and extraction of ideas
that are truly novel,
so it doesn't increase
creativity, so which one is it?
Well, fortunately,
there's an entirely
distinct set of literature
that has taken all the other
literature into consideration,
and here's where we arrive.
So there's a really nice study
that explored creativity
in cannabis users,
and we will provide a link to this study.
First author is Emily LaFrance,
and the title of the paper,
somewhat amusing in its own right,
which is, it starts with a question,
inspired by Mary Jane, of course,
Mary Jane being one of
the old school versions
or ways of talking about
cannabis or marijuana.
Nowadays, people refer
to it mainly as pot,
as other names too, of course,
and the title of the paper is,
"Inspired by Mary Jane
Mechanisms Underlying
"Enhanced Creativity in Cannabis Users."
And I really like this study
for a couple of reasons.
First of all, they looked at
people who did not use cannabis
as well as people who used cannabis,
so they had two different groups,
but they did not evaluate
creativity of the cannabis users
while they were under the
influence of cannabis.
They looked at the level of creativity
in these cannabis users
when they were not under
the influence of cannabis
and asked whether or not
their ability to be creative
was enhanced by cannabis.
Now we're going to compare this to studies
in which people come into the laboratory
and actually use cannabis,
and then they evaluate
creativity under that context.
But this study has some unique takeaways
that I think are really interesting.
First of all, they did, yes,
see evidence for enhanced creativity,
and when I say enhanced creativity,
I mean within the context of
this divergent thinking thing
that I talked about a moment ago.
And when I say enhanced,
I mean significantly
greater than in non-users,
so people that don't use cannabis.
So right now I can imagine
that all the cannabis users
are cheering, "Yes, cannabis
increases creativity,
"makes people more creative
than they would be otherwise."
Well, this is interesting.
We have to ask ourselves
how that was accomplished.
And it turns out that
one of the major ways
in which it was accomplished
is that cannabis users,
even if they're not under
the influence of cannabis,
are far more open to novel ideas,
and they have a more
explorative and reduced anxiety,
or I should say lower
anxiety mode of thinking
when they explore novel ideas,
which is essential for divergent thinking.
So they observed both enhanced divergent
and convergent creative type
thinking in cannabis users.
And the source of that, they conclude is,
and here, I'll just quote,
"Cannabis users' higher levels
"of openness to experience are responsible
"for their enhanced
self-reported creativity
"and convergent thinking
test performance."
So it's not necessarily that cannabis
is increasing the capacity
of the brain areas
that are associated with creativity,
but rather, cannabis appears
to be increasing an openness
and probably doing that in
part through lowering anxiety
in particular people, and that openness
is leading to inclusion of more ideas
during the divergent thinking process.
They're willing to consider throwing up
more things on the wall to see
if they stick, so to speak.
So in their conclusions, they
have a really nice statement.
Again, I'll just read from the paper,
because they said it better
than I ever could, quote,
"While mainstream media
has propagated the idea
"that cannabis expands the
mind and enhances creativity,
"our results show the link
between cannabis and creativity
"is largely a spurious correlation,"
meaning that it's not the case
that cannabis increases creativity, but,
and I inserted the 'but' in this quote,
but "driven by differences in personality
"that are related to cannabis use.
"For example, openness to
experience that are related
"to both cannabis use and
augmented creativity."
This is a real chicken/egg
argument. What do I mean by that?
What I mean is, this paper finds
that people who are
more open to experience
are more likely to use cannabis,
and people who use cannabis
are going to be more
open to new experiences,
and that combination of
features, openness to experience,
and what that openness to
new experiences brings,
enhances the convergent
and divergent thinking
that is characteristic
of the creative process.
So in short, cannabis
increases creativity,
but through changes in personality
that tap into the creative process,
rather than directly
impacting the neural circuits
that, for instance, turn on creativity.
And I have to say, this
study is really important,
because by exploring cannabis users,
not while under the influence of cannabis,
they were able to tap
into this very important,
what I believe to be fact.
Because if you think about a study
in which you would have
one group using cannabis
and another group not using cannabis,
and then you give them some
task that taps into creativity,
you will see effects and very likely,
you'll see effects where
cannabis might even increase
divergent and convergent
thinking and creativity.
Those results have actually been published
many times before.
But given the varied
effects of cannabis and THC
that we talked about earlier,
through all of that
complex signaling stuff,
you can imagine that there
will also be other studies,
and in fact, there are,
where divergent and convergent
thinking and creativity
is not assisted by cannabis
and might even be reduced
by ingesting cannabis.
However, if one considers
that divergent thinking
is absolutely crucial to
the creativity process
and the range of things
that one will explore
will be enhanced by openness
and by reduced levels of anxiety,
so a willingness to
explore different options,
some of which might seem completely crazy,
and cannabis increases
the personality types
and reduces the anxiety that
create that sense of openness,
well then it makes perfect sense
why cannabis would increase creativity
in certain individuals, but not directly.
And this study, the
one I just referred to,
which I should say was published
in the journal,
"Consciousness and Cognition,"
and again, we'll provide a link to it,
did a wonderful job of teasing out
this impact of cannabis on personality,
which then impacts creativity.
So if somebody asks you,
or if you're wondering,
or if you feel like cannabis
increases creativity,
in some sense the answer is 'yes,'
but the answer is 'yes'
because of the ways
that it shapes openness to new ideas
and can, I should say 'can,'
because not in everybody,
but can, in some
individuals, reduce anxiety.
What this means is that
if you are somebody
who experiences anxiety or
increased levels of focus
from cannabis, regardless of the strain,
and here I have to imagine people
are exploring different strains,
if they're exploring them at all,
exploring different modes of delivery,
smoking or ingestible, et cetera.
If you're somebody who
experiences anxiety,
it's very likely that you won't
have the increased openness
to experience and divergent ideas
that will facilitate creativity.
However, if you are somebody
who achieves heightened levels
of relaxation and reduced
levels of anxiety from cannabis,
regardless of which strain we
happen to be talking about,
well then, yes, it will position you
to be in a heightened state of creativity,
at least as defined by convergent
and divergent thinking.
One of the more characteristic,
or I should say stereotype
qualities of people
that smoke a lot of
marijuana or ingest cannabis
through other means is there
changed patterns of speech.
In fact, there's a lore
in the clinical realm
that you can predict or
get some strong indication
as to whether or not
somebody is a cannabis user
or pot smoker based on their voice
and their particular tone of voice
and their lack of inflection.
There's a lot of speculation here,
but fortunately, it's been studied.
So I'd like to discuss now
whether or not cannabis can
impact patterns of speech,
both acutely, meaning while
under the influence of cannabis,
and over time, in chronic cannabis users.
And when I say 'chronic cannabis use,'
I want to be very specific what I mean.
Chronic cannabis use
does not necessarily mean
that people are smoking cannabis
or ingesting cannabis every day,
although certainly if they are,
that qualifies as chronic use.
Chronic use is regular use over time
of anywhere from twice a week or more.
So using cannabis once a month
would not be considered chronic use,
even if it's for many, many years.
Using cannabis or ingesting cannabis
in some way or form twice a week
would be considered chronic use.
Then of course, some of you out there
are going to ask me to
split hairs and say,
"Well, what if somebody
uses it twice a month?"
Well, listen, the clinical literature,
and the scientific literature
don't get that specific.
And of course, they're an
infinite number of ways
to arrange one's cannabis use,
everything from zero, none at all,
to constantly, every day, all
day and everywhere in between.
But think of chronic use
as twice a week or more.
Think of occasional use as less than that
and realize that within the
realm of chronic use, excuse me,
that 'or more' can be
anywhere from twice a week,
to every day, to just in
the evenings, et cetera.
The effects of chronic use of cannabis,
as I just defined it, on
speech have been studied.
Because of this characteristic,
drawing out of certain
syllables, a slowing of speech,
and in many cases a total
change or alteration
in the way that people
speak and use language,
both when under the influence of cannabis
and when not under the
influence of cannabis
if they're chronic users.
And here we really want to
distinguish between THC and CBD
and just make it really simple and say
that CBD is not responsible
for most of the psychoactive
effects of cannabis,
whereas THC is, and again,
the ratio of CBD to THC is
going to be relevant there,
but let's just think
about cannabis and THC
as one in the same for this
portion of the discussion,
realizing that, of course,
they are not exactly the same thing.
There's an excellent study entitled,
"Adults with History of
Recreational Cannabis Use
"Have Altered Speech Production,"
and we will provide a link to that,
first author, Adam Vogel,
really like this paper.
It was published in the journal,
"Drug and Alcohol Dependence."
We will provide a link to it for you
if you'd like to peruse it in more detail.
The title itself, "Adults
with a History of Recreational
"Cannabis Use Have Altered
Speech Production,"
tells you pretty much
everything you need to know,
except there's some
important nuance in here,
because, as I mentioned earlier,
people who smoke sativa
varieties of cannabis
oftentimes will become more
talkative, much more talkative.
However, whether or
not people tend to rely
on sativa cannabis use
or indica cannabis use,
there is a very consistent finding
that people who are chronic users,
again twice a week or more,
recreational use or medicinal use,
undergo pretty profound changes
in the way that they speak,
but in a very specific set of ways.
Now, first of all, the changes in speech
shouldn't surprise us at all,
because both sativa varieties of cannabis
and indica varieties of cannabis
impact those brain centers
involved in movement,
the basal ganglia, remember
the go, no-go circuitry,
the circuitry that makes
you want to do things,
and the circuitry that makes
you want to withhold action?
And it tends to shift the body and brain
toward more inaction.
And cannabis impacts CB1
receptors in the cerebellum,
which is involved in motor
planning, execution and balance.
So, regardless of whether or not people
are using cannabis of the
sativa or the indica variety,
there are disruptions in motor circuitry.
And, as you may have heard,
if you listened to our episode
with Rockefeller professor,
Dr. Erich Jarvis,
who works on speech and
movement, speech is movement.
The movements of the mouth,
the movements of the hands,
those are intimately related
in terms of our speech.
In fact, the centers of the
brain involved in hand movements
are part of the speech
areas and vice versa.
Erich actually pointed out
that if you put your
hands behind your back,
provided you normally do
have use of your hands,
it actually will reduce
your fluidity of speech,
and so I'm going to put them
back in front of me now.
The point is, smoking marijuana
or consuming marijuana
by edible changes one's speech
and does it in a very specific way.
And in this study by Adam
Vogel and colleagues,
they explored a huge different
variety of aspects of speech.
And this can be done
using spectral processing,
which is fancy nerd speak
for looking at how much
inflection there is
or looking at how long people hold vowels
or consonants, et cetera, and again,
these are people not under
the influence of cannabis,
but rather people who tend
to be under the influence
of cannabis when not
participating in the study,
in other words, chronic
recreational cannabis users.
So what are the two major
shifts that cannabis causes
on our patterns of speech?
Well, the first one is a change
in what's called spectral tilt.
Again, that's fancy nerd speak
for vocal effort and intensity.
So, I'm not a pot smoker, I confess,
but if I were to say the sentence,
"Vocal effort and intensity
"are important components of speech,"
that's the way I would say that sentence
if I was striving to
enunciate very carefully
and to accent certain words and syllables.
A pot smoker or somebody who
uses recreational cannabis
fairly often would have
reduced spectral tilt,
AKA, vocal effort
intensity, and might say,
[mumbling] "Spectral tilt is
vocal effort in intensity,
"and it differed between
groups and appeared to change
"in line with the duration of
abstinence from cannabis use."
That I think is not a far cry
from the change in spectral
tilt that they observed here.
In addition, there are
changes in verbal timing,
that is pronunciation of words
and accenting particular
syllables of words
in people that consume
cannabis or smoke cannabis.
So rather than emphasize
particular words within a sentence,
so again, I'll just use
a sentence from the paper
so that you can gain more
knowledge from the paper,
"Cannabis," and I'll say it
the way that I would say it,
since I'm not a cannabis user.
"Cannabis, marijuana, is
the most commonly used,
"illicit drug in the world with
approximately 4% of adults,
"aged 15 to 64 years reporting recent use,
"and the citation is from
the United Nations Office
"on Drugs and Crime, 2019."
So that would be the way
that I would typically read that sentence.
And having gone into
the data on this paper,
and of course evaluated references therein
and listened to some of
the spectral analysis
that they include as data,
you can literally go
into these papers online
and hear recordings of
people who are cannabis users
or non-cannabis users,
and I'll try and give you a a clear sense
without picking an extreme
example of how somebody
who's a fairly consistent or
even occasional cannabis user
might read that very same sentence.
"Cannabis, marijuana, is
the most commonly used
"illicit drug in the world
with approximately 4% of adults
"age 15 to 64 years reporting recent use,
"and the citation comes from
the United Nation Office
"on Drugs and Crime in 2019."
Now you'll notice that
wasn't a dramatic difference.
And, of course I could
have taken the liberty
to pick an extreme example of the sort
that they did occasionally observe
in evaluating subjects for this paper.
I could have said something like,
[mumbling in low tone]
"Cannabis, marijuana,
"is the most commonly used illicit drug,"
but frankly that would've been
selecting an outlier example,
and I don't want to do that.
I don't want to skew the data as they say.
Rather, if you heard the
first time I read the sentence
and the second time I read the sentence,
what's mainly different is the difference
in the amount of enunciation and accenting
of particular words and
symbols within a sentence.
So the total content that's
delivered is exactly the same,
and while I wasn't measuring my pace,
the overall rate of communication
is essentially the same,
but there's less lilting
and falling of the voice
and less accenting.
That's the major consistent
effect of cannabis use.
Now of course, there
are examples of people
who are using a lot of cannabis,
and it impacts brain centers
involved in movement and speech,
so much so that they really do have
the really drawn out kind of, nah,
and oftentimes this will
be detected in the laugh.
There's this stereotypical stoner laugh,
as it's sometimes called.
Rather than say "Ha, ha, ha"
or that's a fake laugh, obviously.
It's hard to make myself laugh
if something's not actually funny.
I'll have to think of something funny.
When people say like, "Ha!"
That's a bit more of
the way I might laugh,
like, "Ha," sort of the inspiratory laugh
or the, "Ha," which is expiratory laugh.
People who use cannabis chronically
will often do that, "Haa,"
which is the back of the throat,
[laughs raspingly] it's
neither inspiratory
nor expiratory laugh,
and believe it or not,
there's an entire literature
on inspiratory, inhaling,
versus expiratory laughs,
and there's also a literature on cannabis
altering the pattern of
inspiratory and expiratory laughs.
It almost sounds like a sarcastic laugh
when, in fact, they may not
be feeling sarcastic at all.
And I have a very close
friend and colleague
who's a phenomenal
neurosurgeon and neuroscientist
by the name of Dr. Eddie Chang.
He's the chair of neurosurgery at UCSF,
and his lab and him
are expert in the study
of neuroscience controlling
language and speech.
And he often tells me that he can predict,
with almost certainty,
whether or not somebody
is a regular cannabis user
based, not just on the patterns
of speech that they use,
but even just by recording
specific neurons in their brain
that underlie the laugh reflex
and certain patterns of speech.
So this idea that cannabis
use changes your ability
to speak and enunciate clearly
does appear to be true.
And the stereotype that cannabis use
tends to create more of a drawl
or, if you will, a laziness in the laugh,
and some of the reflexive
enunciations that people use,
does also appear to be true.
And I say all that, of
course, with the caveat
that many people out there
will know individuals
or perhaps you,
yourselves, are individuals
that may use cannabis but that
have incredible articulation,
probably better than mine
and better than other people out there
who speak for a living, so I'm not saying
that 100% of people that
use cannabis regularly
can't speak well or clearly.
That's simply not what I'm saying,
and I don't want to
communicate that idea at all,
but it is the case that people
who are regular cannabis users
are impacting the neural
circuits involved in movement.
Movement also controls speech,
and therefore, cannabis
is impacting speech.
Now I'd like to turn our attention
to whether or not cannabis
can increase sexual activity,
sexual desire, and/or sexual function,
so we're going to be talking
about libido, about sexual desire
and about effects of cannabis on hormones.
And while this might
sound like a discussion
that's purely oriented towards
recreational use of cannabis,
that is people using
cannabis to heightened
or increase their sense of
arousal for sexual activity,
it actually ventures into
the clinical realm too,
meaning there have been
excellent peer-reviewed studies
that I'll describe to you in a moment
exploring the use of cannabis
or THC, more specifically,
for something called hypoactive
sexual desire disorder,
which refers to a persistent
or recurrent deficiency
or absence of sexual
fantasies and thoughts
and/or desire for, or
receptivity to, sexual activity.
This is a disorder that is fairly common,
anywhere from 6% to 9% of
people, both males and females.
It used to be considered higher prevalence
in females than in males,
but now those numbers
seem to be evening out.
So basically, there are
anywhere from 6% to 9%
of people out there who have
very diminished sexual desire.
And so, a number of those people
are interested in figuring out ways
to increase their amount of sexual desire,
and of course, there are people
in the general population
who may not have hyperactive
sexual desire disorder
who are interested in using
cannabis recreationally
in order to increase their desire for,
or their experience of, sexual activity.
Now first we have to acknowledge
that sexual desire and activity
is a complex set of processes,
meaning it's not just
one event, sex, the verb.
It involves arousal, it
involves sex, the verb,
and it involves a whole set of
mindsets and emotional states
that vary tremendously
between individuals.
But once again, we can distill
out a few basic principles,
and I should emphasize,
these are by no means the only chemicals
and neuro circuits
involved in the sexual arc,
as we'll call it, desire,
the act of sex, et cetera,
but they are central to
it, they are vital to it.
They would be considered
what I would call necessary
but not sufficient,
so there'll be other
chemicals involved too,
but the main chemicals in neuro circuits
are those involved in dopamine,
so the so-called
mesolimbic reward pathway,
in particular, a brain structure
called nucleus accumbens,
which we'll talk about more in a moment,
is vital to all motivated
behaviors and to the seeking out
of all particular types of
pleasurable experiences,
and sex is no exception.
So when we hear that the
nucleus accumbens is activated,
that almost always means that dopamine
has been released in that area
and other areas of the brain body,
and we can consider dopamine central
to the desire for,
pursuit of, an act of sex.
In addition to that, there
are molecules like oxytocin,
which are involved in pair bonding,
and they're going to be
neural circuit specific
to the oxytocin circuitry,
but in terms of sexual
arousal and sexual behavior,
it's really the dopamine pathway
in this nucleus accumbens,
which are especially vital.
That allows us to address the question,
does cannabis increase, decrease,
or have no effect on sexual desire
and/or the ability to have sex?
And therein, we will find
some very interesting answers,
and because, once again,
it will point to the fact
that the effects of cannabis
on different individuals
can be highly divergent,
meaning in one set of individuals,
cannabis will make them far less anxious.
And in another set of individuals,
the same strain of cannabis,
at the same dosage,
will make them extremely anxious.
The same can be said
also of sexual activity.
And this was beautifully illustrated
in the context of sexual
desire in the journal,
"Psycho-pharmacology," in
a paper published in 2017.
The title of this paper is,
"Individual Prolactin Reactivity
"Modulates Response of Nucleus
Accumbens to Erotic Stimuli
"During Acute Cannabis
Intoxication, an fMRI Pilot Study."
So I'll give a little bit of definition
to some of the terms in the title
that will make it easier for
you to understand the paper,
but then I'll just march
through the results,
because they're very straightforward
and easy to understand
and very interesting.
fMRI is just functional
magnetic resonance imaging,
so basically subjects in this experiment
came into the laboratory.
They were either people who
had not used cannabis before
or who had used cannabis before.
They were placed into a brain scanner,
one of these fMRI devices.
It looks like a tube that
people are backed up into
and then they can view images in there,
and their brain can be imaged
without having to remove any skull
or drill into the skull, no neurosurgery.
The participants in
this study were grouped
according to whether or
not they had experienced
any aphrodisiac effects
during the intoxication with cannabis,
so that would be the first group, Group A,
they literally called it
group A for aphrodisiac.
And then the second group,
and this is the only thing I
don't like about this study,
is rather than call it group B,
they called them 'group non A,'
which just gets a little confusing.
So I'll try and simplify all this.
There are two groups,
and one group experiences sexual arousal
when under the influence of
cannabis, THC specifically.
The other group does not.
And it turns out this is a very
commonly observed divergence
of effects of cannabis.
Some people experience
a lot of sexual arousal
from cannabis and THC in
particular, and some people do not,
in fact, they experience
suppression of sexual desire,
and it's always been a
little bit mysterious
as to why that is.
Well, in this study, they showed people
in both groups erotic images,
and they measured sexual arousal
through a number of different measures.
We won't go into all that.
It was largely subjective.
There have been other studies
where they've actually measured things
like erections in males and
vaginal lubrication in females,
so-called autonomic responses
that people can't lie about,
so to speak, and that
tap into other aspects
of the so-called sexual arousal process.
In this study, they
also took blood samples
to look at the concentration
of things like cannabinoids,
so this is a really nice study
in that they actually
measured how much THC
was in the bloodstream
in different individuals
who reacted to these erotic
stimuli in different ways.
And they measured
hormones, namely cortisol,
which is a stress hormone,
which tends to negatively correlate
with sexual arousal and prolactin.
And the interesting
takeaway from the study was
that for people, and it didn't matter
if it was males or females,
'cause they looked at both,
for people that experienced
elevated prolactin levels
under cannabis intoxication,
that's how they refer to it.
People take cannabis,
they measured prolactin.
Some people had elevated
prolactin and some people did not.
For the people that had
elevated levels of prolactin,
they did not observe activation
of brain areas associated
with sexual arousal,
in this case, the right nucleus accumbens,
so you have two nucleus accumbi,
I guess they would be called,
one on each side of the brain,
and the activation of that brain area
is strongly associated with
dopamine and with arousal
and sexual arousal in
particular in this study,
and if people had elevated prolactin,
they did not experience
activation of nucleus accumbens,
and they did not report
feeling sexually aroused
to those pictures, at least
not to the same degree
as the other group.
So some people's prolactin levels go up
when they ingest cannabis,
and those people do not
achieve elevated levels
of sexual arousal when under
the influence of cannabis,
even if they're looking at erotic stimuli.
That makes sense, because prolactin
is mutually inhibitory, as we would say.
It's kind of in a push-pull with dopamine.
When dopamine levels are high,
prolactin levels tend to be low,
and when prolactin levels are high,
dopamine levels tend to be low.
The other group, so-called Group A,
that experienced elevated
levels of sexual arousal
when under the influence of cannabis
and viewing erotic stimuli,
that group did not show
elevated levels of prolactin
in response to cannabis.
So this, I believe,
resolves a longstanding
controversy in the field,
which is, does cannabis
increase sexual arousal?
Well, it depends.
If you fall into the category of person
who has elevated levels of prolactin
in response to cannabis,
then no, actually cannabis
will suppress your sexual
response and desire.
If, however, you are in
the category of person
that does not have elevated
levels of prolactin
in response to cannabis,
well then, erotic stimuli can potentially
and in fact, do increase sexual arousal
in the majority of individuals.
Now, many of you are probably hearing this
and wondering whether or not you fall
into one category of
individual or another.
And the key thing here to understand
is that levels of prolactin
heading into the study
did not predict whether or
not people would respond
to cannabis with elevated or non elevated
or even reduced levels of sexual arousal.
It was whether or not people's
prolactin levels went up
or did not go up, that predicted
whether or not their levels
of arousal would go up or not.
So if you are somebody who, yes,
does experience elevated
levels of sexual arousal
and function went under
the influence of cannabis,
well that's very likely that cannabis
does not increase your prolactin levels,
at least not to a significant
degree while you're taking it.
And if you're somebody who
does not experience increases
in sexual arousal or function
or even diminished sexual
arousal and function
when under the influence of cannabis,
it's very likely that cannabis
is increasing your levels of prolactin.
Unfortunately, there's
no way to know or predict
based on some other measure.
I think the outcome measure,
that is increased or not increased
or even reduced sexual arousal
is really the litmus test
by which one can figure that out.
While we are on the topic
of the effects of cannabis
on sexual function and
hormones like prolactin,
it's probably worth mentioning
that cannabis has been studied extensively
for its impact on other hormones,
and we can summarize those
literature in the following way.
And here I'm referring to
studies only on adults.
We'll talk about the
developing brain and body
in a little bit, but it is very clear
that smoking cannabis
increases prolactin levels.
Very, very clear.
Now, you might say, "Didn't,
you just describe a study
"about a set of individuals
whose prolactin didn't increase
"and as a consequence,
"their level of sexual desire went up?"
Yes, there are a subset of individuals
for which that's true, but
people who smoke cannabis
do experience increases in prolactin,
and that's especially pronounced in people
that smoke cannabis
more than twice a week.
So this is important, prolactin,
as I referred to earlier,
is reciprocal or mutually
inhibitory with dopamine.
One way to think about
this is in the context
of the normal sexual arousal arc
whereby dopamine is increased
when people are sexually
aroused, but then after orgasm,
both in males and females,
prolactin levels skyrocket.
This is actually what creates
the so-called refractory period for males
during which they cannot
achieve erection again
for some period of time.
That relates directly to how long
the prolactin increase lasts.
Prolactin is also increased
in new parents of all species,
including humans, which
at least partially,
explains some of the reported
or typical reductions
in sexual desire and
activity in new parents.
Now, there are other reasons for that too,
sleep deprivation, but nature is smart
and has arranged a set
of hormones and circuits
in the brain and body,
such that when tending
to a newborn is the most
important thing, it relegates,
it reduces the importance
of producing more children
and sexual activity in those moments
and days and weeks, sometimes longer.
So when prolactin levels are
up, dopamine levels are down.
Smoking marijuana more than twice a week
significantly increases prolactin.
There are fewer studies exploring
whether or not edible
marijuana has the same effect,
although the preliminary evidence
suggests that it does not.
I get into this in a lot more
detail in a future episode,
all about hormones with Dr. Kyle Gillett,
who's been on this podcast before.
But he verified that, and
my read of the literature
is that the edible forms
of marijuana, cannabis,
probably again, let's put
an asterisks next to this,
but it appears do not have as as much
of a prolactin elevating effect
and therefore, not as much of
a dopamine suppressive effect
and therefore, not as much
of a testosterone suppressing effect,
and that gets to the
issue of testosterone.
Does cannabis, marijuana
suppress testosterone?
And this is a very controversial
literature and here's why.
Some studies say, "Yes,
it suppresses testosterone
"in males and females," and keep in mind
that testosterone in
females is vital for libido
and cognitive function,
cellular repair, et cetera,
so it's not just important
in males, of course.
However, other studies say that cannabis
does not decrease testosterone,
and it seems to depend on
whether or not the cannabis
is brought into the system
by way of smoking or edible.
And it seems to depend on
whether or not the cannabis
is used chronically by
an individual or acutely.
And here I just want to zoom out and say
that studies on cannabis or
drugs of any kind in humans
are really complicated.
If you think about it,
someone has to come into the laboratory,
and let's say you want to
study chronic cannabis use.
Well, you can't keep them in
the laboratory all the time,
so you have to rely on their self-report
of how often they use
cannabis and in what form,
and you can't really control
from one individual to the next
of how much cannabis and THC
they're bringing into their system.
One person might smoke
cannabis out of a bong
and take big, deep, lungs-full
bong inhalations or such.
Other people might smoke joints.
Other people might use edibles.
It becomes very complicated
to know what people have done
and that they're reporting it accurately,
and no joke here, especially if marijuana
is impacting the
short-term memory systems.
They might not actually remember.
They might not be tracking it that well.
Contrast that with
studies of the acute use
of cannabis and THC, where
people who are not regular users
come into the laboratory and now suddenly,
with institutional guidelines
and safety protocols,
are under the influence
of THC and cannabis.
Well, now you're dealing with a person
who may not have experience
with the elevated heart rate
and blood pressure that's
characteristic of cannabis,
'cause it is a stimulant,
at least when initially
brought into the system,
even if it might eventually
lead to relaxation.
So now you've got someone who's anxious
or somebody who's not
anxious, who's deeply relaxed,
and you're trying to study these effects,
so it's a moving target of sorts,
and it's very complicated to
study marijuana and cannabis
in its various derivatives in this way.
Now you can probably appreciate better
as to why there's so little nuanced data
about sativa versus indica,
versus different ratios of CBD and THC.
It's really difficult to do these studies
in the first place.
That said, the general rules
are smoking marijuana increases
prolactin in men and women,
which will reduce
dopamine and testosterone.
Smoking marijuana chronically,
meaning more than twice a week,
does appear to reduce
testosterone significantly
and elevate so-called aromatase enzymes,
which are the enzymes
that convert testosterone into estrogen.
This might partially explain the effect
that occurs in about 35% of
males, which is gynecomastia,
which is a development of
breast tissue in males,
in particular young males,
who have elevated levels of testosterone
or who are taking exogenous testosterone
for testosterone replacement therapy
or if they're taking high
doses, anabolic steroids,
or in females, the
increase in breast size,
which is due to additional estrogen
from testosterone converted to estrogen.
So it does appear that
marijuana and cannabis
increase estrogen, reduce
testosterone, increase prolactin,
especially in chronic users.
Now, I'm sure that some
people out there will say,
well, their testosterone
levels are exceedingly high
or they are fine, meaning
the constellation of symptoms
associated with low testosterone
and elevate estrogen
are not present in them.
That probably means one
of two things, or both.
They either had elevated
levels of testosterone
to begin with, so their
ceiling was higher,
so bringing it down didn't
have that much of effect,
or that they have very low levels
of aromatase in their system.
There are some anecdotal evidence
that smoking particular
parts of the marijuana plant,
in particular, the seeds,
can increase aromatase
in the conversion of
testosterone to estrogen.
I think in the old days,
the lore was the seeds make you sterile,
and I think that was related
to what I just told you,
this increase in conversion
of testosterone to estrogen.
There's a vast literature
on the effects of cannabis on fertility.
Yes, it does seem to alter sperm motility
and sperm health and function
when taken chronically,
more than twice per week,
in particular high doses
of high potency THC.
This is something we will
cover in far more detail
on a future episode all about fertility.
And in females, there's
an increase in estrogen
as a consequence of smoking marijuana
and increasing prolactin
and estrogen in parallel.
Whether or not that's
detrimental isn't clear,
although I point out that
elevated estrogen and prolactin
can be associated,
again, can be associated,
not necessarily, and
certainly, not causative,
but can be associated with elevated levels
or frequency of breast cancer detection.
So cannabis and its effects on hormones
are not without consequence.
There are effects of cannabis
on cortisol in some individuals.
It greatly increases
cortisol due the anxiety
and paranoia it can create,
and in other individuals
it reduces cortisol.
Again, we have these divergent effects.
But I want to be very clear,
the effects on prolactin,
meaning elevated prolactin,
the effects on testosterone,
meaning, at least most studies point to,
reduced levels of testosterone
and increased estrogen.
That seems to be true
for most all individuals
that chronically use cannabis,
whereas the effects on
cortisol tend to be divergent.
Cannabis increases cortisol
in some individuals
and decreases cortisol in others.
In general, increases in
cortisol that are ongoing
are not healthy for us and so on.
And then of course, there are
other effects on hormones,
and I'll just briefly summarize those,
that THC in particular, not
CBD, but THC in particular,
is known to be strongly inhibitory
for something called
gonadotropin-releasing hormone.
This is a hormone that's
released from the brain,
from the hypothalamus
that then feeds onto,
or I should say signals
to the pituitary gland,
which is also near the roof of your mouth,
a lot of stuff happening
near the roof of your mouth
it turns out, biologically,
and reduced levels of
gonadotropin-releasing hormone
caused by cannabis use,
reduced levels of LH luteinizing hormone
and FSH, which reduce
levels of testosterone
and sperm production in males
and egg health and ovulation
and menstrual function in females.
Now, I'm sure there are a
number of women out there
who will say they have perfectly
normal menstrual cycles
despite using cannabis.
I'm certainly not going to dispute that,
but if you are somebody who's
trying to maximize fertility
or regulate or balance hormones,
marijuana and cannabis reduces GnRH.
That is the gonadotropin-release
from the hypothalamus
and thereby reduces luteinizing hormone
and follicle stimulating hormone,
which are released from the pituitary
and travel in the bloodstream
to support normal ovarian
function and health
and normal testicular function and health
in females and males, respectively.
Up until now I've been
discussing the biological
and psychological effects of cannabis.
Now I'd like to shift our attention
to some of the negative
health effects of cannabis
and shine light on some of the individuals
or groups out there that
need to be especially wary of
and probably avoid cannabis use entirely,
including ingestion of
cannabis by way of edible.
And I frame things that way,
because I think there is an
increasingly large number
of people out there that
appreciate that smoking tobacco
or smoking cannabis, vaping tobacco,
yes, vaping tobacco, or vaping cannabis,
each and all have negative
health consequences on the lungs
and on the so-called
endothelial cells of the body,
the cells that make up the vasculature,
the capillaries and blood vessels.
If you don't already know
this, I'll make it very clear,
and I'll make it very brief.
Whether or not you smoke or
vape tobacco or cannabis,
you are severely impairing the
function of endothelial cells
that make up the capillaries
and blood vessels
of your brain and body,
and that is known to decrease
cognitive capacity over time,
increase probability of strokes,
severely impact lung function,
and also lead to things like
peripheral neuropathies.
It leads to sexual dysfunction,
because of lack of blood
flow to the genitals,
can lead to other aspects
of reproductive damage,
including to the ovaries and testes.
Essentially, there is no
other way to state it,
except that smoking and vaping
have negative health consequences
that are independent of the substances
that people are trying to
get into their bloodstream
by smoking or vaping.
So people smoke and vape tobacco,
and people smoke and vape
cannabis, and in both cases,
if we just set aside the
direct effects of tobacco
and the direct effects of cannabis,
we can confidently say that
the process of smoking,
of inhaling smoke into the lungs,
and yes, also vaping,
bringing the chemicals
that transport nicotine,
or in this case, cannabis,
into the lungs by way of vaping
are both severely detrimental
to endothelial cells.
I think a few years ago, when
vaping wasn't as prominent,
there was this question and this idea
that maybe vaping was
going to be far healthier
or at least not as bad as smoking,
but now we can see a huge number
of negative health effects of vaping,
some of which are distinct
from the effects of smoking.
So if you'd like more information
on smoking versus vaping,
please see the episode
that I did on nicotine.
We will also do an entire episode
all about vaping in the future,
but there's really no way
to slice it and dice it
or candy coat it.
The fact of the matter
is that smoking has clear
and severe negative health
consequences, regardless of
whether or not you're smoking
tobacco or cannabis, THC,
and vaping has negative
health consequences,
whether or not you're using
the vape to bring in nicotine
or THC or some combination of THC and CBD.
That's simply the way it is.
With that said, now I'd
like to focus our attention
on the direct effects that cannabis has,
either by way of THC action
or by way of CBD action
in terms of positive or
negative health effects
on the brain and body, and
we're going to explore that
first as a function of age.
And the reason we're going to do that
is related to a fact that I mentioned
at the beginning of the episode,
which is that the CB1
and the CB2 receptors,
the two receptors for cannabis
to which THC and CBD and CBN
and all other psychoactive
compounds of cannabis bind to
to have their actions are
present throughout development.
Believe it or not,
they are present very
soon after conception,
and the CB1 and CB2 receptors
actually play a critical role
in the development of the fetus.
Now, you might wonder why that is,
because of course, the developing fetus
doesn't necessarily expect to see cannabis
or to be exposed to
cannabis and THC and CBD.
But, as you recall, endogenous
cannabinoids are present
in the adult brain and body
and endogenous cannabinoids,
it turns out, are also present
in the developing fetus.
In fact, endogenous
cannabinoids are present
at much greater levels
in the developing fetus
than they are after a child is born,
and levels of endogenous cannabinoids
actually go down across development.
I find this really interesting.
What this means is that
endogenous cannabinoids
and activation of the
CB1 and CB2 receptors
are an integral part
of neural development,
and this is going to
become especially relevant
in considering whether
or not pregnant mothers
should or should not use cannabis or CBD,
and it also points to some
very interesting biology
in terms of how the brain develops
and how the body develops.
Now the development of the brain
and nervous system and body
is a fascinating and vast literature,
certainly far too vast to
cover in today's episode,
especially at this late hour as it were,
but we will have a future episode
all about brain development.
In terms of the effects of cannabis,
it's sufficient to say
that cannabinoid receptors
are present and active
in the developing fetus.
They're present and active in the newborn.
They're present and active in adolescence.
And across that time, from
conception until adolescence,
endogenous cannabinoids
are mainly responsible
for the actions of those
cannabinoid receptors.
During that time, the
cannabinoid receptors
are having very specific effects
that are distinct from
their effects later in life,
and those effects can largely be explained
in terms of neural development.
Again, we don't have time for
an entire lecture on this now,
but during development,
your body was a collection
of a bunch of cells.
It's actually called a blastula,
which means a ball of
cells, and then those cells
actually have to grow out connections
and duplicate themselves,
and this is a very interesting process
by which neurons initially
are situated far apart,
and then they grow out connections
and make contacts with one another.
They remove certain connections,
depending on what kind of
life events you're exposed to.
If you have a wonderful
event early in life
or a traumatic early life,
those connections change, et cetera.
The important point for today's discussion
is that the CB1 receptor, in particular,
is expressed on every neuron
in the developing brain
and has been shown to be important
for every aspect of neural development,
from the proliferation of cells,
meaning getting enough
cells to create a brain,
to the outgrowth of the so-called axons,
the little wires that connect
up neurons with one another,
to the steering, the direction
which those axons go in
development, which is essential,
and even so far as to
explain the connections
that form between neurons,
the so-called synapses,
and then how those synapses work.
So the basic statement here is
that endogenous cannabinoids
and CB1 receptor activation are critical
for every aspect of brain
wiring and development.
With that in mind, the
statement I'm about to make
is absolutely terrifying, at least to me,
and frankly, it should be
terrifying to you as well.
And the statement is,
the current statistics
on cannabis use in pregnant
mothers is absolutely shocking.
The most recent survey of pregnant mothers
in the United States
show that 15%, one-five,
15% of pregnant mothers
report using cannabis
in some form or another, either smoking it
or more likely ingestion of in edible,
because they are aware
of the negative effects
of smoking on the developing
fetus, ingestion of an edible
to increase THC and/or
CBD during pregnancy,
which to me, I have to say,
as a developmental neurobiologist
is, frankly, it's scary.
It's absolutely scary,
because that CB1 receptor
is not just a minor player
in neural development.
It is absolutely central
to every critical aspect
of brain wiring and development.
Now, the long-term implications
or even the short-term
implications of this,
15% of mothers self-reporting
the use of cannabis
at some point during
pregnancy are not yet known.
This is, as we would say, an
experiment that's ongoing.
But I'd be remiss if I
didn't point out these data
and just implore you,
please, please, please,
if you are pregnant or
considering getting pregnant,
you're a cannabis user, whether
or not you're using edibles,
if you're a CBD user, please
do whatever is necessary
to not ingest cannabis or smoke cannabis
or ingest CBD during pregnancy.
Now, there may be certain
clinical indications
by which your physician and your OB/GYN,
and the pediatrician that will eventually
be the pediatrician for your
child will prescribe CBD,
although it's hard to
imagine what those are.
I contacted a number of different
pediatricians and OB/GYNs
and not a single one said
they would ever suggest,
and in fact would strongly
discourage their patients
from using cannabis during pregnancy.
But I think that the advent
of edible forms of cannabis,
and the combination of THC
and CBD in certain products,
and the fact that most
people view CBD as safer,
because it does not include,
or does not have, I should say,
the psychoactive effects that THC does,
has led to a situation where you have 15%
of pregnant mothers using cannabis
at some point during pregnancy
and maybe even frequently
throughout pregnancy,
and the effects on the developing fetus
are completely unknown.
But recall that cannabis
and THC and CBD outcompete,
meaning they park in the receptor
for endogenous cannabinoids
and prevent endogenous cannabinoids
from having their normal
level and pattern of action,
so this is absolutely critical.
I cannot encourage you enough,
or rather, I should say,
I cannot discourage
enough the use of cannabis
and any related compounds in cannabis,
edible or smoked, certainly not smoked,
but even edible during pregnancy,
and certainly in breastfeeding,
lactating mothers,
the same is also true.
Recall that cannabis and THC and CBD
are incredibly lipophilic.
They're fat soluble,
and they get into cells very readily,
and they cross the blood brain barrier.
They cross the blood placental barrier.
So when I encountered this statistic,
I had to kind of wipe my eyes a few times.
I could not believe it, and
yet I crosschecked that number
with a few other studies.
A few others have come
in a little bit lower
at somewhere like 13% to 14%,
and a few have come in
a little bit higher,
but the average of 15% is
both striking and shocking,
so I don't know how to make
the message more clear.
I hope that is clear.
Please do not use any cannabis, THC
or related things including
CBD, smoked or edible
if you're pregnant, lactating, et cetera.
Now we are at the point
where we need to consider
some of the negative
health effects of cannabis
that have been well documented
in peer-reviewed studies.
And before I do this,
I want to return to a
point that I made earlier,
which is that nothing I am about to say
relates directly to issues of legality.
If we consider alcohol, for instance,
alcohol is legal in
most areas of the world.
It's certainly legal in the US,
and yet there's an age limit for its use.
Typically, it's not available to people
until they're 21 or older.
It's not to say that
certain people don't use it
before age 21, but it's not legal.
It is illegal to buy or possess alcohol,
consume alcohol before age 21,
and I think with good reason,
because the brain is still developing.
Likewise, we can have a informed
discussion about cannabis
and its various components
that can fully acknowledge the reality,
which is that one of the major
harms of cannabis in the past
has been the legal ramifications
of cannabis being illegal.
That's a statement that is
no longer controversial,
and this is not a discussion
about legalization or non legalization.
If you look to the scientific literature,
the epidemiological literature,
there are wonderful data
out of Carleton University
and elsewhere in Canada showing that
many of the negative
effects of marijuana and THC
are due to the criminal
justice system, itself,
that is the creation of
illicit drug businesses,
the creation of organized crime,
the creation of a number
of different features
related to the illegality of cannabis.
And again, this isn't the
topic of today's episode,
but that should be acknowledged.
And at the same time,
we need to acknowledge
that when a compound, a drug
or whatever you want to call it
becomes legal, there's
a tendency to assume
that it's safe and safe for everybody.
And with respect to cannabis
and THC and perhaps even CBD,
but certainly for THC and
cannabis that's smoked or vaped
or consumed in edible form,
that is simply not the case.
There are clear data pointing
to negative health effects
of cannabis use and THC use,
which again, is not to say
that there are not positive effects
on mood, anxiety, pain relief, et cetera.
Those are out there and they exist,
and we will mention
some of those of course,
and we've talked about some of those,
creativity for instance, et cetera.
But if we do not acknowledge
the negative health effects
that are documented in the literature,
then we are overlooking
some very important data,
especially as it relates to
the development of psychosis
in certain individuals.
So, with that said, there
are very strong data,
and I will provide links
to these resources,
pointing to the fact that for people
who are chronic users of cannabis,
that is using it twice a week or more,
that over time, their levels
of anxiety actually increase,
and this is true even for individuals
that are using strains of cannabis,
that while under the influence
of cannabis, reduce anxiety.
Over time, meaning over the
course of 12 or more months,
there is a well-documented
effect of the anxiety relief
that cannabis and THC initially brought,
being less and less potent.
That is people need to smoke
more of it or ingest more THC
in order to achieve the same
level of anxiety relief,
and in some cases, a
switch from anxiety relief
to increase in anxiety,
and again, that's increase in anxiety,
not just when the drug
is not being consumed,
but also while under the
influence of the drug.
Why would that be?
We have to go back to our
understanding of the CB1 receptor
and the potency with which THC
binds to that CB1 receptor.
When THC is brought into the
system over and over again,
meaning twice a week or more,
the binding of THC, that CB1 receptor,
eventually causes a
habituation or attenuation
of the entire process
of binding the receptor
and creating the psychoactive effects.
So initially it creates anxiety relief,
but over time, the affinity for
the receptor doesn't change,
meaning it can still park in that slot
with a lot of affinity, a lot of strength,
but there are fewer receptors available,
and then the signaling that's
downstream of those receptors
becomes less and less robust.
Now this is a topic we didn't get into
in too much detail today,
because I didn't want to include
even more biological
detail, but the CB1 receptor
is a so-called G protein-coupled receptor.
That's a mouthful, but a
G protein-coupled receptor
basically is like a bucket brigade.
So while some receptors
in the brain and body
are such that when something,
a chemical binds to them,
that receptor has a direct action,
like it opens and allows
stuff to rush into the cell,
increases the excitability of the cell,
so called fast effects,
these G protein-coupled receptors,
and CB1 is a G protein-coupled receptor,
they are more like a bucket brigade
where they kick off a
process through one molecule
that then is handed
off to another molecule
that then is handed off
to another molecule.
It's a long chain or cascade of events.
Those long chains or cascades of events
have a lot of opportunity for
regulation, for adjustment.
Receptor systems in the brain and body,
especially receptor systems
like the cannabinoid system
that are used to being
tickled, not punched,
tickled by endogenous cannabinoids,
every once in a while
some binds, has an effect,
but certainly not bound
with incredible potency
and over and over again as they are
when THC is coming into the system.
Well those systems eventually, over time,
they adjust themselves so that the body
and those cells can achieve
so-called homeostasis.
So when people are using
THC more than twice a week,
what ends up happening is those
G protein-coupled receptors
in the downstream signaling mechanisms
start to adjust themselves,
and it requires more and more drug,
so either higher dosages
or more frequent use,
and a lot of the positive effects,
the so-called decrease in anxiety,
increased focus, increased creativity,
some of that starts to wane,
it starts to dissipate,
and people wonder why they
have to use so much cannabis
just to achieve a fraction of the effect
that they used to be able to
achieve with even a lower dose.
So anxiety is getting worse over time,
and that's anxiety during the drug use
and outside of the drug use.
Some people work around that
or try to work around that
by using varying strains of cannabis
or changing the pattern of
delivery from smoking to vaping
or from vaping to edible and
from edible to transdermal.
Anyway, they go through
a lot of gymnastics
and writhing and seeking,
but nonetheless, anxiety
increases over time.
Also, it's very clear that
depression increases over time
and especially, this is surprising to me,
but especially for individuals
that were not depressed
at the the outset of their use.
In other words, they
didn't start using cannabis
because they were depressed,
but rather the depression starts to emerge
as a consequence of the
cannabis and THC use.
So that's serious, in fact, we now know,
based on really solid
epidemiological evidence,
that depression is not a strong predictor
of seeking out cannabis.
It doesn't drive terribly many people
to seek out cannabis use,
but cannabis use, itself, makes
people four times likelier
to develop a chronic major depression.
So anxiety is increasing,
depression is increasing,
and this turns out to
be especially relevant
and important to young people.
Why do I say that?
Well, if you look at the data,
and again, I think some
of the strongest data
are data to come out
of the Canadian system.
They've done some really
beautiful controlled studies.
I really hope to invite some of the people
who arranged and ran those studies
as guests onto the Huberman Lab Podcast.
But if you look at the data out of Canada,
or you look at some of the data
out of Northern Europe and the US,
what you find is that the probability
that somebody will use cannabis
and then go on to use it chronically,
correlates very strongly with age.
So for instance, some of the
highest degree of cannabis use
is among individuals 16 to 24 years old.
In fact, in individuals
who are 16 to 24 years old,
and in particular, in students
and people who are working,
surprising, more than in
unemployed populations,
being young, 16 to 24, at
least to me that's young,
and being a student or
working doubles the likelihood
that somebody is going to use
cannabis on a regular basis,
twice or more per week.
The typical age of initiating
cannabis use nowadays
is about 19 years old, so 18.7,
and about 20% of people
in that age bracket,
of 16 to 24 years old,
are using cannabis daily,
either by vaping, by smoking or by edible.
That's an enormous number,
at least by my read.
It's an enormous number,
and here's why it's of
really serious concern.
During the ages of 16 to 24,
the cannabinoid receptors
are still available.
They are not being as strongly driven
by endogenous cannabinoids,
but by ingestion of THC and/or CBD,
there are downstream effects
on the signaling within those cells
that all the data point
to creating a much,
much higher likelihood of
developing major depression,
severe anxiety or psychosis at later ages.
So to be very clear, cannabis use,
between the ages of 16 to
24, in both males and females
is increasing anxiety,
increasing depression
in the immediate years and
within the one year's time or so,
so much so that people are
using the cannabis ongoing
in an attempt to reduce that anxiety
and reduce that depression,
but in addition to that, the cannabis use,
and because of the signaling
mechanisms involved
are predisposing those individuals
to psychosis later in life.
If you look at individuals
who start using cannabis,
even younger, age 14,
or even as young as 12,
the probability of
psychosis later in life,
in particular schizophrenic
or schizophrenic-like episodes
more than doubles, so this
is of really serious concern,
and this is completely aside
from any so-called positive effects
or beneficial effects of cannabis
that people might derive from
occasional use as adults,
meaning people older than 25.
So for the person who's older than 25,
who eats an edible every once in a while,
or who smokes cannabis
every once in a while,
and people love to make the argument,
it's not as bad as alcohol,
which frankly, is a terrible argument,
because if you saw our episode on alcohol,
[laughs] alcohol is pretty bad,
but even so, it's just
not a good argument.
It's saying that something is good,
because it's not as bad as something else
is simply just not a
good or valid argument,
at least not biologically speaking.
The use of cannabis in young populations
is very strongly predisposing
people to psychotic episodes,
and we know the mechanism
by which this occurs.
This occurs by a thinning of
the so-called gray matter,
and it's called gray matter
because with neurons,
nerve cells, they have
a so-called cell body,
that's the part that contains the DNA
and manufacturers all the
neurotransmitters, et cetera.
And those are shipped out to
the other parts of the neuron
that include the axon,
the wires between axons,
and those axons under the microscope,
because they have a lot of
fatty tissue around them,
and this is healthy fatty tissue
that allows electrical
transmission to be fast,
that fatty tissue, those
portions of the cells,
are called white matter,
so you have gray matter and white matter.
Gray matter are the so-called cell bodies
where the DNA and all the
stuff is manufactured.
White matter or the axons or the wires
through which all the key
components are shipped out
to the synapse, et cetera.
Wonderful data and I do say wonderful,
because it is part of a
large scale consortium,
and we will provide a link to the paper.
This was published in
"Translational Psychiatry"
just this year, point to the fact
that adolescent cannabis
use accelerates the thinning
of the prefrontal cortex and
the gray matter in particular.
So what this means is, while
during normal development,
the gray matter, the prefrontal cortex
and all the cells there
are indeed intended,
it's a normal process for it to thicken
and then thin a little bit
as connections are adjusted
and people learn and mature and grow up,
this is part of the normal
healthy maturation process,
independent of cannabis use.
When kids, 'cause these
really are kids, use cannabis,
and it doesn't matter the
mode of cannabis delivery,
whether or not it's vaping
or smoking or edible,
that gray matter thins at
a much, much greater rate.
And the reason I like this paper published
in "Translational
Psychiatry" this year so much
is that they link the
amount of cannabis use,
heavy, moderate, light or no cannabis use,
to the rate of prefrontal
cortical thinning,
and it's absolutely clear from these data
that the more often young people,
meaning individuals between
the age of 14 and 25,
the more often they consume
or smoke or vape cannabis,
the faster and the more extreme
that cortical thinning is.
And the cortical thinning is occurring
in exactly the area of the brain
that's involved in planning,
in control over one's emotions,
in reflexes, in organizing one's life
in a number of different ways,
anywhere from cleaning
one's room, literally,
knowing what goes where,
to making plans that
extend out through the day,
through the week, through a year,
essentially becoming a
functional human being
involves using your prefrontal cortex
in a variety of different contexts
and different time domains,
the time domain of an hour,
the time domain of a day.
Making plans and being
able to execute plans
is fundamental to being
a healthy human being,
and it's absolutely clear from these data
that the more cannabis one uses,
the more impaired those
neural circuits are.
There's simply no other
way to to view these data.
In fact, so much so, that even
small amounts of cannabis use
are associated with rates
of cortical thinning
and degrees of cortical thinning
that are really detrimental
and concerning for normal
cognitive processes.
If you were somebody who smoked marijuana
or consumed cannabis
in any form or another
during adolescence, does that mean
that your prefrontal cortex
can never be rescued,
that it can't come back?
Well, the short answer is,
it probably can be rescued to some degree.
It will depend on how much
cannabis you were using
and how often and what strains
of cannabis, et cetera.
There's really no traveling back in time,
as my graduate advisor used to say.
Time machines are broken.
At least for now, we
don't have time machines.
So all you can really
do is try and emphasize,
first of all, quitting
cannabis in any form
and focusing on behaviors that
emphasize endothelial cell
blood flow health to the brain,
so that would be cardiovascular exercise,
adequate nutrition, not smoking nicotine,
and there are a number of
other things that one can do.
We will do an entire episode
all about trying to reverse
the effects of cannabis
and other drug use during adolescence.
We don't have time to do a
deep dive on that right now,
but all the things that
standardize and promote health,
adequate sleep, good social connection,
regular cardiovascular and
weight training exercise,
healthy nutrition, and what
that represents to you,
healthy metabolic function
and weight, et cetera,
those are all going to
facilitate some recovery
of brain function, in particular,
prefrontal cortical function,
by way of all the positive effects
that those behaviors and choices have.
But with that said, if
you are in the age bracket
that I've been referring to,
this 14 to 25 year old age bracket,
and you are a occasional even
or chronic cannabis user,
you should be very, very
careful and concerned
about the long-term effects
that that could potentially have.
That statement is bolstered
by another statistic,
which is that unlike a lot of other drugs,
the rate of cannabis
use is strongly related
to how dangerous people
perceive cannabis to be.
Now, that might seem
obvious, on the one hand,
if you think something
is very, very dangerous,
you would expect that the probability
that somebody would use it
would be very, very low,
and if they think something is safe,
the probability would be high.
But that isn't necessarily the case.
If you think about it,
cannabis is a unique instance
in which nowadays we are hearing,
yes, it's becoming legal
in a number of areas,
and we talked earlier about why
that's probably a good thing
in most circumstances,
but that we aren't just
hearing that cannabis is safe,
or it's not just being implied
that cannabis is safer,
but many more people are talking
about the positive effects of cannabis
without a lot of discussion
about the negative effects of cannabis.
And I realize that saying this
is going to upset some people out there,
because I know that there
are a number of people
who fought very hard for
the legalization process,
and I want to acknowledge that.
I also want to acknowledge the
many known positive effects
of cannabis in adults
with very occasional use,
provided it is delivered
safely and in the safe context
and setting and with legality.
That is entirely distinct from the issue
of whether or not cannabis is safe
for the developing brain and body.
Again, I'm not demonizing
anybody for using cannabis,
but I want to make the point
very simply and very directly.
It is far and away a different
circumstance for the brain
for an individual to be 25 years or older
and using cannabis in whatever form,
occasionally or maybe even frequently,
than it is for a young
person, aged 14 to 25,
to be using cannabis,
either by smoking or vaping
or by edible or any other
form, on the brain and body.
It's absolutely clear that
the brain continues to develop
at least until age 25, and
that a huge number of systems
related to mood regulation,
so-called executive function,
the ability to organize one's thoughts,
plan and execute plans,
essentially to become a
functional human being,
that's one portion of becoming
a functional human being,
but certainly an essential one.
All of that relies on the fine tuning
of this neural circuitry
that we've been talking
about up until now,
and it's abundantly clear that cannabis
and THC in particular, dramatically
disrupt those processes.
So if this isn't clear enough,
just from my statements,
I'd like to point to a particular paper.
This is one of the more impactful papers
in this area in recent years.
This is a paper published in
"Lancet Psychiatry" in 2022.
Title is "Association of Cannabis Potency
"with Mental Ill Health and
Addiction, A Systematic Review."
There are a number of
very important points
in this very fine paper.
"Lancet Psychiatry" is one of the premier
medical journals out there,
and they evaluated a
huge number of studies.
They actually looked at
more than 4,000 studies.
They selected the ones that
were only the most rigorous
in terms of study design and analysis
and rigor of conclusions, and
they looked at how early use
of cannabis impacted later
probability of development
of psychosis and other
psychiatric conditions,
and the takeaways from
this study are very clear.
First of all, chronic cannabis use,
so more than twice per
week, has consistently
been associated with
mental health disorders.
I'm pulling some phrases
directly from the paper.
Heavy cannabis use, meaning cannabis use
more frequent than twice per week,
has been associated
with four times the risk
of psychosis later in life, in particular,
schizophrenia and bipolar-like episodes.
Now, we've done an episode
on bipolar disorder.
It's also called bipolar depression.
We have not yet done one on schizophrenia,
but both bipolar disorder
and schizophrenia
have a very, very strong
genetic component.
There's a 30, three-zero,
30 times greater likelihood
that you'll have bipolar disorder
if you have a first relative
who has bipolar disorder.
And then, it's also the
case that using cannabis,
especially during adolescents
and the teen years,
and up until age 25,
create a four times
greater risk of psychosis
for those that have a predisposition
to bipolar disorder and/or schizophrenia.
Now, I don't hear very much
about this in the media.
This paper got some attention
and then it got swept away.
I don't think that was an
intentional sweeping way.
There's just a lot of events
in the world as you well know.
But I think it's a particularly
important set of findings,
because obviously, in
looking at so many studies,
it distills out the strongest
findings that are out there
and really pulls the consistent messages
that are arriving from all
these different studies.
And as they point out, and
again, I'm paraphrasing here,
this is the first systematic review
of the association of cannabis potency,
and all of the data point
to a very clear conclusion,
which is the more potent
the THC concentration,
the higher probability
of developing psychosis
or a major depressive episode
or a major anxiety disorder later in life.
That should be of particular
concern, because we know,
we are absolutely clear about the fact
that with the advent of all
these new strains of cannabis,
and with the engineering
and availability of cannabis
at much higher potency,
meaning THC potency,
the risk of psychosis is going up and up
and is likely to continue going
up unless something is done
to reduce the frequency of
cannabis use to zero, ideally,
or to very low frequency, very low potency
in adolescence and teens and
people age 25 or younger.
I know a lot of people don't
want to hear this message,
because first of all, it's alarming,
and second of all, as I mentioned earlier,
the statistics tell us that
the greatest number of people
that are starting to use cannabis
are in the age bracket of 16 to 24.
Many of them are functional
in other areas of life.
They're students, they
are employed, et cetera.
But when you couple that with the fact
that the most frequent
adopters of cannabis use
are in this age bracket of 16 to 24,
they're twice as likely to
use as other individuals
or to start using cannabis
as are other individuals.
Plus, the general perception out there,
because of the way that
cannabis is discussed
in the media and by sports
figures and by celebrities
and by politicians, et cetera,
that it's not as bad as
alcohol and maybe not that bad
and maybe even has health benefits,
then you're essentially
setting up a system
where young people are far more likely
to adopt and continue cannabis use
without realizing these
serious health consequences
that await them later.
With all of that said, I, of course,
again want to acknowledge
that there have been
well-demonstrated effects of
cannabis for reducing pain,
in particular in chemotherapy
and in the context
of reducing nausea in people suffering
from cancer or chemotherapy.
There is a well-known effect
that one can generally
point to as positive,
using cannabis for things like glaucoma,
for lowering intraocular pressure
and offsetting the loss of neurons
that would lead to blindness,
although there are other tools, of course,
that don't involve cannabis use
that can accomplish that as well,
so called intraocular pressure
lowering drugs or drops.
There is a list of probably
a dozen or more psychological
and bodily ailments that can
be aided by cannabis use,
in particular edible cannabis
use of particular strains.
I, of course, am going to address each
and every one of those in
episodes where I'm talking,
for instance, about eye
disease or about chronic pain.
I am in no way, shape or form
trying to rob the incredible
efforts of the laboratories
and people that have worked very hard
to study and establish
the valid uses of cannabis
for treating various ailments
and that continue to study
cannabis in order to try
and ameliorate the symptoms
of different ailments.
But today, I really wanted
to emphasize the biology of cannabis,
some of the often discussed effects,
I guess one could call
them positive effects,
things like enhanced creativity
and really point to the nuance
and actually the divergence
of people who take cannabis
and some experience
heightened levels of
creativity and some do not.
Some people experience heightened
levels of sexual arousal
and some people experience
the exact opposite,
and so on and so forth,
rather than focus on all
the potential positive
and emerging positive data about cannabis
in different medical contexts.
And at the same time, I strongly
feel that it's important
to acknowledge the shocking,
because there's really no
other way to describe it,
the shocking effects of cannabis
use on the developing fetus
and the fact that so many pregnant
and lactating mothers are using cannabis.
I mean, that number 15% still
has me dizzy with disbelief,
and yet we need to acknowledge this
and address this immediately.
And I think it's vital to
understand that cannabis use
through any delivery mechanism,
smoking or vaping or edible or otherwise,
is very, very concerning,
in fact, dangerous to
the developing brain,
certainly for the fetal
brain and for the baby brain,
but also for the adolescent brain
and for the teen and young adult brain,
not just because of the effects
that it can have in the immediate term,
those slow creeping increases
in anxiety and depression,
brought on by cannabis use,
but also the time release, if you will,
on the development of
psychosis and other types
of major psychiatric
disorders later in life.
I acknowledge we've covered
a lot of ground today,
and yet there's still far more ground
that we could have covered
and that we will indeed
cover in future episodes.
Nevertheless, if you are learning from
and are enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel.
That's a terrific zero-cost
way to support us.
In addition, please
subscribe to the podcast
on both Spotify and Apple,
and on both Spotify and Apple,
you can leave us up to a five-star review.
If you have questions for us
or comments or feedback of any kind,
please put that in the
comment section on YouTube.
We do read all the comments.
Please also check out
the sponsors mentioned
at the beginning of today's episode.
That's the best way to
support this podcast.
As mentioned earlier,
the Huberman Lab Podcast
now has a premium channel.
You can subscribe to that
by going to hubermanlab.com/premium.
There, for $10 a month or
$100 for the entire year,
you can get access to
all of the monthly AMAs,
and you'll be supporting
peer-reviewed research
to develop further protocols
for mental, physical
health and performance.
Again, that's hubermanlab.com/premium.
Not so much today, but
in many previous episodes
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we talk about supplements.
While supplements aren't
necessary for everybody,
many people derive
tremendous benefit from them
for things like enhancing sleep and focus
and hormone optimization.
The Huberman Lab Podcast
has partnered with Momentous supplements.
If you'd like to see the supplements
that the Huberman Lab Podcast
has partnered with Momentous on,
you can go to livemomentous,
spelled O-U-S,
so livemomentous.com/huberman,
and there you'll see a
number of the supplements
that we talk about
regularly on the podcast.
I should just mention that
that catalog of supplements
is constantly being updated.
If you haven't already signed up
for the Neural Network Newsletter,
this is a monthly Huberman
Lab Podcast newsletter
in which you get some
brief show note summaries
as well as a lot of actionable
tools in summary form.
Many people find these very useful
for distilling out the
vast amount of information
that we cover on the podcast.
So for instance, if you
go to hubermanlab.com,
you can click on the menu,
click to Neural Network
Newsletter or simply newsletter,
and you can sign up,
just give us your email.
We do not share your email with anybody.
And again, it's completely zero-cost.
We also have examples
of previous newsletters
that you can download immediately
without having to sign up for anything
and decide whether or
not you want to sign up.
Again, that's the Neural
Network Newsletter
at hubermanlab.com.
If you're not already
following us on social media,
we are @hubermanlab on
Instagram, on Twitter,
on Facebook and on LinkedIn.
And especially on
Instagram and on Twitter,
I cover many of the
tools that are discussed
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
but also a lot of science
and science-based tools
not covered on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
Again, it's @hubermanlab on all platforms.
So once again, thank you for joining me
for today's discussion all about cannabis.
And as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[bright music]