- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
(upbeat guitar music)
I'm Andrew Huberman
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
For today's podcast
we're going to talk about
the parts list of the nervous system.
Now that might sound boring,
but these are the bits and pieces
that together make up everything
about your experience of life,
from what you think about
to what you feel, what you imagine,
and what you accomplish
from the day you're born
until the day you die.
That parts list is really incredible
because it has a history
associated with it
that really provides a window
into all sorts of things
like engineering, warfare,
religion, and philosophy.
So I'm going to share
with you the parts list
that makes up who you are
through the lens of some of
those other aspects of life
and other aspects
of the history of the discovery
of the nervous system.
By the end of this podcast
I promise you're going
to understand a lot more
about how you work and how
to apply that knowledge.
There's going to be a little bit of story.
There's going to be a lot of discussion
about the people who made
these particular discoveries.
There'll be a little bit
of technical language.
There's no way to avoid that.
But at the end you're
going to have in hand
what will be the equivalent
of an entire semester of learning
about the nervous system and how you work
So a few important points
before we get started.
I am not a medical doctor.
That means I don't prescribe anything.
I'm a professor, so sometimes
I'll profess things.
In fact, I profess a lot of things.
We are going to talk about
some basic functioning
of the nervous system parts and et cetera,
but we're also going to talk
about how to apply that knowledge.
That said, your healthcare, your wellbeing
is your responsibility.
So anytime we talk about tools
please filter it through
that responsibility.
Talk to a healthcare professional
if you're going to explore
any new tools or practices
and be smart in your
pursuit of these new tools.
Also wanna emphasize that this podcast
and the other things I do on social media
are my personal goal of bringing
zero cost to consumer information
to the general public.
It is separate from my role
at Stanford University.
In that spirit I really want to thank
the sponsors of today's podcast.
The first one is Athletic Greens
which is an all-in-one drink.
It's a greens drink
that has vitamins, minerals,
probiotics, prebiotics.
I've been using Athletic Greens since 2012
so I'm really delighted that
they're sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I like it is because
I like vitamins and minerals,
I think they're important to my health
and it can be kind of overwhelming to know
what to take in that landscape.
So by taking one thing
that also happens to taste really good
I get all the vitamins minerals,
et cetera, that I need.
There's also a lot of data there now
about the importance of the gut microbiome
for immune health and
for the gut brain access,
all these things.
And the probiotics and prebiotics
are important to me for that reason.
If you want to try Athletic Greens
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman,
and put in the code word
Huberman at checkout.
If you do that
they'll send you a year's
supply of vitamin D3 and K2.
There's a lot in the news lately
about the importance of vitamin D3.
We can all get vitamin D3 from sunlight
but many of us aren't
getting enough sunlight.
Vitamin D3 has been shown to be relevant
to the immune system and the
hormone systems, et cetera.
So once again
that's athleticgreens.com/huberman,
enter Huberman at checkout,
and you get the year supply of D3 and K2
along with your Athletic Greens.
This podcast is also brought
to us by Inside Tracker
which is a health monitoring company.
It uses blood tests and
saliva tests to look at things
like DNA and metabolic markers
and monitors your hormones,
a huge number of different
parameters of health
that really can only
be measured accurately
through blood and saliva tests.
I use Inside Tracker because
I'm a big believer in data.
There's a lot of aspects to our biology
that can only be accurately measured
by way of blood tests and saliva tests.
The thing that's really
nice about Inside Tracker
is that rather than just giving
you a bunch of numbers back
of the levels of these
things in your body,
it gives you, through a
really simple platform,
information about what to do
with all those levels of hormones
and metabolic markers, et cetera.
It also has a feature which
is particularly interesting
which it measures your inner age,
which is more a measure
of your biological age
as opposed to your chronological age.
And all that information is organized
so that you can make changes
in your nutritional regimes
or your exercise regimes
and watch how those
markers change over time.
So if you want to try Inside Tracker
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman
and they'll give you 25% off at checkout.
So let's talk about the nervous system.
The reason I say your nervous
system and not your brain
is because your brain is
actually just one piece
of this larger, more
important thing, frankly,
that we call the nervous system.
The nervous system includes
your brain and your spinal cord
but also all the connections
between your brain
and your spinal cord and
the organs of your body.
It also includes, very importantly,
all the connections between your organs
back to your spinal cord and brain.
So the way to think about how
you function at every level
from the moment you're
born until the day you die,
everything you think and
remember and feel and imagine
is that your nervous system
is this continuous loop
of communication between the
brain, spinal cord, and body
and body, spinal cord, and brain.
In fact, we really can't
even separate them.
It's one continuous loop.
You may have heard of something
called a Mobius strip.
A Mobius strip is almost like one of
these impossible figures
that no matter which angle
you look at it from
you can't tell where it
starts and where it ends.
And that's really how your
nervous system is built.
That's the structure that
allows you to, for instance,
deploy immune cells,
to release cells that
will go kill infection
when you're in the presence of infection.
Most people just think about that
as a function of the immune system
but actually it's your nervous system
that tells organs like your spleen
to release killer cells
that go and hunt down
those bacterial and viral
invaders and gobble them up.
If you have a stomach ache, for instance,
sure, you feel that in your stomach,
but it's really your nervous system
that's causing the stomach ache.
The ache aspect of it is
a nervous system feature.
So when we want to talk about experience
or we want to talk about how
to change the self in any way,
we really need to think about
the nervous system first.
It is fair to say
that the nervous system governs
all other biological systems of the body,
and it's also influenced by
those other biological systems.
So if we're talking
about the nervous system
we need to get a little
specific about what we mean.
It's not just this big loop of wires.
In fact, there's a
interesting story about that
because at the turn of the
sort of 1800s to 1900s,
it actually was believed
that our nervous system
was just one giant cell.
But two guys, that names
aren't super important,
but in fairness to their
important discovery,
Ramon y Cajal, a Spaniard,
Camillo Golgi, an Italian guy,
figured out how to label
or stain the nervous system
in a way that revealed, oh my goodness,
we're actually made up of
trillions of these little cells,
nerve cells that are called neurons.
And that's what a neuron is.
It's just a nerve cell.
They also saw
that those nerve cells
weren't touching one another.
They're actually separated by little gaps.
And those little gaps you
may have heard of before,
they're called synapses.
Those synapses are where the chemicals
from one neuron are kind of
spit out or vomited into.
And then the next nerve
cell detects those chemicals
and then passes
electricity down its length
to the next nerve cell and so forth.
So really the way to think about
your body and your thoughts
and your mind is that you are
a flow of electricity, right?
There's nothing mystical about this.
You're a flow of electricity
between these different nerve cells.
And depending on which
nerve cells are active
you might be lifting your
arm or lowering your arm.
You might be seeing something
and perceiving that it's red
or you might be seeing something
and perceiving that it's green,
all depending on which nerve
cells are electrically active
at a given moment.
The example of perceiving
red or perceiving green
is a particularly good example
because so often our
experience of the world
makes it seem as if these out these things
that are happening outside us
are actually happening inside us.
But the language of the nervous
system is just electricity.
It's just like a Morse code of some sort
or the syllables and words and consonants
and vowels of language.
It just depends on how
they're assembled, what order.
And so that brings us
to the issue of how the
nervous system works.
The way to think about how
the nervous system works
is that our experiences, our memories,
everything is sort of
like the keys on a piano
being played in a particular order, right?
If I play the keys on a
piano in a particular order
and with a particular
intensity, that's a given song.
We can make that analogous
to a given experience.
It's not really that the key, you know,
A sharp or E flat is the song.
It's just one component of the song.
So when you hear that,
you know, for instance,
there's a brain area
called the hippocampus,
which there is, that's involved in memory.
Well, it's involved in memory,
but it's not that memories
are stored there as,
you know, sentences.
They're stored there as patterns
of electricity in neurons
that when repeated, give you the sense
that you are experiencing the thing again.
In fact, deja vu,
the sense that what you're
experiencing is so familiar
and like something that
you've experienced previously
is merely that the neurons
that were active in one circumstance
are now becoming active in
the same circumstance again.
And so it's really just
like hearing the same song
maybe not played on a piano
but next time on a classical guitar,
there's something similar about that song
even though it's being played
on two different instruments.
So I think it's important
that people understand the
parts of their nervous system,
and that it includes so much
more than just the brain
and that there are these
things, neurons and synapses.
But really that it's
the electrical activity
of these neurons that
dictates our experience.
So if the early 1900s were when
these neurons were discovered,
certainly a lot has happened since then.
And in that time between
the early 1900s and now
there's some important events
that actually happened in history
that gave us insight into
how the nervous system works.
One of the more surprising
ones was actually warfare.
So as most everybody knows in warfare
people get shot and people often die
but many people get
shot and they don't die.
And in World War One, there
were some changes in artillery,
in bullets that made for a situation
where bullets would
enter the body and brain
at very discrete locations
and would go out the other
side of the body or brain
and also make a very small
hole at that exit location.
And in doing so produced a lot
of naturally occurring
lesions of the nervous system.
Now you say, okay, well,
how does that relate
to neuroscience?
Well, unlike previous years
where a lot of the artillery
would create these big
sort of holes as the bullets
would blow out of the brain or body,
I know this is rather gruesome,
when the holes were very discrete
they entered at one point
and left at another point,
they would take out or destroy
very discrete bits of neural
tissue, of the nervous system.
So people were coming back from war
with holes in their brain
and in other parts of their nervous system
that were limited to
very specific locations.
In addition to that,
there was some advancement
in the cleaning of wounds that happened
so many more people were surviving.
What this meant was that neurologists
now had a collection of patients
that would come back and they'd have holes
in very specific locations of their brain.
And they'd say things like,
well, I can recognize faces
but I can't recognize who
those faces belong to.
I know it's a face, but I
don't know who it belongs to.
And after that person eventually died
the neurologist would figure out,
ah, I've had 10 patients that all told me
that they couldn't recognize faces.
And they all had these bullet holes
that went through a particular
region of the brain.
And that's how we know a lot
about how particular brain regions
like the hippocampus work.
In fact, some of the more
amazing examples of this,
where people would come
back and they, for instance,
would speak in complete gibberish
whereas previously they
could speak normally.
And even though they were
speaking in complete gibberish
they could understand language perfectly.
That's how we know that
speech and language
are actually controlled
by separate portions
of the nervous system.
And there are many examples like that.
People that couldn't recognize
the faces of famous people
or, and that actually brings us
to an interesting example in modern times.
Many, many years later in the early 2000s
there was actually a
paper that was published
in the journal "Nature",
excellent journal,
showing that in a human being,
a perfectly healthy human being,
there was a neuron that would become
electrically active only when the person
viewed the picture of
Jennifer Aniston, the actress.
So literally a neuron that
represented Jennifer Aniston,
so-called Jennifer Aniston cells,
neuroscientists know about
the Jennifer Aniston cells.
If you can recognize
Jennifer Aniston's face
you have Jennifer Aniston neurons,
and presumably also have neurons
that can recognize the faces
of other famous and non-famous people.
So that indicates
that our brain is really
a map of our experience.
We come into the world and
our brain has a kind of bias
towards learning
particular kinds of things.
It's ready to receive information
and learn that information,
but the brain is really
a map of experience.
So let's talk about what
experience really is.
What does it mean for your brain to work?
Well I think it's fair to say
that the nervous system really
does five things, maybe six.
The first one is sensation.
So this is important to understand
for any and all of you
that want to change your nervous system
or to apply tools to make your
nervous system work better.
Sensation is a non-negotiable element
of your nervous system.
You have neurons in your eye that perceive
certain colors of light and
certain directions of movement.
You have neurons in
your skin that perceive
particular kinds of touch,
like light touch or firm touch
or painful touch.
You have neurons in your ears
that perceive certain sounds.
Your entire experience of
life is filtered by these,
what we call sensory receptors
if you want to know what the name is.
So this always raises
an interesting question.
People ask, well, is
there much more out there?
Is there a lot more happening in the world
that I'm not experiencing
or that humans aren't experiencing?
And the answer of course is yes,
there are many species on this planet
that are perceiving things
that we will never perceive
unless we apply technology.
The best example I could think
of off the top of my head
would be something like infrared vision.
There are snakes out there,
pit vipers and so forth,
that can sense heat
emissions from other animals.
They don't actually see their shape.
They sense their heat shape
and their heat emissions.
Humans can't do that
unless of course they
put on infrared goggles
or something that would allow them
to detect those heat emissions.
There are turtles and
certain species of birds
that migrate long distances
that can detect magnetic fields
because they have neurons,
again, it's the nervous system
that allows them to do this.
So they have neurons in
their nose and in their head
that allow them to migrate
along magnetic fields
in order to, as amazing as this sounds,
go from one particular
location in the ocean,
thousands of miles away
to all aggregate on one particular beach
at a particular time of year
so that they can mate, lay eggs,
and then wander back
off into the sea to die.
And then their young
will eventually hatch,
those cute little turtles
will shuffle to the ocean,
swim off and go do the exact same thing.
They don't migrate that
distance by vision.
They don't do it by smell.
They do it by sensing magnetic fields.
And many other species do
these incredible things.
We don't, humans are not
magnetic sensing organisms.
We can't do that
because we don't have receptors
that sense magnetic fields.
There's some data that maybe some humans
can sense magnetic fields
but you should be very skeptical of anyone
that's convinced that they can do that
with any degree of robustness or accuracy,
because even the people that can do this
aren't necessarily aware that they can.
Maybe a topic for a future podcast.
So we have sensation,
then we have perception.
Perception is our ability
to take what we're sensing
and focus on it and make sense of it,
to explore it, to remember it.
So really perceptions are
just whichever sensations
we happen to be paying
attention to at any moment.
And you can do this right now.
You can experience perception
and the difference between
perception and sensation
very easily.
If, for instance, I tell
you to pay attention
to the contact of your feet,
the bottoms of your feet,
with whatever surface they
happen to be in contact with,
maybe it's shoes, maybe it's the floor,
if your feet are up maybe it's air.
The moment you place your,
what we call the spotlight of attention
or the spotlight of
perception on your feet.
You are now perceiving
what was happening there,
what was being sensed there.
The sensation was happening
all along however.
So while sensation is not negotiable
you can't change your receptors
unless you adopt some new technology,
perception is under the
control of your attention.
And the way to think about attention
is it's like a spotlight,
except it's not one spotlight.
You actually have two
attentional spotlights.
Anyone that tells you you can't multitask,
tell them they're wrong.
And if they disagree with
you tell them to contact me
because in old world
primates of which humans are,
we are able to do what's
called covert attention.
We can place a spotlight
of attention on something,
for instance, something
we're reading or looking at
or someone that we're listening to.
And we can place a second
spotlight of attention
on something we're
eating and how it tastes
or our child running around
in the room or my dog.
You can split your
attention into two locations
but of course you can
also bring your attention,
that is, your perception,
to one particular location.
You can dilate your attention
kind of like making a
spotlight more diffuse
or you can make it more concentrated.
This is very important to understand
if you're going to think about tools
to improve your nervous system,
whether or not that tool is
in the form of a chemical
that you decide to
take, maybe a supplement
to increase some chemical in your brain
if that's your choice,
or a brain machine device
or you're going to try
and learn something better
by engaging in some focus
or motivated pursuit
for some period of time each day.
Attention is something
that is absolutely under your control,
in particular when you're rested.
And we'll get back to this.
But when you are rested, and
we'll define rest very clearly,
you are able to direct your attention
in very deliberate ways.
And that's because we have
something in our nervous system
which is sort of like a two way street.
And that two way street is a communication
between the aspects of our
nervous system that are reflexive
and the aspects of our nervous
system that are deliberate.
So we all know what it's
like to be reflexive.
You go through life, you're walking.
If you already know how to walk
you don't think about your walking.
You just walk.
And that's because the nervous
system wants to pass off
as much as it can to reflexive action.
That's called bottom up processing.
It really just means that information
is flowing in through your senses,
regardless of what you're perceiving,
that information is flowing up
and it's directing your activity.
But at any moment, for instance,
let's say a car screeches in
front of you around the corner,
and you suddenly pause.
You are now moving into deliberate action.
You would start looking around
in a very deliberate way.
The nervous system can be
reflexive in its action
or it can be deliberate.
If reflexive action tends to
be what we call bottom up,
deliberate action and
deliberate perceptions
and deliberate thoughts are top down.
They require some effort and some focus.
But that's the point,
you can decide to focus
your attention and energy
on anything you want.
You can decide to focus your
behavior in any way you want.
But it will always feel
like it requires some
effort and some strain.
Whereas when you're in reflexive mode,
just walking and talking and
eating and doing your thing
it's going to feel very easy.
And that's because your nervous system
basically wired up to be able
to do most things easily
without much metabolic demand,
without consuming much energy.
But the moment you try and
do something very specific,
you're going to feel a
sort of mental friction.
It's going to be challenging.
So we've got sensations, perceptions,
and then we've got things
that we call feelings slash emotions.
And these get a little complicated
because almost all of us,
I would hope all of us,
are familiar with things
like happiness and sadness
or boredom or frustration.
Scientists argue like crazy,
neuroscientists and psychologists
and philosophers for that matter,
argue like crazy about what
these are and how they work.
Certainly emotions and feelings
are the product of the nervous system.
They involve the activity of neurons.
But as I mentioned earlier,
neurons are electrically active
but they also release chemicals.
And there's a certain
category of chemicals
that has a very profound influence
on our emotional states.
They're called neuromodulators.
And those neuromodulators
have names that probably
you've heard of before.
Things like dopamine and serotonin
and acetylcholine, epinephrine.
Neuromodulators are really interesting
because they bias which
neurons are likely to be active
and which ones are likely to be inactive.
A simple way to think
about neuromodulators
is they are sort of like playlists
that you would have on any kind of device
where you're going to play
particular categories of music.
So for instance, dopamine,
which is often discussed
as the molecule of reward or
joy, it is involved in reward.
And it does tend to create
a sort of upbeat mood
when released in appropriate
amounts in the brain.
But the reason it does
that is because it makes
certain neurons and neural
circuits as we call them
more active and others less active.
Okay.
So serotonin, for instance,
is a molecule that when released
tends to make us feel really
good with what we have,
our sort of internal landscape
and the resources that we have,
whereas dopamine more than
being a molecule of reward
is really more a molecule of motivation
toward things that are outside us
and that we want to pursue.
And we can look at healthy conditions
or situations like being
in pursuit of a goal
where every time we accomplish something
en route to that goal, a little
bit of dopamine is released
and we feel more motivation, that happens.
We can also look at the extreme example
of something like mania,
where somebody is so
relentlessly in pursuit
of external things like
money and relationships
that they're sort of in this
delusional state of thinking
that they have the
resources that they need
in order to pursue all these things
when in fact they don't.
So these neuromodulators can exist
in normal levels, low levels, high levels.
And that actually gives us a window
into a very important aspect
of neuroscience history
that all of us are impacted by today,
which is the discovery of antidepressants
and so-called anti-psychotics.
In the 1950s, '60s, and '70s,
it was discovered that
there are compounds,
chemicals that can increase
or decrease serotonin,
that can increase or decrease dopamine.
And that led to the development
of most of what we call antidepressants.
Now, the trick here or the problem
is that most of these drugs,
especially in the 1950s and '60s,
they would reduce serotonin
but they would also reduce dopamine
or they would increase serotonin,
but they would also increase
some other neuromodulator chemical.
And that's because all these
chemical systems in the body,
but the neuromodulators in particular,
have a lot of receptors.
Now, these are different
than the receptors
we were talking about earlier.
The receptors I'm talking about now
are sort of like parking spots
where dopamine is released.
And if it attaches to a
receptor, say on the heart,
it might make the heart beat faster
because there's a certain
kind of receptor on the heart.
Whereas if dopamine is released
and goes and attaches to muscle
it might have a completely
different effect on the muscle.
And in fact, it does.
So different receptors on
different organs of the body
are the ways that these neuromodulators
can have all these different effects
on different aspects of our biology.
This is most salient in the example
of some of the antidepressants
that have sexual side effects
or that blunt appetite
or that blunt motivation.
You know, many of these
which increase serotonin
can be very beneficial for people.
It can elevate their mood.
It can make them feel better.
But they also if their,
the doses are too high
or if that particular drug
isn't right for somebody
that person experiences
challenges with motivation
or appetite or libido
because serotonin is binding to receptors
in the areas of the brain
that control those other things as well.
So we talked about sensation.
We talked about perception.
When we talk about feelings,
we have to consider these neuromodulators.
And we have to consider also
that feelings and emotions
are contextual.
In some cultures showing a
lot of joy or a lot of sadness
is entirely appropriate,
in other cultures it's
considered inappropriate.
So I don't think it's fair to say
that there is a sadness
circuit or area of the brain
or a happiness circuit
or area of the brain.
However, it is fair to
say that certain chemicals
and certain brain
circuits tend to be active
when we are in motivated states,
tend to be active when we are
in non-motivated lazy states,
tend to be active when we are focused
and tend to be active
when we are not focused.
I want to emphasize also
that emotions are something
that we generally feel
are not under our control.
We feel like they kind
of geyser up within us
and they just kind of happen to us.
And that's because they
are somewhat reflexive.
We don't really set out
with a deliberate thought to be happy
or a deliberate thought to be sad.
We tend to experience them
in kind of a passive reflexive way.
And that brings us to the next
thing, which are thoughts.
Thoughts are really interesting because
in many ways they're like perceptions
except that they draw on
not just what's happening in the present
but also things we remember from the past
and things that we
anticipate about the future.
The other thing about thoughts
that's really interesting
is that thoughts can be both reflexive,
they can just be occurring all the time
sort of like pop-up windows
on a poorly filtered web browser,
or they can be deliberate.
We can decide to have a thought.
In fact, right now you could
decide to have a thought
just like you would decide
to write something out
on a piece of paper.
You could decide that you're
listening to a podcast,
that you are in a particular location.
You're not just paying
attention to what's happening,
you're directing your thought process.
And a lot of people don't understand
or at least appreciate
that the thought patterns
and the neural circuits
that underlie thoughts
can actually be controlled
in this deliberate way.
And then finally there are actions.
Actions or behaviors are perhaps
the most important aspect
of our nervous system.
Because first of all,
our behaviors are actually the only thing
that are going to create any
fossil record of our existence.
You know, after we die, the
nervous system deteriorates,
our skeleton will remain.
But it's, you know, in the moment
of experiencing something very joyful
or something very sad, it
can feel so all encompassing
that we actually think
that it has some meaning
beyond that moment.
But actually for humans and
I think for all species,
the sensations, the
perceptions and the thoughts
and the feelings that
we have in our lifespan,
none of that is actually carried forward
except the ones that we take
and we convert into
actions such as writing,
actions such as words,
actions such as engineering new things.
And so the fossil record of
our species and each one of us
is really through action.
And that, in part, is why so
much of our nervous system
is devoted to converting
sensation, perceptions, feelings,
and thoughts into actions.
In fact, the great neuroscientist
or physiologist Sherrington
won a Nobel prize
for his work in mapping
some of the circuitry,
the connections between nerve cells
that give rise to movement.
And he said, "Movement is
the final common pathway".
The other way to think about it is that
one of the reasons that
our central nervous system,
our brain and spinal cord
include this stuff in our skull
but also connects so heavily to the body
is because most everything
that we experience,
including our thoughts and feelings,
was really designed to either
impact our behavior or not.
And the fact that
thoughts allow us to reach
into the past and anticipate the future
and not just experience
what's happening in the moment
gave rise to an incredible capacity
for us to engage in behaviors
that are not just for the moment,
they're based on things
that we know from the past
and that we would like
to see in the future.
And this aspect of our nervous
system, of creating movement,
occurs through some very simple pathways.
The reflexive pathway basically
includes areas of the brain stem
we call central pattern generators.
When you walk, provided you
already know how to walk,
you are basically walking
because you have these
central pattern generators,
groups of neurons that generate
right foot, left foot,
right foot, left foot
kind of movement.
However, when you decide to move
in a particular deliberate way
that requires a little more attention
you start to engage areas of your brain
for top-down processing
where your forebrain
works from the top down
to control those central
pattern generators
so that maybe it's right foot, right foot,
left foot, right foot,
right foot, left foot
if maybe you're hiking along
some rocks or something.
And you have to engage
in that kind of movement.
So movement, just like thoughts,
can be either reflexive or deliberate.
And when we talk about deliberate
I want to be very specific
about how your brain works
in a deliberate way
because it gives rise to
a very important feature
of the nervous system that
we're going to talk about next,
which is your ability to
change your nervous system.
And what I'd like to
center on for a second
is this notion of what does it mean
for the nervous system to
do something deliberately?
Well, when you do something deliberately,
you pay attention, you are
bringing your perception
to an analysis of three things,
duration, how long something
is is going to take
or should be done,
path, what you should be doing,
and outcome, if you do something
for a given length of time,
what's going to happen.
Now when you're walking down
the street or you're eating
or you're just talking
reflexively, you're not doing this
what I call DPO, duration, path, outcome,
type of deliberate function
in your brain and nervous system.
But the moment you
decide to learn something
or to resist speaking
or to speak up when you
would rather be quiet,
anytime you're deliberately
kind of forcing yourself over a threshold,
you're engaging these brain circuits
and these nervous system circuits
that suddenly make it feel as
if something is challenging.
Something has changed.
Well, what's changed?
What's changed is that when you engage
in this duration, path, and outcome
type of thinking or
behavior or way of being
you start to recruit these neuromodulators
that are released from
particular areas of your brain,
and also it turns out from your body.
and they start cuing
to your nervous system.
Something's different.
Something's different
now about what I'm doing.
about what I'm feeling.
Let's give an example where perhaps
somebody says something
that's triggering to you.
You don't like it.
And you know you shouldn't respond.
You feel like, oh, I shouldn't respond,
I shouldn't respond, I shouldn't respond.
You're actively suppressing your behavior
through top down processing.
Your forebrain is actually preventing you
from saying the thing that
you know you shouldn't say
or that maybe you should wait to say
or say in a different form.
This feels like agitation and stress
because you're actually
suppressing a circuit.
We actually can see examples
of what happens when
you're not doing this well.
Some of the examples come from children.
If you look at young children
they don't have the forebrain circuitry
to engage in this top down processing
until they reach age 22, even 25.
But in young children, you see
this in a really robust way.
You'll see they'll be
rocking back and forth.
It's hard for them to sit still
because those central pattern generators
are constantly going in the background.
Whereas adults can sit still.
A kid sees a piece of candy that it wants
and will just reach out and grab it.
Whereas an adult probably would ask
if they could have a piece
or wait until they were
offered a piece in most cases.
People that have damage
to the certain areas
of the frontal lobes don't
have this kind of restriction.
They'll just blurt things out.
They'll just say things.
We all know people like this.
Impulsivity is a lack of top down control,
a lack of top-down processing.
The other thing that will
turn off the forebrain
and make it harder to top-down processing
is a couple of drinks containing alcohol.
The removal of inhibition is actually
removal of neural inhibition,
of nerve cells suppressing the activity
of other nerve cells.
And so when you look at people
that have damage to their frontal lobes
or you look at puppies or
you look at young children,
everything's a stimulus.
Everything is a potential
interaction for them.
And they have a very hard time
restricting their
behavior and their speech.
So a lot of the motor system
is designed to just work
in a reflexive way.
And then when we decide
we want to learn something
or do something or not do something,
we have to engage in this
top-down restriction.
And it feels like agitation
because it's accompanied
by the release of a neuromodulator
called norepinephrine,
which in the body we call adrenaline.
And it actually makes us feel agitated.
So for those of you that are
trying to learn something new
or to learn to suppress your responses
or be more deliberate and
careful in your responses,
that is going to feel challenging
for a particular reason.
It's going to feel challenging
because the chemicals in
your body that are released
in association with that effort
are designed to make you
feel kind of agitated.
That low-level tremor
that sometimes people feel
when they're really, really angry
is actually a chemically
induced low-level tremor.
And it's the, what I call limbic friction.
There's an area of your brain
that's involved in our more
primitive reflexive responses
called the limbic system.
And the frontal cortex is in a friction,
it's in a tug of war with
that system all the time.
Unless of course you have
damage to the frontal lobe
or you've had too much
to drink or something.
In which case you tend to
just say and do whatever.
And so this is really
important to understand
because if you want to
understand neuroplasticity,
you want to understand how
to shape your behavior,
how to shape your thinking,
how to change how you're able
to perform in any context,
the most important thing to understand
is that it requires top-down processing.
It requires this feeling of agitation.
In fact, I would say
the agitation and strain
is the entry point to neuroplasticity.
So let's take a look at
what neuroplasticity is.
Let's explore it, not as the
way it's normally talked about
in modern culture,
neuroplasticity, plasticity is great.
Well, what exactly do people mean?
Plasticity itself is just a process
by which neurons can
change their connections
and the way they work
so that you can go from things
being very challenging and deliberate,
requiring a lot of effort and strain,
to them being reflexive.
And typically when we
hear about plasticity,
we're thinking about positive
or what I call adaptive plasticity.
A lot of plasticity can be induced,
for instance by brain damage,
but that's generally not
the kind of plasticity that we want.
So when I say plasticity,
unless I say otherwise
I mean adaptive plasticity.
And in particular
most of the neuroplasticity
that people want
is self-directed plasticity.
Because if there's one
truism to neuroplasticity,
it's that from birth until about age 25
the brain is incredibly plastic.
Kids are learning all sorts of things
but they can learn it passively.
They don't have to work
too hard or focus too hard,
although focus helps, to learn new things,
acquire new languages, acquire new skills.
But if you're an adult
and you want to change your
neural circuitry at the level
of emotions or behavior or
thoughts or anything really,
you absolutely need to ask
two important questions.
One, what particular aspect
of my nervous system
am I trying to change?
Meaning, am I trying to change my emotions
or my perceptions, my sensations?
And which ones are
available for me to change?
And then the second question is
how are you going to go about that?
What is the structure
of a regimen to engage neuroplasticity?
And it turns out that the
answer to that second question
is governed by how awake
or how sleepy we are.
So let's talk about that next.
Neuroplasticity is the ability
for these connections
in the brain and body
to change in response to experience.
And what's so incredible
about the human nervous
system in particular
is that we can direct
our own neural changes.
We can decide that we
want to change our brain.
In other words, our
brain can change itself
and our nervous system can change itself.
And the same can't be said
for other organs of the body.
Even though our other organs of the body
have some ability to change,
they can't direct it.
They can't think and decide,
you know your gut doesn't say,
oh, you know, I want to be able
to digest spicy foods better
so I'm going to rearrange the connections
to be able to do that.
Whereas your brain can decide
that you want to learn a language
or you want to be less
emotionally reactive
or more emotionally engaged,
and you can undergo a series of steps
that will allow your brain
to make those changes
so that eventually it becomes
reflexive for you to do that,
which is absolutely incredible.
For a long time it was
thought that neuroplasticity
was the unique gift of
young animals and humans,
that it could only occur when we're young.
And in fact, a young brain
is incredibly plastic.
Children can learn three languages
without an accent reflexively,
whereas adults, it's very challenging.
It takes a lot more effort and strain,
a lot more of that duration,
path, outcome kind of thinking
in order to achieve those plastic changes.
We now know, however, that
the adult brain can change
in response to experience.
Nobel prizes were given
for the understanding that the young brain
can change very dramatically.
I think one of the most
extreme examples would be
for people that are born blind from birth
they use the area of their brain
that normally would be used
for visualizing objects and colors
and things outside of
them for braille reading.
In brain imaging studies it's
been shown that, you know,
people who are blind from
birth, when they braille read,
the area of the brain
that would normally light
up, if you will, for vision
lights up for braille reading.
So that real estate is reallocated
for an entirely different function.
If someone is made blind in adulthood,
it's unlikely that their
entire visual brain
will be taken over
by the areas of the brain that
are responsible for touch.
However, there's some evidence
that areas of the brain
that are involved in hearing and touch
can kind of migrate into that area.
And there's a lot of interest
now in trying to figure out
how more plasticity can
be induced in adulthood,
more positive plasticity.
And in order to understand that process
we really have to understand something
that might at first
seem totally divorced
from neuroplasticity,
but actually lies at the
center of neuroplasticity.
And for any of you that are interested
in changing your nervous system
so that something that you want can go
from being very hard or
seem almost impossible
and out of reach to being very reflexive,
this is especially important
to pay attention to.
Plasticity in the adult human
nervous system is gated,
meaning it is controlled
by neuromodulators.
These things that we talked about earlier,
dopamine, serotonin,
and one in particular
called acetylcholine,
are what open up plasticity.
They literally unveil plasticity
and allow brief periods of time
in which whatever information,
whatever thing we're sensing
or perceiving or thinking,
whatever emotions we feel
can literally be mapped in the brain
such that later it will become much easier
for us to experience and feel that thing.
Now, this has a dark
side and a positive side.
The dark side is it's actually very easy
to get neuroplasticity as an adult
through traumatic or terrible
or challenging experiences.
But the important question
is to say, why is that?
And the reason that's the case is because
when something very bad
happens, there's the release
of two sets of
neuromodulators in the brain,
epinephrine which tends to make
us feel alert and agitated,
which is associated with
most bad circumstances.
And acetylcholine, which tends to create
a even more intense and
focused perceptual spotlight.
Remember earlier we were
talking about perception
and how it's kind of like a spotlight.
Acetylcholine makes that
light particularly bright
and particularly restricted to
one region of our experience.
And it does that by making certain neurons
in our brain and body
active much more than all the rest.
So acetylcholine is sorta
like a highlighter marker
upon which neuroplasticity
then comes in later and says,
wait, which neurons were active
in this particularly alerting
phase of whatever, you know,
day or night, whenever
this thing happened.
So the way it works is this,
you can think of epinephrine
as creating this alertness
and this kind of unbelievable
level of increased attention
compared to what you
were experiencing before.
And you can think of acetylcholine
as being the molecule that
highlights whatever happens
during that period of
heightened alertness.
So just to be clear,
it's epinephrine creates the alertness,
that's coming from a subset
of neurons in the brain stem
if you're interested,
and acetylcholine coming
from an area of the forebrain
is tagging or marking the neurons
that are particularly active
during this heightened level of alertness.
Now that marks the cells,
the neurons and the synapses
for strengthening,
for becoming more likely
to be active in the future
even without us thinking about it.
Okay?
So in bad circumstances
this all happens without
us having to do much.
When we want something to happen, however,
we want to learn a language,
we want to learn a new skill,
we want to become more motivated,
what do we know for certain?
We know that that process
of getting neuroplasticity
so that we have more
focus, more motivation,
absolutely requires the
release of epinephrine.
We have to have alertness
in order to have focus
and we have to have focus
in order to direct those plastic changes
to particular parts of our nervous system.
Now, this has immense implications
in thinking about the various tools,
whether or not those are
chemical tools or machine tools
or just self-induced regimens
of how long or how intensely
you're going to focus
in order to get neuroplasticity.
But there's another side to it.
The dirty secret of neuroplasticity
is that no neuroplasticity occurs
during the thing you're trying to learn,
during the terrible event,
during the great event.
During the thing
that you're really trying
to shape and learn,
nothing is actually
changing between the neurons
that is going to last.
All the neuroplasticity, the
strengthening of the synapses,
the addition, in some
cases, of new nerve cells
or at least connections
between nerve cells,
all of that occurs at a
very different phase of life
which is when we are in sleep
and non-sleep deep rest.
And so neuroplasticity,
which is the kind of Holy
Grail of human experience of,
you know, this is the New Year
and everyone's thinking
New Year's resolutions.
And right now, perhaps
everything's organized
and people are highly motivated
but what happens in March or April or May?
Well, that all depends
on how much attention
and focus one can continually bring
to whatever it is they're trying to learn,
so much so that agitation
and a feeling of strain
are actually required
for this process of
neuro-plasticity to get triggered.
But the actual rewiring occurs
during periods of sleep
and non-sleep deep rest.
There's a study published last year
that's particularly relevant
here that I want to share,
it was not done by my laboratory,
that showed that 20 minutes of deep rest,
this is not deep sleep,
but essentially doing something
very hard and very intense
and then taking 20 minutes
immediately afterwards
to deliberately turn off
the deliberate focused
thinking and engagement
actually accelerated neuroplasticity.
There's another study
that's just incredible.
And we're going to go into this
in a future episode of the
podcast not too long from now,
that showed that if people are
learning a particular skill,
it could be a language
skill or a motor skill,
and they hear a tone just
playing in the background,
and the tone is playing
periodically in the background,
like just a bell.
In deep sleep, if that bell is played
learning is much faster for the thing
that they were learning
while they were awake.
It somehow cues the
nervous system in sleep,
doesn't even have to be in dreaming,
that something that
happened in the waking phase
was especially important.
So much so that that bell
is sort of a Pavlovian cue,
it's sort of a reminder
to the sleeping brain,
oh, you need to remember what it is
that you were learning at
that particular time of day.
And the learning rates and
the rates of retention,
meaning how much people can remember
from the thing they learned,
are significantly higher
under those conditions.
So I'm going to talk about how
to apply all this knowledge
a little bit more in this podcast episode
but also in future episodes.
But it really speaks to
the really key importance
of sleep and focus,
these two opposite ends
of our attentional state.
When we're in sleep these DPOs,
duration, path, and outcome
analysis are impossible.
We just can't do that.
We are only in relation to
what's happening inside of us.
So sleep is key.
Also key are periods
of non-sleep deep rest
where we're turning off our analysis
of duration, path, and outcome,
in particular for the thing
that we were just trying to learn.
And we're in this kind of liminal state
where our attention is
kind of drifting all over.
It turns out that's very important
for the consolidation, for the changes
between the nerve cells that will allow
what we were trying to learn to go
from being deliberate and hard
and stressful and a strain
to easy and reflexive.
This also points to how different people,
including many modern clinicians,
are thinking about how to prevent
bad circumstances, traumas,
from routing their way into
our nervous system permanently.
It says that you might want to interfere
with certain aspects of brain states
that are away from the
bad thing that happened,
the brain states that
happened the next day
or the next month or the next year.
And also, I want to make sure
that I pay attention to the
fact that for many of you
you're thinking about neuro-plasticity
not just in changing your nervous system
to add something new
but to also get rid of things
that you don't like, right?
That you want to forget bad experiences
or at least remove the
emotional contingency
of a bad relationship
or a bad relationship to some thing
or some person or some event.
Learning to fear certain things,
less to eliminate a phobia,
to erase a trauma.
The memories themselves don't get erased.
I'm sorry to say
that the memories don't
themselves get erased,
but the emotional load of
memories can be reduced.
And there are a number of different ways
that that can happen
but they all require this thing
that we're calling neuroplasticity.
We're going to have a
large number of discussions
about neuroplasticity in depth,
but the most important thing to understand
is that it is indeed a two phase process.
What governs the transition
between alert and focused
and these deep rest and deep sleep states
is a system in our brain and body,
a certain aspect of the nervous system
called the autonomic nervous system.
And it is immensely
important to understand
how this autonomic nervous system works.
It has names like the
sympathetic nervous system
and parasympathetic nervous system
which frankly are complicated names
because they're a little bit misleading.
Sympathetic is the one that's associated
with more alertness.
Parasympathetic is the
one that's associated
with more calmness.
And it gets really misleading
because the sympathetic nervous
system sounds like sympathy.
And then people think
it's related to calm.
I'm going to call it the alertness system
and the calmness system,
because even though
sympathetic and parasympathetic
are sometimes used, people
really get confused.
So the way to think about
the autonomic nervous system
and the reason it's important
for every aspect of your life,
but in particular for neuroplasticity
and engaging in these focus states
and in these de-focused states
is that it works sort of like a seesaw.
Every 24 hours, we're all
familiar with the fact
that when we wake up in the morning
we might be a little bit groggy
but then generally we're more alert.
And then as evening comes around
we tend to become a little
more relaxed and sleepy.
Eventually at some point
at night, we go to sleep.
So we go from alert to deeply calm.
And as we do that, we go
from an ability to engage
in these very focused
duration, path, outcome
types of analyses
to states in sleep that
are completely divorced
from duration, path, and outcome
in which everything is
completely random and untethered
in terms of our sensations,
perceptions and feelings
and so forth.
So every 24 hours, we
have a phase of our day
that is optimal for thinking
and focusing and learning
and neuroplasticity and
doing all sorts of things.
We have energy as well.
And at another phase of our day
we're tired and we have
no ability to focus.
We have no ability
to engage in duration, path,
outcome types of analyses.
And it's interesting that
both phases are important
for shaping our nervous system
in the ways that we want.
So if we want to engage neuroplasticity
and we want to get the most
out of our nervous system
we each have to master
both the transition between
wakefulness and sleep
and the transition between
sleep and wakefulness.
Now so much has been made
of the importance of sleep.
And it is critically important
for wound healing, for
learning as I just mentioned,
for consolidating learning,
for all aspects of our immune system.
It is the one period of time
in which we're not doing
these duration, path, and
outcome types of analyses.
And it is critically important
to all aspects of our health,
including our longevity.
Much less has been made, however,
of how to get better at sleeping,
how to get better at the process
that involves falling
asleep, staying asleep,
and accessing the states of mind and body
that involve total paralysis.
Most people don't know this
but you're actually paralyzed
during much of your sleep
so that you can't act out
your dreams, presumably.
But also where your brain
is in a total idle state
where it's not controlling anything,
it's just left to kind of free run.
And there are certain
things that we can all do
in order to master that transition,
in order to get better at sleeping.
And it involves much more
than just how much we sleep.
We're all being told, of course,
that we need to sleep more
but there's also the
issue of sleep quality,
accessing those deep
States of non DPO thinking.
Accessing the right timing of sleep,
not a lot has been discussed
publicly, as far as I'm aware,
of when to time your sleep.
I think we all can appreciate
that sleeping for half an
hour throughout the day
so that you get a total
of eight hours of sleep
every 24 hour cycle
is probably very different and not optimal
compared to a solid block
of eight hours of sleep.
Although there are people
that have tried this,
I think it's been written
about in various books.
Not many people can
stick to that schedule.
Incidentally, I think it's
called the Uberman schedule,
not to be confused with
the Huberman schedule
because first of all
my schedule doesn't
look anything like that.
And second of all
I would never attempt
such a sleeping regime.
The other thing that is
really important to understand
is that we have not
explored, as a culture,
the rhythms that occur
in our waking states.
So much has been focused
on the value of sleep
and the importance of
sleep, which is great.
But I don't think that most
people are paying attention
to what's happening in their waking states
and when their brain
is optimized for focus,
when their brain is optimized
for these DPOs, these
duration, path, outcome
types of engagements for
learning and for changing
and when are their brain
is probably better suited
for more reflexive thinking and behaviors.
And it turns out
that there's a vast
amount of scientific data
which points to the existence
of what are called ultradian rhythms.
You may have heard of circadian rhythms.
Circadian means, circa, about a day.
So it's 24 hour rhythms
because the earth spins
once every 24 hours.
Ultradian rhythms occur throughout the day
and they require less
time, they're shorter.
The most important ultradian rhythm
for sake of this discussion
is the 90 minute rhythm
that we're going through
all the time in our ability
to attend and focus.
And in sleep, we are,
our sleep is broken up
into 90 minute segments.
Early in the night
we have more phase one and
phase two lighter sleep.
And then we go into
our deeper phase three
and phase four sleep.
And then we return to phase
one, two, three, four.
So all night, you're going
through these ultradian rhythms
of stage one, two, three, four,
one, two, three, four, it's repeating.
Most people perhaps know that.
Maybe they don't.
But you wake up in the morning,
these ultradian rhythms continue.
And it turns out that we are optimized
for focus and attention
within these 90 minute cycles
so that at the beginning of
one of these 90 minute cycles
maybe you sit down to learn something new
or to engage in some new
challenging behavior,
for the first five or 10
minutes of one of those cycles
it's well-known that the
brain and the neural circuits
and the neuromodulators are
not going to be optimally tuned
to whatever it is you're trying to do.
But as you drop deeper
into that 90 minute cycle
your ability to focus and to
engage in this DPO process
and to direct neuroplasticity and to learn
is actually much greater.
And then you eventually pop out of that
at the end of the 90 minute cycle.
So these cycles are occurring in sleep
and these cycles are
occurring in wakefulness.
And all of those are governed
by this seesaw of alertness to calmness
that we call the autonomic nervous system.
So if you want to master and
control your nervous system,
regardless of what tool you reach to,
whether or not it's a pharmacologic tool
or whether or not it's a behavioral tool
or whether or not it's a
brain machine interface tool,
it's vitally important to understand
that your entire existence is occurring
in these 90 minute cycles,
whether or not you're asleep or awake.
And so you really need to
learn how to wedge into
those 90 minute cycles.
And for instance, it
would be completely crazy
and counterproductive
to try and just learn
information while in deep sleep
by listening to that information
because you're not able to access it.
It would be perfectly good,
however, to engage in a focused
bout of learning each day.
And now we know how long
that focused bout of learning should be,
it should be at least one 90 minute cycle.
And the expectation should
be that the early phase
of that cycle is going to be challenging.
It's going to hurt.
It's not going to feel natural.
It's not going to feel like flow.
But that you can learn
and the circuits of your
brain that are involved
in focus and motivation
can learn to drop into
a mode of more focus,
get more neuroplasticity in other words,
by engaging these ultradian cycles
at the appropriate times of day.
For instance, some people
are very good learners
early in the day and not
so good in the afternoon.
So you can start to explore this process
even without any information
about the underlying neurochemicals
by simply paying attention,
not just to when you go to sleep
and when you wake up each morning,
how deep or how shallow your
sleep felt to you subjectively.
But also, throughout the day,
when your brain tends to be most anxious.
Because it turns out that has a correlate
related to perception
that we will talk about.
You can ask yourself
when are you most focused?
When are you least anxious?
When do you feel most motivated?
When do you feel least motivated?
By understanding how the different aspects
of your perception, sensation, feeling,
thought, and actions,
tend to want to be engaged
or not want to be engaged.
You develop a very good window
into what's going to be required
to shift your ability to focus
or shift your ability to engage
in creative type thinking
at different times of
day, should you choose.
And so that's where we're
heading, going forward.
It all starts with mastering this seesaw
that is the autonomic nervous system,
that at a course level is a transition
between wakefulness and
sleep, but at a finer level,
and just as important,
are the various cycles, these
ultradian 90 minute cycles
that govern our life all the time,
24 hours a day every day of our life.
And so we're going to talk
about how you can take control
of the autonomic nervous system
so that you can better
access neuroplasticity,
better access sleep,
even take advantage of the phase
that is the transition
between sleep and waking
to access things like
creativity and so forth.
All based on studies
that have been published
over the last 100 years,
mainly within the last 10 years
and some that are very, very new.
And that point to the use
of specific tools that will allow you
to get the most out of
your nervous system.
So today we covered a lot of information.
It was sort of a whirlwind tour
of everything from neurons and synapses
to neuroplasticity and the
autonomic nervous system.
We will revisit a lot of
these themes going forward.
So if all of that didn't
sink in in one pass,
please don't worry.
We will come back to these
themes over and over again.
I wanted to equip you with a language
so that we're all developing
a kind of common base set of
information going forward.
And I hope the information
is valuable to you
in your thinking about what
is working well for you
and what's working less well
and what's been exceedingly challenging,
what's been easy for you
in terms of your pursuit
of particular behaviors
or emotional states where your challenges
or the challenges of people
that you know might reside.
As promised in our welcome video,
the format of the "Huberman Lab" podcast
is to dive deep into individual topics
for an entire month at a time.
So for the entire month of January
we're going to explore this
incredible state that is sleep
and a related state, which
is non-sleep deep rest
and what they do
for things like learning,
resetting our emotional capacity.
Everyone's probably familiar with the fact
that when we're sleep deprived
we're so much less good at
dealing with life circumstances.
We're more emotionally labile.
Why is that?
How is that?
But most importantly,
we're going to talk about
how to get better at sleeping
and how to access better sleep
even when your sleep timing
or duration is compromised.
We're also going to talk
about the data that support
this very interesting state
called non-sleep deep rest
where one is neither asleep nor awake,
but it turns out one can recover
some of the neuromodulators
and more importantly the processes
involved in sensation, perception,
feeling, thought, and action.
It's sure to be a very rich
discussion back and forth
where I'm answering your
questions and providing tools.
And I'm certain you're also going to learn
a lot of information about neuroscience
and what makes up this
incredible phase of your life
where you think you're not conscious,
but you're actually resetting
and renewing yourself
in order to perform better,
feel better, et cetera,
in the waking state.
If you want to support the podcast,
please click the like button
and subscribe on YouTube.
Leave us a comment if you
have any feedback for us.
And on Apple, you can also
leave a review and comments
for us to improve the
podcast experience for you.
Please also check out our
sponsors and thank you so much.
We'll see you on the
next episode next week.
(upbeat guitar music)