- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
- I'm Andrew Huberman, and I'm
a professor of neurobiology
and ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring you zero cost
to consumer information
about science and science related tools
to the general public.
And keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I've long been a believer in
getting regular blood tests
and the simple reason for that
is that so many of the factors
that impact our immediate and
longterm health and wellbeing
can only be analyzed from blood.
And now with the advent
of modern DNA tests,
you can get additional
layers of information
that can really support your understanding
about what's going on deep
under the hood, so to speak
inside your body and brain
and what to do about it.
And I think that's really
where InsideTracker
sets itself apart from
other similar tests.
What InsideTracker
offers is, first of all,
they make the tests very easy.
They can come to your home to
take your blood and DNA test
or you can go to a
testing center nearby you.
Then you get the information back
and rather than just getting information
about whether or not the
levels of various things
are high or low,
you also get to find
out what to do about it.
So it offers directives
related to nutrition,
to exercise and so forth.
It's really allow you to be in control
of your overall health,
both where you are now
and its long-term trajectory.
With InsideTracker, they
also have something which is
it can give you a readout
of your inner age.
They have something
called the inner age test
that really compares your biological age
to your chronological age,
something that's of extreme
importance and interest
because it has to do with
lifespan or predicted lifespan.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker
you can visit insidetracker.com/huberman
and if you do that, you'll get 25% off
any of InsideTracker plans.
Use the code Huberman at checkout.
That's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off
any of InsideTracker's plans
and use the code Huberman at checkout.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Helix Sleep.
Helix Sleep is a company that
makes mattresses and pillows
ideally suited to your sleep needs.
I've been sleeping on a Helix mattress
for the last six months,
and I can honestly say
it's the best sleep that I've ever gotten.
Helix Sleep has a quiz that can match you
to the ideal mattress and pillows for you.
It's a quiz that takes
just about two minutes,
asks you questions like do
you tend to sleep on your side
or your back on your stomach?
Or maybe you don't know,
whether or not you tend to wake up
feeling too warm or too cold?
Various questions about your sleep habits.
At the end of that quiz,
it matches you to a specific mattress
that's perfect for your sleep needs.
For me, it matched me to the dusk, D-U-S-K
because I wanted a mattress
that wasn't too firm nor too soft
and I really love the mattress.
As I mentioned, I've been
sleeping terrifically well
ever since I got that mattress.
If you're interested in
upgrading your mattress
you can go to helixsleep.com/huberman,
take their two minutes sleep quiz
and they'll match you
to a customized mattress
and then you'll get up to
$200 off all mattresses
and you'll get two free pillows.
They have a 10 year warranty.
You get to try it out for a
hundred nights, risk-free,
if you don't like it, they'll
even pick it up for free,
take it away but I really think you will,
I certainly love mine.
Again, if you're interested,
you can go to helixsleep.com/huberman
for up to $200 off
and two free pillows.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Theragun.
Theragun is a handheld
percussive therapy device
that releases deep muscle tension.
I first learned about
Theragun on a lab expedition.
We're actually headed out to ocean
where we were doing diving
with great white sharks,
filming those for our VR fear
experiments in the laboratory
and it was very long days
of carrying Pelican cases,
those are cases these hard
plastic cases with equipment,
it was diving, we were all
sore and tired all the time.
And someone had brought along a Theragun.
It was the first time I had seen one
and pretty soon that thing
was getting passed along
and became one of the more
coveted devices on board.
Everyone wanted time with this
thing because it was great,
you could give yourself
a really terrific massage
and get deep into the
tissue and relieve soreness.
When I got back, I got a Theragun
and so I'm delighted that
they're sponsoring the podcast.
Whether or not you want
to treat your muscles
because they're tense from working out
or whether or not you just
want to release stress,
it's a terrific tool.
Many of you are familiar probably
with professional massages
but Theragun is
interesting because you can
basically give yourself
a deep tissue massage,
anytime, anywhere, it's also very quiet.
If you want to try Theragun,
you can try it for 30 days.
They start at only $199.
You can go to
theragun.com/huberman right now
and you can get your gen
fourth Theragun today,
that's the one that I use or
another one of their models.
That's Theragun.com/huberman
to try Theragun.
This episode marks the
beginning of a new topic
for the Huberman Lab Podcast.
As many of you already know,
we go deep into a
particular topic over four,
sometimes even five episodes.
We just closed out the
episodes on hormones.
Now we are going to talk
about how to optimize physical performance
and skill learning.
We're going to look deep
at the science behind this
as well as specific practices.
In fact, today, you're going
to hear about specific tools
that you can use to improve
endurance and strength by up to,
I'm not making this up,
three or four times your current capacity.
This is based on studies
that were done at Stanford
and are currently in use
by collegiate and professional teams.
If you're not a professional
athlete or a serious athlete,
that's okay.
The topics, this month
and all the information
we are going to cover
are going to make you
a better recreational exerciser as well.
If you're not an exerciser
and you're thinking
about getting into that
or if you live in the Northern hemisphere
and you're just thinking
about the beach this summer
or fat loss, muscle
building, that sort of thing,
this month we're going to
cover all of that as well.
There's so much confusion out there
about how to optimize fat
loss, muscle building,
improvements in flexibility, for instance,
or skill learning.
I know many of you, aren't so focused
on the cosmetic aspects
of physical exercise
but are interested in
actual skill learning,
we're going to talk about that too.
I want to just take a moment
to reflect on something
that came up last episode.
If you didn't see that episode,
that's quite all right.
But last episode, we were talking
about the hormones,
adrenaline, and cortisol
and how to leverage those
towards attention and learning
and there was a little bit of confusion
that I want to clarify.
I mentioned an optimal
protocol for learning
that involves leveraging
adrenaline also called epinephrin
and it involved four steps.
The four steps that I spelled out
were to be calm and focused
while one is trying to acquire
or learn the new skill,
cognitive skill or motor skill,
then to have a spike in adrenaline.
I mentioned ways to do that,
using cold or breathing or other tools,
immediately after the learning episode
then to incorporate what I
call non sleep deep rest,
a 20 minute episode of a shallow
nap or some other protocol
like NSDR, non sleep deep rest protocol
of which we always provide
links in the captions.
And then to try and optimize
sleep later that night
and the subsequent night.
Some of you heard this
and it sunk in right away
and it was straight forward.
Others said, wait, I thought
from a previous episode
even before that, you said you're supposed
to do non sleep deep rest
immediately after learning, no.
We added another step,
the logic still follows
that you want to be calm
and focused during learning,
then you want to spike
adrenaline at the end.
Most people get that backward,
they're drinking too much coffee
or even taking nootropics and things,
trying to be really
focused while learning.
Some people are taking
Adderall recreationally
something I don't recommend,
that's actually getting
the whole process backwards
if you look at the data in the physiology.
You want to spike adrenaline at the end
or immediately after a learning episode
and then non sleep deep rest
and then sleep itself, okay?
Four steps, hope that
clarifies things for you,
if you have any additional questions
please put them in the
comment section below.
Okay, so let's talk about
physical performance.
There are so many variables
to physical performance
and we can manage physical
performance and skill learning
from a variety of contexts.
I made just a short list
of some of the things
that come to mind that
can powerfully impact
physical performance and skill learning.
Some of them are what I
would consider foundational.
They allow you to show
up your current ability
and if you were to disrupt those,
you would perform less well.
So things like getting
a good night's sleep,
things like being properly hydrated,
things like being well nourished,
whatever that means to you.
I know some of you like
to exercise fasted,
some of you prefer to
have food in your stomach
or have eaten a couple hours before.
There are supplements, there are drugs,
there are different ways to breathe,
there are so many tools related
to mindset, visualization,
there are machines and devices,
it's just a vast space,
but it's not infinite.
And there are a few things
in the list of things
that can impact and even
optimize physical performance
and skill learning that
have an outsized effect
that any of you can use.
Many of them, most of them
are low to zero costs.
So today we are going to
focus on what I believe to be
one of the most powerful tools
to improve physical performance
and skill learning and recovery
and we'll talk about why that's important
and that's temperature.
Now many of you might think,
oh, well that's kind of boring,
I want to know about the
magic pill that I can take
that's going to allow
me to dunk a basketball
if I currently can't or I
want to know about the thing
that's going to let me
run further and faster
is going to shed fat.
Believe it or not, temperature
is the most powerful variable
for improving physical
performance and for recovery.
I would argue it's even
more important than sleep
because temperature itself
is going to dictate how well
and when you sleep and the
depth of your total recovery.
There are two aspects to
temperature of course,
there's heat and there's cold.
We are mainly going to focus on cold
as a way to buffer heat.
In a previous podcast episode,
I talked all about growth hormone.
You can find that episode about
fibroid and growth hormone
and how heat can be a powerful stimulus
for increasing growth hormone
which is involved in
tissue repair and et cetera
and burn fat and improve
metabolism in various ways.
However, cold I would argue
is even more powerful than heat as a tool
and I'm not just talking
about putting ice packs
on sore muscles or slightly
sprained limbs and ankles
and things of that sort.
We're going to talk about cold
from the standpoint of thermal physiology.
This is a literature that's
rich in scientific information
that goes back very deep
into the last century
where physiologists and
neuroscientists figured out
that there are different
compartments in your body
that heat and cool you differently
and that you can leverage
those in order to double
and as I mentioned before
even triple or quadruple your work output
both strength, repetitions, and endurance.
So this is not weak sauces that they say,
this is the stuff that can
really shift the needle quite a bit
and it's not just about well once,
it's about being able to
perform well and recover
from that performance so
that you do even better
when you're not incorporating these tools
on days where for instance,
you can't access cold
or an ice pack or an ice bath
or things of that sort, okay?
So we're going to cover cold,
we're going to talk a little bit
about the physiology of cold
and heat and how they work
because as you've probably
heard me say before
if you can understand some mechanism,
if you can just push yourself
through a little bit of new knowledge,
into understanding a
little bit of mechanism
about how you work, you'll
be in a far better position
to implement the tools in the
best and most flexible ways
for your needs.
This is why at the Huberman Lab Podcast,
I never ever do a just list of the things
that you should do.
I don't believe in that,
just tell me what to do.
First, I tell you why
you should do something.
What's the logical framework
that it's grounded in
and then we distill that
down to specific protocols.
For those of you that are
too impatient for that,
there are millions, if not billions
of other resources out
there that will take you
into the cul-de-sac of one
protocol that will work
and then stop working or might
work for you indefinitely,
that's not how we work here.
This is about really
understanding the mechanism
so that you can tweak
things and modify things,
adjust the timing and the dosage of things
and really get the most out
of these tools and protocols.
Everything I'm going to talk about
pertains to both endurance exercise
and strength and speed type exercise.
So sprints, weightlifting, endurance work
and to some extent, flexibility
but we're going to cover
flexibility in depth
as well as another feature
that's not often talked about
which is suppleness or
smoothness of movement
over different ranges of
movement in a subsequent episode.
Let's start by talking about temperature.
What is temperature?
How does temperature impact the body
and its ability to perform,
including learn new skills?
So everyone probably remembers,
or has at least heard of
the word homeostasis, right?
That the body wants to remain
in a particular range of temperatures,
that it doesn't like to
be too hot or too cold.
And I want to emphasize from the outset
that there are many mechanisms
that are installed into us
by way of our evolutionary
design and our genome
meaning we were just born
with this stuff ready
to keep our body temperature
in a particular narrow range.
Heating up too much is just plain bad.
It's not just bad for
physical performance,
it's bad for all tissue health.
If your brain heats up too
much, neurons start dying
and those neurons don't come back, okay?
You may have heard about neurogenesis,
the ability for the brain
to regenerate itself
or generate new neurons and adulthood,
there's very little neurogenesis
excuse me, in adulthood,
even after anytime after puberty really
and you don't want to lose neurons
in the central nervous system.
If you get too hot, that'll happen.
It's called hyperthermia, you
want to avoid hyperthermia
and you have many mechanisms
that are built into you to
avoid becoming hyperthermic.
The other thing that
happens when we get too warm
is that we have in all of our cells,
what are called enzymes.
You generally know if
something's an enzyme
because it ends in the
letters, A-S-E, right?
So lipase is an enzyme
that exists to digest fats.
You have proteases that are
there to digest proteins, right?
So anytime you see A-S-E
chances are it's an enzyme.
Enzymes are proteins, and they
have a particular structure
and their structure becomes
modified when heat increases
and that's not good.
You want their structure
to be of a particular type.
Imagine a car with four wheels,
let's just say the car is the enzyme.
If it gets too hot, it's like
two of the wheels fall off
and that thing can't function.
So one of the reasons
why the body and nature
goes through so much effort
to build in mechanisms
to make sure that we don't become too warm
is because when we get to warm,
these enzymes don't function,
cells stop functioning,
they stop being able to generate energy,
they stop being able to digest things,
you stop being able to think
and eventually those cells
start dying off entirely.
So keeping temperature in a
particular range is really good,
you don't want to get too hot.
We have much more flexibility
in terms of getting cold.
Now you don't want to
become hypothermic either.
You can die from hypothermia
just like you can die from hyperthermia.
However that you have a
lot more range to be cold
than you do to be too warm, okay?
And in general, the idea is
to keep the body and brain
in a particular range but
anytime we do anything,
our body temperature can shift.
So for instance, if you were
to stand next to a campfire
or you were outside on a hot day,
various things would happen
to dump heat from your body.
If you were outside on a cold day
or you were to get into a
cold shower or a cold lake,
various things would happen
to insulate heat within your body.
This is all pretty straightforward
and obvious I realize.
Now, what are those things?
Well, there are a huge category of them.
When you get into cold water,
you secrete adrenaline.
On a hot day, if it's really
hot or in a very hot sauna
or in the hot desert,
you will generate what are
called heat shock proteins
which will set off other sets of cascades,
metabolic cascades, biological cascades.
But the simplest way to think
about this process is that
when we get cold, we
tend to vasoconstrict.
Our blood vessels tend to constrict
and we tend to push energy
toward the core of our body
to preserve our core organs, okay?
So our periphery, our hands
and our feet and our toes
and our legs become colder
and our core therefore can
maintain blood to that area
and we are insulating our core.
Conversely, when we heat up
our blood vessels vasodilate,
they expand a bit and more
blood flows to our periphery
and more blood can move
throughout the body generally
and we will perspire, we will
sweat, water will actually
get pulled out of the
blood to some extent,
moved up through sweat glands
and will be brought to the skin surface
so that it can be dumped,
we are dumping heat.
Animals, as you know vary
in their capacity to sweat.
Some animals like camels
won't start sweating at first
if they heat up, what
they'll do is they'll spit,
they'll dump heat by spitting, okay?
Dogs pant, Castilla is
off to my left here,
he pants when he gets
too warm, he can't sweat
or dogs can maybe sweat a little bit.
But we can sweat and
you've probably noticed
that on a humid hot day,
you'll feel much warmer
just walking or running than you would
with the equivalent exercise or movement
than you would on a cold day.
And some of you probably
know this, but if you don't
the reason is you sweat on a cold day,
but because the air is dry typically,
you will bring that sweat to the surface
and provided you're wearing clothes
that allow some air to get
out away from the body,
so you're not wearing,
you know, really tight,
you know spandex type clothing
or something like that,
or, you know seal type
saran wrap type clothing
that sweat will evaporate
off into the dry atmosphere.
Whereas on a humid day,
the reason you see people
in New York and Florida
on a humid summer day
and they're like moving
their shirts off themselves
and you see people with, you know
big sweat stains and back sweat stains
and all this kind of stuff
is because they're sweating
as they normally would, but it's humid
and so there is the humidity,
the air doesn't allow transfer
of that sweat into the
atmosphere as readily
and so you're hot, okay?
So without the evaporation,
you're going to be warmer.
So we evaporate off sweat, we sweat
and we vasodilate when
we want to dump heat.
When we want to maintain
heat, we vasoconstrict
and we tend to not sweat.
The other thing that happens
is you'll get goosebumps.
So-called goose pimples
they're sometimes called.
Those are a throwback to the time
where we had fur over
most, not all of our body.
All mammals in the cold have a process
whereby adrenaline is
released at low levels
typically into the body,
that adrenaline activates
what are called sympathetic fibers,
they have nothing to do with sympathy,
those little fibers, which are neurons,
those fibers that what I'm
saying are fibers are neurons,
not clothing fibers,
reach up into the skin
so your whole body is covered
with these little tiny neurons
that reach up into the
skin and when we are cold,
they actually mechanically
take the hair follicle
and bend it up, it's a
process called pilo erection,
P-I-L-O erection, okay?
So on a hot day, you
want to dump heat, okay?
So on a hot day, what would happen is
you'd actually not see those goose pimples
because you want the hairs lying down
which actually you would think
that might insulate you more
but we'll actually let
more heat dissipate out
through the skin.
On a cold day, you get these
goose pimples or goosebumps
which are really just
an ancient carry over
from the body's attempt to
make hair stand up on end.
And when hair step stand up on end
and they're very close together
that traps air in between
them and actually creates
a sort of insulated blanket of warm air.
If you've ever seen an animal
like a a Malamute or a Husky,
you might think, oh that
poor thing on a hot day,
what does it do?
You know, with all that hair?
Well, it can be warm so the
animal will typically pant
and its hair will lay down,
which you might think would act
as more of a blanket, but on a cold day
what'll happen is they'll
become very puffy.
Their hair will stand up on end
and that's actually trapping
heat between the hairs
and they're actually quite well insulated.
So it's very important that
if you want to understand
how you can leverage temperature
for physical performance,
you have to understand
that you have vasoconstriction
to conserve heat,
vasodilation to dump heat,
that you are sweating to dump heat,
and you have conservation of fluids
in order to preserve heat.
That's the most important thing
in terms of understanding the mechanisms
of maintaining and dumping heat.
And now the most important
thing to understand is that
if you get too hot, not only
do those enzymes stop working
but your ability to contract
your muscles stops, okay?
I'm going to repeat this
because it's vitally important.
ATP is involved in the process
of generating muscle contractions,
it doesn't matter if
you're running a marathon,
doesn't matter if you're
doing a yoga class,
going for a 700 pound squat,
the range of temperatures
within which ATP can function
and muscles can contract is very narrow.
Somewhere around 39 or 40
degrees Celsius, it drops off
and you will not be able to
generate more contractions.
Now that's pretty hot,
but that temperature
can be generated locally really fast.
Now, if you're too cold,
it's true it's hard to
generate muscle contractions.
I got into doing some cold water
swimming a little while ago
and we would joke that, you
know, you come out of the water,
we do no wetsuits,
I'm not recommending
people do this necessarily
unless you're with certainly
with somebody else who's skilled
at doing it, which I was.
And you come out
and you feel like you
have claws for hands.
You can, you know, you
could never text on a phone
for the first few minutes,
I mean, the water was very, very cold
and you can't even move your face
and so muscles will become rigid
but heating up muscles causes
them to fail to be able
to generate more contractions.
Put simply if you get too
hot, you stop exercising.
You may not even realize it
but your will to exercise further,
your ability to push harder
is entirely dependent on
the heat of the muscle
both locally and your whole system.
So let's talk about your whole system
because I just described heat
dumping and heat maintaining.
I told you that increasing heat
makes it hard for muscles to contract.
It will stop you from being
able to run further and faster,
it will stop you from being
able to lift more weights,
more sets, more repetitions.
If you can keep temperature
in range however,
in a proper range, you will
be able to do more work,
you will be able to create greater output,
you'll be able to lift more
weight, more sets, more reps
and you'll be able to run further.
Now, there are data that I'm going to talk
about in a little bit that
are absolutely striking
that underscore that statement.
There are data from my
colleague Craig Heller's lab
in the department of biology at Stanford
and there are data that
are now being implemented.
They were first implemented
in a grant funded by DARPA
but now in professional sports teams.
Many, if not all the NFL teams
are now using this technology
as well as military uses it
and not just for sports
performance, but also firefighters,
construction workers, other professions
where elevated heat becomes
a barrier to performance
and you can leverage this to
really improve your workouts.
And when I say really
improve, it is striking.
I'm going to give away a
little hint of this now
and then I'm going to
tell you a little bit more
of the data later after
I tell you the protocols.
Proper cooling of the body,
which has to be done
in a very specific way,
has allowed recreational athletes,
college students and typical adults
as well as professional athletes
to go from doing their usual output.
In this case what comes to mind best
would be a particular
professional athletes
that a member of the 49ers at the time
was able to do 40 dips on
his first set, 30, 20, 20,
basically to 10 sets of dips
unassisted with anything else.
That's an impressive
especially since he's a really large guy,
40 dips is as a respectable,
these are strict, full, full range dips.
And then by the 10th set,
there's a steep drop-off.
Using proper cooling of
particular body compartments,
he was able to triple that
within less than a week
and maintain that performance
even without the cooling approach.
So it was actually a
conditioning effect, all right?
I'll get back to this in a little bit
but there are other
fantastic leaps of effort
and leaps of performance
that were demonstrated
including endurance running.
Before I continue any, I
just want to underscore again
that overheating is terrible.
There's a famous example of this.
This was about 10, 15 years ago
when a number of dietary supplements
that included things like
epinephrin which is a stimulant,
it's a beta adrenergic stimulant,
drugs like Clenbuterol,
which were then banned from the Olympics,
which are still out there
have been in recreational use
which were beta adrenergic
agonist so these are drugs
that sort of mimic epinephrin
adrenaline to some extent,
I know I'm oversimplifying this here.
They improve flat loss because
of the effects on metabolism
but they heat up the body.
And what happened was, this
hit the press very widely
is high school football players
and various professional
athletes were dropping dead
because they were overheating
during practice or in competition.
So much so that Clenbuterol was banned.
Although every once in a while,
somebody gets in trouble for using this,
there was an incidence of this recently
in professional boxing which
was attributed to a bad meat
that had contained the Clenbuterol.
I don't know what the source was,
I don't have any commentary about that,
but it still is in use,
but these drugs increased
body temperature,
increased fat loss, but
carry is severe danger
and that's the danger of hyperthermia.
In fact, I would argue and I
think in talking to some folks
at in various professional
fighting organizations
it's very clear that a lot
of the deaths that one sees
in professional combat
sports may have to do
as much with dehydration and overheating
as it does with getting hit in
the head, which is also bad,
but that things can compound
that can have a synergistic effect.
And just a note about
that and hyperthermia
and it's dangerous as well.
My first project ever in science
was to evaluate the thermogenic
effects of MDMA or ecstasy.
That was my senior thesis
in college actually.
And what we found was that indeed drugs
that remove your understanding
of how warm you are
cause you to not take on
the appropriate behaviors
to cool yourself, right?
So your vasoconstriction
and you're sweating,
those are autonomic,
those are going to happen no matter what
unless you happen to take
something that blocks that effect.
However, there are a lot of things
that we as humans do to prevent
ourselves from overheating
and the main one is stop.
When we are running in the desert
or when we're running very
hard and suddenly we stop,
oftentimes that's because
the muscles are overheating,
it's a subconscious thing.
We won't often think, oh,
I'm really much too warm,
it's just that we stop
and it's a self-preservation mechanisms.
Sometimes it kicks into early,
sometimes it kicks into late.
Kicks in too late, you can die.
There's an instance in the 1984 Olympics
where there was the first year I believe
that there was a women's marathon,
I think that's correct.
And one of the front runners
or top picks for winning
was heading into the stadium
and all of a sudden, it
seemed as if she was lost,
she was kind of wandering around
not knowing where she should go
and in fact, she was in a position to win
or at least take second
place, at least take silver,
got totally disoriented and
did miserably in the race
and she was hyperthermic,
she was running against
that reflex to stop.
So dumping heat is key.
So how do you dump heat in
order to perform longer safely?
Well, in order to understand
that you have to understand
that the body has three main compartments
for regulating temperature, okay?
We don't just have a
center and a periphery,
we have three main compartments
and there's one compartment in particular
that all of you or most all
of you, I have to assume have
and if you can understand how that works,
you can do tremendous
things for your performance
and for your recovery.
So what I'm about to tell you
will allow you to perform
better in all forms of exercise
and it is not commonly known,
unfortunately, I'm here
to try and change that.
You have three compartments
for increasing or dumping
heat in your body.
One is your core, we
already talked about that.
Your core organs, your heart,
your lungs, your pancreas, your liver,
this is the core of your body.
The other is your periphery,
which are obviously your arms
and your legs and your
feet and your hands.
But then there's a third component
which has their three
locations on your body
that are far better at
passing heat out of the body
and bringing cool into the body
such that you can heat up
or cool your body everywhere very quickly.
Those three areas are your
face, the palms of your hands
and the bottoms of your feet.
Now, the skin on your hands
and on the bottoms of your feet
and to some extent on your
face are called glaborous skin.
That's G-L-A-B-O-R-O-U-S glaborous skin.
And what's special about
those areas of your body
and the glaborous skin
is that the arrangement
of vasculature, of blood
vessels, capillaries and arteries
that serve those regions is very different
than it is elsewhere in your body.
Now, this has ancient roots.
Typically, if you were
another mammal, like a bear
or some sort of ape, you would
have hair all over your body.
Now we all know some pretty hairy people.
I presume you've heard that
there are these hairy people,
I know a few excessively hairy people
and Castilla is excessively hairy
but he's not a person obviously
but all mammals have hair
on their bodies, too.
Some people have very light
hair or very fine hair.
We don't have hair on these
glaborous skin regions.
Now, of course you can have
beard or facial hair growth
but there are still
regions like the cheeks
and other areas that maintain
this special vasculature.
Okay, so technically the hands and feet
are real glaborous skin
and the face is not always
quite classified as glaborous
but these three locations
face, palms of hands
not tops and bottoms of feet
are very good at dumping heat
and bringing in cool.
And the reason is there's
a rule in vascular biology
that blood moves from
arteries to capillaries
and then to veins, and then
back to the heart, okay?
So arteries which are
the big ones obviously,
capillaries which are the little fine ones
where oxygen and carbon
dioxide are exchanged
and veins which then bring
blood back to the heart
and other tissues of course.
In these three regions
of your hands, your face
and the bottoms of your feet,
we have what are called AVAs.
AVAs are a very special
pattern of vasculature.
AVAs are described in
the medical textbooks.
You can find them in Grey's anatomy
not the television show
but the actual Grey's anatomy textbook
which is a real thing that exists
and in all medical textbooks, okay?
So let's talk about AVAs and what they are
and why they allow these
three regions of the body
to heat or cool ourselves more readily.
So what are AVAs?
AVAs are arterio-venous anastomosis.
So if you want to look that up
you can just look up
AVAs veins, capillaries,
arteries if you like, but
I'll spell it for you.
A-R-T-E-R-I-O, arterio
venous, V-E-N-O-U-S,
arterio-venous anastomosis,
A-N-A-S-T-O-M-O-S-E-S.
Arterio-venous anastomosis, okay?
You want to know about
Arterio-venous anastomosis, trust me
and you want to remember
that they are in your hands,
the bottoms of your feet and on your face,
and in particular on
the palms of your hands,
not the tops of your hands.
Now, before I said blood flows typically
from arteries to capillaries, to veins,
and then back to the heart.
But AVAs are direct connections
between the small arteries
and the small veins.
They bypass the
capillaries to some extent.
They are little short vessel segments,
they have a big, large inner diameter
and they have this very
thick, muscular wall.
And they get input from what
are called adrenergic neurons.
They get input from neurons
that release norepinephrine
and epinephrine,
which allows them to contract or dilate.
Now there's some rules of physics
that talk about how the radius of a pipe
and small changes in the radius of a pipe
leads to massive increases in
the rate and amount of stuff
that can flow through that pipe, okay?
There's a rule of physics
that says essentially
that the radius is proportional
to the amount of stuff
that can flow through
something to the fourth power.
We're not going to make
this a physics class,
but if you want to look that up, you can,
you can just look up how
does the radius of a tube
or pipe relate to how quickly
or how much stuff can flow through it?
What you need to know,
even if you don't want to know
any of the underlying physics
is that these AVAs allow more heat
to leave the body more quickly
and more cool to enter
the body more quickly
than other venous arterial capillary beds
throughout the body.
In other words, you can heat
up best at the face, the palms
and the bottoms of the feet,
and you can cool down best
at the face, the palms and
the bottoms of the feet
than you can anywhere else on your body.
And when I say heat up or cool down,
I mean actually heat or cool
the core end your brain.
Okay, so this is vitally important.
I realize we're getting down
into the mechanistic weeds
here, but you need to know
that these three
compartments of your body,
palms, bottoms of feet and face
are your best leverage points
for manipulating temperature
to vastly improve physical
performance, okay?
I also want to point out
that the work that I'm
going to tell you about
is not work from my laboratory.
It's the work of, as I mentioned,
my colleague Craig Heller's
laboratory at Stanford
and we're going to have
Craig on as a guest
to talk more about these discoveries,
they are his and his
colleagues discoveries
and how you can leverage them.
They're building out
some amazing technology.
I had a conversation with Craig yesterday
as a prelude to this episode
and to the future conversation with him
so you're getting the
very latest on this topic.
So what Craig and his colleagues did
really illustrates perfectly
what these body surfaces can do and why.
They were studying overheating
in athletes and in military
and in construction workers
and trying to prevent it.
And they did a bunch of experiments,
I won't go into all of them now
but what they essentially found
was that cooling the palms,
palmer cooling allowed people, athletes,
and recreational athletes
to run much further,
to lift more weight and
to do more sets and reps
to a absolutely staggering degree.
Let's talk for a second, a
bit more about why we stop,
why we shut off effort when we get too hot
because in doing so,
you'll really understand
how and why the best protocols exist
for being able to do more work,
to be able to exercise longer
and actually to feel good doing it.
You actually can make
a doubling of your dips
or believe it or not a
tripling or quadrupling or more
of your pull-ups fairly straightforward.
I mentioned before that
when muscle heats up,
enzymes start getting disrupted
and ATP and muscles can't work so well
and those muscles can't contract.
Let's get a little more
specific about that.
The enzyme that's involved here
is something called pyruvate kinase.
You don't need to know
about pyruvate kinase
but what you do need to
know is that it ends A-S-E
which means it's an
enzyme and pyruvate kinase
is essentially a rate limiting step.
It's a critical step that you can't bypass
if you want muscles to contract
and it's very temperature sensitive.
Therefore, if you can
keep temperature lower,
you can do more work per unit time,
you can do more pull-ups
and that actually was done by Craig
and his colleagues, excuse me.
The pull-ups weren't
actually done by Craig,
I don't know how many
pull-ups Craig can do,
I'll ask him next time,
both cooled and uncooled,
how many pullups he can do.
But what they essentially did
is they brought someone
into their laboratory
who could do 10 pull ups on the first set
and they were able to get 10,
rest two or three minutes get another 10,
rest or three minutes and
if you've ever tried this,
what you find is that you start dropping
to eight, seven, six, et cetera.
Now, the person might not necessarily feel
like they're overheating,
but the muscle is heating up.
Then with their knowledge that these AVAs,
that these that these portals
in the palms are a great way
to both heat the body, but also
to dump heat from the body,
they used the device
and I'll talk about
what you can do at home
but a device where they had people hold on
to what was essentially a cold tube.
Now this is crucial, the
tube can't be so cold
that it causes vasoconstriction
because then the cold
won't pass from the tube
to the hand and to the core.
But if it's the right temperature,
it's neither too hot nor too cold,
that cool from the cold
tube passes into the hand,
these so-called palmer regions
and then cools the core
and in theory by lowering body temperature
would allow the person or
the athlete to do more work
and indeed that's what they saw.
The actual data, the specific data showed
that subjects could do,
at least the subjects they worked with,
on their first day with no
cooling about a hundred pull-ups
across the timeframe that they had, okay?
So it might've taken
anywhere from 10 to 15
or maybe more sets depending
on how skilled that person was
but in a fixed amount of time.
Then they came back and did the cooling.
They did it the very next day
which if you've ever trained a muscle,
the very next day typically
you wouldn't do as well in its training
if it took any damage
from the previous session
or you at least do as well,
but you probably wouldn't
do what they then observed,
which was, they started
after every other set,
the person would just hold the cold tube,
cool down the body after every other set,
rest everything else was kept the same
and they found that they
went to 180 pull-ups,
which is incredible, it's a near doubling.
And by doing this repeatedly
over several sessions,
over several weeks, they quickly
went in the cooling group
from a maximum of somewhere
between 180 and 200 as I recall,
I'm sort of estimating now,
to 600 pull-ups in the
equivalent amount of time
which is absolutely incredible.
They then repeated this in
a study on the bench press
and actually the bench press
study was pretty interesting
because they actually had a control group
that was admittedly
taking specific amounts
of anabolic steroids,
the antibiotic steroid
was testosterone cypionate
which is essentially testosterone,
and indeed the testosterone cypionate,
the steroid group improved at
a rate of about 1% per week.
There were differences
and the cooling group
basically left all other
groups in the dust,
it was just remarkable.
So cooling the core, I
want to be very clear
that it's not cooling the muscle,
wasn't about cooling the chest alone
or just cooling the palms,
it was about allowing cold
to pass through the palms
because of the unique vasculature
that's there, these AVAs
allowed the subjects to do
far more work per unit time.
And the important thing is that
if they were to come back
after doing 600 pull-ups
or 500 pull-ups, you might say,
well, wow that's going
to create a situation
where recovery is going to
be absolutely impossible.
They could come back, not use the cooling
and they still saw a
highly significant increase
in the amount or the
number of pull-ups or dips
or bench press weight
that they could do, okay?
So what that meant is that
it was both an excellent performance
and an excellent training stimulus
that they were able to recover from, okay?
I don't know if all of
you are following this
but these are the sorts of increases
in exercise output that
are absolutely staggering
and that's why professional
teams and the military
and others capitalized on them
very quickly and use these.
Okay, now you may be asking
what about endurance, right?
Not everyone wants to be
able to bench press a lot
for multiple reps and sets.
And I should just mention
for the bench pressing,
it was, I believe they were
they found people that
could bench press two 25,
so that's two 45 pound plates
on the 45 pound standard Olympic bar
for repetitions of anywhere from six to 10
and then they had them do the same thing.
They did a set, they'd
rest two or three minutes,
sometimes up to four minutes,
then do another set,
repeat, repeat, repeat,
and with cooling, they were able
to increase the amount of work,
the number of reps with the same weight.
Sometimes they did have to increase sets
to approximately double,
so it was pretty fantastic.
So with endurance, similar
increases have been shown
and the way that they do those tests
are a little bit different
and they also point to a
really important mechanism
of why we stopped doing work at all
when we perceive that we are
putting in too much effort.
So it gets right to the
heart of the relationship
between temperature in
muscle and your willpower,
those are directly related.
Your body heat and your willpower
are linked in a physiological way.
So I'm not talking about the kind of stuff
that you see as kind of like
clickbait on the internet,
or like increase willpower
now or become resilient now,
or never do this again if you
want to be mentally strong,
I'm talking about a
physiological mechanism
that exists in the body and
brain that causes you to stop
or that will allow you to
continue to go harder and further
than you normally would.
Okay, so let's talk
about willpower and heat
and how heat shuts you down.
In other words, if you are cool,
if your body temperature
is in a particular range,
not only can you go further,
but you will go further if you want to.
Said differently, if you heat up too much,
you will stop or you will die.
Typically people stop, there
are individuals who will push
to the point where they black out and die,
in the same way that, and
please don't do this experiment,
there are people who can
sit down face to face
and say, let's hold our breath
and whoever breathes first loses.
Some people will just
go until it's painful
and then they'll gasp
and take a big breath.
There are always those individuals
who can override that reflex
and they will go until
they pass out, okay?
And if you do that in water,
you can very easily die,
so please don't do that experiment.
But there's a reflex that
relates the body to the brain
and the brain to the body
that shuts off our effort
when we get too hot.
So what Craig and his colleagues
and now others have done
is to do a test in the laboratory
where rather than ask
people to run outside
until they absolutely
don't want to run anymore,
you put them on a treadmill
and you set the speed, okay?
So they have to keep up with the treadmill
and at some point they quit.
And you take groups and you do those
in different temperature environments.
So some people are running
in a nice chilly laboratory,
they get their heart rate up.
So maybe their heart rate goes from,
you know, 40 or 50 baseline heart rate,
maybe it gets up to 80 or a hundred
and then they keep the rate of
the treadmill going the same
and they'll just plateau.
So they're getting into a
steady state cadence or rhythm
and their heart is beating it
more or less a steady state.
Eventually they'll probably stop
'cause they have something else to do
but people will continue
at that temperature
and at that heart rate,
unless you start turning up
the temperature in the room
and at some point they will stop
and they'll stop much
earlier when it gets hot
because of something
called cardiac drift, okay?
So let's say I'm running
and I'm running at a steady
cadence on this treadmill
and my heart rate is 85 beats per minute
or a hundred beats per
minute, doesn't matter,
let's say a hundred just
for sake of example.
Well, just making the room hotter
is going to increase
my heart rate further,
even though I'm at the same output
and the brain does a computation,
it somehow figures out that
there's a heat component
that's increasing heart rate
and there's an effort
component from running
that's driving heart rate.
And if the heat component
and the heart rate output
from the effort, get to hit
a certain threshold, I stop.
Okay, ad some of you may think,
well there are people who just run
and run and run and never stop,
eventually everyone stops.
Maybe it's because of the race ended,
maybe it's because, you
know, everyone else quit.
I actually saw some stuff online,
there are these races where people
just will continuously do the same loop
until everyone else drops out
and then one guy or girl
keeps going past everybody.
But typically it stops
because the race is over
or because people quit.
Increasing temperature
increases the rate of quitting
in part, not entirely, but in part
because of this thing called cardiac drift
which you've probably experienced
if you've been out on a hot
day and you're walking uphill
you might stop to take a breath.
If you sit in a sauna, your
heart rate will increase.
Heat increases heart rate,
effort increases heart rate.
At a steady effort, you'll
have a steady heart rate.
If you increase the
heat in the environment
that you're engaging in
that steady heart rate,
your heart rate will now
go up due to cardiac drift
and you will quit, okay?
So Heller and colleagues
have done experiments
where they do palmer cooling
under these environments.
And that's wonderful because
not only does it enable people
to go further and faster for much longer
that's been shown statistically
significant every time
but it also protects the brain and body
against hyperthermia,
overheating, coma, nerve injury,
nerve death, and actual death, okay?
So you can see why this
is such a valuable tool.
So what are they doing?
Well, in this case too they're
having them cool their hands
and they're cooling the palms.
Cooling the bottoms of the
feet is a little trickier
but cooling the face could
actually work as well.
And we're going to talk
about cooling the face
and how to incorporate this.
So at this point, I've just really wanted
to impress upon you not impress
you, but impress upon you
the fact that you have these
three surfaces of your body
that are very good at
passing cold into the body,
such that it cools the
core body temperature
and that's a good thing
for health and safety
and in order to maintain work output
over longer periods of time,
or actually just do more work.
I mean to me the result
is just so staggering
is the hundred to 180
pull-ups in the controls
and then 600 pull-ups in the
cooled individuals, right?
They actually also feel mentally
as if they can do more work.
It's not just that they can,
their willpower is adjusted somehow
by these shifts in temperature.
Now, before we continue
and get to the exact ways
that any number of us can
start to use this information,
I want to talk about the
opposite thing, which is heating.
And you have to remember
that these surfaces,
the palms and the bottoms
of the feet and the face
will not just a range with these AVAs,
these special ways to pass
blood from arteries to veins
in order to cool us for
better athletic performance
or to heat us for on cold days
but for both of those things.
Now Heller and colleagues
and others have also explored
how these can be used to heat up the core.
There are times when we
want to heat up our core.
Typically we hear that most of the heat
escapes through our heads,
so we'll put on a hat when we go outside,
that's actually not true.
Most of your heat escapes
through your face,
the palms of your hands and
the bottoms of your feet.
Now you should know why that's the case.
What this means is that
for post-surgery patients
or for people that are hypothermic,
indeed you want to heat the core, right?
But actually I was on a swim recently
where a friend became hypothermic.
He was kind of slurring his words
and kind of staggering around
when we got him back on the beach,
we brought him over to
the lifeguard station,
he turned out to be fine.
Again, this is why cold water swims
are something that you
really need to do in groups,
not alone and you really have
to know what you're doing.
There were reasons for why
this happened that day,
but, you know we were basically
people thought we were a little strange
until they realized what was happening.
We were walking down the beach
basically sandwiching him
between at our chest
because we were still warmer
than the ambient environment,
the environment around us.
And we were pushing our chest against him
to try and warm him up
to warm up his core.
In retrospect, that was
the wrong thing to do.
In talking with Craig and
talking to other colleagues
that work on thermogenesis.
What we should have done was warm,
hit the palms of his hands,
the bottoms of his feet
and his face because that
would insulate the heat loss.
Now he was very cold
so presumably there was vasoconstriction
of the veins at these locations.
And so it's not clear
that that would have been
the only strategy to use
but they have explored how to
heat up post-surgery patients
and one of the best ways to do that
is to get warm socks on
the bottoms of the feet,
get gloves on the hands
and if it can be done
safely to warm the face.
Now, of course you don't
want to obstruct respiration
and things of that sort.
But again the ability to
pass heat into the body
or to remove heat to the body
is best done through these three surfaces.
I can't emphasize that enough.
So I mentioned before that
you want to cool the palms
or the bottoms of the feet
although that's a little
harder to do or the face
but not so much that the
blood vessels constrict
because then you won't be able
to pass cool into the body
because those pipes got smaller
and therefore you can't
pass cool into the body.
So how can you start to incorporate this?
Well, Craig and colleagues have a company
that they've spun out through Stanford.
We'll talk about that when
we sit down with Craig
that has made engineered devices
that are optimal for this
that are going to keep
those passages open,
keep the size of the, those
veins correct to pass cool
into the body quickly for sake
of elite sports performance
and even recreational sports performance
but you can actually
start to incorporate this.
First of all, I always get asked
how cold should the water be?
Should it be ice water?
Should it be very cold water?
The answer is no.
If you want to experience
some of this effect
without a device, one thing you could do
would be for instance to do, I dunno,
I'll use the, the, the gym or
the treadmill as an example.
You could do your maximum
number of pull-ups, stop
and then you could actually
put your hands into
or on the surface of a sink
that is presumably stopped up
with cool water.
So not ice water, not
freezing cold, but cool water,
slightly cooler than body temperature
before you started training
would be a good place to start.
You do that for 10 to 30 seconds.
Then you could go back
and do your next set.
You would repeat the cooling,
you would want to extend the
amount of cooling somewhat
so you might want to do that
for 30 seconds to a minute.
This is not going to be perfect,
you're going to have to play
with how cold to make it
in order to get the optimal effect
but you ought to see
an effect nonetheless.
The same is true if you're
running and you're fatiguing,
obviously you don't want
to become hyperthermic,
cooling the hands or the
bottoms of your feet or the face
would be the ideal way to dump heat
in order to be able to
generate more output.
Now, the face is something
that we haven't talked a lot about.
Everything I've told you
up until now also says
that if you are somebody
who tends to get cold
when you are outside, say in
the winter or even in the fall,
you tend to run cold, warming your face
is going to be the most important thing
that you can do.
Now, it's kind of hard to do
that without looking strange
like wearing a ski mask
or something like that
but that is going to be more effective
than covering and warming
any other part of your body
although it'd be quite strange
if you only had a ski mask on
and you weren't wearing clothes
anywhere else on your body,
I don't recommend doing that outside,
that will get you into all
sorts of other kinds of trouble.
That wouldn't be good for anybody.
But now you understand the
principle and the locations
at which to deliver heat and cold.
So let's say that you are out for a run
and you want to incorporate
this cooling mechanism,
I talked to Craig about this,
I said, what would be the
kind of poor person's approach
to this before this devices
commercially available?
And he said, well, you, you
could take a frozen juice can,
if you have one of those
or a very cold can of soda
and you would want to
pass it back and forth
between your two hands.
The reason the passing back
and forth is really important
is because you, again you
don't want it to be so cold
that you constrict those veins portals
that it will allow cold
to go into the body.
Now, there are certainly people
that are working on bike handles,
and that can actually cool the hands.
You can expect with
the Olympics coming up,
people are aware of these data
and are starting to incorporate
it into a number of things.
Here's what you don't want to
do and there are sports teams
that I won't mention by name or brand
that have made this mistake
and it costs them dearly.
You don't want to cool the core
if you want to cool the body, right?
If it's very hot day and
you're going to train,
getting into an ice bath first,
sure it will cool you down,
but it's not going to be as
effective as cooling the palms,
the bottoms of the feet and the face.
I have a friend who does some
important work in this space
with people in various,
let's just say cultures
where heat is generated quite a lot
and they need to dump heat,
ice packs delivered to the face
are something that they actually use
in order to dump heat quickly.
Now, again, you don't want
to keep the ice pack on your face.
These are people that are
very high work output, right?
Firefighters and similar,
at very high work output
and then they'll put this essentially,
it's like a cool face mask on their face.
It allow their core body
temperature come down
and then they remove it,
they're not keeping it on there so long
that they're getting the
vasoconstriction, okay?
So there are a number of
ways that you could do this.
And again, I'm not giving
specific temperatures
because it depends on how hot that day
and how hot your body temperature is.
So you can see why there's a
need to create more devices
for this, but you can see
a considerable improvement
in endurance, in strength
and in all kinds of explosive
and sort of, you know,
explosive power type output
in athletics by using
these surfaces of the hands
and bottoms of the feet and face.
The one that I've tried
because in anticipation of
this episode was the dips
where then I would cool my hands,
I actually decided to cool the
bottoms of my feet as well,
because it just feels good
and it's particularly hot out lately,
so no shoes or socks on,
put my feet into the bottoms of my feet
just kind of hovering
about a centimeter or two
below the surface of a bucket of water
that was just slightly, it felt cool,
slightly cooler than
body temperature or so.
It just basically what
came out of the spigot
after I let it run for a little bit.
And indeed I saw a 60% increase
in the number of dips I
can do in a single session.
So it's actually a
quite significant effect
and you don't have to be perfectly precise
in order to do it.
And of course, if you want to
heat up for whatever reason,
like you're camping or you're
lost in the environment,
remember these three surfaces
are going to be the best
way to heat your as well.
So up until now, we've been
talking about how to use cold
during a workout in order
to improve performance
and indeed cold applied
to the appropriate parts of
the body, the appropriate times
can vastly improve our performance
and endurance and strength.
Now, I want to talk about
the use of temperature
in particular cold to improve the speed
and the depth of recovery.
Recovery is obviously vital, right?
During a weight training session
or during an endurance session,
that's just the stimulus for
getting better the next time
and if you don't recover, you
not only won't get better,
but you'll get worse.
There's a lot of interest
in the use of cold
in order to improve
recovery in the short term.
We see this and probably
the best example of this
would be fighters in combat sports
between rounds or athletes during
in between quarters or halftime,
that's one form of recovery.
The ability to go back
into the sport very soon
on an order of minutes,
anywhere from like one minute
in between rounds and
typical combat sports
or several minutes and
a half time, et cetera.
Typically what we see is
people cooling their core,
cooling the back of their neck,
cooling the top of their heads.
So it might be, you know,
a sponge with cold water
over the top of the head
or an ice pack on the back of the neck,
or in some cases even
wearing cold ice vests,
that's actually been done.
That's going to be a very inefficient way
to improve recovery of that kind.
Far better would be to cool the face,
the palms of the hands
or the bottoms the feet
for the reasons that I
described up until now.
Submerging the body in an ice
bath, or taking a cold shower,
say up to the neck or up to the chest
or getting under cold water
or jumping in a cold lake
or something of that sort,
or in the locker room,
getting under the cold shower
also would be a terrible way
to cool off the body quickly
compared to the ways that I described
through the palms of the
hands, the bottoms of the feet
or the face for the following reason.
First of all, it's not optimizing
those portals of the face,
palms the hands and the feet
and in addition, if it's
very cold and you submerge
or you cover a lot of
the body with that cold,
you're going to cause constriction
of the very vessels and pathways
that allow the body to
efficiently dump heat.
So again, the key thing
is to cool these one
or two or three of these surfaces
but not so cold that you
cause the vasoconstriction.
So what does this mean for you?
It means that getting in an
ice bath or a cold shower
or putting an ice pack
on the back of your neck
in most cases is not going to be as good
as splashing cold water on your face
or even just holding your
face in a damp cool cloth
or something of that sort.
It seems kind of counterintuitive,
you think, oh if I just
jump into an ice bath,
I'm going to cool down much faster
than if I just cooled these,
you know one or two or three
of these select regions of the body
but that's actually not the case.
And then of course
there's recovery that occurs
from session to session.
So outside of the game or the
match or the exercise session
and many people are now relying
on things like cryotherapy
which requires a lot
of expensive equipment,
big, you know liquid
nitrogen driven machine.
Those aren't so common for most people
or accessible for most
people, but a lot of people
are using cold baths or
ice baths or cold showers.
And again, that's not
going to optimize recovery.
In fact, it's going to
have an additional effect
that is going to potentially
block the training stimulus.
When you get into an ice
bath indeed, there are,
provided it's not very, very cold,
if you get into a cold shower,
provided is not very, very cold,
you are indeed blocking
some of the inflammation
that occurs because of
the training session.
But in doing so you also
are blocking pathways,
such as mTOR, mammalian
target of rapamycin,
which are involved in the adaptation
for a muscle to become stronger or bigger.
Put simply, covering the body in cold
or immersing the body
in cold after training
can short circuit or
prevent the hypertrophy
or muscle growth response.
It has other effects that
can be positive, right?
It can induce thermogenesis, et cetera,
it can reduce inflammation
but it can prevent some of the
positive effects of exercise.
Now, it hasn't been examined
so much for endurance work
but let's say you come back
from around of endurance work
or run or a bike or a swim,
getting into a cool bath
or cooling the palms, the
bottoms of the feet or the face,
in my opinion, based on
the science would be better
than completely immersing
the body in the ice bath
or the cold shower.
There is a time and a place
for the use of the ice
bath or the cold shower
or the cold plunge, those tend to be
when you want to deliberately
increase brown fat thermogenesis
or when you want to deliberately
work on mental resilience.
And in a subsequent episode on fat loss
I'm going to talk about how
to optimize the use of cold
specifically for increasing
metabolism and fat loss.
But for now, since we're
talking about the use of cold
for improving performance and recovery,
the suggestion that I'm going
to provide is based on the work
of Craig Heller and colleagues
that I've been talking about
as well as a excellent book
I mainly rely on textbooks
and special volume books which
are collections of papers
from experts in a particular area
that go beyond standard kind
of college level textbooks.
The one that I've been relying on
is called "Thermoregulation
in Human Performance,
Physiological and Biological
Aspects" by Effie Marino.
I don't know the publisher,
I don't know the author.
I do recognize some of the names
of the particular papers there,
but I just want to be clear
there's no sort of business
relationship or deal with them
but it's an excellent text,
it's called "Thermoregulation
in Human Performance".
You can find it online
if you want to go really deep into this
but basically what they show is that
if you can cool the body back
to its resting temperature,
for and by resting temperature, I mean
within the range that you would see
at any time of waking
day, but not in exercise.
So just bringing that the body
temperature down to baseline.
If you can do that,
the sooner you can do
that after a workout,
the sooner that the muscle will recover,
that the tendons will recover
and that the person you
can get back into more endurance training,
more weight training, et cetera.
So cold actually can be a very
powerful tool for recovery
but to maximize return to
baseline levels of temperature,
it's my belief based on the studies
that are published in this book
as well as my discussions with
my colleague, Craig Heller
and in reviewing the literature overall
that just simply cooling the entire body
by jumping into an ice
bath or a cold shower
is not the best way to go.
You really want to rely
on one of these three
glaborous skin portals of the palms,
the bottoms of the feet or the face.
So now you probably know more
than you ever wanted to know
about how we regulate body temperature
and how it can be applied to exercise
both during the exercise session
and afterward to optimize recovery.
Many of us, all of us, presumably
are also eating and drinking
things and taking things
at various times that
can impact this process.
And so, because of that, we should ask
whether or not those things
are impacting body temperature.
And when we do that, we find
that there are certain things
that many of us are doing
that are actually
impairing our performance.
So for instance, if you are
taking a pre-workout drink
or you're ingesting a lot of
caffeine or other substance
to bring your body temperature
up before exercise,
you are limiting the amount
of exercise that you can do.
I can recall a time in college
when I would drink a lot of espresso
back then ephedrine was
sold over the counter,
I remember taking it,
it will really energize you for workouts.
You can generate a lot of energy
and get extremely focused
taking those things.
They do increase heart rate,
they can be quite dangerous,
I don't recommend people take them.
In fact, I think ephedrine
is now off the shelves
as a non prescription compound
because various people died from taking it
who were sensitive to
it or exercised in heat.
But looking back at that,
I realized it was a foolish approach.
It was increasing core thermogenesis.
Sure I might've burned a few more calories
but actually when I look at the data
that are coming from specific cooling
and how that can so
increase in performance
if done properly and then I
compare that to the effects
of taking some sort of thermogenic
compound, whatever it is
some pre-workout or some pill
or high levels of caffeine,
it's very clear that
increasing body temperature
prior to working out is
the exact wrong thing
that one would want to do.
You don't want to stay so cold
that you can't generate
good muscle contractions.
You don't want to be like I am
coming out of the cold ocean,
you know, with claws for hands
but one wants to have your
body temperature in a range
that still allows you to
work hard and perform well.
Now, in terms of recovery,
things like alcohol,
we know our vasodilator.
So those are going to cause
people to drop body temperature.
So you might think, oh, well
that sounds great for recovery
and I don't think people
should be drinking who are
you know, have problems
with alcohol intake,
you know, alcoholics
or they're not of drinking age, et cetera.
I'm not a drinker, but
I do have a good friend
who's a quite accomplished athlete
who basically drinks a beer or two
after his long runs or cycling
and you know, his argument
is well, I'm dumping body
heat and I like a beer
and he's probably right, it's
probably a really good tool
provided you don't have
issues with alcohol
that would preclude that as a tool
or you're not of drinking age.
But anything that you
ingest after exercise
that would increase body temperature
is going to impede recovery.
Anything that you do that
lowers body temperature
provides it's in safe ranges
is going to accelerate recovery.
And that brings us to the
whole host of compounds
that people take that can
increase body temperature.
And many people are taking these things
in order to increase fat
burning and increase metabolism
but in my opinion
it's impeding their
ability to perform well.
And especially if the performance
is something that you're focused on
aside from body recomposition,
losing fat building muscle.
But even if you're focused on
losing fat, building muscle
you have to ask yourself, is
the body temperature increase
that I'm getting from these
compounds really worth it
given that it can block
or prevent my performance
from being as good as it could?
In other words, is it
worth taking something
that makes you feel very
energized to go work out
but then you now know that
you are stopping earlier
and you're performing
less well, fewer reps,
fewer steps overall, is it worth it?
If you had not taken that thing
then you could perform much longer
and at much higher capacity.
Some of you are probably
saying, well, that's ridiculous
because when I drink a quadruple espresso
and I pop a whatever pre-workout
or drink a pre-workout
then I know I can go much further.
Ah, that might be true but
the increase in temperature
is also costing you on the recovery side.
And unless you're doing other things
to improve your recovery and
I know many people that are,
I don't judge but many people
who are doing those things
are also augmenting their recovery
through hormone augmentation
and other performance enhancing tools,
then for the typical
person who's not doing that
it's probably shooting
yourself in the foot.
So let's take a look at what
some of those compounds are
and what they and just briefly review
whether or not they would be a
good or a bad idea to include
if your main goals are performance
or your main goals are
body recomposition or both.
So let's just briefly discuss stimulants.
This could be caffeine,
this could be any other kind of stimulant
that are typically in a pre-workout drink
or anything that might get you
revved up before exercising.
This could even be very strong tea,
I've mentioned I'm a big consumer of mate.
I like a yerba mate, I love that stuff
and I also drink caffeine.
I drink love coffee of various kinds
mushroom coffee, black
coffee, espresso, et cetera.
I'm a chronic caffeine user,
I don't think I'm an addict
but I'm a chronic caffeine user.
Meaning when I drink caffeine
my heart rate doesn't increase so much
that it feels like a shock to my system.
Some people are not caffeine adapted
or they're very caffeine sensitive.
Here's the straightforward rule.
Caffeine for somebody who
doesn't drink caffeine very much
will constrict the blood vessels
and will increase retention of body heat
and it's probably a bad
idea before exercise.
For somebody who's caffeine adapted
and is used to drinking caffeine,
it won't have that
vasoconstriction effect,
that's what the data point
too, because I'm adapted to it
but it will cause vasodilation
and will allow me to dump body heat.
So for me, I use it before I train
or do any kind of exercise
because I tend to do
that early in the day,
it won't prevent me from sleeping
and it causes vasodilation.
And then afterwards I'm aware
that it causes vasoconstriction
after the caffeine wears off.
So for somebody who drinks two or three
or more cups of coffee
a day or mate a day,
so we're talking intake
of anywhere from a hundred to
400 milligrams of caffeine,
what you want to do is
you want to make sure
that you would do that before exercise
and probably not after exercise,
not just makes logical sense
given what we know about
thermal regulation.
And if you're somebody who
doesn't drink caffeine,
drinking caffeine before a workout
is going to be about the worst thing
that you could possibly do
because it's going to
increase core body temperature
through its thermogenic effects
and it's going to constrict
your blood vessels
and make it even harder to dump heat.
So I don't suggest that
people drink caffeine or not,
I just suggest that you think about
whether or not your
caffeine adapted or not,
and decide whether or not
you want to drink caffeine.
In general, you're going to be
better not drinking any caffeine
than you are drinking caffeine
unless you're a heavy
caffeine user or abuser.
In which case not drinking caffeine
is going to give you vicious headaches
and is going to make it
very hard to get motivated
because you're just not used to it.
It takes about three weeks
to get used to no caffeine.
It's brutal, I've done it
before, I've done caffeine fast,
I don't know that I ever
want to do it again,
that's how painful it was.
But you get headaches
because of the effects on
vasodilation and constriction.
If you like caffeine
use in moderate amounts
and use it before your not after.
If you don't like caffeine or
you don't use it very often,
stay away from it
anywhere close to exercise
before or after for that matter.
One of the more commonly used compounds
that's sold over the counter
are non-steroid anti-inflammatories
so things like Tylenol and
Advil and other trade names
and Neproxin sodium things of that sort,
almost all of those drop body
temperature to some extent.
And that's why it's often recommended
that people take them
when they have a fever
although the whole business
of dropping body temperature artificially
when you have a fever is itself
an interesting discussion
whether or not that's the most
adaptive or best thing to do
certainly you don't want
fever to go too high,
can be very dangerous, can kill you
but artificially dropping body temperature
with these compounds can be tricky.
Now, a number of athletes
especially endurance athletes
will rely on these non-steroid
anti-inflammatory drugs
specifically to keep
body temperature lower
during long bouts of exertion.
This is a little bit of
a pharmacologic version
of dumping heat instead
of using palmer cooling
or you know, face ice pack cooling,
they're relying on pharmacology
to drop their core body temperature.
That has certain obvious advantages,
those advantages should be obvious
and the reasons for them should be obvious
based on everything we've
talked about up until now
lower temperature allows
you to go further harder
with more intensity.
However, they do have effects on the liver
and they can also have
effects on the kidneys
and during long bouts of exercise
or even short bouts of exercise,
water balance and salt balance
are also going to be vital
to maintain in order to perform well,
generate the best muscle
contraction, stay mentally alert
and also to stay alive.
We will do an episode on
salt electrolytes and water
and water balance but you
probably want to think carefully
about whether or not
you want to use non-steroid
anti-inflammatories
before any training session
just for the performance
augmentation effect
unless you're working
carefully with a coach
whether or not you've
done that in practices
and of course, whether or
not you are in a situation
where monitoring your
body temperature carefully
is going to be important.
You might ask, well, when would that be?
Well, desert races, summer
training and races, winter rides,
you certainly don't want
to get too cool either.
So alcohol, caffeine and
non-steroid anti-inflammatory drugs
because of their effects on temperature
will impact performance and recovery
but you want to be cautious
about how you approach them.
I personally am more a
fan of using caffeine
in moderate doses for the
reasons I described before
as well to use the cooling of the palms,
cooling of the bottoms of my feet, right,
by placing them into a
bucket or into a cool bath
after training or cooling
the face after training
or sometimes even during training.
It just seems like
there's more of a margin
to play with the variables,
to heat up the water
or cool it down a little
bit to include one palm
or the other palm.
There's all sorts of good parameter space
as we call it in science
that you can play with
and work with to find what works for you
whereas when you pop a pill,
sure you can adjust the dose
and you can adjust it next time
but once it's in you, it's in you
and there's going to
be some period of time
before you can modulate it.
What I've offered today
are ways in which you can use temperature
to powerfully improve performance.
And if you think about it,
you can vary that from set to set,
you could do your pull ups or your sprints
and then cool your palms,
and then try and go with
colder water the next round
or warmer water the next round
or do both feet and palms and face.
I mean, you can do all sorts
of things moment to moment
and see what works for you again
essentially zero cost or no cost.
Whereas when you pop
something, you take a pill,
you're basically in that regimen
for the next hour or two or more.
You can always take more, but
you can't really take less.
You can't really extract it
from your body in real time
so it doesn't give you
a lot of opportunity
to play scientists, which
is what I like to do
because what I'm always trying to do
is trying to dial in the
best protocols possible
based on the mechanisms and data.
And if you can do that moment to moment
that places you in a position of power.
Once again, we covered a lot of material.
By now, after seeing this episode
or listening to this episode,
you should understand a lot
about how your body heats and cools itself
and the value of that
for physical performance.
I hope you'll also appreciate
that you have tools at your disposal
to vastly improve your
physical performance.
And should you try those,
please let us know how it goes.
If you decide to do palmer
cooling during your runs
or after your runs, during
your weight workouts,
during your yoga sessions,
whatever it is, let us know,
please place that in the comments.
I've given you specific
protocols and some direction,
but I've also left it slightly vague
because it, as I mentioned earlier
I don't know all the
environmental conditions,
I don't know how hot your yoga studio is
or how cool your gym happens to be
or your body temperature or time of day.
Remember your temperature will vary
according to the time of day,
we did a whole episode
about that related to sleep.
Typically your body temperature
is rising early in the day
and is coming down as you
approach the late evening
and late night hours for sleep,
in the middle of the night
your temperature is very low
at its absolute lowest
something we call the temperature minimum.
So we don't know exactly where you're at.
You need to take the information
that you receive today
and should you try and incorporate it
try and do it intelligently.
Don't cool yourself off
so much that you know
become cryogenic and please
don't warm yourself up.
In fact, we didn't talk at
all about warming yourself up
because warming yourself up too
much can be quite dangerous.
You never, ever, ever
want to be hypothermic,
that's what your body and your
brain are trying to avoid.
We talked a little bit about supplements
but not the standard sorts of supplements
I usually list off on these episodes.
Rather, we talked about caffeine,
non-steroid anti-inflammatories
and how those can impact temperature,
how alcohol can impact temperature.
And I should just mention in closing
that every time we eat, we
also increased temperature.
There's a eating induced
thermogenic effect
but that's a minor one,
that's a small one.
So you wouldn't worry about
eating before training
because of its effects on temperature
because it tends to be really minor.
Going forward, we're going to
talk more about temperature
and other ways to improve
physical performance
and skill learning.
We're going to talk about specific ways
to accelerate fat loss,
to improve muscle growth,
to improve suppleness and flexibility.
These approaches and
mechanisms are anchored deeply
in neuroscience and physiology
and the relationship
between our peripheral
organs, which include our skin
and our brain and all
the organs in between.
So it's really a pleasure for
me because I'm able to look
to the textbook literature that exists
and really came out over the
last 50 to a hundred years
and unlike a lot of areas of neuroscience
which are still sort of mystical,
like consciousness and dreaming,
of which we understand a little bit
about these core mechanisms
of temperature and physiology
which are so powerful,
involve very concrete studies
that as you learn today
are very actionable.
If you're enjoying this podcast
and you like the information
that you're receiving,
if you're incorporating into
your life in useful ways,
please recommend the
podcast to other people
if you think they could
benefit from it as well.
Please subscribe to
the podcast on YouTube,
so you want to hit the subscribe button
as well hit the notifications button.
We come out with new episodes every Monday
but from time to time, we
also release shorter content
and we will be releasing
additional content
in between episodes from time to time.
If you don't already subscribe
on Apple and or Spotify,
please do so.
Also on Apple, you have
the opportunity to leave us
up to a five star review
if you think that we
deserve a five star review
and to leave us feedback.
They have a comment section there,
it's really a feedback section
where you can rate and
describe the podcast
as you experience it.
If you'd like to support
the podcast in other ways,
please check out our sponsors.
That's a terrific way to support us.
We also have a Patreon, you can find it
at patreon.com/andrewhuberman
that allows you to support the podcast
at any level that you like.
Today we didn't focus so
heavily on supplements,
but in other episodes I have,
and there are certainly supplements
that are beneficial for sleep,
for performance, for learning,
immunity and so forth.
We've partnered with
Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E.com,
because Thorne supplements
we believe to be the most stringent
in terms of what they put on the bottle
is actually what's in the bottle,
so the amounts are precise
and the quality of the
ingredients is very precise.
They partner with the Mayo Clinic,
all the major sports teams
so we're delighted that
we're partnered with Thorne.
If you want to see the
supplements that I take
you can go to thorne.com/u/huberman
and you can see the
supplements that I take,
you could get 20% off
any of those supplements
should you choose to order them
as well as 20% off any other supplements
that Thorne happens to make.
That's Thorne, thorne.com/u/huberman
to get 20% off any of the
supplements that Thorne makes.
And last but not least,
I want to thank you for
your time and attention.
I realize this is a lot of information,
I hope you'll find some
of it to be actionable
and useful for you and
for people that you know
and as always thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]