- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
[gentle music]
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
Neurobiology and Ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I've long been a fan of
getting blood work done.
And the simple reason for that,
is that most of the things
that you want to know
about your health, such as
hormones, metabolic factors,
blood sugar levels, et cetera,
can only be analyzed from blood.
And nowadays there are
also excellent DNA tests
that can also give you
valuable information
about what's going on at
the cellar, molecular,
even the neural circuit level
within your brain and body.
InsideTracker makes getting
blood and DNA tests easy.
You can go to a testing site
where they draw your blood,
they take your DNA sample,
or they can come to your
home if you prefer that.
As well, they have a
really amazing dashboard.
The dashboard lets you understand
what your levels of various hormones
and metabolic factors et cetera mean,
and what you should do about them.
And I think that's one of the main things
that really separates InsideTracker
apart from other blood and DNA tests.
Most tests you get the results back,
but there are no directives
about what to do specifically
in order to bring the
numbers into the ranges
that you would like for your goals.
InsideTracker makes all
of that extremely simple
and extremely clear.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman,
and if you do that, you'll get 25% off
any of InsideTrackers plans.
Use the code Huberman at checkout.
That's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off
any of InsideTrackers plans.
Today's episode is also brought
to us by Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an all-in-one
vitamin, mineral probiotic drink.
I started taking Athletic
Greens back in 2012
and I've taken it ever since.
So I'm delighted that they're
sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I started
taking Athletic Greens
and the reason I still take it now,
is that Athletic Greens
really lets me cover
all my nutritional basis
in terms of vitamins,
minerals and probiotics.
There's so much data now
pointing to the fact
that the gut microbiome
and the gut brain axis is
important for metabolism
and for endocrine health.
The vitamins, minerals and
probiotics in Athletic Greens
make me feel confident that
I'm covering all my bases.
I do take other supplements,
but with Athletic Greens
I know that I've got all the
foundational stuff handled.
It also tastes really good.
Tastes fine on its own,
you can mix it with
water, which is what I do.
I add a little bit of
lemon juice or lime juice,
because I like a little tartness
flavor in there as well,
but most people just mix it with water,
it mixes up super easily.
I drink it once or twice a day.
Usually once mid morning, and
once again in the afternoon.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman.
And if you do that, you can
claim their special offer
which is a year supply of vitamin D3K2.
There is now a ton of
evidence that vitamin D3
is involved in countless
metabolic processes,
hormonal processes that are important
for overall health and wellbeing.
Vitamin D3, you can get
from the sun of course,
but most people are
deficient in vitamin D3.
So if you go to
athleticgreens.com/huberman
you'll get the Athletic Greens,
you'll get the year's
supply of vitamin D3 and K2
and you'll get five free travel packs.
So once again it's
athleticgreens.com/huberman,
to get Athletic Greens, the vitamin D3K2,
and that's a year supply plus
the five free travel packs.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Munk Pack.
Munk Pack is a company that
makes keto-friendly snacks
that taste incredible
but have just one gram of sugar or less.
And indeed they taste incredible.
In fact, my production team
here at the Huberman Lab Podcast
teases me because I actually
have to keep the boxes
of Munk Pack bars in my basement
'cause otherwise I'll
tear through all of them.
I remember the first time
I tasted it, I was like,
all right, here we go, a keto bar.
I'm not a big fan of bars in general,
most of them don't taste good to me.
And I tasted the Munk Pack bars,
and they are absolutely awesome.
They come in a lot of different flavors.
I'm partial to the caramel sea salt one,
but they also have sea
salt dark chocolate,
peanut butter dark chocolate.
They have a bunch of flavors.
They're all incredible,
I've tried them all.
Which is why I keep them in my basement.
As I mentioned previously on this podcast,
I'm neither keto nor carbo.
I don't really follow a
particular diet in that sense.
I eat in a way that maximizes my alertness
and my levels of focus during
the day when I want to work,
and that maximize my
transition to sleep at night.
So, I basically eat low carb
keto-ish during the day.
And I know the ketonistas will
say that I'm not in ketosis
and I can manage to get into ketosis.
But the main idea,
is I keep my carbohydrates
low during the day.
And then at night I do eat carbohydrates.
So for me, the Munk Pack
bars are a really good snack
usually in the afternoon,
with a cup of coffee,
especially if I'm going
to train soon after that,
or if I just want to snack and
I'm going to continue working.
As I mentioned before, they
are absolutely delicious.
They also don't have any of
the stuff that's bad for you.
No soy, trans fat, sugar,
alcohols, artificial colors,
all that stuff that we
know we should avoid.
If you want to try Munk Pack
bars, you can go to Munk Pack,
that's M-U-N-K, MunkPack.com,
and enter the code Huberman at checkout
and you'll get 20% off your first purchase
of any Munk Pack product.
That's Munk Pack, M-U-N-K-P-A-C-K.com,
and enter the code Huberman at checkout
to get 20% off your purchase.
This month, we're talking
all about hormones.
Hormones are incredible
and they control so many
processes in the brain and body.
Last episode, we talked about
the role of estrogen and testosterone.
Today we're going to talk about
how hormones impact feeding and hunger,
as well as satiety, the feeling
that you don't want to eat
or that you've eaten enough.
Now, it's important to understand
that hormones don't work
alone in this context.
Today I'm going to describe some hormones
that have powerful effects
on whether or not you
want to eat more or less
or stop eating altogether.
But they don't do that on their own,
they do that in cooperation
with the nervous system.
So today, I would say as much
or perhaps even more
than any other episodes,
we're going to hear a lot of biology
but there are multiple what
I'm going to call entry points
for tools that you can apply
in order to regulate
your levels of hunger,
your meal timing, your levels of satiety
of not wanting to eat more.
And many of this is
actionable with behaviors,
but of course, we're also
going to talk about supplements
and we're actually going to talk about
a little bit of brain
machine interface devices
that can actually be involved
in manipulating these incredible things
that we think of as hunger
and appetite and satiety.
So, the first thing that you need to know
about the nervous system side,
the neural control,
over-feeding and hunger,
is that there's an area of your brain
called the hypothalamus.
It's in the forebrain,
which tells you it's in
the front of your brain,
and it's at the base of the forebrain.
Now, the hypothalamus contains
lots of different kinds of neurons
doing lots of different kinds of things.
There are neurons in your hypothalamus
controlling sexual behavior,
controlling body temperature,
controlling circadian rhythms,
the desire to sleep or be awake.
Even neurons controlling rage.
There are actually neurons that
if we were to stimulate them
would send you or anyone into a rage.
They're just powerful control centers
for the brain and body.
There's a particular
area of the hypothalamus
called the ventromedial hypothalamus.
And it's one that researchers
have been interested
for a long time now, in
terms of its relationship
to hunger and feeding.
And the reason is, it creates
these paradoxical effects.
What do I mean by that?
What they found was that
sometimes lesioning,
or disrupting the neurons in
the ventromedial hypothalamus
would make animals or people hyperphasia,
they would want to eat crazy.
And other lesions in other
individuals or animals
would make them anorexic,
it would make them not want to eat at all.
It would make food aversive.
So that means that the
ventromedial hypothalamus
is definitely an
interesting control station
for hunger and feeding and satiety,
but it doesn't really
tell you what's going on
at a deeper level.
In fact, it's a little bit
confusing or paradoxical.
It turns out that there
are multiple populations
of neurons in there, we're
going to talk about those.
Some are promoting feeding,
and some are promoting
not feeding or not eating.
Now, the other neural
component of all this
that you need to know about,
actually has to do with your mouth.
So there's an area of your cortex,
so that's a little bit
further up in your brain,
called the insular cortex.
And it processes a lot of
different kinds of information.
Mostly information about
what's going on inside you,
so called the interoception.
The insular cortex has neurons
that get input from your mouth,
from the touch receptors in your mouth.
And insular cortex has powerful control
over whether or not you're
enjoying what you're eating,
whether or not you want to
avoid what you're eating,
whether or not you had enough,
or whether or not you want
to continue eating more.
And that has to do, believe it or not,
with the touch or sensation of eating.
I'm very familiar with this.
I'm one of these people,
I love eating so much,
that I just like the mere act of chewing.
You know, I like celery sticks enough.
I'm not crazy about them, but
you know they taste fine to me
and I like chewing on celery sticks,
but I actually just like chewing on them.
I could eat all day long
except that it's not healthy to do that.
But the mere act of chewing
for me is very pleasurable.
People who chew gum feel this way as well.
And just as a point about gum or chewing,
if you choose something like celery
or cucumber slices or chew gum,
provided it doesn't have any
sugar or caloric content,
it's not going to drive increased hunger.
That generally isn't the case.
But if you eat something with
sugar, as we'll find out,
it has a very specific
action in the insular cortex
and in other areas of your nervous system
that promotes the desire to eat more.
But the key point right now
is to know you've got
these two brain areas,
the ventromedial hypothalamus,
that's involved in hunger
and lack of hunger,
sort of an accelerator
and a brake on feeding.
And you have this insular cortex
that gets input from your mouth,
and cares about chewing and
the consistency of foods
and all sorts of interesting things
that are just very tactile.
And I think most people think
about the touch receptors on,
excuse me, the taste
receptors on the tongue.
But we often don't think about
the touch or tactile essence of food.
And the thing that comes to mind just now
is I've gone to sushi several times,
and some people really like the urchin.
I don't like the urchin.
There's something about it
that kind of creeps me out
about the consistency,
other people love it.
So it's highly individual
and it's probably learned,
and there's some probably
cultural background to this
if you were raised eating urchin.
Some people love that
consistency or that touch.
So touch has a lot to do
with whether or not
you want to eat or not.
Now, let's get back to the
ventromedial hypothalamus.
Sometimes it makes animals
or people want to eat more,
sometimes less, so what's going on there?
There's a classic experiment that was done
in which researchers took two rats,
and so-called parabiosed
them to each other.
What that meant is that
they did a little surgery
and they linked their blood supply
so that they were forever
physically linked to one another
and could exchange factors in the blood,
but their brains were separate,
their mouths were separate,
and they essentially did
everything separately
except that they were
linked to one another.
So they had to walk together
and go to the same
places in order to do it.
This parabiosis experiment
revealed something really important.
When they lesioned the
ventromedial hypothalamus
in one of the rats that was
connected to the other rat,
that rat got very, very
fat, just really obese,
huge rat, super rat, jumbo rat.
The other one however, got very thin,
it actually lost weight,
despite consuming the same
amount of food that it had
prior to the other one getting the lesion.
So what does this tell us?
This tells us that there's
something in the blood
that's being exchanged
between the two animals,
because it was their blood
supply that was linked.
And that tells us that there's
hormone or endocrine signals
that are involved in the desire to eat,
and hunger and appetite.
And so next, we're going to talk about
what those endocrine signals are,
and then I'm going to immediately point
to some entry points that you can use.
And you can use these
even if you're not parabiosed to anything.
And that can allow you to
time your meal frequency,
and predict when you're
going to be hungry or not.
As well as a drive up appetite.
Believe it or not, there
are people out there
who are trying to eat more.
Although I think far many more
people are trying to eat less
because nowadays, the data
just point to the fact
that there is essentially
an epidemic of diabetes,
type II diabetes and obesity.
And most everyone agrees now,
that maintaining a healthy body weight
and body weight composition,
is one of the best paths to longevity
and to just feeling very good
and actually being able to think.
Cognitive functioning
is actually linked to levels
of adipose tissue and so forth.
So, let's talk about the endocrine factors
that regulate feeding, hunger and satiety.
One of the really
exciting things to emerge
in the science of feeding and
appetite in the last 20 years,
is the discovery of another brain area.
And not just the
ventromedial hypothalamus,
but it's an area of the brain
called the arcuate nucleus.
And the arcuate nucleus
has some really
fascinating sets of neurons
that release even more
incredible molecules
and chemicals into the blood.
And these chemicals act as accelerators
on feeding and appetite, or breaks.
And the really cool thing
is that you can actually
control these molecules
through simple behaviors.
And once you understand
what these molecules are,
you'll start to understand
why that's the case.
And the control points
that you have right now
in order to control your
appetite in either direction,
increase or decrease.
So, first of all, there are set of neurons
in this arcuate nucleus
called the PMOC neurons, okay?
I don't want to get into
what the acronym stands for,
but I'll do it anyway.
It's the Proopiomelanocortin system, okay?
So these are PMOC neurons,
Proopiomelanocortin.
And if you heard melano,
that should tell you
it has something to do with pigmentation
in skin cells or in hair cells,
pigmentation of some sort,
because of melanin.
Last episode, I talked a little bit
about the relationship between
light dopamine and melanin.
So you should already be
thinking, wait, melano means
it probably has something
to do with that system,
and indeed it does.
Now, the POMC neurons, make
something called Alpha MSH.
Melanocyte-stimulating hormone,
Alpha-Melanocyte-stimulating hormone.
If you don't want to remember
any of the other acronyms
and terms I've talked
about, this episode so far,
do try and remember M-S-H, okay?
Mouse, Sam, Hamster, M-S-H, okay?
MSH reduces appetite
and it's a powerful molecule, all right?
So just put that on the shelf,
MSH reduces appetite.
Now, there's another population of neurons
in the arcuate nucleus,
called the AgRP neurons.
And there I'm truly not going
to read you what that stands for
'cause it's related to the mouse strain
it was first identified in,
but humans have these cells
as well, but AgRP neurons.
The AgRP neurons stimulate eating.
And anytime you are approaching food,
or you feel some excitement
about food or anxiety,
because some people actually experience
a kind of heightened anxiety.
Some people actually get a
little bit of a resting tremor
before they eat,
even if they don't have any
sort of eating disorder.
There's kind of a ramping
up of autonomic activity.
That's largely due to the
activity of these AgRP neurons.
So, the activity in these
AgRP neurons goes way up
when animals or people are starved.
And I don't mean starved
for long periods of time,
but I mean when they
haven't eaten for a while.
And the activity of MSH,
the release of MSH goes up
when we've eaten.
However, there are other
things that will stimulate
the release of things like MSH.
So, just briefly the
experimental evidence,
if you kill AgRP neurons,
animals and people stop eating.
There are people of lesions.
They just stop eating,
they become anorexic.
I know you're familiar with
anorexia as a clinical term,
but that's actually a term that's used
in the scientific literature
about a pattern of behavior, okay?
As well as a clinical term of course.
If you were to stimulate the AgRP neurons,
animals or people eat like crazy.
They will eat to the
point where they burst.
Which just sounds horrible,
but it just tells you
this is the accelerator on eating.
And yes, it has relationship
to the ventromedial hypothalamus
I talked about earlier,
but I don't want to go
back there just yet,
we will circle back.
So Melanocyte-stimulating hormone,
such an interesting hormone.
This thing can shut
down the desire to eat.
The Melanocyte-stimulating hormone,
is released from the medial pituitary.
We talked about the pituitary last time.
This is a gland that is
very closely positioned
to the hypothalamus.
Actually some of the hypothalamus neurons
actually project their neural connections
directly into the pituitary,
to release things like
gonadotropins and luteinizing hormones,
stuff we talked about last time
in reference to testosterone and estrogen.
But MSH is released from the
medial portion of the pituitary
and it stimulates the desire
to not eat, to cease eating.
What's really interesting,
is that Melanocyte-stimulating hormone
is activated by ultraviolet light.
And it's not activated by
ultraviolet light to the skin
or directly to pituitary,
it's activated by ultraviolet
light to the eyes.
Now, if you've been watching this podcast
or listening to this podcast
for any period of time,
or you've heard me on other podcasts
or you follow my Instagram,
I am a big fan of this whole
thing of getting morning light
in order to synchronize
circadian rhythms, et cetera,
avoiding light in the middle of the night.
This is yet another reason
why getting ample light, ideally sunlight,
but it could be other sources
of UV light to the eyes,
stimulates MSH, this has been
shown over and over again.
And keeps the desire to
eat or appetite in check,
in healthy ranges.
This is also why in the
spring and summer months,
animals and people eat less.
Now, for hibernating
animals it's different,
because they bear hibernate, actually.
Ashley bears don't truly
hibernate technically,
by a scientific criteria
they don't hibernate,
but they go into a kind of torpor.
The hibernating animals
they don't eat much
because they're in boroughs or dens,
or they're just wrapped
up in a little ball
or whatever it is that
hibernating animals do.
So they're of course going to
eat far less in the winter.
But that's a unique scenario,
we are not hibernating animals.
But humans generally have greater appetite
in the cold winter months.
And it's not just because of the holidays
and the abundance of food
that we're presenting ourselves with,
but when we get a lot of
sun our appetite is reduced
or at least it's easier to control.
And that is due in part,
because if you're getting
ample sunlight to the eyes,
it's converted into a
signal for the MSH neurons,
the neurons that release MSH, excuse me
these PMOC neurons release MSH.
And then MSH can bind its receptors,
and can keep the break
on appetite in check.
So the takeaway tool from this,
is make sure you're getting enough light
not just in the morning,
but throughout the day.
And yes, it has to be light to your eyes.
And blasting your eyes with
sunlight or artificial light
to the point where it's
damaging or painful,
won't accelerate or improve this process.
It's about getting photons,
ultraviolet light to the eyes consistently
throughout the day.
That's best accomplished
by not wearing sunglasses
provided you can do that safely.
And if you don't have
access to enough sunlight,
then you can do this
with artificial light.
This also points again to our old friends,
the blue blockers.
Many people know I'm not a
huge fan of blue blockers
especially not during the daytime,
because they block a lot of the UV
and shorter wavelength
light that you want and need
to create alertness, but
also to create release of MSH
from the medial pituitary.
Now there are people out there,
subcultures, that actually inject MSH.
That are taking MSH or
things similar to it.
I am not suggesting people do that.
But there are three main
consequences of doing that.
First of all, it reduces
appetite, no surprise there.
And they're actually using
it as a dieting drug.
This is kind of in the underground.
I don't know what the legal status is.
And again, I'm not
promoting that people do it.
Two, it makes them very, very
tan, which makes sense, right?
Melanocyte-stimulating hormone.
And the third is, it
purportedly, never tried it,
purportedly sends libido through the roof,
to the point where it's
actually distracting
for other activities.
It actually can create priapism,
which is a kind of
chronic erection in males
to the point where it actually
can be physically damaging
to the genitalia.
So this is a drug,
I don't know whether or
not it's call it a drug.
It's a substance that one can
regulate with healthy levels,
with sunlight and perhaps
artificial UV light.
I have not heard much about
treatments for obesity
involving getting ample sunlight
or getting ample UV light,
but to me, the logic is just very clear.
And so if you're pursuing those avenues,
you certainly should
talk to your physician
but you might want to think about
how some of those logic hangs together.
Absolutely fascinating hormone,
I think most people aren't aware of it.
And the subcultures that are aware of it
are using it for two very
particular end points,
and they're using it at
super physiological levels.
That's enough about that
'cause I really don't know.
I've talked to a few people in research.
Believe it or not for this podcast,
I reached out to a few people
and asked whether or not
the these are side effects
in air quotes.
I've heard about are true,
and indeed they're true.
But again, that's super
physiological, controlling MSH,
it's actually Alpha MSH levels
through viewing ultraviolet light
seems like an interesting
and mechanistically logical thing to do,
if your goal is to keep appetite in check.
So MSH inhibits hunger.
Next, let's talk about a hormone peptide
that activates hunger.
And this is a really interesting one
because it relates to when you get hungry,
in addition to the fact
that you get hungry at all.
And it's called ghrelin,
it's spelled G-H-R-E-L-I-N.
Ghrelin is released
actually from the GI tract.
And its main role is to
increase your desire to eat.
And it does that through
a variety of mechanisms.
Part of that is to stimulate
some of the brain areas,
the actual neurons, that
make you want to eat.
In addition, it creates
food anticipatory signals
within your nervous systems.
So you start thinking about the things
that you happen to like to eat
at that particular time of day.
And this is fascinating.
Ghrelin is sort of like a clock,
a hormonal clock that
makes you want to eat
at particular times.
Now, the signal for ghrelin
is reduced glucose levels
in the blood.
We're going to talk a lot today
about glucose and insulin,
ways to manage glucose and insulin.
But for now the simple version of this,
is you normally want your glucose
to be in a kind of modest range,
and I'll explain what
range is in a little bit.
But if it drops too low, ghrelin
is secreted from your gut.
It activates neurons in your
brain at various locations
including the PMOC neurons,
and the other neurons of the wingin' it.
It also activates the
VMH in particular ways.
And it might even activate
some of these neurons
that are in the periphery in your mouth
that actually make you salivate
and want to eat, right?
Now, we all know about
the famous Pavlovian,
experiments of Pavlov's dogs.
You know, they start
salivating to the bell.
After the bell was presented
with food, you remove the food,
and then just the bell can
stimulate the salivation.
We become Pavlovian at times.
But rarely is it ever discussed
what the neural pathways for that are.
And it turns out that these hormones
that are secreted from the
gut can stimulate the neurons
to create a sensation and
a desire for certain foods
at certain times of day.
You've done this experiment.
If you are somebody who eats breakfast
at more or less the same time each day,
let's say 8:00 AM plus
or minus 20 minutes.
And then you eat lunch 12:30
plus or minus 20 minutes.
Or let's say you're somebody like me
who typically skips
breakfast, and just eats lunch
usually around 11:30 or
12 or something like that.
Your ghrelin secretion will start to match
when you typically eat.
And it does that.
And it's able to override
the low levels of glucose
in your bloodstream,
because the ghrelin system also gets input
from a clock in your liver
that is linked to the
clock in your hypothalamus,
in your brain.
And what this means is, if
you eat at regular meal times,
you'll start to get hungry a few minutes
before those meals times.
If you've ever wondered why
your stomach kind of starts to growl
because it's a particular time of day,
and you're like, Oh I must want to eat,
well, that's ghrelin.
And for those of you that don't know
why your stomach growls, I'll
also tell you that today.
It's actually really interesting.
It not at all what you expect,
and it's not just the gurgling
of liquids in your stomach.
That's not what it is.
It's actually a muscular phenomenon.
So, ghrelin is secreted as
a food anticipatory signal,
to get you motivated to
go eat at regular times.
So, nowadays there's a lot of interest
in intermittent fasting.
There's also a lot of interest
in just what meal plans
and schedules and what to eat in general,
in order to maximize one's
health and wellbeing.
And people have all
sorts of cosmetic reasons
and brain reasons and metabolic reasons
for wanting to control this kind of stuff.
So let's make it really simple
by first looking at the extremes.
Some people need to eat
every two or three hours.
They feel this, "I need to
eat every two or three hours,"
or else their blood sugar drops.
In general, blood sugar
doesn't drop so low,
that they truly need to eat
in order to alleviate a blood sugar issue.
Although sometimes that can happen.
Some people are truly
hypoglycemic, low blood sugar.
But most people as the blood
sugar starts to head down
towards the low-ish ranges,
ghrelin is secreted.
And so for those people
not eating on the clock,
it's very disruptive to them
because it activates these
neurons in the brain.
For people who eat once
a day or twice a day,
or tend to shift their meals,
you know, and they might eat a lot
but during a limited
so-called feeding window,
it's kind of interesting humans
now eat and talk about foods
in ways that for years I used
to hear about in classes,
in courses, and research
lectures about feeding animals,
you know, restricted feeding windows.
And we owe a great deal of
gratitude to Satchin Panda,
who was a colleague of mine
when my lab was in San Diego
at the Salk Institute, who
really is one of the pioneers
of this restricted feeding window work
and has done a beautiful work.
He has a book that's excellent
called 'The Circadian Code'
that I highly recommend.
And he's done a lot of important work
on neurons in the retina,
that control circadian timing,
but also the relationship
between feeding windows
and health.
And he's sort of among the
major proponents I should say,
of circadian eating, that means
eating during the daytime,
not at night or intermittent fasting,
restricting feeding windows
to anywhere from four
to six to eight hours.
I'll use myself as an example
of the transition from
regular feeding schedule
to a more intermittent-ish fasting,
although I don't really fall
into true intermittent fasting.
So I was one of these people
that just got so accustomed
to waking up and eating about
an hour after I woke up.
That to go from eating
every three or four hours
to eating twice a day, lunch and dinner,
maybe a couple of snacks in
the afternoon or something.
At first it was excruciating.
I remember thinking like,
this is really brutal pushing out feeding.
I didn't think I could exercise
unless I had eaten first.
We now know that during
most all forms of exercise
unless you're really focused
on optimal performance
like you've got to hit key lifts
or you have to sprint
at your maximum speed.
And maybe even then that you
can exercise faster just fine,
because you're mainly relying
on sources like glycogen
from the liver, some
undigested food sometimes,
as gross as that may seem it's true,
as well as body fat if the
exercise about is extremely long.
But what that means is
that if you suddenly go
from eating on a very regular
schedule to skipping a meal,
or pushing your meal timing
out or shifting at all,
you're going to have
ghrelin in your system.
And that ghrelin is going to
stimulate the desire to eat
by acting at the level of your brain.
And it is indeed at
that point, just mental.
When we hear about just
mental, just physical,
it's really kind of the same thing
'cause it's all chemicals, brain and body.
But it's the stimulation of
neurons that anticipate feeding.
You're stimulating the
arcuate nucleus neurons
that make you want to
eat those AgRP neurons.
So ghrelin stimulates the AgRP neurons,
which makes you want to eat.
So what can you do with this?
What this means is,
if you want to start shifting
your feeding schedule
to one where you're not
eating quite as frequently,
and there are some advantages to that
that aren't just in the
biochemistry and health related,
you know, cellar health related things.
But some of them include
not having to think about
or buy food, right?
You actually don't have to
think about food all day
if you're not eating so often.
The other is, it gives you
a far more social flexibility, right?
You can go to a noon
meeting if you have to
or you can go out to dinner
at a particular time.
And you know, I guess it
makes it kind of tough
if you want to meet
somebody for breakfast,
'cause then you're the dork
who's just like sipping black coffee
and like refusing everything.
But anyway, I've been that dork.
So it's one of those things
you just kind of work with.
But the fact of the matter
is, ghrelin secretion,
because of its relationship
to the nervous system,
can be shifted by about
45 minutes per day.
Now, it's going to vary.
Some of you have more
so-called willpower, you know.
But if you really want to just start
pushing that first meal out
or shifting in any direction,
some people might want to eat
in the early part of the day
and not in the evening.
Trying to shift the
mealtimes out the spacing
by about 45 minutes, is
what the neural circuits
that link the ghrelin system
to the neural circuits
that control feeding, really can handle
because it's a form of neuroplasticity.
And so what this would look like is,
if you normally you eat
breakfast at eight o'clock
plus or minus 20 minutes,
and you want to start eating
your first meal at noon
you would take maybe four or five days
and just start pushing the meal out
by about 45 minutes to an hour each day.
So it's not quite as painful.
Or you can just take the plunge
and just do it all at once.
I have a colleague who was
a neurosurgeon at Stanford,
came up through my lab,
he's now at Neuralink,
and he has a great practice.
He keeps his ghrelin system at random.
What he does is he skips one meal per day
and he makes his external
schedule dictate that.
So, sometimes he skips breakfast,
sometimes he skips lunch,
sometimes he skips dinner,
he just skips one of the
three major meals per day.
And in doing that, the ghrelin system
has always kind of kept off kilter.
And it probably also allows him
to have a lot of neural flexibility,
what we call top-down control.
Just the knowledge, Oh, you
know the hunger I'm feeling
isn't necessarily hypoglycemia.
And in his case, it's
almost certainly not.
And therefore what I'm feeling here
is an activation of these AgRP neurons,
and therefore I can push
my meal schedule around
however I want.
Now, I should mention that
top-down mechanisms are powerful.
Belief, motivation,
these things can really
shift neural circuits.
We're going to talk more
about that a little bit later.
But there are also people who
are genuinely hypoglycemic
and they need to take really good control
of their blood sugar levels
and try and keep them stable.
And so of course, you want to do
what's medically safe for you.
I'm not at all recommending
that people that suffer from hypoglycemia
suddenly disrupt their
blood sugar patterns
in any direction, that
wouldn't be healthy.
But for most people out there
who have reasonable blood glucose levels,
it's kind of interesting and kind of fun
to play with these parameters
in order to optimize what you want to do.
And sometimes that might
change across the year
with schedules.
Many find great benefit
in having flexibility
over when they eat.
Regularity of eating equals
regularity of ghrelin secretion
equals regularity of activity
of these AgRP neurons,
meaning you'll be hungry
at very regular intervals.
So that's something
that you can work with,
it's grounded in deep mechanism
of hormone and neural systems,
and there's a lot of modern research
to support what I just said.
So, if MSH inhibits feeding,
makes us want to eat less
and ghrelin makes us want to eat more,
there's another hormone
called CCK, Cholecystokinin,
that is potent in reducing
our levels of hunger.
Now, I learned about CCK back
when I was an undergraduate.
So, well over 20 years ago,
when it was first discovered.
And there was a lot of excitement
about CCK at that point
as a diet drug.
You know, anytime there's a molecule
or a chemical discovered
in the brain or body
that can suppress feeding, the
diet industry just goes wild
and they think, this is
going to be the thing
that's going to allow people
to move from being obese
to losing all sorts of
unhealthy weight, et cetera.
A similar phenomenon was
observed with leptin.
Leptin is a hormone
that's made by body fat
that signals to the brain when
there's a lot of body fat,
and in animals injections of leptin
can make fat animals thin.
They lose a lot of adipose or fat.
In humans, it didn't work out that way.
It just the studies were done
and leptin was successful
in treating a certain
rare form of diabetes,
but it really wasn't very
potent as an anti-obesity drug.
Similarly, CCK has been
looked at as an obesity drug,
something to reduce obesity.
But it had some pretty
unhappy side effects
actually caused some pretty
serious side effects.
Now that's as drug.
However, CCK when released
at normal levels by your gut
has a powerful effect
in suppressing appetite
for a period of time.
And there are healthy and
direct ways to activate CCK.
Now, CCK is in the GI tract,
it's released from the GI tract.
And it's release is
governed by two things.
One is a subset of very
specialized neurons
that detect what's in the gut,
the specific contents of the gut.
And by certain elements of the mucosa,
of the mucus lining of the
gut and the gut microbiome.
So what's really interesting,
is that CCK is stimulated by fatty acids
and particular fatty acids
that we'll talk about.
Amino acids, and particular amino acids
that we'll talk about,
as well as by sugar.
Now, let's put sugar on
the shelf for a moment.
We're going to talk a lot about sugar
because if CCK inhibits
appetite and reduces feeding,
and it can be triggered by
fatty acids, amino acids,
or sugars, then you might say,
well, then in eating a lot of sugars
should make us not want to eat more,
but we all know that eating sugar
makes us want to eat far more.
That's the role of a lot of sugars.
And that has to do with
a separate mechanism
we'll talk about today.
So, which fatty acids in the gut
stimulate the release of CCK?
It turns out it's the omega-3 fatty acids,
the ones that come from
algae or krill or fish oil.
I talked about this in
the episode on nutrition
and some of the things
related to the gut microbiome.
And I'm going to revisit that now.
Omega-3 fatty acids and
Conjugated linoleic acid, CLA,
either from food or from supplements,
stimulate the release of CCK
which then reduces, or
at least blunts appetite.
And I'm not talking
about blunting appetite
to anorexic levels where you
don't want to eat at all.
I'm talking about regulating appetite
to the point where animals
and people don't over-consume.
So it's keeping appetite
at a healthy level.
The other thing that stimulates
CCK that I mentioned,
are amino acids.
So when we eat, we have
the ability to break down
different macronutrients,
you know, carbohydrates, fats
or proteins, into sugars and glucose,
that then we can convert to ATP
and all that stuff from a
Krebs cycle from high school.
We're not going to go into that today,
that's for a future episode.
But amino acids are one of the things
that we are eating for.
Amino acids both can be used as energy
through a process called gluconeogenesis,
of converting proteins into energy.
Or those amino acids can be broken down
and then rebuilt into things
like preparing, excuse me,
repairing muscle tissue
as well as other forms of cellar repair.
They're involved in all sorts of things
related to protein synthesis.
What does this mean?
If we eat the proper amino
acids at the proper levels,
if we ingest omega-3's and
CLA's, Conjugated linoleic acids
at the proper levels, or
get them from supplements,
there's a blunting of appetite.
Appetite is kept clamped and
we don't become hyperphagic.
We don't overeat.
We tend to eat within
healthy or normal ranges.
So this is very important,
because most people don't
understand that when we're eating,
we are basically fat foraging
and amino acid foraging.
And there are several
studies now have shown,
that people and animals
will essentially eat
until they feel they've
consumed enough omega-3's,
omega-6's, CLA's, and certain amino acids.
In other words, even
if it's not conscious,
we are eating until we
trigger the activation of CCK.
Now, there are other reasons
why we shut down eating too.
Are literally, the volume of
food in our gut can be large,
and we can feel very distended.
That's the physical reason obviously.
There are other reasons,
maybe we just have top-down control.
We have knowledge that
this is the end of the meal
and we stop 'cause we
have to go back to work
or to a meeting, or we tell
ourselves we've had enough.
But at a subconscious level,
the gut is informing the brain
via CCK and other mechanisms
when we've ingested
enough of what we need.
And these omega-3's and
CLA's and certain amino acids
are vital for sending out that
signal that we've had enough.
Now, which amino acids is
actually really interesting?
We have essential amino acids
and we have non-essential amino acids.
Among the essential amino acids,
there's one in particular
that can trigger the release
of CCK very potently,
and that's glutamine.
Glutamine is a very
interesting amino acid.
First of all, it's been
shown in a few studies
to play a role in bolstering
the immune system.
It can increase the number of killer cells
in the immune system.
It is consumed but in supplement form.
You know, people can take it.
You know, a teaspoon of glutamine
or some people take
glutamine throughout the day,
if they're really into it
or for whatever reason,
they think they're
battling off an infection
or something of that sort.
Glutamine can also of course
be derived from foods.
And you can just put into the Internet,
do an Internet search
and find out what foods
are rich with glutamine.
Some of the ones that I'm
aware of off the top of my head
are like cottage cheese,
and things of that sort.
But other foods have glutamine as well.
Once a threshold level of glutamine
and other essential
amino acids are reached,
once the threshold level of
these Alpha-3, excuse me,
Omega-3 fatty acids and CLA's
are reached, CCK is released,
and it helps reduce the activity
of those AgRP neurons
that promote feeding.
So as you can see, feeding is an interplay
between brain and body.
And it's some of the micronutrients
and even the breakdown
of particular nutrients,
that's putting the accelerator
or the brake on the feeding process.
It's not just one thing.
So from an actionable standpoint,
you, we should probably all
be trying to get our omega-3,
Omega-6 ratios correct anyway,
because they are antidepressant.
I talked about the peer
reviewed studies on that.
They are healthy for the gut microbiome,
and we should be seeking
sufficient glutamine.
Now, whether or not you decide
to supplement with glutamine
or not, is up to you.
One of the reasons why
one might want to do that,
and again, you should
always check with a doctor,
especially if you have any
predisposition to cancers
or you have cancer, many cancers
and tumors like glutamine,
so that's something to note.
But one reason why you might
want to supplement with glutamine
or consider eating foods
that are rich in glutamine,
isn't just to keep your
appetite in healthy ranges,
but as well, glutamine can
actually reduce sugar cravings.
So this is very interesting.
I have a friend, he's an absolute
chocolate, sweets addict.
He's a grown adult, but he
eats candy and chocolate
as if he was like a 14 year old kid
hanging out at the
local convenience store.
It's really incredible.
And he has probably a sugar addiction,
but he's very aware of this
and he's managed to kick
all other addictions.
So, for whatever reason, it
stimulates his brain and body
in the ways that make him
want more, but he hates this.
It's actually quite frustrating for him.
He's somebody who cares
a lot about his health.
He took the approach that I
know many other people have
who know about this role of glutamine,
of taking a teaspoon
or a couple of teaspoons of glutamine
several times throughout the
day or anytime he craves sugar.
And indeed, glutamine, well,
reduced sugar cravings.
Some people who are really on
the kind of ketogenic front,
will mix it with a little
bit of half and half
and down that,
and because I guess it
makes it taste better,
it's a little bit chalky.
So, glutamine has some very
interesting properties.
But I think for most people
that aren't suffering from
adverse levels of craving,
making sure you're getting
the right omega-3's
that can come from a variety of sources,
check out the episode we did on nutrition
if you want to learn more about that.
And CLA's, and making sure
that you're getting enough glutamine
is going to be important for making sure
that the CCK signal gets through.
The one thing I do want to
mention about glutamine,
it's a minor effect, but it
alone can have a small increase,
excuse me, it alone can
increase blood sugar.
It's not a huge increase in blood glucose.
But because the gut takes proteins
and breaks them down
into these amino acids,
and essentially looking for
glutamine and things like it,
other essential amino acids as well.
When you ingest glutamine
or branch chain amino acids,
there is a small but real
increase in blood glucose.
And that's because they
are essentially food.
And there I'm talking about
the supplemental version.
So, just know glutamine can
increase blood sugar slightly,
especially diabetics should know that.
It can reduce sugar cravings.
And just know that what your
gut is doing at a core level
is it's forging, it's waiting,
and it's trying to assess
levels of omega-3 fatty acid,
conjugated linoleic acid,
and glutamine, and other
essential amino acids.
You are essentially trying
to eat to get these nutrients
and then a signal can be
deployed up to your brain,
that you're not really interested
in eating that much more.
Whenever preparing an
episode for this podcast
I'm always faced with
a particular challenge,
which is, how many tools should I offer
that involve doing something new?
You know, a new behavior,
a new exercise, supplement,
something, things of that sort.
And how many should be
related to not doing things,
avoiding things.
It's never really fun to talk about
all the things that
we're supposed to avoid,
but some of them are so powerful
in light of the mechanisms
of a given topic
that I'd be remiss if
I didn't mention them.
So now you understand how hormones,
and peptides like CCK and
ghrelin impact appetite.
There's one particular aspect of food
that can powerfully impact CCK.
And I think most people,
I'm guessing 99.9% of people out there
are not aware of this.
And it has to do with
highly processed foods.
There's a lot of reasons
why one would want to avoid
highly processed foods.
In fact, if you're
interested in that topic
and the history of whole foods,
transitioning to highly
processed foods in this country,
I highly recommend you
listen to a YouTube video
by Dr. Robert Lustig,
he's at university of
California, San Francisco.
It's very easy to find, put
Stanford, Robert Lustig,
it was a talk hosted by Stanford.
Gives a a beautiful description
of the history of this,
and why the food industry
started packing in
additional sugars and salts,
and turning foods into commodities,
it's really fascinating.
It has no conspiracy theory
is just all scientific facts.
It's really a wonderful lecture.
It has millions of views, it
should be very easy to find.
We can provide a link
to that, and we will.
There's another reason
to avoid highly processed foods however,
and that has to do with
what's called emulsifiers.
Now, many of you are
familiar with emulsifiers,
even though you don't know it.
When you put detergent in the laundry
that contains emulsifiers,
the goal of that detergent
is to bring together fatty
molecules with water molecules
and be able to dissociate
them and break them up
to get the stains out of
clothes and things of that sort.
There are a lot of emulsifiers
put into processed foods.
And those emulsifiers allow
certain chemical reactions
to occur that extends the
shelf life of those foods.
So it's like candy bars and cereals,
and all sorts of things
that are in processed foods.
The worst of which are the
typical kind of pastries
that you see at the convenience store.
But this extends into
chips of various kinds
and even some meats of various kinds,
they pack this stuff into meats.
They have names like soy
lecithin and other things.
Why are emulsifiers bad?
Okay, there are a lot of
reasons why they're bad,
but the reason why they're bad
for the mechanisms that we've
been talking about today,
is that when you ingest those foods,
you're bringing those
emulsifiers into your gut.
And those emulsifiers strip away
the mucosal lining of the gut,
and they actually cause the
neurons that innervate the gut,
that extend those little processes
we call axons into the gut, to
retract deeper into the gut.
And as a consequence, you're
ingesting a bunch of food
and the signals like
CCK never get deployed.
The signals that actually shut down hunger
are never actually triggered.
And so, as a consequence
you want to eat far more
of these highly processed foods.
In addition, if you then go
from eating a highly processed food
to non highly processed foods,
you're not able to measure
the amounts of amino acids,
sugars, and fatty acids in
those foods as accurately.
You've actually done structural
damage at a micro level,
but structural level damage, excuse me,
to the mucosal lining of the gut.
Now, this can all be repaired
if you stay away from
highly processed foods
for some period of time.
But the negative effects
of these emulsifiers
are quite real.
So, to make it really clean and simple,
emulsifiers from highly processed foods
are limiting your guts ability
to detect what's in the foods you eat
and therefore to deploy
the satiety signals,
the signals that shut down hunger.
In addition to that, there's
a parallel mechanism at play,
that I talked about in a previous episode
but I'll remind you again, that
you have neurons in your gut
that are sensing sugar,
and are sending a subconscious
signal up to the brain
via the vagus nerve.
And those neurons trigger
the release of dopamine,
which makes you crave more of that food.
So now you've got parallel signals
making you want to eat more sugar,
making you unaware of how
much sugar you've eaten,
and that are disrupting the
inputs to the nervous system
that signal to the rest
of your brain and body
that you've obtained enough fatty acids
and you've obtained enough amino acids.
So these highly processed
foods are really terrible.
And you know, I'm not out here to say,
you know, never enjoy a
processed food of any kind,
I'd be a hypocrite 'cause
I do eat processed foods
from time to time.
Although the ones that I tend to eat,
I try and make of the healthier variety.
But eating whole foods
has tremendous value
and eating highly processed food
has tremendous negative impact on the gut
and on the gut brain axis.
And so, recently there
was a paper that came out
in Cell, Cell Press journal,
it's kind of the apex of Cell journals,
which is a phenomenal.
This paper showed that,
ingesting highly processed food
leads to more intake of not
just highly processed foods
but other types of food in general.
There was kind of an
overeating compensation
generally across foods
for people that consume
these highly processed foods.
And there are a lot of other reasons
to avoid highly processed foods.
So again, I don't like to
focus too much on the do nots,
I like to arm you with tools to do.
But I think this visual of certain foods
and these emulsifiers
actually stripping away
some of the critical lining of your gut
and disrupting the hormone
signaling to the brain
controlling feeding, is important
enough and cryptic enough,
meaning it hasn't been talked about,
it works at a subconscious level,
and that it's important
that people are aware of it
so they can make decisions
about what they do want to eat
or not want to eat for themselves.
Before moving on, I just
want to say one more thing
about highly processed foods.
There was an absolutely beautiful study
done by my colleague,
Chris Gardner at Stanford,
exploring whether or not
certain diets were better than others.
They looked at vegan,
vegetarian, omnivore,
I don't know if they
looked at all meat or not,
but they looked at the
different forms of diets,
intermittent fasting, et cetera.
And they essentially found that,
whichever diet people adhered to,
whichever one they followed,
was equivalent to the others.
Provided that they followed it,
they lost the equivalent amount of weight.
There really wasn't a strong
effect of the food type
or the pattern of eating, et cetera.
However, in a study like that,
adherence is very high because
people are a part of a study.
And for many people,
the ability to adhere
to a certain eating plan
is one of the most, if not
the most powerful determinants
of whether or not a given diet
meaning nutritional plan works.
Now, this thing about highly
processed foods however,
is really diabolical.
Because it truly says,
and I think the recent
data in cell metabolism
and other journals really proves that,
a calorie is not a calorie.
That's absolutely absurd
because of these emulsifiers
and the contents of these
highly processed foods.
In fact, the data in
humans points to this.
So what they did is they
took in-patient adults,
so they had total control
over their food intake.
And they received either ultra processed
or unprocessed diets for
14 days, as a short study.
The diets were matched
for calories, sugar,
fat, fiber, and macronutrients.
So everything else was matched.
Just processed or non-processed
is the major variable.
And basically what they found,
is that the people who are
eating the processed food diet
happened to eat much more, right?
This was after this period of
putting them on either diet
and clamping for all other variables.
Then they would eat much more,
and the body weight
changes were much more.
And those body weight changes,
were such that they
couldn't be accounted for
by just increased calories.
So, the bottom line is
that highly processed foods
are just bad for you.
They increase weight gain.
They disrupt the lining of your gut
in a way that disrupts things like CCK
and proper satiety signals.
And they contain a bunch of
things, in particular sugars,
but other things as well,
that disrupt not just the hormonal systems
but also the neural systems
that control the desire to eat
after the diet is done.
So there's just so many reasons
why these highly processed
foods are terrible,
and they can explain a lot
of the ill health effects
that we've seen in the last 50 years
not just in the United States,
but all over the world.
That enormous increase in
diabetes, juvenile diabetes.
It's just remarkable
how far down the path of diet we've gone.
And it's clear, it's almost a smoking gun
what the cause of this is.
If you'd like to learn more about that
please refer to the Lustig lecture.
He also spells out why non-processed foods
is far more economical in terms of
just at the level of the
household or individual
as well as at the societal level.
Really interesting stuff,
I highly recommend you check it out.
So now let's move on
to some other hormones
that regulate hunger and
satiety, in particular insulin.
Now, you've probably
heard of insulin before.
Insulin is the thing that's
lacking in type I diabetics,
that's why they have to inject
insulin whenever they eat.
The reason they have to do
that, is because when they eat
their foods are broken down into glucose.
And in order to shuttle glucose
to the appropriate tissues in the body,
and also to keep glucose levels
in check, you need insulin.
So the simplest way to think
about insulin and glucose
is that when you eat, that food
is broken down into sugars,
that's true whether or not
it's fats or it's sugars,
or eventually if it's proteins,
they are oxidized into fuels as we say.
And those fuels can be used
as the name fuel implies into energy,
they're eventually made into ATP.
There's a bunch of biochemical steps there
we're not going to go into today,
but that's essentially how it works.
You break down food into glucose.
Now, if you're ketogenic,
we'll talk about that in a little bit.
But in general, you eat,
food is turned into glucose.
Your blood sugar needs to be
kept in a particular range.
Hypoglycemic means too low,
hyperglycemic means too high.
And what they called
euglycemic E-U, glycemic,
is the healthy range.
Now, what those healthy ranges are,
in general the healthy
range, the euglycemic range,
is about 70 to a hundred
nanograms per deciliter.
But most of you aren't walking around
with a glucose monitor.
Some of you are, but most of you are not.
The more important question
for us to address right now,
is why is it important
that glucose be kept
at a particular level?
Once you understand that,
keeping glucose in check
starts to have a rationale behind it
and the ways to do that start
to make a lot more sense.
So the reason is, if
glucose levels get too high
because of the way that our
cells in particular neurons,
interact with glucose,
high levels of glucose can damage neurons.
It can actually kill them.
You can start getting what
are called peripheral,
excuse me, neuropathies.
One of the symptoms of
some forms of diabetes
is that people start losing
the sensation of touch
in their fingers or their
hands or their feet,
and they can start going blind.
There's diabetic retinopathies.
So it's very important,
that insulin manage your glucose levels.
Now, there's also type II diabetes
where there's insulin
secreted from the pancreas,
but people are insulin insensitive.
There's a disruption in the receptors
and insulin insensitivity
isn't quite the same
as having no insulin at all,
but it parallels some
of the same mechanisms.
Now, type I diabetes is often picked up
because someone has a sudden weight loss,
because they're not processing blood sugar
the same way they were before.
Type II diabetes is often,
although not always associated
with being overweight
and with obesity.
Both of them are challenging conditions.
Type II diabetes almost
always can be managed
by managing one's weight.
And of course there are
prescription drugs and supplements
that can help manage those.
We're going to talk about all of that.
But for most people that
don't have diabetes,
the important thing is to manage glucose,
to keep it in that euglycemic range.
And there are a number of
different ways to do that.
Some of them are behavioral,
some of them are diet based,
and some of them are based on supplements
or prescription drugs.
So let's talk about those now.
So if you eat, and in particular
if you eat carbohydrates,
blood glucose goes up.
If you eat fats, blood glucose
goes up to a far less degree.
And if you eat proteins,
depending on the protein,
it will eventually be broken down for fuel
or assembled into amino acid
chains for protein synthesis
and repair of other tissues
and bodily functions.
But glucose goes up and
then is kept in range.
When you are hungry, you
secrete a different hormone
and that's called glucagon.
And glucagon's main role,
is to pull stores of energy
out of the liver and the muscles.
And once those are depleted,
you'll eventually tap into body fat, okay?
So, and this is for people
that have a typical blood glucose range,
so that 70 to 100 euglycemic range.
So, the two kind of push and pull systems
that we're going to think
about now to keep this simple,
is that you have the insulin
system managing glucose,
and you've got the glucagon system
pulling energy out of
your liver and muscles
for immediate fuel.
And eventually you'll
pull fuel out of body fat
if you've been active for a very long time
and all your glycogen stores are depleted
or close to depleted.
So what does this all mean?
There's a lot of important biochemistry
and a lot of important cellar processes
involved in whether or not
your anabolic or catabolic.
Whether or not you're breaking things down
or building things up.
Let's talk about feeding
in a simpler way, however.
And let's weave the tools
to manage blood glucose,
to keep it in check, as we do that.
So, let's say you had a meal
and that meal consisted
of rice, a carbohydrate,
some meat or fish, let's
say a piece of salmon,
and some vegetable, some fibrous vegetable
like asparagus or cabbage
or something like that.
If you were to eat all of that at once,
you know, you take a bite
of one, a bite of the other,
you're going to mix it up.
You know, one of these, it
all ends up in the same place
kind of people, mix it all up.
Then you'll experience
an increase in insulin
and increase in blood glucose
that's moderately fast.
It's going to increase pretty quickly.
What's remarkable,
is that the order that you
consume each macro-nutrient
has a pretty profound influence
on the rate of insulin
and glucose secretion into the blood
and how quickly those levels rise.
So if you will make it really simple.
If you were to eat the rice first,
your glucose would rise in a sharp spike,
especially if it doesn't contain any fats
to slow the absorption.
Now, that might be good
if you're very hungry
and you want to get an
increase in glucose.
In fact, this is the reason
why you're often served bread
before meals, because it is...
And sometimes it's bread and butter,
or chips before meals or appetizers,
are designed to get your
blood glucose going up high
because big steep
increases in blood glucose
tend to promote the desire
to consume more glucose.
And this also relates
to the dopamine system
and the way that something
tasty in the mouth
and sugar in the gut and
fats and sugars in the mouth,
trigger the activation of a
lot of systems in the brain
and body to consume more
of whatever you have
or whatever is available to you.
So, the basic idea is
that eating carbohydrates
and/or fats early in a meal
will give a steep rise in blood glucose.
However, if you were to eat
the fibrous thing first,
so a lot of chewing, but not
a big rise in blood glucose
because in general there's...
Unless it's laid in with sugar.
Or something we're just talking about
some vegetable, fibrous vegetable,
that will actually blunt
the release of glucose
until you eat the fish and the rice.
But believe it or not
it will actually blunt
the glucose increase
that the rice would cause.
Now, I'm not talking about
neurotically eating each macro-nutrient
separately in sequence.
I'm just trying to give you a picture
of what's happening ordinarily.
So what this means is,
if you feel a lot of food related anxiety,
or you feel you're one of these people
that you can kind of sense
like your blood sugar
increasing very quickly,
a lot of people can sense
this, some people can't,
has a lot to do with how well
they manage their blood sugar
as well as some of the
psychological factors.
And yes, their family
and historical reasons,
you know, I've got friends
who had a lot of siblings,
and when they sit down to eat
they have to really suppress the desire
to not beat up everyone else at the table
and take all the food.
It's sort of like not...
It's hard for them to understand
that there's plenty to go around,
because of their upbringing.
So there are psychological
top-down effects.
A lot of the psychology around food
is geared towards getting people
to be relaxed when they eat
and these sorts of things.
But these blood sugar
effects are real just cellar
and basic biochemistry
of how the body manages sugars
ingested into the blood.
So what does this all mean?
It means that if you want a
steep increase in glucose,
you are very, very hungry,
then you should eat the
carbohydrate laid in food first,
or you should eat a bunch
of macronutrients combined.
So that would be like the
hamburger or the sandwich,
the bread, the whatever's
in that sandwich altogether,
usually that's protein
and vegetables as well.
If you want to have a more
modest increase in glucose
or you want to blunt
the increase in glucose,
then have the, at least some
of the fibrous thing first,
and then the protein and
then the carbohydrate.
You will notice that your blood glucose
will rise more steadily,
and that you'll achieve
satiety earlier in the meal.
Or at least you won't get this huge peak
at sort of the Thanksgiving meal effect.
Some of you are international,
so if you don't celebrate Thanksgiving
is a time of year where...
It used to be the one-time
a year or two times a year
where Americans would
give themselves permission
to eat enormous meals.
Now that seems to happen a lot more often.
But there is this effect of you're full
and yet you're hungry for more,
that's because your blood
glucose has gone through the roof
and it's triggered a
number of other mechanisms.
There's also usually a lot
of alcohol consumption,
and alcohol itself because it's a sugar
will increase blood
glucose very, very sharply.
It depends on the alcohol,
some alcohols have more sugar than others.
But basically what you're trying to avoid
are steep increases in blood sugar.
And the order that you eat foods
has an enormous impact on that.
The other thing that
has an enormous impact
on how long and shallow,
or how steep that curve of glucose is,
depends on on whether or not
you recently were moving,
are moving or start moving after you eat.
So it turns out that
your blood glucose levels
can be modulated very, very
powerfully by movement.
If you did any kind of intense exercise,
or even just walking or jogging,
or cycling anything before you eat
your blood glucose levels
will be dampened somewhat.
And that has to do with the
release of something called,
some people call it GLUT4,
which sounds like glutton.
Other people call it GLUT4.
These are things that are
involved in shuttling glucose
to particular cells in the body,
namely toward muscle and glycogen stores
and away from body fat stores.
It has to do with sequestering
of glucose from the blood.
The point is that, if you're somebody
who struggles with blood sugar regulation,
in addition to getting your
body weight in a healthy range,
doing all the other sorts of things
that you should be doing,
the key thing is to try
and get some movement,
sometime as circuit meal.
Now, very few people
can actually eat and
walk at the same time,
although I do it all the time.
Not because I'm trying to
regulate my blood sugar
but just 'cause I tend to be busy.
I eat and drive, [mumbles] busy.
Busy if I'm not giving this podcast,
or if sleeping, I'm eating,
but except the early part
of the day when I fast.
But the bottom line here is that,
if you, for instance take a
30 minute walk after a meal,
your blood glucose will be blunted
in ways that are beneficial.
If you have exercised in the
recent hours before a meal,
that can be beneficial.
The order that you consume
foods is beneficial.
And there are a few things
that you can consume
that can also adjust blood glucose levels.
So let's talk about those,
but I thought it was
important to really tamp down
that it's not just what you eat,
we talked about that before,
but also the order that
you eat those things,
believe it or not,
whether or not you
combine macro-nutrients,
carbohydrates, proteins and
fats and fibrous vegetables.
And whether or not you've moved recently.
The higher intensity the movement,
the greater the GLUT4 increase,
and the more that the blood
glucose will be blunted
and you'll shuttle more
of that to glycogen
and muscle stores.
And even just moving after a meal,
even just a calm easy walk,
can really adjust the ways in
which blood sugar regulated
for the better.
I don't want to perseverate
on this processed foods,
hidden sugars thing too much.
But understanding now
a little bit about how
insulin and glucose work,
you can probably imagine why hidden sugars
are such an attractive thing
from the standpoint of
processed food manufacturers.
Because if they can put sugar
in that you can't even taste,
that sugar is going to
amplify the amount of glucose,
it's going to increase the
rate of glucose increase
into your bloodstream
and it's going to promote more feeding.
So in that case, you're
really being tricked.
It's not that you're actually reaching
for the additional appetizer
and your blood glucose is going up.
The food that you ate
is actually increasing your
appetite as you eat it.
It's a positive feedback loop.
So don't want to demonize those
any more than I already have,
but you should be aware that
these things are happening
at the level of your
bloodstream and brain.
The other thing I'd like
to address for a moment,
is this notion of stable blood sugar
versus lay bile blood sugar
or unstable blood sugar.
Some people just have stable blood sugar.
They can go long periods
of time without eating
and feel fine.
Other people get really
shaky, really jittery,
and/or when they do eat,
they feel really keyed up.
Sometimes they'll even sweat.
Sometimes their vision will go blurry.
And some of that can actually be
because they've become hyperglycemic.
And those effects that you experience
when you are hyperglycemic
are the early warning signs
of the kinds of things that damage neurons
and lead to the really terrible stuff
they talked about before
like peripheral neuropathies.
Now, it takes some time
for those things to occur,
those neuropathies to occur.
But whether or not your blood
sugar is all over the place
or whether or not stable,
can be impacted by a number of things.
One of those things is exercise.
So these days there's a lot of interest
in what they call zone two cardio,
which is that kind of steady state cardio,
where you can just nasal breathe
even at pretty high output,
where you could maybe have a conversation.
Although I'm such a huge proponent
of nasal breathing during exercise,
most forms of exercise
especially zone two cardio,
that you probably shouldn't be talking
while you're doing that cardio
unless it's absolutely essential.
But periods of zone two cardio
that lasts anywhere from
30 minutes to an hour
or sometimes more for
your endurance athletes,
can create positive effects
on blood sugar regulation,
such that you people can sit
down and enjoy whatever it is,
the hot fudge sundae,
or whatever the high
sugar content food is.
And blood glucose management is so good.
Your insulin sensitivity is so
high, which is a good thing,
that you can manage that blood glucose
to the point where it doesn't
really make you shaky,
it doesn't disrupt you.
And you know, to say nothing
of the weight-related issues
or the adipose fat gain, et cetera,
that's a separate issue
because people vary there.
But basically doing zone two
cardio for 30 to 60 minutes,
three to four times a week
makes your blood sugar really stable,
and that's an attractive thing
for a variety of reasons.
On the flip side, high
intensity interval training
or resistance training
AKA weight training,
are very good at stimulating
the various molecules
that promote repackaging of glycogen.
So sprints, heavy weight lifting,
circuit type weightlifting
provided there is some
reasonable degree of resistance,
those are going to trigger
are all sorts of mechanisms
that are going to encourage the body
to shuttle glucose back into glycogen,
converting to glycogen,
into muscle tissue,
restock the liver, et cetera.
Depleting one's glycogen
actually takes some time.
You know, if you do a couple
sets of tricep extensions
and some crunches, you're
not depleting your glycogen.
Glycogen depleting workouts
are very high intensity.
Generally they're less than an hour or so,
but those are the sort
that are going to lead to big increases
in the kinds of enzymes
and metabolic pathways
that are going to repack
glycogen and shuttle most things
towards restorage of foods
not into adipose tissue, not into fat,
but taking glucose and
making it into fuels
that you can access later
for more of that high intensity activity.
And I should mention that
one of the advantages
of high intensity interval training
or weightlifting of various kinds,
is that it causes long standing increases
in basal metabolic rate.
I don't want to go too far down this path
because we're going to do an entire month
on human performance and
athletic performance.
But it's not just the increases in muscle
that increase metabolism,
because muscle burns more energy
than other types of tissues,
except your brain, which
truly burns the most energy.
Anyway is the main reason
why your basal metabolic
rate is what it is.
Well, high-intensity training.
So it could be sprints,
it could be high intensity
interval training
of different kinds, it
could be weight training,
also has an effect of
increasing thermogenesis
even long after you've
completed the exercise.
So there's a long tail.
There's a kind of post
exercise metabolic effect
that's also beneficial.
So it's not an either or,
it's really that high
intensity interval training
and resistance training.
And things of that sort are
very good for one reason.
And the zone two cardio is
very good for other reasons.
And now you can see why
it's just a healthy thing
and why most people should
probably be doing exercise
most days of the week, if
not every day of the week.
If your goal is to manage blood glucose
and your goal is to manage
some of the metabolic factors
that control repackaging of glycogen
and encouraging excess glucose
to not get diverted into body fat stores.
We haven't talked a
lot about lipids today,
that's because most of today's
discussion is about hormones
and insulin is the dominant hormone
in terms of mobilizing and
managing glucose in the body,
at least for most people.
But fats are very important.
And there's just a little
anecdote about fats
that I think will be useful in thinking
about why you want to manage
what they call the LDL or HDL ratios.
And this is deserving an entire episode,
many, perhaps even several episodes.
But some of you may be
familiar with LDLs and HDLs,
some of you may not.
The LDL is low density lipoprotein.
This is the one that you
don't want it to be too high.
Castillo's dreaming, he's barking.
He loves all forms of cholesterol
but that's just Castillo dreaming.
So LDLs are the ones that
you want to keep low.
You don't want those
to go excessively high.
HDLs, the high density lipoproteins
are the ones that are the
so-called healthy lipoproteins.
That's all fine and good.
But you might ask yourself,
what are they doing?
What is the actual role of these things,
and why would you want
healthy levels of HDL
and not too much LDL?
Well, one of the reasons is,
that fats don't like water, right?
They are hydrophobic.
And yet you need to move
fats in your bloodstream,
all tissues in your body need fats.
They need cholesterols, they're...
In last episode we
talked about cholesterol
is a precursor to the
sex steroid hormones,
estrogen, and testosterone
and other hormones as well.
Well, HDL and LDL, actually coat fats
to allow them to be transported
through the bloodstream.
They do a number of other things as well.
But HDL, is a key component
of the delivery system
that brings those fats
to the liver, ovaries,
testes, and adrenals.
In other words, having
adequate levels of HDL is good,
because it allows fats to
be delivered to the tissues
that manufactured testosterone, estrogen,
cortisol in healthy levels and the liver.
So this is why when LDLs are too high
what's happening is
you're not getting fats
to the correct tissues.
And you can get buildup of fats
like fatty liver disease
and some of these things can happen.
A high sugar content
can even lead to some of
these fatty liver conditions
that starting to happen
is actually the first time
in human history perhaps
that we're aware of anyway.
That we're starting to
see liver conditions
that normally were associated
only with severe alcoholism
starting to come from sugar content.
So what does this mean?
This means keep your LDL
and HDL ratios proper.
You want those HDLs in order
to deliver fatty molecules
to the very tissues that use cholesterol
in order to manufacturer hormones.
So how do you keep LDLs and
HDLs in their proper ratios?
Well, a lot of people don't realize this,
but the debate about dietary cholesterol
and its relationship
to LDL and HDL ratios,
it is a barbed wire debate.
I don't want to get into it right now.
There are still a lot of open questions
as to how much dietary cholesterol
impacts LDL and HDL ratios.
I don't want to get into that now,
I'm not taking a stance either way.
But what is very clear,
is that having highly elevated glucose,
consuming too much sugar
or not managing glucose in your body
through some of the mechanisms
that we've been talking
about up until now,
can also negatively
impact LDL, HDL ratios.
So managing glucose goes way beyond
just managing blood sugar,
and making sure that you don't
lay down too much body fat,
making sure your metabolism stays high
and making sure you're not
getting jittery at meals.
It also has to do with
making sure that you're creating
enough of the molecules HDL
and not too many of the molecules LDL,
that are going to disrupt
the delivery of things
to the organs of your body
that allow you to make healthy
levels of testosterone,
estrogen, and so forth.
If that wasn't clear, let
me make this ultra simple.
You want healthy levels of HDL,
and you want low levels of LDL,
because if you have ovaries
it will allow the fats that
need to get to the ovary
to produce estrogen, to get there.
And if you have testes,
it will allow the fats
and the cholesterol
molecules that you need
in order to manufacture
testosterone to get to the testes.
As well, in order to have
proper adrenal function
and proper liver function,
you want HDL and LDL in
the healthy correct levels.
So now we've talked a lot
about behavioral tools
and the underlying biological mechanisms
that justify those tools in
particular circumstances.
Now, I'd like to turn to
supplements and prescription drugs
that regulate the hormone systems,
controlling feeding and satiety.
There are a huge number of these.
Some have more powerful
effects than others.
There are two that I want to describe
because they've been getting
a lot of attention recently.
First of all, there's a
prescription drug Metformin,
which was developed as a
treatment for diabetes.
And it works potently
to reduce blood glucose.
It has dramatic effects
in lowering blood glucose.
Metformin involves changes
to mitochondrial action
in the liver.
That's its main way of depleting
or reducing blood glucose.
And it does so through the
so-called AMPK pathway,
and it increases insulin
sensitivity overall.
Metformin is a powerful drug.
In fact, I'm surprised that so many people
have sought it out, given
that most of the people
that I'm aware of that sought
it out are not diabetic.
I think for diabetics it
seems to be a useful drug.
For non-diabetics, it can also of course,
lower blood glucose.
It also has the potential
to make people hypoglycemic,
genuinely hypoglycemic.
So, you really need to approach
Metformin with caution.
I get a little concern
when I hear about people
blasting Metformin,
simply because fasted states
or low blood sugar states
are healthy.
Doing that pharmacologically
can have long standing effects.
You really want to
approach that with caution.
Now, there's a comparable drug,
it really should be called a drug.
But it's non-prescription,
that's also in fairly
prominent use out there
called berberine, B-E-R
B-E-R-I-N-E, berberine, correct.
So berberine is a really
interesting compound.
Its actions very much mimic Metformin.
So let's talk about
berberine for a second.
Berberine actually comes from
various plants and tree bark.
It is sold in supplement
stores, it's sold online.
It is, as far as I know
unregulated, it is powerful.
If you're going to
experiment with berberine,
you definitely want to talk to your doctor
and you want to approach it with caution.
It also works to activate
the so-called AMPK pathway.
AMPK by the way stands for
Adenosine Monophosphate-activated
protein kinase, AMPK.
And it inhibits a protein
tyrosine phosphates 1B pathway.
I think that's enough nomenclature.
It activates a certain pathway
that's associated with
fasting and low blood glucose.
The effects of berberine
are as far as I can tell,
when looking at the literature,
are very similar if not
identical to Metformin.
Now, the number of studies
out there on this are many.
So I'm just going to review a few of them
and their major effects.
As always, I invite you
to check out examine.com.
It's a wonderful website
where you can put in any
supplement or compound
or biological goal for that matter.
And it will list out the various effects
in the human effect matrix.
So studies on humans,
if they're available.
And it will tell you whether
or not they're strong effects
or weak effects or modest effects.
And it will point to the
specific subject population,
it's a wonderful resource.
So berberine, not surprisingly
has very strong effects
in lowering blood glucose.
There are four studies on this.
In fact, they say that
berberine is one of the more
if not the most effective supplements
for lowering blood glucose.
It talks about dosages there.
Although I'll just mention
that I've tried berberine,
and the dosages that are
typical on the bottle
of most supplements, is
much higher than I needed.
So when I took berberine,
two things happened,
first of all, I got a
pretty splitting headache.
It gave me pretty vicious headache.
So for me it was a no, almost immediately.
The other thing is, I
became so hypoglycemic.
That in order to get
my blood sugar back up,
I think I ate something like 10 donuts
and I didn't feel like I had
ingested all that much sugar.
It was really kind of weird.
I was hyperphagic for sugar.
I was craving sugar, craving sugar
and I was very thirsty as well.
And so, I don't want to
promote any bad behavior,
but I know that certain people use this
when they've overeaten sugars
or they're doing their cheat days,
something that I'm
personally just not a fan of.
And they want to keep
their blood sugar in check
or they know they're going
to consume a huge meal.
They'll take berberine to
keep blood glucose clamped.
And it does do that.
It has very strong effects.
Three peer reviewed
studies on HbA1c levels.
HbA1c is something that can
be measured in a blood test.
That is sort of an average readout
of your blood sugar levels
over the previous two or three months,
sometimes shorter period.
But that's mostly what HbA1c is about.
So, it radically decreases
your blood sugar levels.
It actually lowers cholesterol.
It acts remember on the liver,
and the liver is involved
in cholesterol metabolism.
And remember it's both
sugars, blood glucose,
and dietary fats.
Perhaps it's still heavily debated
in terms of how your
blood total cholesterol
HDL and LDL are regulated.
So it seems to lower total cholesterol,
and it seems like it lowers
HDL and LDL in parallel.
So that's interesting.
One study showed a minor increase in HDL,
the so-called good cholesterol.
Insulin levels dropped, not surprising.
Another study showed a
slight decrease in LDL,
though seem to be kind of minor.
Here's a kind of interesting one,
just to help you remember berberine
as of the fact that it
comes from tree bark,
isn't trigger enough to remember it.
Direct contact of
berberine on canker sores
seems to eliminate canker
sores very quickly,
which is kind of cool.
I've not had canker sores in a few years
but when I dig down,
they're extremely painful.
I don't like those.
So that's kind of interesting,
and there's some study references there.
I find it amazing that
these compounds exist.
You've got this
prescription drug Metformin,
and then you've got berberine,
this stuff from tree bark,
and they have effects that
are essentially equivalent
to one another.
So again, I'm not promoting their use
or even their exploration,
but those compounds do
exist, they're out there.
And check out examine.com
if you'd like to learn more.
Certainly do your
reading, do your homework,
before you start just popping the stuff.
And if you have hypoglycemia
or hyperglycemia,
be especially careful and also
do understand that dosages
and dose requirements vary.
So if you do go down this path,
really approach things carefully.
Always start with the lowest amount
that you could get away with.
For me, the headache thing
just made it a no-go.
I do keep a bottle of
it in a full disclosure,
in the odd chance
that I feel like eating
a ton of doughnuts.
It's not so much about not
ingesting the calories,
it's just that I don't like the feeling
of being hyperglycemic,
the blurry vision, just feeling lousy,
I do love donuts.
Other things that impact blood
glucose in supplement form.
Chromium has been shown in
29 studies to have a minor,
I want to emphasize a minor
effect on reducing blood glucose.
Things like L-carnitine,
something we've talked about
here on the podcast before
in terms of its relationship
to power output in ATP production
for both aerobic and anaerobic exercise,
as well as sperm quality and egg quality.
We talked about that long ago.
Things like Panax ginseng
can have positive effects on,
I should say, can have effects
of reducing blood glucose slightly.
I don't want to give a
valence to or judgment
to whether or not it's
positive or negative.
Here's something that's interesting
that you should know about.
Caffeine has very reliably been shown
to increase blood glucose
just a little bit, okay?
So I always thought that caffeine
would drop blood glucose,
but it actually can increase
blood glucose just slightly.
Things like magnesium.
We talked about magnesium
as a tool for enhancing
the passage into sleep,
in particular magnesium
threonate and bisglycinate.
Magnesium can also have a modest
reduction in blood glucose.
You're just trying to get the impression,
everything reduces blood glucose,
but that's certainly not the case.
And then a couple episodes ago
when we were discussing nutrition
we talked about artificial
sweeteners, sucralose,
aspartame, NutraSweet.
Some of those are generic names.
Some of those might be brand names
and how they have negative
effects on the gut microbiome
and that's supported
by a number of studies.
There's one artificial sweetener,
it's stevia, S-T-E-V-I-A,
which seems to lower blood
glucose just slightly.
And I still can't find data
on whether or not Stevia
impacts the gut microbiome
in either direction.
Many of the things that I consume
do have small amounts of Stevia in them.
So I'd love to know if anyone out there
is aware of quality
peer reviewed research,
as to whether or not Stevia
impacts the gut microbiome
similarly or differently from
other artificial sweeteners.
Please let me know.
Please send me the references.
I'd really appreciate it
if put it in the comment
section on YouTube or elsewhere.
Comment section on YouTube
would be the best place.
So Stevia seems to lower
blood glucose a little bit,
which makes it kind of an
attractive artificial sweetener
if one is going to use
artificial sweeteners.
But remember, sweet taste itself
stimulates the desire to eat,
which will increase more blood glucose.
So I'm guessing that they
probably cancel each other out.
So you have to think
logically about these things.
Vitamin B3, so some of the B vitamins
do indeed stimulate appetite
by triggering increases in blood glucose,
vitamin B3 in particular.
I don't know if B6 does.
Things like zinc seem
to lower blood glucose.
And then there've been an
enormous number of other things
that have been tested for
their roles in blood glucose.
Apple cider vinegar, anything acidic.
This is well-known now
that any kind of acidity,
so it could be lemon juice or lime juice,
or Apple cider vinegar,
lowers blood glucose slightly.
Some of those can also have other effects
that we're not talking about today.
So that's kind of interesting
because there's a movement now
towards creating a sort
of people talk about
becoming more alkaline,
you know, what these...
I hate to break it to you
but you don't really want
your body to be too alkaline.
You want to stay in the right
pH or else you're start...
There are conditions that
make you more alkaline.
You don't want to be too
acidic or too alkaline.
If you see a beverage or something
that purports that ingesting that beverage
is going to make you more alkaline,
that is absolutely false.
There's no evidence for that,
is impossible biochemically.
It's just marketing.
But nonetheless ingesting
foods that are acidic
can make some slight
adjustments to the pH of the gut
in ways that can slow or
alter the absorption of foods
and can blunt blood glucose.
You can try this sometime if you want,
if ever you're feeling
kind of over sugared out
like you ate something
with too much sugar.
You can drink a small
amount of lemon juice
mixed with water or lime juice,
and you'll notice that it will blunt
that kind of hyperglycemic
effect just a little bit.
Again, you don't want to
use this as a medical tool,
but the effect is fairly potent.
And then, excuse me.
And then there are a
number of other things
like capsaicin and hot chili peppers
that will lower blood glucose.
The list goes on and on,
The most powerful one is
absolutely berberine and Metformin,
but that's really heavy caliber stuff.
And the other ones I mentioned
have more minor effects.
I do want to mention because
I'm sure some of you out there
are curious about the ketogenic diet.
I'm going to do an entire
episode about ketosis
and the brain and the body,
but the ketogenic diet has
been shown in 22 studies
to have a notable
decrease on blood glucose.
And that is not surprising,
because the essence of the ketogenic diet
is that you're consuming
very little or zero
of the foods that promote big
spikes in insulin and glucose.
If you consume enough protein,
some of that protein can
be converted into glucose,
of course, through gluconeogenesis.
But the ketogenic diet
has a very strong support
for its role in regulating
blood sugar, which is glucose.
But the specific effects
of the ketogenic diet,
and one particular effect
that I'll address later
but I'll mention now,
which is, the ability
of the ketogenic diet
to adjust thyroid hormone levels
in ways that make it
such that if you return
to eating carbohydrates
after being in ketosis for too long,
you don't manage fibroid
and carbohydrates as well,
that has been shown as well.
So we're going to dive deep into ketosis
in a future episode.
So for you ketonistas does
out there don't worry,
I certainly have nothing
against ketogenic diet.
I actually don't have anything
for against any particular nutrition plan.
I know it works for me, at
least at this stage in my life.
And I'll update it if I need to.
I'm simply trying to get
you as much information
as I possibly can,
so that you can navigate
through that landscape
in a way that's in keeping
with your particular goals.
So now you understand
a lot about blood sugar
and how it's managed,
and the ways that you can manage it better
depending on your particular needs.
This is also a good
opportunity for us to look back
at some of the medical literature,
because it really points
to just how far we've come
in terms of understanding
these important mechanisms.
And it points us in the direction
of some actionable protocols.
So diabetes, which is these
huge increases in blood glucose,
because there's no insulin,
was known about as early as 1500 BC,
which is just incredible.
And the way physicians then understood
that certain people had high blood glucose
without actually knowing
what blood glucose was,
is that they would take the
urine of particular patients,
and they'd find that ants
preferably move toward
and consume the urine of
certain patients and not others.
And they understood that there
was something in that urine
that was correlated with the weight loss
and some of the other
probably very unfortunate health symptoms
that these people were experiencing.
So they knew that there was
something in blood and urine.
But you might be asking
yourself, wait, that's urine.
But as I tell every kid
that I meet, two things.
I tell a kid, your brain is here,
I make them point to their head.
And then I tell them, do you know what?
Do you know that your urine
is actually filtered blood?
And they usually go, [grunts].
I get parental permission
to do this first.
But most adults don't realize
that your urine is actually
just filtered blood.
And that's why if you
see blood in your urine,
that's a problem.
You want to filter the blood,
but urine is filtered blood.
Now, this business of measuring
blood sugar from the urine
has been something that lasted way beyond
these early stages of 1500 BC.
It turns out that as late as 1674,
physicians at Oxford
university were figuring out
who had pathologically high
levels of blood glucose
by analyzing their urine.
And again, they were measuring
the sweetness of their urine,
and this is medical fact.
They would do this
by taking urine samples
from different patients,
and tasting them.
And they developed an intuitive sense
of what excessively sweet urine was
relative to the other
urines that they had tasted.
So for those of you that are
in the medical profession
or those of you that are seeking
out the medical profession,
do you understand this
is not done anymore?
And you can also just
reflect on how far we've come
in terms of the medical profession itself.
In our ability to measure
things from the blood
and measure things from urine
without having to ask ants
which urine is sweeter
or ask oneself, which urine is sweeter.
So indeed we are making
progress as a species.
Before we close out today I
want to talk about one more tool
that many of you will
probably find useful.
I certainly have, I'm a
big consumer of caffeine,
although I don't consume a ton of it,
I consume it very consistently.
So I'm big on consuming Mate,
which is a strong caffeinated tea.
And I generally do that early in the day.
Although I do delay about
two hours after I wake up
for reasons I've talked
about in previous episode,
to maintain that nice arc
of alertness and focus.
I do drink black coffee as
well, mushroom coffee as well,
I love that stuff.
But Mate, also called Yerba
Mate, is an interesting compound
because unlike coffee,
it has been shown to increase
something called glucagon
like peptide GLP1.
And increase leptin levels.
Now, we didn't talk a
lot about glucagon today.
Glucagon is really elevated
in the fasting state.
I mentioned that it's sort
of the opposite of insulin
in kind of rough terms
that's one way to think about it.
But GLP1, or glucagon-like peptide one,
is increased by ingesting Mate
and it acts as a pretty
nice appetite suppressant.
Now, I'm not trying to
suppress my appetite.
I like to eat as I mentioned before.
But it works really well
to stimulate the brain
and to give you a level of alertness
and to do a lot of the
things that coffee does.
It also contains electrolytes.
So we meaning our neurons and our brain
run on a variety of factors,
electrical activity and chemical
transmission, et cetera,
but they require adequate
levels of sodium potassium
and magnesium.
So, if you were to learn the biology
or the physiology of the action potential,
the firing of a neuron,
something we teach every first
year neuroscience student,
and I'd be happy to teach
you if you're interested.
You'll hear about sodium
rushing into cells
and potassium entering and leaving cells
in order to allow neurons to communicate.
Electrolytes are critically important
for the function of the nervous system.
And many things that act as diuretics,
that promote excretion
of water, like caffeine,
can also take electrolytes out along
with in particular sodium.
And sometimes the lightheadedness
or the brain fog that people experience,
isn't just because electrolytes are low
but because they're
kind of out of balance.
So I like Mate because it has
electrolytes, it has caffeine.
It stimulates the release of
this glucagon-like peptide
GLP1, and it's been a big help to me
in extending that early
morning fasting window
out to about noon or so
when I eat my first meal.
It also just tastes really good.
I don't drink it out of the gourd
even though I have Argentine lineage.
The gourd to me it's just
kind of an inconvenience,
I drink it out of a mug.
There's no promotion here.
I have no relationship to
any Yerba Mate plantations
or companies, I just happen
to really like the stuff.
And the fact that glucagon-like
peptide one is enriched
or is released more when you drink Mate.
And the fact that GLP1
can regulate blood sugar
in ways that keep your blood sugar
in that we called euglycemic,
not too high, not too low mode,
is one reason why ingesting
Mate is attractive to me.
If you go to South America,
well, you'll see especially
among Oregonians,
but also Argentines, is
people actually carry
a thermos of this stuff with them around
and bring it to meals in restaurants.
And it's just considered
cultural convention,
it's not unusual to see that.
So we don't see that so
much here in the States
but I happen to really love this stuff.
I brew my own,
because that's the most
economical way to do it.
And I really enjoy it.
It can be a little bitter for some people.
The real key there if you want to know,
the Mate trick is to not use water
that's really boiling hot.
You go just shy of boil
and then it doesn't have that
same kind of tobacco like
or really acidic flavor to it.
It's just a little bit sweeter,
although not quite sweet.
So, Yerba Meta GLP1, can
manage in healthy ways
leptin levels, glucose
levels, and glucagon levels
in ways that if it serves you,
that you might want to try.
So once again, we covered an
enormous amount of material,
focused on how hormones
regulate feeding, hunger,
and when one feels they don't need to eat,
so-called satiety, that you've had enough.
As always, we covered a lot,
but I could not be exhaustive
about all the information
related to this topic.
It's just so vast.
For instance, we did not
talk about thyroid hormone,
an extremely important hormone and pathway
in the body and brain.
We are going to do an
episode related to thyroid
and tools to regulate thyroid, I promise.
Having seen this episode,
you will be able to digest that
material with far more ease.
We also didn't talk about the fact that
testosterone and estrogen
can impact blood glucose
in ways that are opposite to one another.
That when estrogen levels are high,
appetite tends to be reduced.
When testosterone levels are high,
appetite tends to increase.
So there are all sorts
of interesting interplays
between the various hormones.
But that's too much of a deep dive of now.
Right now, we've just focused today mainly
on things like ghrelin, on things like,
Melanocyte simulating hormone,
incredible powerful hormone
that can suppress appetite.
On things like Cholecystokinin
that comes from the gut
and can suppress appetite.
On things like food emulsifiers.
On the fact that when you're eating
you are amino acids seeking,
even though you might not realize it.
That you are also seeking
out particular fatty acids
in particular, the conjugated
linoleic acids and Omega-3's.
So I've tried to give you a
number of actionable tools.
Many of them behavioral.
Some of them are based on supplements
or even prescription drugs.
Again, always do what's
best for your health,
and do that in company with
a healthcare professional.
I'm not a physician, I
don't prescribe anything.
I'm a professor, I
profess a lot of things.
And I try and share with you
what I think to be the best
high quality peer reviewed literature.
So that's what I've done today.
Really appreciate your time and intention.
Many of you have continued to ask
how you can help support the podcast.
And we really appreciate the question.
There's several ways to do that.
The first is to like a
video that you've seen
if you like it, and please
subscribe to the YouTube channel.
That's perhaps the most important thing
about the YouTube channel.
As well, leave us a comment.
If you leave us a comment
in the comment section
that helps us.
And please ask questions.
Those questions and your comments
do inform content of future episodes.
We read them all.
Except the negative ones we don't read,
I'm just kidding, we read them all.
In addition, please subscribe
on Apple and/or Spotify
or both if you like.
And on Apple, you have the
opportunity to leave us
up to a five star review if
you feel we deserve that.
Apple also lets you leave a comment,
some feedback for us as well.
Please do check out our sponsors
that we mentioned at the
beginning of the podcast.
That's the best way perhaps
to support the podcast.
As well we have a Patreon account.
It's patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
And there you can support the
podcast at any level you like.
And today, as well as
in previous episodes,
I've mentioned various supplements.
If you're interested in
seeing what supplements I take
and you want to explore for
some other supplements as well,
you can go to Thorne
T-H-O-R-N-E.com slash U, the
letter U, slash Huberman.
Thorne is a supplement company
that we believe to have
the highest stringency
in terms of what they put
in the various supplements that they make.
And the amounts that they
put are very accurate.
They've partnered with the Mayo Clinic.
They partnered with all
the major sports teams.
And we've partnered with them
because we believe in
their levels of stringency
and accuracy.
If you go to thorne.com/u/huberman,
you can see what I take
and you'll also get 20% off
any of those supplements
or any of the other
supplements that Thorne makes.
So that's where you can find
out more about supplements
and the ones that I take.
And again, you get the 20% discount
on any supplements that Thorne makes.
And last but not least,
thank you for being with us.
I hope you learned a lot.
I hope you explore some of the tools
and that the mechanistic
information that you learned today
will serve you well.
If you know anyone that's
interested in this topic
or you think that someone
could benefit from it,
please suggest the
podcast to them as well.
And most of all, thank you
for your interest in science.
[upbeat music]