- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
[guitar music]
I'm Andrew Huberman, and I'm
a professor of neurobiology
and ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Four Sigmatic.
Four Sigmatic is a wellness company
that makes mushroom coffee.
And if you're asking yourself,
why would you want to
put mushrooms in coffee?
First of all, let me tell you
these are not psychedelic
mushrooms and no,
the coffee doesn't taste like mushrooms.
The coffee is delicious
and you don't taste mushrooms at all.
I know this because I've been
using Four Sigmatic coffee
and been stocking it in my
laboratory for several years now
long before I ever had the podcast
or Four Sigmatic was a sponsor.
The two kinds of mushrooms that
are in Four Sigmatic coffee
our lion's mane and chaga mushrooms,
both of which have been shown
to have a slight anxiolytic
effect to reduce anxiety.
And lion's mane has also been shown
in several studies to lower the symptoms
of depression just slightly.
Although I wouldn't consider
it a treatment for depression,
that's an attractive benefit,
as well as have some effect at
offsetting cognitive decline.
Albeit slightly, the effects were real
in the studies that I've found.
So if you'd like to try Four Sigmatic,
you can go to foursigmatic.com/huberman.
That's F-O-U-R-S-I-G M-A-T-I-C
dot com slash Huberman.
And if you do that, you'll
get 40% off your order
plus free shipping on
mushroom coffee bundles.
That's foursigmatic.com/huberman
for up to 40% off and free shipping.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Blinkist.
Blinkist is an app that has thousands
of nonfiction books condensed
down to just 15 minutes
of key takeaways that you
can read or listen to.
I'm a big reader and I'm a
big consumer of nonfiction.
And most of the time I consume books
in their traditional form like a book
where you flip the pages and so forth.
I also listen to full length audio books.
However, over time we know
that we forget lots of things.
And even though sometimes I think
I got all the critical
information from a book,
when I listen to Blinkist and
I get the 15-minute rundown,
either an audio or in written form,
what I find is there key points
that oftentimes I missed.
And so it's a great way for
me to both jog my memory
and to bring forward ideas
that I hadn't considered previously.
They have thousands of nonfiction titles
and some really terrific
ones in the science category.
For example, David
Eagleman's book "Livewired"
which came out recently as a
book I read in full length form
and I've listened to the
Blinkist version of it as well.
"Livewired" is a book
about neuroplasticity.
The brain's ability to change
in response to experience.
I get so many questions and requests
for books about neuroplasticity.
In my opinion, "Livewired"
is the most recent
and up-to-date and the best one to date.
So that's there.
David Sinclair's book "Lifespan."
David, as many of you know,
is a professor of genetics
at Harvard Medical School.
"Lifespan" is this terrific
book about aging as a disease
and the future and present
of longevity treatments.
Very interesting book.
As well as Matt Walker's
book, "Why We Sleep."
Matt, of course, is a
professor at UC Berkeley
and "Why We Sleep" is a terrific book
about why we sleep, the
science of sleeping,
and things you can do
to improve your sleep.
All of those are on Blinkist.
But with Blinkist you get unlimited access
to their massive library of nonfiction.
If you'd like to try Blinkist,
right now they have a special
offer just for our audience,
just for Huberman Lab Podcast listeners.
You can go to blinkist.com/huberman
and you can try Blinkist
free for seven days,
so that's zero cost,
and you'll get 25% off
your new subscription.
That's Blinkist, B-L-I-N-K-I-S-T
dot com slash Huberman
to get a free seven day trial
and get saved 25% off when you sign up
but only if you go to
blinkist.com/huberman.
This episode is also
brought to us by Munk Pack.
Munk Pack is a company that
makes keto-friendly snacks
that taste incredible
but have just one gram of sugar or less.
As I've said before on this
podcast, I am not in ketosis.
I'm not ketogenic.
I don't advocate or follow
any one particular diet.
For me, what works is to fast
in the early part of the day
and to eat low carb and
keto-ish throughout the day.
That's for alertness and attention.
So I can work and focus
and I don't feel sluggish or brain fog.
And then at night and in the evening
is when I tend to eat my carbohydrates
to aid the transition to sleep.
That's what works for me.
Munk Pack bars are a terrific snack
whether or not you're keto all the time,
whether or not you're low carb,
or even if you're not, they
are absolutely delicious.
And I don't say that lightly.
I'm not a big fan of bars in general.
Most bars to me tastes like
a combination of, you know,
a metal bumper mixed with some cardboard
and some lawn trimmings
and some artificial sugar.
Munk Pack bars, when they were sent to me,
I was like, all right, I'll try them.
I tried it.
Like, uh-oh, this is a problem
'cause I liked them very, very much.
And when I say it's a problem,
it really is a problem.
I actually keep the Munk
Pack boxes in my basement
so that I don't tear
through them all at once.
I'm a huge fan of the
caramel sea salt flavor.
It's delicious.
Just talking about it
makes me hungry for one.
But they also have sea salt,
dark chocolate, peanut
butter dark chocolate.
They're terrific.
In addition to being keto-friendly,
they're also gluten-free, plant-based,
non-GMO, no soy, trans fat,
sugar alcohols or artificial colors.
So all the bad stuff that you don't want.
And as I mentioned before, they're keto,
less than one gram of sugar.
If you want to try Munk Pack,
you can go to munkpack.com.
That's M-U-N-K Pack dot com.
And enter the code Huberman at checkout
and you'll get 20% off your first purchase
of any Munk Pack product.
That's M-U-N-K-P-A-C-K dot com
and enter the code Huberman
at checkout to get 20% off your purchase.
This month, we've been
talking all about hormones,
which are these absolutely
incredible chemicals
in our brain and body.
They impact our entire lifespan.
So from the time that we are in the womb,
they're controlling the development
of our brain and our bodies.
After we are born,
they're still controlling
the development of our brain and bodies.
And I did say development,
and that's because, contrary
to what most people think,
development lasts the entire lifespan.
From the time you're conceived
until the time you die,
you are developing, you are changing.
And hormones are constantly
updating and changing
the different functions of your body.
They have two major kinds of effects.
One are immediate effects,
so they can actually bind to
or kind of park in parking spots on cells
and impact all sorts of things
like the growth of cells, et cetera.
They also can control gene expression.
This is the way that
hormones during puberty
control body hair growth
and breast development
and growth of muscles and limbs and height
and all sorts of things.
They are incredible.
We've talked about
testosterone and estrogen.
We talked about insulin and glucagon
and some of the other things.
Today, we are going to
talk about metabolism.
Mainly going to talk about thyroid hormone
and growth hormone and some
other related pathways.
I'm going to explain to you the logic
of how thyroid hormone
and growth hormone work.
It will become obvious
why I've paired thyroid
and growth hormone together
in the same episode.
And I will of course talk about tools
that you can use to elevate
or reduce thyroid hormone.
There are cases where people
want to reduce thyroid hormone.
I will talk about tools that you can use
to elevate growth hormone.
There are rare cases where people
want to reduce growth hormone.
Most people are interested
in increasing growth hormone.
So today is going to be
rich with information,
rich with actionable tools.
And as always, the idea is to spell out
an organizational logic
so you can come away
from this episode and in fact
the entire month on hormones,
really understanding at some level
what these things we call
hormones are and how they work.
And that's really to arm
you to encounter information
going forward, whether
or not it comes from me
or from somebody else, a book or a course,
someplace else online to
make sense of how to work
with these incredible
chemicals we call hormones.
Before we begin to talk about
thyroid and growth hormone
and how our metabolism works
and how to control metabolism,
I want to answer a few
questions that I received
from you from the audience.
Every once in a while,
someone will send me a
quite earnest question
about something they saw on the internet.
And one of the things I've
heard about quite a bit
in the last couple of
weeks as we've been talking
about hormones and food
intake and how those interact
is this question of are certain foods
particularly good for
certain organs of the body?
And can that be predicted
on the basis of the shape of those foods?
So first of all, I want to
acknowledge the question
as a valid one, because I see this
every once in a while out there.
People will say, well, you know,
walnuts are in the shape of the brain
and therefore they are good
for your brain or, you know,
a particular fruit like the
beet often looks like a heart
and it's good for your heart.
And I certainly invite
questions of all kinds,
provided they're sincere questions.
However, I am not aware
of any science whatsoever
supporting the idea that
the shape of a given food
or object for that matter is relevant
to its functional role in the
body in reference to biology.
Now, beets contain something
that we're going to talk about today.
They contain a substance called arginine,
which actually can control the dilation
of blood vessels and arteries.
So it has some relationship
to heart and heart health.
Walnuts contain various fatty acids
that maybe, I want to underscore maybe,
beneficial for certain
aspects of brain health
but there's no evidence whatsoever
that the shape of the
food itself is relevant.
And, you know, I think what's happened is,
is that people have gone out there
and found foods that
contain certain substances
like carrots and vitamin A
or walnuts and particular fatty acids
or beets and arginine.
And they've selected the foods
that happen to be in
the shape of the thing,
the organ that the particular
substance like vitamin A
or fatty acids and so forth
might benefit or support.
But of course, there are
many, many other sources
of these nutrients that
don't come from walnuts
or from beets or from carrots.
And so I guess the short way to put it
is that the idea that
the shape of some food
is an indication of
whether or not that food
would be healthy for a
particular organ in the body
is absolutely unfounded.
I don't know of any evidence for it
and I'm not out to quash
anybody's great love
of these foods.
I enjoy all the foods I just described,
but the shape of things
in the physical universe
bears very little, if any, relevance
to the nutrients that it contains
and therefore the organs that it supports.
So thank you for your question
but if you see that out there,
I don't even think you
need to tell the person
who's putting that information
out into the world.
I would just, you know, back away slowly.
One other thing, before we
move into today's material,
last episode, I talked about the problems
with emulsifiers in highly processed foods
and the way that they can strip
the mucosal lining of the gut.
And they can limit the
signaling of hormones like CCK
that can signal to the brain satiety,
the signal to stop eating.
And then we got into a discussion
about artificial sweeteners
and I threw out Stevia as
an artificial sweetener.
And several people
reached out to correct me
that Stevia is not an
artificial sweetener,
it is a noncaloric sweetener,
and you are correct.
I lumped artificial and
noncaloric sweeteners together.
And thanks to many of you that
also sent me some references.
It does not appear that
Stevia can negatively impact
the gut microbiome.
It does seem unique among
noncaloric sweeteners.
There are probably others out there.
The other thing that we
discussed is how Stevia
can lead to slight
increases in blood glucose
but can also improve insulin
management just slightly,
probably cancels to zero
in terms of its impact
on blood glucose,
provided it's not at concentrations
that are super, super sweet.
Ingestion of anything that's very sweet,
whether or not contains calories
or not, artificial or not,
will create an insulin response.
In fact, just walking past a bakery
and smelling delicious baked goods
can increase your insulin secretion.
And so we just want to point that out.
Thank you for the information
and the references that you found.
Please send additional
ones if you do find them.
And I appreciate that you
allow me to make corrections
every once in a while I must speak here
and the opportunity to make corrections
keeps us all on the same page.
And please do keep any
feedback that you have
about particular things I
cover here coming my way.
There is so much interest in metabolism.
We hear about having a
high or a low metabolism.
There are some people out there
who would like to reduce their metabolism.
They simply can't eat enough
to maintain their weight.
Most people, however, struggle
with the opposite issue.
They struggle to maintain a healthy weight
and/or their metabolism is too low.
Now, there are a variety of reasons
why metabolism can be low.
Today, we are going to
talk about two hormones,
thyroid hormone and its related pathways
and growth hormone and
it's related pathways,
which arguably are the two hormones
and two systems in the body
that are most significant
for setting your overall
level of metabolism.
Before we dive into those,
I just want to cover a little
bit of what metabolism is.
And I want to talk about
which organs in your body
use the most energy.
So metabolism is the
consumption of energy,
not necessarily eating,
but it's the use of energy
in the cells of the body
for growth of tissues,
for repair of tissues,
and also just for day-to-day
maintenance of function.
A good example of maintenance of function
would be your brain.
Most of your metabolic needs,
your so-called basal or
resting metabolic needs
are for your brain, for thinking.
If you were to just sit in a bed all day
and do nothing but think,
that consumes about 75%
of your metabolic needs.
Now, there's also moving around.
If you have a job that
requires a lot of heavy labor
or lifting things or you're a new parent
and you're carrying kids around
and you're going up and down the stairs
or back and forth to the refrigerator
for formula, et cetera,
well then you're burning more
energy, burning more calories.
But even if you are
very physically active,
unless you're an ultra
marathoner or a marathoner,
chances are that 75%
of your metabolic needs
are coming just from your brain.
And that's because neurons
consume a lot of energy.
Neurons, of course, are just
the nerve cells of your brain.
So these two hormones, thyroid
hormone and growth hormone,
we think of as related to
metabolism of things in the body,
keeping body fat low, and
keeping muscles strong,
and tendons strong and
repairing themselves, et cetera,
but they are also key for brain function,
for the ability to
maintain cognitive function
throughout the lifespan.
So the big theme I'd like to introduce
is that metabolism isn't
just about losing weight
but having a high metabolism,
provided it's not too high, is great.
It means that you will
have more lean tissue,
more bone and muscle and
less adipose tissue, fat.
And we know that that's healthy.
How much fat and how much muscle?
Well, that varies,
and the numbers on this
are always shifting.
But in general, muscle
and its related tissues
burns more energy than
does adipose tissue or fat.
And the water in your body
doesn't consume any energy.
So metabolism can be increased
simply by adding muscle to your body
and reducing fat or adjusting
the ratio of the two.
But regardless, even if
you're not interested
in changing body composition,
these two hormones,
thyroid hormone and growth hormone,
are super important for
metabolism of all kinds,
including tissue repair after injury,
including maintaining cognitive function
and well-being and the ability
to think clearly as you age,
offsetting dementia and so forth.
So the big theme here really
includes the previous episodes.
You don't have to have seen those episodes
but for the last three
episodes and today as well,
we've been talking about hormones,
these substances that are
released from one location
in the body that go and act
other locations in the body.
I'm going to tell you how that works
for thyroid and growth hormone.
But now that you've heard
about testosterone and estrogen
and you're going to hear about
thyroid and growth hormone,
I want you to realize that
there's a repeating logic.
First of all, there are
neurons in your brain
in an area called the hypothalamus,
which just means it's
below the thalamus, hypo.
It sits at the base of your brain,
in the front, it's part of the forebrain.
So it's more or less above
the roof of your mouth,
maybe about a centimeter or so,
and then about a centimeter
forward in most people.
And neurons in the
hypothalamus release hormones
that are called releasing hormones.
So we've talked in previous episodes
about, for instance,
gonadotropin-releasing hormone.
So those are a little
neurons that then signal
another brain area called the pituitary
to release other hormones.
Today, we're going to see this again.
In the brain, you have neurons
that release thyrotropin
or thyroid-releasing hormone.
You also have growth
hormone-releasing hormone.
So anytime you hear releasing,
chances are those are neurons
that are in your brain
and they extend little wires we call axons
into your pituitary and the pituitary
releases a bunch of hormones
into the bloodstream.
And the pituitary releases things
that most often have the
name of stimulating hormone
because they stimulate organs.
So in keeping with the
theme of thyroid hormone,
you have thyroid-releasing
hormone in the brain,
tells the pituitary to release
thyroid-stimulating hormone
and then the thyroid, which
we'll talk about in a moment,
releases thyroid hormones.
In the testosterone and estrogen episode,
we talked about how you have
gonadotropin-releasing hormone,
there's the releasing
again, up in the brain.
Remember, releasing hormone
comes from the brain.
Then you had things
like luteinizing hormone
and follicle-stimulating hormone,
which were in the pituitary
and those traveled
to the ovaries or the testes
and acted on those tissues, okay?
So please try and embed this logic.
If you hear the word releasing hormone,
it's coming from the brain,
and that makes it actionable
in certain ways that
we'll return to later.
In addition, the pituitary is letting go
of all these hormones into the bloodstream
that are stimulating different tissues.
So for thyroid, it's
thyroid-stimulating hormone.
And then it goes to the thyroid.
And the thyroid is a little
butterfly-shaped gland
that's right around the Adam's apple.
If you want to see yours, not directly
'cause it's got skin over it,
what you would do is
you'd take a sip of water,
you'd look in the mirror
and you'd swallow.
And the thing that moves up
and down, that is your thyroid.
Now, some people call it your Adam's apple
because it sits right near
this protrusion in the trachea,
which is the Adam's apple.
No matter, whether or
not you're male, female,
or regardless of what your
chromosomal background is,
everyone has an Adam's apple.
It tends to be more pronounced in people
that got a surge of testosterone
early in development
because it has a testosterone
sensitivity to it.
And that actually controls the timbre,
the so-called deepness of the voice.
So the thyroid gland sits right there
and it's got four little bumps behind it
called the parathyroid gland.
And it releases two
hormones into the blood
to stimulate different
tissues and their metabolism.
And those hormones are called T4 and T3.
So if this is already sounding
like a lot of information,
it's really easy, I promise.
Releasing hormone comes from the brain.
Stimulating hormone
comes from the pituitary.
And in this case, we're
talking about the thyroid,
binding up that stimulating
hormone and saying, oh,
I need to release something.
And it releases T4 and T3.
And guess what?
You can basically forget about T4.
T4, it's not completely
inactive, it has some roles,
but T3 is the one that's
more or less active.
Now, what does thyroid hormone do?
A lot of people think, oh, thyroid,
it's like metabolism and
people who are hyperthyroidal
have bulging eyes and are real thin
and people who have
hypothyroid are overweight
and their eyes are like are, you know,
half closed or something.
And indeed thyroid hormone controls
a lot of the features of
the face and the eyes.
And it can control amounts of
adipose tissue and so forth.
But the main role of
thyroid hormone, of T3,
is to promote metabolism.
And that doesn't just mean
the consumption of energy,
it means the utilization of energy,
including the buildup of tissues.
So it acts on all sorts of
target tissues in the body.
It acts on muscle, it acts on the liver,
it acts on the cartilage,
it acts on the bone.
And it's not just
involved in using energy,
it's also converting energy.
I do realize I said that twice.
It's involved in taking fats
and breaking them down into fatty acids
and converting those into ATP,
which is an important thing
for cells to use energy.
It's also involved in taking sugars
and turning those into energy.
And yes, it goes to adipose tissue to fat.
We have different kinds of fat
that we'll talk about today
but it goes to white fat
and it liberates or helps
liberate some of the fats
from those fat cells
and use them for energy.
And this is why higher thyroid
is associated with leaner bodies.
Lower thyroid is associated
with less lean bodies.
So one thing that's absolutely
key and is actionable,
we're right there already in
discussing tools is iodine.
Iodine comes from things
in the ocean, right?
And here are a couple of
interesting facts about iodine.
And then we'll talk about whether or not
you should be supplementing iodine or not.
First of all, iodine is most common
in sea salt, in kelp and in seaweed.
And most people can get enough iodine
from the food they eat and/or
the table salt they consume.
Almost all table salt
from all over the world,
regardless of where you
are, contains iodine.
The thyroid needs iodine
in order to produce thyroid hormone.
And you need sufficient
levels of thyroid hormone,
not too much, but you need it.
So chances are you are
getting enough iodine.
Although, you might not,
especially those of you
following a particularly,
quote, unquote, clean diet,
might not be getting enough iodine.
Here's the deal with iodine.
Iodine combines with an amino acid
that we've talked about
before called L-tyrosine.
L-tyrosine comes from meat, from nuts.
There are some plant-based
sources as well.
It is the precursor to dopamine.
But in the thyroid,
iodine combines or works
with L-tyrosine to produce T3
and T4, the thyroid hormone.
So you absolutely need sufficient iodine,
you need sufficient L-tyrosine,
and then you also need something else,
which is called selenium.
And we'll talk about selenium in a moment.
So there's a condition that shows up
in little pockets in the world.
It's not super common, meaning
it's not very widespread,
but in certain areas that
are far away from the ocean,
at one point, this was historically
in the Midwestern states
of the United States,
in some mountain regions
of other countries,
in some areas of Africa that
were far from the ocean,
people would get extremely
swollen bulges in their necks.
And this was called goiter.
And the reason they were
getting those swollen bulges
is because the thyroid
itself was hypertrophying.
It was growing in an attempt
to churn out more thyroid.
And because it was getting a lot
of stimulating hormone from the pituitary.
And I don't want to go
too far off track here
but as you recall,
the brain and the pituitary
are paying attention
in a cellular sense to the
levels of hormones in the blood.
And when those hormones get too high,
they shut off the stimulating hormone,
they shut down the signal to make more,
kind of like a thermostat.
When the levels are too low,
like there's not enough
testosterone in the bloodstream
or there's not enough estrogen,
the brain will continue to push
out the signal to make more.
Similarly, if there's not
enough thyroid circulating
or there's not enough
iodine to make thyroid,
therefore not enough
thyroid hormone circulating,
the thyroid gland itself
is not getting shut down.
There's tons of stimulating hormone
and releasing hormone
coming from the brain,
like release, release, release,
and there's no way they
can make thyroid hormone
and so the gland just gets
bigger and bigger and bigger.
And so people get goiter.
This is one of the reasons why
table salt has iodine in it.
Although there are other foods
that have iodine in it as well.
So how much iodine do you need?
Well, you don't need a whole lot.
Some people who are hypothyroidal might,
and I want to emphasize might,
you absolutely should talk to your doctor.
This is a serious matter.
Anytime you're talking about hormones
or manipulating levels of thyroid,
you absolutely want to
talk to your doctor.
Some people benefit from
supplementing iodine.
It is contained in most salts.
It's in Himalayan salt,
not always, but often.
I know these days, there's
a lot of excitement
about pink salts and sea salts and what,
you know, they're kind
of artisan salt thing
has kind of taken off in the
foodie land, which is great.
Some of them are actually quite tasty.
You can just take it directly
if you like the taste of salt.
But iodine can be supplemented
through things like kelp and
seaweed and kelp tablets.
Now, if you are hyperthyroidal,
you make too much thyroid,
that actually can be a problem.
So really, the best way to figure this out
is to get your blood levels
tested of thyroid hormone.
But there's so much iodine in the ocean
that believe it or not people
that live near the coast
can actually just absorb
it through the air,
just by breathing ocean air.
So that gives you a sense
of just how little iodine
you actually need to
consume in food or in salt.
So if you're within a
few miles of the ocean
or you visit the ocean from time to time,
you're probably getting plenty.
It does have to come
together, as I mentioned,
with L-tyrosine,
and this is why foods
that contain L-tyrosine,
and provided that you have
sufficient iodine in your diet,
and if you have sufficient
selenium in your diet,
does serve to increase your metabolism.
And that again is for the
growth and repair of tissues.
And that's really important.
It's not just about keeping
your metabolism high
so that you can be on
the leaner side of things
or adjust your body weight, excuse me,
your body composition
ratios the way you like.
Repair of injuries,
repair of brain tissue,
clearance of any damage from neurons,
clearance of any damage to the body
is also going to depend on thyroid.
Again, metabolism being this kind of rate
of fuel consumption and
use in the body, generally,
not just about body mass
indexes and things of that sort.
So let's talk about selenium
because it's really important.
And even though most
people are getting a lot
of sufficient iodine,
and most people are probably
getting enough L-tyrosine.
I'm guessing most people may
not be getting enough selenium
if their goal is to
increase thyroid hormone,
at least that's what the literature says.
Without going into the biochemistry,
selenium is important in order
for thyroid hormone to be made
because of the way that
it allows L-tyrosine
and iodine to interact.
And the thing is most people
aren't getting enough selenium
because they don't eat foods
that are high in selenium.
Now, how much selenium you need
will depend on where you live.
It actually varies country by country.
Some countries I found
say that you should get 100 micrograms,
some say 200, some say 155.
The average was about 155 micrograms,
the countries I looked at.
People who are trying to
increase thyroid levels
might want to consume more selenium.
And if you consume a vitamin, of course,
you want to make sure if it has selenium
that you're not overdoing it by consuming
a lot of selenium rich foods either.
But nonetheless, I think it's fair to say
that most people probably could do well
by ingesting slightly more
selenium than they currently are.
Although, of course,
always talk to your doctor.
Brazil nuts are the heavyweight champion
of foods to get selenium from.
It has very high
concentrations of selenium.
In just six or eight Brazil nuts
contain something like 550
micrograms of selenium.
It's also present in fish.
So certain fish like yellowfin tuna,
although nowadays whenever
I mention tuna or shellfish,
which is the other rich
source of selenium,
people will tell me immediately
there are all sorts of issues around farm,
not farm, mercury, et cetera.
So I've never particularly
liked eating fish
'cause of the way it tastes.
So that's why I avoid it.
But for those of you that like it,
I'm sure you're much more skilled
in knowing which fish to buy
and which fish not to buy.
Ham, of all things,
contains a lot of selenium,
for whatever reason pork does.
I'm not a big consumer of pork.
Beef has some selenium,
but what's interesting
if you look at the sources,
you know, pork, beef,
turkey, chicken, cottage
cheese, eggs, brown rice,
what you want to understand
is that Brazil nuts,
six to eight Brazil nuts has
550 micrograms of selenium.
And all the other foods I mentioned
at much greater portion size
than equivalent to six
to eight Brazil nuts,
either by volume or by calories,
they have something like 30
to 50 micrograms of selenium.
So if you're not eating Brazil nuts,
I'm guessing most people aren't,
and you're not eating a
lot of animal based foods,
which I know many of you aren't,
then you're probably not
getting enough selenium.
And again, you can have
these levels measured
or you can just check what
you're consuming and figure out
whether or not you're meeting
the ration that you need
in order to get healthy levels of thyroid.
It is present in things
like mushrooms, but again,
in a bowl of mushrooms, you
know, what is the equivalent
to a bowl of mushroom is
12 micrograms of selenium.
And if the daily ration is
something in 100 to 200 range,
again, look it up for the area you are.
You can see really quickly
why even though things
like mushrooms and spinach
and milk and yogurt
and lentils and cashews,
and now we're into the vegetarian segment
of the list that I constructed,
you're probably not
getting enough selenium.
So it's kind of an interesting thing.
If you're an experimenter
and you get the clearance
from your doctor,
you could try increasing
your selenium levels
and see how that impacts your metabolism.
Again, Brazil nuts are probably
going to be the most direct way
to get sufficient selenium levels
but because levels are
so high in Brazil nuts,
it also means that you
could overdo it as well.
I'm not really aware of
what the consequences are
of getting too much selenium,
although you can get too much
of anything and I'm guessing
those consequences aren't good.
I also want to mention that for children,
their daily requirements
of selenium are much lower,
as low as 30 or 40 micrograms
for kids 14 years or younger.
And in some areas, I really
want to underscore this,
the amount of selenium
that's recommended daily
is as low as 55 micrograms.
So it's not that you should be shooting
for thousands or even
high levels of hundreds
of micrograms of selenium.
And again, that's
micrograms, not milligrams.
So again, look into what you need
but if you're somebody who's interested
in keeping thyroid function
healthy and productive,
then you certainly want to make sure
you're getting enough iodine,
you're getting enough selenium
and you're getting enough L-tyrosine.
And it's interesting
when you start looking
at the various foods, especially
highly processed foods,
then you start to realize
that perhaps many people,
maybe you, are not.
Not incidentally, selenium
has some other effects
on health that can be quite positive.
And even though these
don't relate to thyroid
or growth hormone function specifically,
I think you might want to know about them,
given that we're on the topic of selenium.
The first is that there are three studies,
all of which showed very high efficacy
for reducing the risk of
something called preeclampsia,
excuse me, preeclampsia.
Preeclampsia is seizures that are related
to blood pressure issues during
or around the delivery of a new baby.
And actually, it's a rare-ish condition
but it actually can be quite deadly.
And so the fact that selenium is important
for offsetting preeclampsia
risk is interesting.
I don't know the exact mechanism
and I'm guessing there are
only a few of you out there
that are either pregnant or
thinking of conceiving soon,
but that's worth noting.
Obviously, anything related
to pregnancy or lactation,
especially talk to your doctor.
I'm guessing that selenium is probably
in a lot of prenatal formulas
but that's one clear benefit
of having sufficient selenium.
The other is a reduced
prostate cancer risk.
There's a study showing that
having sufficient selenium
can reduce prostate cancer risk.
And there is some evidence
that if you consume foods
from areas with soil
that's low in selenium,
that can be a problem.
And last episode, we talked
about all these issues related
to soil quality, things that
are making their way into food
that are disrupting hormones and so forth.
But having sufficient selenium from food
could offset the low content in any soil.
And so that apparently can
reduce prostate cancer risk.
It's a minor effect
but it's a statistically significant one.
And the other one is a reduction in acne,
which is interesting.
I'm guessing that that probably has to do
with the thyroid hormone pathway
because of the way thyroid
hormone can impact the liver.
And it turns out that the liver
and various biochemical reactions
in the liver can impact acne.
And that's probably an
episode all into itself
but those are just some
additional benefits
of getting a sufficient selenium.
Okay, so we're already deep into tools
related to making sure that
you have sufficient selenium,
iodine, and L-tyrosine
in order to make enough
thyroid hormones that can
support your metabolic processes
in your liver, your muscles, your tendons,
for whatever purpose,
keeping your metabolism high,
for body composition
reasons or for healing,
for keeping your brain working well.
Earlier I mentioned, there are people
who are following very clean diets.
So these are people that
consume no processed foods.
You know, any starch they might eat
is going to be maybe a rice or a grain
or any protein they might consume
is going to be either from, let's hope,
from humanely raised animal sources
or maybe they're pure plant-based.
Believe it or not, those folks
are actually very
susceptible to low iodine
because it turns out that
diets that are very meat rich
and don't have many vegetables,
as well as diets that
are very vegetable rich
but don't have many meats or salts
are at risk of lowering thyroid hormone
by way of the iodine
pathway and other pathways.
And so let me try and
simplify this for you.
Chances are if people are
doing the all-meat diet,
they're not sprinkling, they're
not wrapping those steaks
in seaweed and they may
or may not be supplementing with iodine.
Chances are they're probably
consuming iodine salt
but their requirements go up
if they're not consuming vegetables.
People who are consuming
vegetables is kind of interesting.
We always hear
that we should have our
cruciferous vegetables
and those are so important
but there are actually substances,
compounds within high quality
cruciferous vegetables
that can interfere with
thyroid hormone function.
So if you're eating a lot of that stuff,
a lot of cabbages and
just look up your other,
I think broccoli is a
cruciferous vegetable,
and I won't read off the whole list,
you could just put into the internet.
But we're always told to eat a lot
of the dark, leafy green stuff.
Well, unless that dark, leafy green stuff
is kelp or seaweed,
chances are that we're
not getting enough iodine
unless we're adding salt to our food.
And chances are that we may be lowering
the total amount of
thyroid that we're making,
as well as the fact that
in plant-rich diets,
it's hard to get enough L-tyrosine
and I don't want, you know,
I'm not here to inflame
any of the vegans or the carnivore folks.
I don't take a stance
either way on any of that.
I'm just learning, trying
to report the science.
The point I want to make is
your health is important.
So if you are purely plant-based
and you're eating a lot
of cruciferous vegetables,
make sure you're getting enough iodine.
It does seem like the
cruciferous vegetables
can increase the need for further iodine.
And same thing if you're
purely on this all-meat diet
or your keto, and you're not
ingesting many vegetables.
So I always thought that the
cleaner the diet, the better,
but it turns and probably that's true
from the standpoint of, you
know, hormone regulation,
you know, estrogen and
testosterone and other hormones.
The highly processed
foods really are terrible.
There's so much evidence for that.
The phthalates in plastics
and the processed foods
and the emulsifiers,
all this stuff we talked
about previous episode,
but it does seem to be that people
that are not getting enough
iodine for whatever reason,
really need to check out whether
or not their iodine levels
need to be increased because of the fact
that they're consuming so
many plants or so many meats
and in some cases,
plants that actually
lower thyroid hormone.
And not to beat a dead horse or cabbage,
but there are a number of
things that iodine can do
that are positive that are sort of,
they're related to thyroid, not directly,
they're kind of offshoots
of the thyroid pathway
on their downstream of it, we would say,
in terms of how they
impact metabolic function.
One of those is to reduce something
called c-reactive protein.
Some of you may have heard
of CRP or c-reactive protein.
C-reactive protein is
something that you want to keep
at modestly low levels.
It's associated with
inflammation and various forms
of heart disease and even eye
disease, macular degeneration.
So it does appear that
iodine supplementation
or getting sufficient iodine
from food, either works,
is associated with reduced
levels of c-reactive protein
in the blood and an
anti-inflammatory effect.
And the anti-inflammatory
effect brings us back
to our old friend, interleukin 6.
Remember, they're these
inflammatory cytokines.
They have many, many names
because there are many, many of them.
Interleukin 10 is the one
that's anti-inflammatory.
Interleukin 6 is the
one that's inflammatory.
Anytime you see IL-6,
that usually means that there's
an inflammatory response,
there's a wound, there's
inflammation of the brain,
somebody is either sleep
deprived or had a brain injury
or they're dealing with
some sort of infection.
IL-6 is kind of a
catch-all for inflammation.
And it does appear that
iodine supplementation
can reduce circulating IL-6
associated with inflammation.
So in that sense,
iodine can have an
anti-inflammatory effect.
So by now, it should be abundantly clear.
If you care about thyroid hormone,
if you care about the
pathways that it impacts
like having a high level of metabolism,
which I guess if for no
other reason is attractive
'cause then you can eat more
and still maintain a
healthy body composition,
but also for brain health,
cognitive function,
tissue repair, all that stuff,
keeping c-reactive protein
low, keeping IL-6 low,
make sure you're getting enough iodine,
selenium and L-tyrosine.
If you're curious how
thyroid actually increases
the metabolism, allows you
to eat more, et cetera.
It relates to something
we covered last issue,
which is glucose.
Remember when you eat
something, blood sugar goes up,
insulin is secreted from the pancreas
and it makes sure that blood
glucose doesn't go too high,
which can damage tissues or too low,
which can make you hypoglycemic.
Thyroid increases glucose uptake
by various tissues, in
particular muscle and bone.
It actually can increase
bone mineral density,
which is a really good thing.
As you get older, injuries,
when I say older, I mean
basically 30 and older,
the reason you can recover
more quickly from injuries
if you have a healthy thyroid
and healthy thyroid pathways
is because you can consume energy.
That energy is diverted toward bone repair
and muscle repair and cartilage repair.
And so the way it does this
again is by increasing ATP.
But the whole idea here is that iodine,
selenium, L-tyrosine, allow
thyroid to be at healthy levels
so that thyroid then can
take glucose in the blood
and divert it to tissues
for it to be used,
in particular your brain.
And that's why these things
that we're talking about,
supplementing or getting from food,
can actually improve or
support brain function.
People are always asking me,
what is the food that I
should eat for my brain?
Like, are blueberries good for your brain?
Or they do ask me, are
walnuts good for your brain
'cause it looks like a brain?
We talked about that earlier.
The fact of the matter is what you need
are nutrients that support hormones
and biological pathways
that support the brain.
That's the way to think about it.
And I realized when people ask,
what should I eat to support my brain?
That's basically what
they're asking in short form.
So keeping your thyroid hormone healthy
at healthy levels that is,
is going to be terrific
for your brain because
75% of your metabolism
is from your brain.
The ability of your brain to use glucose
or ketones for that matter
is going to be aided
by having healthy thyroid.
So do the things, take
the things, eat the things
that are going to allow you
to have healthy levels of thyroid hormone.
I'm sure a number of you
are out there wondering,
do I have healthy levels
of thyroid hormone?
Those can be measured from the blood.
There are some telltale signs
of having really high thyroid
or really low thyroid, and I
could start listing those off.
They're easy to find online as well.
Things like bulging eyes,
inability to maintain
weight, shaky, anxiety,
that's kind of hyperthyroidal,
thinning of hair,
this kind of thing.
I don't want to get into
diagnosing hypothyroidism
and hyperthyroidism.
It's just impossible 'cause you're there
and I'm here and we're kind
of shouting back and forth
through a tunnel of video and comments.
If you're concerned about
having excessively high
or excessively low levels
of thyroid hormone,
absolutely look up what the symptoms are.
Talk to your physician.
And there are a number of good treatments.
I didn't talk about prescription drugs
that can improve symptoms
related to hypo or hyperthyroid.
Of course, they have synthesized thyroid.
So if you don't make enough thyroid,
you can take thyroid,
it's by prescription.
If you have too much thyroid,
sometimes they'll take
out the thyroid gland
or they can administer drugs
that will either block
receptors or will interfere
with some of the pathways from the brain
to the pituitary or from
the pituitary to the thyroid
in order to adjust the
thyroid hormone that way.
So there are the big guns
in terms of the treatments
for different thyroid disorders
but we're not talking
about thyroid disorders,
we're talking about how to get
and maintain thyroid levels
in healthy ranges and some
straightforward ways to do that
through diet and supplementation.
There's also a lot of evidence
that for people who menstruate,
levels of thyroid hormone
can fluctuate dramatically
across the menstrual cycle.
So that's really going to be
a process of experimentation.
I don't know that you could,
you could, in theory, take
blood at different phases
of your cycle and figure
out whether or not
your thyroid hormone was
excessively high or low
at different phases of the cycle.
That's going to be pretty tough to do.
If you have an endocrinologist
that's willing to do
that with you, terrific.
I think most people are
going to have to figure out
how supplementing the sorts of things
that we talked about before,
or getting them from foods relates
to different aspects of their cycle.
In general, the first half of
the cycle before ovulation,
people crave carbohydrates and sweets more
and that makes total
sense based on the biology
of the menstrual cycle.
Thyroid hormone is going to go up as you,
as anyone, male or female,
menstruating or not,
increases more starchy carbohydrates.
This is interesting because
ketogenic diets have been shown
to slightly lower thyroid levels.
And that makes sense
because in ketogenic diets,
blood glucose levels are very low.
And thyroid hormone is
secreted in large part
in proportion to how much
glucose is in the bloodstream
and how much that glucose,
excuse me, needs to be regulated.
So I'm not trying to
demonize the ketogenic diet.
I think it definitely has its place.
There are 22 studies now
showing that it can dramatically
reduce blood glucose.
And about a third of those show
that thyroid hormone levels
are slightly reduced,
sometimes significantly,
if not more, in the ketogenic diet
that may explain, I want
to highlight may explain
the fact that when people go
back to a more traditional diet
if they've been on a ketogenic
diet for a long time,
that oftentimes they will
gain weight very quickly
as they bring carbohydrates
back into their diet.
Some people are cycling
between ketogenic and non-ketogenic
every three, four days.
So-called cyclical ketogenic diet.
Some people are staying ketogenic
for long periods of time.
Some people six days on, one day off.
So there's a huge variation there.
The point is that carbohydrates,
starchy carbohydrates in particular,
support the healthy
production of T3 and T4.
And so if you're very low carbohydrate,
you're going to have a
reduction in T3 and T4.
And so if you're going
to bring carbohydrates
back into your diet,
then you might want to
do it more gradually.
And for those of you that menstruate,
and are craving carbohydrates
in the early part of the cycle,
that is actually associated
with having a healthy cycle.
If any of you have had a healthy
cycle on a ketogenic diet,
that would be interesting.
Maybe let me know through the comments
or point me in the
direction of some research
if you're aware of it.
So as you can start to see,
there's this really beautiful interplay
between the different hormones,
between insulin and glucose,
between estrogen and thyroid,
between thyroid and blood
glucose and the ketogenic diet.
It all starts to fit together
in ways that make a lot of sense
once you understand just
kind of the core elements
of what the hormones are
and the variety of
tissues that they work on.
The simple version of this
is if you haven't had a
carbohydrate for a year,
then your T3, T4 levels
are going to be pretty low.
And I'm sure there's some
ketonistas out there.
They're going to say, wait, no,
thyroid hormone levels go up with keto.
That might be true for other reasons,
indirect reasons related
to hormone pathways
that are cascade from being in ketosis
for long periods of time.
Great.
But for most people that don't
consume any carbohydrate,
T3, T4 are going to go down.
And when they start to consume foods
that require thyroid metabolism
in order to work with, to metabolize,
then weight gain can
sometimes happen more quickly.
So it's just something to consider.
And it's something to work with carefully
if you're going to be cyclic
ketogenic, long-term ketogenic.
And if you're not ketogenic,
and you're consuming carbohydrates.
And the three things that
we talked about earlier,
selenium, tyrosine and iodine,
chances are unless there's
an underlying condition there
that your levels of
thyroid are going to be
in healthy range.
Next, we're going to talk
about growth hormone.
Growth hormone has
received a ton of attention
in the last 20 years.
I actually remember when
it was for sequenced.
This was a huge deal.
There was a huge patent drama.
I won't mention the universities
of the people involved.
There were companies and
monster patents and payouts
and it was really interesting.
You can look that up online
if you're interested in some
of the scientific history.
Growth hormone is a
pretty straightforward one
for you to understand
now because it follows
the exact same logic as thyroid hormone.
In fact, their functions
are so closely overlapping
on the, you know, when we
first look at the face of it
that you're probably going to think,
why do you have these two systems?
So just very briefly, growth
hormone-releasing hormone.
So remember releasing means
it comes from the brain,
comes from the brain
and tells the pituitary
to release growth hormone,
and then growth hormone is released
into the bloodstream
where it goes and acts
on a ton of tissues, muscle, ligaments,
bone, fat, et cetera,
to increase metabolism.
It sounds just like thyroid hormone.
And they do work in parallel.
And that's why we've lumped them together
in the same episode.
They increase metabolism and repair
and growth of tissues.
A conversation about growth
hormone would be incomplete
if we didn't talk about
the kind of extremes.
There are certain people who are born
that don't make enough growth hormone,
and they end up very short in stature.
There are certain people who
make a ton of growth hormone
and they end up very, very large.
They tend to have very large appendages.
They have something called acromegaly.
It's kind of like a
ridging of the forehead.
It's actually a bone ridge.
They are giant.
And it used to be called giantism.
And most people of course
are in a range of height
and appendage length.
That doesn't imply
that there's a growth
hormone disruption there.
Growth hormone received a lot of attention
after it was sequenced because
that meant the opportunity
to inject growth hormone
and replace growth hormone that was lost.
And there was actually a lot of cases
of people taking their
kids and trying to get them
to be taller for whatever reason
by injecting growth hormone.
Today, we're going to
talk about the things
that anyone can do to
increase growth hormone.
And there are reasons why certain people
would want to do that.
People who overproduce growth hormone
certainly would not want to do that.
People who underproduce it
would probably want to do that.
People that make normal, quote, unquote,
levels of growth hormone
might want to do that
as they age because during
puberty and development,
the pituitary is churning
out tons of growth hormone.
It's responsible for the
growth, not surprising,
of the body and all its features.
Height, just being one of those.
And so as we age, we
make less growth hormone.
And that is one of the
reasons why we recover
more slowly from injuries.
It's one of the reasons
why we accumulate body fat.
And it's one of the reasons
why our metabolism slows.
And so growth hormone replacement therapy
has been tremendously
popular in the last 20 years,
which is not to say it doesn't
carry its problems, it does.
Here's one of the major problems
with injecting growth hormone.
Not saying people shouldn't do this
if the doctor has approved
it or it's in keeping
with their particular life goals,
but growth hormone, if it's
in levels that are too high,
will cause growth of all tissues.
So not just muscle, not just reduction
in body fat by metabolizing, you know,
by allowing fatty acids to
be pulled out of storage
and used for ATP, but it
will also cause increase
in growth of the heart and the lungs
and the liver and the spleen.
And so this is the concern
with abuse of growth hormone.
So we're not going to be talking
about abuse of growth hormone.
We will, however, talk about
tools that anyone can use
to increase levels of growth hormone.
Some of them are behavioral,
some of them are supplement-based
and some of them interact with
behaviors and supplements.
And what's cool about the discussion
about growth hormone is that the tools
that exist out there to
increase growth hormone
are very actionable.
Most people can do these without the need
for any equipment or even any supplement.
Although there are some
supplement related themes
for tools for growth hormone increase.
And also the increases that one can get
in growth hormone are substantial.
So normally, when you
talk about the difference
between taking something
as an exogenous substance
like testosterone or estrogen
versus using supplements
or behaviors to increase them,
you're talking about tenfold
differences from, you know,
administering the prescription compound.
In terms of growth hormone,
there are things that can
increase growth hormone three,
four, 500% or more.
And even though that's
a short-lived increase,
they can have very powerful effects
on metabolism and on repair of tissues.
So let's talk about those.
Okay, let's go step by
step in terms of the things
that anyone, perhaps everyone,
should be doing in order to maintain
healthy growth hormone levels
or increased growth hormone levels.
Unless you have overproduction
of growth hormone,
chances are these things
are going to benefit to you.
However, as always, I want to emphasize,
talk to a doctor before you do anything,
including remove any treatments.
So anything you would add or take away,
that's the responsibility of you
and your healthcare provider, okay?
I don't just say that to protect me,
I say that to protect you.
First of all, growth hormone is released
every night when you go to sleep
and it's released in
the early part of sleep,
during so-called slow-wave sleep.
So the two conditions that have to be met
in order for growth hormone
to be secreted regularly
for tissue repair, et cetera,
are you need to get into slow-wave sleep
that so-called deep sleep
and you need blood insulin
and glucose to be relatively low.
So eating within two hours of sleep,
excuse me, eating within
two hours of going to sleep
is going to suppress
growth hormone release.
That's very clear.
However, some people are
going to have problems
falling asleep if they are too hungry.
So you have to work with that
and decide what you're going to eat.
And when you're going to eat that thing
so that you're not so hungry
that you're having trouble falling asleep.
The episodes on sleep that were covered
in episodes two, three, and
four of the Huberman Lab Podcast
has, I believe, more tools
there than you could ever want
or make use of in terms
of how to optimize sleep.
So you can refer to those, if you like.
So don't eat too close to sleep
and then get into slow-wave sleep.
And as I talked about in one
of those earlier episodes,
the first half of the night,
slow-wave sleep and
deep sleep predominate.
The second half of the night,
it's another kind of sleep,
we call it REM sleep.
So what is special about
this early phase of sleep?
This is how you should be thinking
if you listen to this podcast.
You should be thinking, okay,
I hear that something is important,
it's related, it's in the pathway,
but mechanistically when we
say get into slow-wave sleep,
get into deep sleep,
that's when growth hormone is secreted.
The question you should
be asking yourselves
as scientists of yourselves
is wait, why slow-wave sleep?
What in particular about
slow-wave deep sleep
allows the pituitary to
release growth hormone?
Like, what is it?
Because if you can understand that,
if you can understand a
little bit of mechanism,
there are actually ways
that you can increase
the amount of growth
hormone that you release
both in sleep and out of sleep.
So the answer is it's delta
wave activity in the brain.
Delta waves are these big
giant waves of activity
in the brain that correlate
with slow-wave sleep
as opposed to faster waves of activity
that is associated with
rapid eye movement sleep.
So slow-wave sleep and the delta activity
actually triggers the
neurons in the brain,
the releasing hormone, right?
Growth hormone-releasing hormone neurons
to signal to the pituitary.
Now, how do I know this is true?
And what can you do with this?
Well, we know this is true
because researchers have taken people
and sleep deprived them,
and they just asked, well,
is it just one period
of time every 24 hours
and then the pituitary
releases growth hormone?
If that were the case, that would say
that growth hormone is just released
in a so-called circadian dependent way.
Every 24 hours is the pulse of it, but no,
it's always relating to slow-wave
deep sleep and delta waves.
And this is cool because what it means
is that even if you're not
measuring your brainwaves
during sleep, which most
of you probably are not,
you might be measuring slow-wave sleep
or deep sleep using a
device like a Whoop or Oura.
And even if you're not,
what this means is that during the day,
there's the potential
to also increase growth hormone release
if you can get the brain into
the so-called delta waves.
And it turns out there
are things you can do
in waking as well to increase
growth hormone release.
So we're going to talk about those next.
But as a tool and to just really make sure
that we put brackets around this,
try and have blood glucose not too high.
So if you do need to eat close to bed,
you wouldn't want to eat anything
that would increase
blood glucose too much.
Try not to eat too close to bedtime.
Get into deep sleep early in the night.
Get the growth hormone release.
And understand that it's
the delta waves of activity,
the sweeping big waves of
activity in the neurons
that stimulate the brain
to stimulate the pituitary.
Because once you understand that,
then you have something to anchor to
in terms of thinking what
are the things I can do
in waking that will allow me
to release more growth hormone
which for most people is
going to be a good thing.
Several times before on this podcast,
I've talked about the fact
that I'm not a big fan
of melatonin supplementation
for most purposes.
It might be helpful under
conditions of jet lag.
However, there are a lot of reasons
why I personally don't like melatonin.
It interacts with the
reproductive hormones,
testosterone and estrogen,
and that whole access in
ways that are unattractive,
at least to me.
It suppresses puberty during development.
It's present in much, much
higher doses in most supplements
than one would normally make
like a hundred fold, 300 fold.
However, today I'm going
to talk about an instance
where very low levels of
melatonin supplementation
might actually be advantageous.
And that is aiding the transition
to the delta wave, slow-wave
sleep I just described
because that's the pattern of sleep
and brainwave activity that
triggers growth hormone release.
So whereas most melatonin
supplements are one milligram,
three milligrams, 12
milligrams, this kind of thing,
that is super physiological.
There are some data
showing that microgram,
maybe 500 micrograms of
melatonin, so half a milligram,
can be beneficial in shifting the pattern
of early night's sleep
toward more of the slow-wave
deep sleep delta activity
and improving growth hormone release.
Not a lot of studies but the
ones that I saw are quality.
They were done in subjects that, you know,
both sexes, sufficient numbers, et cetera.
So this is interesting.
So if you're interested in
melatonin supplementation,
you might think about it
just at very low levels.
You know, hundreds of micrograms
as opposed to the milligram dosages.
Most of the ones out there
are going to be in milligram dosages.
So that's one way that
some studies have shown
that you can increase the
amount of growth hormone
that's secreted in early phases of sleep.
Now, the delta wave activity
and the slow-wave activity
in the brain being very important
for growth hormone release
and growth hormone release
being so important for metabolic functions
and peeling away unwanted body fat
and repairing tissues, et cetera,
forces us to ask, well,
what other things can we do
in waking in order to increase
growth hormone release?
So let's start
with the ones that have
a potentially big effect
but are a little bit harder to access.
And for that, I want
to point toward a book,
which is really kind of interesting.
It's not focused on growth hormone
but the book is called "Altered Traits."
This is the book.
It's an excellent book,
"Altered Traits" by Goleman and Davidson.
"Science Reveals How Meditation
Changes Your Mind, Brain, and Body."
Very interesting book.
For those of you that are
interested in meditation,
and perhaps those of you who are not,
but are considering it,
what they talk about in
this book is the fact
that meditation has two
separate lines of effects.
One of those lines of effects are things
that change your state.
So you're stressed.
You sit down, you meditate
and you relax and you go
into a particular state.
The other are the changes
that occur over time
and those are changes in trait.
So personality can actually change
with long bouts of TM meditation
or repeated meditation.
In any case, the reason we're talking
about "Altered Traits" today
is because certain types
of meditation can get people's brains
into states that very closely
mimic slow-wave sleep.
If you hear snoring in the
background, Costello is,
sounds like he's in slow-wave sleep.
These big oscillatory snores
that he's in 23.6 hours per day.
So what this means is for
people that are interested
in increasing growth hormone,
a meditation practice
that allows you to get into
these slow-wave delta type
frequency activity in the
brain may be very beneficial
because as I mentioned before,
that's what's gating
growth hormone release.
It's not just a circadian phenomenon,
it's actually controlled
by these brainwaves.
I did look up binaural beats.
I get so many questions
about binaural beats
and it's a really attractive idea, right?
Binaural beats, for
those of you don't know,
you listen to one frequency
of tone in one ear
and another frequency of
tone and the other ear,
and then the brain essentially
takes the average of the two
or there's some other
wiring in the brainstem
that makes it not quite the average
but it takes the average of
the two for sake of discussion.
And that frequency is
what the brain entrains
or maps onto.
There are a lot of apps that are claiming
that you can get the
brain into delta waves
using binaural beats.
I could not find quality
peer review studies
supporting that, but I know
there are a lot of fans
out there of binaural beats.
If you know of any literature
that's independent of the company
that makes the binaural beat technology,
so unbiased research,
please send it my way.
But in "Altered Traits,"
Goleman and Davidson
talk about the fact that
people who do 20 minutes
of sitting meditation per day
can access these slow-wave
sleep like brain states.
Now, I've talked a lot on here
about non-sleep deep rest,
things like yoga nidra and hypnosis.
I'm not aware that those will put people
into slow-wave sleep per
se, or delta waves per se.
So we're really talking about 20 minutes
of more traditional type meditation.
Okay, so we've talked about
very low doses of melatonin
as a way to trigger delta waves
and more growth hormone release in sleep.
There's science to support that.
We've now talked about a
waking behavior of 20 minutes
of sort of what I would
call standard meditation
or just sitting there,
concentrating on one's breathing
to try and access delta waves.
Binaural beats, no science yet.
Who knows?
Maybe there's science to support it.
If you're aware of it, let me know.
Now, let's move to the
things that one can do
that have been shown to have
what's, let's just be honest,
pretty enormous effects on
growth hormone release in waking.
And these are things
that are very actionable.
One of the things that
can have a dramatic effect
on levels of growth
hormone release in waking
as well as in sleep the
following night is exercise.
But the key is the type of
exercise and the duration.
Now, there's a logic to this.
There are hundreds, if
not thousands of studies
measuring growth hormone,
both during or sometimes after exercise
or the following night.
And the conclusion that one takes away
from all of these is that exercise
has to be of particular
duration and intensity
in order to get growth hormone release.
So first I'm just going to tell you
what I found to be the maximum amount
of growth hormone release
as it relates to a
particular form of exercise.
The particular form of exercise
is either weight training
or it can be endurance training,
but the endurance training
and the weight training
actually have to be limited
to about 60 minutes,
not much longer.
Now, this is important
because it's been shown
over and over again
that if one exercises
too long with weights
or endurance exercise, that
cortisol levels go high enough
that it starts to inhibit the testosterone
and even the estrogen pathways.
This is why I believe
people who overexercise
or exercise a lot can lose
their menstrual cycles.
They stop menstruating.
It's why you get
suppressions in testosterone
if people train too long and too hard.
The cutoff has always been, you know,
60 to 75 minutes of the hard work part.
It's going to vary a lot
from person to person,
but in terms of growth hormone,
the conditions that seem to lead
to the greatest growth hormone
releases are one, get warm.
This is interesting, we're
going to talk about temperature.
So a proper warmup seems to accelerate
the release of growth hormone
once the hard work phase starts.
So 10 minutes of warmup
or so was the number
that I extracted from all these studies.
There's a beautiful review
on this, by the way.
Growth hormone responses
of varying, excuse me,
"Growth hormone, arginine and exercise."
We'll talk about arginine
in a few minutes.
That's by Kanaley, K-A-N-A-L-E-Y.
It was published in Current Opinion
in Clinical Nutrition and Metabolic Care.
The Current Opinion journals are generally
of pretty high quality
in terms of the reviews
just because they tend
to be pretty recent.
And then the references
therein are also quite good.
So what does this mean?
This means warm up.
And when you say warm up,
it doesn't mean just warm
up the limbs and tissues
that you're going to use
so you don't get injured,
actually warm the body.
So there was actually some discussion
about whether or not
in cold winter months,
people should wear like a stocking cap,
bringing the conditions,
making the room warm.
So getting the body warm as a
warmup seems to be important
because temperature of the body
seems to be an important condition
or prerequisite for certain
patterns of exercise
to maximize growth hormone release.
So it's really interesting to me.
I have an obsession with
how body temperature,
light exercise and food interact.
We're going right there with
the fact that if you get warm,
you bring up the body temperature
a degree or two or maybe
three, and then start exercise.
It does appear that
high-intensity exercise,
but again as discussed
in a previous episode,
not exercise that brings
muscles to failure
but close to it.
So if it's weight-bearing exercise,
it would be getting close
to that final repetitions
where you can't complete them
but not pushing through those
or even going to failure
but getting close leads to anywhere
from 300 to 500% increases in
resting growth hormone levels
and 300 to 500% increases
in growth hormone
the following night when you go to sleep,
which is incredible.
Now, I want to dissect this properly.
Okay, so one of the other conditions
that seem to be important, again,
was to have relatively low blood glucose.
So it's looking a lot like
the conditions you need
for sleep in order to get maximum
growth hormone release in sleep.
So not having blood glucose
too high or too low,
that's a discussion unto itself.
You want to have sufficient
energy to do the exercise
but getting warm,
not having blood glucose
too high or too low.
So probably not eating
too close to exercise
or not in ingesting a lot of
sugars during the exercise.
That was supported by
the fact that ingestion
of a sports drink that
contains caloric sugar
immediately flat-line the
growth hormone levels.
So really interesting relationship
between insulin, glucose
and growth hormone.
So then doing the training for anywhere
from 60 to 75 minutes to
maximize growth hormone release.
And then the other interesting thing
was that even after the exercise,
taking body temperature back down
to normal levels relatively
quickly seemed to be associated
with these big spikes in growth hormone.
Otherwise, what would happen
is you get these big spikes
in growth hormone, but if
the exercise went too long
or if body temperature
remained too high for too long,
then you didn't get the second increase
in growth hormone the
following night, okay?
So I hope I made that abundantly clear.
Warm up well, get body temperature up,
exercise 60 to 75 minutes.
Don't go to absolute failure
if your interest is in
growth hormone release
both during the exercise
and later that night.
And if you can bring body
temperature back down
to normal levels by cooling off,
maybe cool shower or maybe
ice pack or something,
or maybe just turning
off the heat in the room
or going outside, whatever it is,
then you increase the probability
that you're going to
increase growth hormone
the following night as well.
And again, these are big
increases, 300 to 500%.
It's almost like you're getting
a second sleep during the day.
But if the exercise is too
hard, if body temperature
stays too high for too long,
you disrupt the whole process
and you don't get the effect
of increased growth hormone.
Growth hormone is really powerful
but it doesn't work alone.
In fact, a lot of the effects
of growth hormone are mediated
by its effects on the liver.
So growth hormone is
released, goes to the liver,
and then the liver releases
something called IGF-1,
insulin growth factor 1.
Insulin growth factor 1 was popular
in the neuroscience
community as an area of focus
because of its ability
to trigger improvements
in memory and learning after exercise.
And indeed exercise triggers
both the release of
growth hormone and IGF-1.
IGF-1 seems responsible
for a lot of the effects
of improved memory.
Some people report that that is due
to increased number of
neurons or neurogenesis,
birth of new neurons.
It's pretty clear that in humans,
that's not what's happening.
Yes in animals, not in humans.
IGF-1 nonetheless has positive effects
on memory and cognition.
And a great way to trigger IGF-1 release
and growth hormone release
is through exercise.
Now, the interesting thing,
and the reason I'm bringing up IGF-1 here
is that certain patterns of exercise,
actually duration of exercise
have different effects
on IGF-1 and growth hormone,
depending on whether or not the exercise
is done by men or women.
There's what we call sex-dependent effect.
And the sex-dependent
effect is as follows.
In this particular study
and several others,
what they did is they had people exercise.
They measured growth
hormone and IGF-1 levels
from the blood before,
during and after exercise.
And they could see when the
greatest increases occurred.
This was standard sorts
of resistance exercise.
So some squats.
There was a sprint like activity.
It doesn't really matter what
the specific exercises were.
None of them were to failure.
These were in kind of the 10 repetition
or less range, six sets.
So kind of standard weight training stuff
that anyone might do.
But what was interesting is
that women were able to access
the biggest peak in
growth hormone and IGF-1
early in the exercise.
So in the first 30 minutes.
So what this means is even
if you just have 30 minutes,
at least for women, there's
going to be a big increase
in growth hormone and IGF-1
in the first 30 minutes.
For men, the biggest
increase occurred later
in the exercise, which was
at 60 minutes or so total.
And so the sex-dependent
effects are interesting.
They point to the fact
that things like cortisol,
testosterone, and estrogen,
which of course vary in different levels
in men and women are going to impact
the release of things like
IGF-1 and growth hormone.
And yes, they did control
for all sorts of things
like diet and they controlled for weight
and prior experience.
It's actually a quite nice study.
If you'd like to check it
out, it's by a Pierce et al,
"Growth Hormone and
Insulin Growth Factor-I
Molecular Weight Isoform Response
to Resistance Exercise Are Sex-Dependent"
in Frontiers in Endocrinology,
fine journal in 2020.
So it's quite recent.
So what does this mean?
This means if you're exercising
and you want growth
hormone release, warm up,
do the type of exercise
that we've been discussing.
Women, in the first 30 minutes,
is when you're going to
get the maximum benefit
in terms of growth hormone and IGF-1.
Men, you have to keep going
for the entire 60 minutes.
So don't tap out early
if you're interested
in getting the growth
hormone and IGF-1 release.
And the same conditions apply
about then cooling down and not making
the exercise last so
long that you don't get
the increase in growth
hormone the following night.
My experience thus far
in doing this podcast
is that people fall into
one of two categories.
There are the just tell
me what to take people,
the people that are really
eager to try supplements
and maybe in prescription compounds.
And then there are people
who are a little bit more shy
about supplementation.
They are more focused on what they can do
with diet and behaviors
and things of that sort.
I don't have a bias either way.
I try and offer tools that are supported
by the scientific literature.
And I always point to safety margins.
There are supplements that
can increase growth hormone
to a considerable degree and no,
these aren't growth hormone itself.
Although, that of course
will increase growth hormone
to a considerable degree.
We will talk about
prescription drugs at the end,
not just growth hormone,
but some other things
that are quite prominently
in use right now,
in particular in the
entertainment industry.
There are pretty interesting compounds.
But first let's talk about supplements.
So this has been known about for some time
but arginine, the amino acid arginine,
as well as the amino acid ornithine
can increase growth hormone
levels substantially.
Now, arginine has a number of effects.
You can get it from food, you
can get it from supplements.
Some people take it in
pill form or capsule form.
Some people will actually
take it by IV, intravenously.
The levels and the amounts
of arginine required
to get big growth
hormone release increases
is pretty substantial.
So some people will take
arginine before bedtime,
some people will take it before exercise.
The prerequisite again
is low blood glucose.
Blood glucose is high, it's
going to quash the effect.
The amounts of arginine that people take
are anywhere from three grams to 10 grams,
or sometimes even more.
Although, this is definitely
a case of more is not better.
There's a threshold at
which growth hormone release
is actually blunted by taking
more than nine grams of arginine.
Now, nine grams of arginine
orally is a lot of pills.
It's at minimum nine pills.
And it can cause some
GI disturbance, right?
People can feel nauseous.
Some people will throw it up.
Some people get some constipation
or diarrhea, et cetera,
or just stomachaches.
I'm certainly not
suggesting people do this
that they take arginine
but that's the reason why most
of the studies that looked
at the role of arginine
on growth hormone levels
did it by IV, intravenous infusion.
So what's interesting, however,
is that whether or not
it's by mouth or by vein,
taking arginine can dramatically increase
growth hormone release and the levels
or the amount of increase was anywhere
from 100 on the low-end but
anywhere basically from 400
to 600% above baseline.
So these are huge increases
in growth hormone.
Now, I've never tried arginine.
Arginine is out there for a
number of different purposes.
One of them is to increase growth hormone.
Some of the supplements out there
to increase growth hormone
include arginine and ornithine.
Arginine does have the
effect of dilating arterials.
And it basically increases blood supply.
The arginine pathway is
involved in vasodilation.
It's actually the pathway
that's downstream of a lot of drugs
that are used to treat things
like erectile dysfunction.
And anytime people have problems
with peripheral blood flow of any kind,
they focus on compounds that
will either disrupt the enzymes
or will adjust the levels of amino acids
to get more vasodilation.
So taking arginine for the purpose
of increasing growth hormone
will also have the effect
of dilating blood vessels
and for people with blood, excuse me,
with heart conditions, that
actually can be a serious issue.
Now, here is something really important
and interesting to note,
which is that increasing arginine levels
with the specific goal of
increasing growth hormone release
can actually short circuit
the effects of exercise
on growth hormone.
Several studies that I looked at,
looked at the interaction
of taking arginine
and the exercise or just the arginine
or just the exercise alone.
And so you don't, unfortunately,
if growth hormone increase is your goal,
you don't unfortunately get to
increase growth hormone 800%
by taking arginine and exercising.
It always seems to be clamped
at about 300 to 500% increases.
Still large increases.
So I make that point for several reasons.
First of all, be aware that arginine
has these other effects on vasodilation.
Take those seriously if
you have a heart condition
or take them seriously in any case.
Second of all, you can
supplement with arginine,
not exercise and get these big increases
in growth hormone by
taking them before sleep.
But if you're taking the
arginine before exercise,
you're going to short circuit
or clamp the effects of exercise
on growth hormone, okay?
So it's something that one could use
but it doesn't have a
synergistic effect with exercise.
The two more or less cancel
each other out, not to zero,
but you end up with the
same effect you would
had you done one or the other.
So hopefully that's clear.
The other thing is if one's goal
is really to increase
arginine in the blood
for whatever reason,
arginine may not actually
be the best way to do that.
Because of the way it's
metabolized in the gut,
it doesn't have access or get access
to the tissues that
you're most interested in
in terms of increasing growth hormone
or vasodilation for that matter.
And in that case,
there's something else called L-citrulline
which has powerful
effects on vasodilation,
powerful effects potentially
on growth hormone levels
via the arginine pathway.
But basically L-citrulline,
it acts as sort of a donor,
or it's kind of a biological
prerequisite for arginine
and can lead to even
bigger arginine increases
than you would get if
you took arginine itself.
And so L-citrulline is out there.
Keep in mind that anything that dilates
the blood vessels will
lower blood pressure.
So L-citrulline, yes, will
lead to increase blood flow
for whatever purpose
you want to use it for,
whether or not that's pumps
in the gym or whatever.
It also can lead to big increases
in arginine and growth hormone,
but it will lower blood pressure.
So be aware of that.
And understand that the biology
isn't so straightforward.
L-citrulline may actually
be the better way
to get arginine increases
than arginine itself.
And ornithine can also
increase growth hormone,
although that's also
through an indirect pathway.
And nowadays, there isn't a lot of focus
on ornithine as a way to
increase growth hormone.
That was kind of all the rage in the 90s,
not so much anymore.
Nowadays, the people are really
in the know for this stuff
tend to focus on L-citrulline.
And if you're interested in
L-citrulline or arginine,
I highly recommend you
go to our old friend,
good friends, examine.com,
because there you can
put it into their list.
You can just put search
and it's totally free.
And it will tell you that blood pressure
will be slightly decreased.
Power output in the gym will increase.
There's very strong
effects on blood glucose.
Fatigue is reduced notably.
Big increases in nitric oxide.
That's also related to the
increase in vasodilation.
Plasma arginine, very high, excuse me,
notable effects, very
high support for studies,
which allow people more training
volume, aerobic exercise,
arterial stiffness is brought down.
There's a huge list of things.
Increase in growth hormone.
So two studies showing,
this was done double-blind.
Great, you always want
to see double-blind,
placebo controlled.
This was only done in
males, not in females.
Unfortunately, just have data from males
but increases in growth hormone,
it's a small, but a
real significant effect.
And again, from quality studies.
So there's a huge number of effects there.
And some of the other kind
of more interesting ones
about L-citrulline that you
might not have thought about
are things like muscle oxygenation
as we scroll down, decreases
in c-reactive protein.
So a lot of the same things
that you might affect,
expect, excuse me, from
the same sorts of compounds
we saw before.
The takeaway here is if you
want to increase growth hormone,
think about the arginine pathway,
but arginine itself might
not be the best direct route
to get there.
L-citrulline might be a better option.
But please do consider take very seriously
the effects on blood pressure.
So we've been talking about big effects
from supplementation or
exercise on growth hormone,
this extremely powerful hormone.
And one thing to note is that
the profile of growth hormone
as we age, changes, I
mentioned that earlier,
but it's important to
understand how it changes.
One thing that's particularly
interesting to me
as somebody who's in his 40s
is that it's actually
between ages 30 and 40
that the amount of growth hormone
that you release each night is reduced
by two to threefold.
That's really incredible.
You know, we hear so much
about testosterone levels
going down as we age or
estrogen levels going down.
But if you recall
from the testosterone
and estrogen episode,
we talked about the fact
that if you really look
at the data, just for
instance, on testosterone,
there are men in their
90s and they are not rare,
it turns out, that are
making as much testosterone
and DHT, dihydrotestosterone,
as they were in their 20s, okay?
So we hear so much nowadays
about how testosterone levels
are dropping, sperm levels
are dropping, et cetera.
And I don't dispute that.
I talked about that in that episode.
But it's clear that testosterone
levels vary tremendously
from person to person.
And just getting older
does not necessarily mean
that testosterone levels are dropping.
Growth hormone levels, it seems,
are dropping when people
are in their 30s and 40s
and they're dropping substantially.
And that seems to be the
case across the board.
You're just not going to find
people in their 40s, 50s and 60s
that are making as much growth hormone
as they were in their teens and 20s.
And as somebody who, I feel really good,
but as somebody who definitely noticed
that as I got into my 40s
that even if I slept the same amount,
I wasn't feeling quite
as I would say able to
recover from exercise
or wound healing even with
the same amount of sleep.
And I was trying to optimize
a great number of things.
This business of growth hormone
became a particular interest to me.
And since the ways to
manipulate growth hormone
in men and women are so straightforward.
And since everybody goes
through this age-related
decline very dramatically,
it seems to me that the things
that we're supposed to be
doing anyway, like exercising,
like trying not to eat
too close to bedtime,
trying to optimize sleep.
All of these are wonderful tools
that we should be pursuing
and perhaps using.
And they can actually offset
the two to three fold decrease, right?
If we're talking about a
two to threefold decrease
for people that are in their 30s and 40s.
And then we're talking about increases
from exercise or maybe
from supplementation
but certainly from
exercise of 300 to 500%.
Well, then, all of a
sudden we're in a position
to actually offset the age-related decline
in growth hormone completely
just through behaviors.
And I think that's quite
interesting and quite powerful.
Now, I'd like to discuss a way that anyone
can increase their levels of
growth hormone dramatically.
And when I say dramatically,
I mean dramatically.
I'll get to the numbers
in a couple minutes.
But we have to remember how
growth hormone is released
in the first place.
Remember, it all starts in the
brain, in the hypothalamus.
The hypothalamus is a
brain area that controls
things like sexual behavior,
temperature regulation,
circadian behavior, meaning
when you want to be awake
and when you want to be asleep,
aggression, all of that.
There are other brain areas involved too
but it has a rich collection
of different neurons
involved in all these
very basic functions.
Now, as we talked about
the releasing hormones,
the growth hormone-releasing hormone,
it comes from neurons in the hypothalamus.
Those then communicate with the pituitary
and the pituitary releases growth hormone
and then the growth hormone
acts on all these
different tissues, muscle,
liver, cartilage, et cetera, body fat.
Makes them use energy.
That's why you lose body fat
when growth hormone levels are high.
It makes you grow muscle,
strengthens bones, et cetera.
Now, one of the things
that has a profound effect
on growth hormone levels,
growth hormone release,
is temperature.
Now, the data on this are very strong
and the data come from both animal studies
and human studies.
So there are a number of studies
that have explored how
making animals cold or hot
can increase growth hormone.
And if you're guessing which
direction this is going to go,
you can probably imagine
that making animals
or people warmer is the way to go
if you want to increase growth hormone.
Now, anytime you're going
to increase temperature
of yourself or anyone else
or an animal, it is risky.
I want to be really clear about this.
Not everyone should engage
in the behaviors I'm about to describe.
And I should just say
the reason it's risky
is it doesn't take much
of a temperature increase
in the brain to cook the
brain, to cook neurons.
And after that point,
neurons can't come back.
And people can die from hyperthermia.
We have a much greater
range in terms of cold.
You can also die of hypothermia.
You can freeze to death.
But you have a much greater
range of getting cold
than you do warming up the brain.
However, there are really
strong data pointing to the fact
that sauna, AKA deliberate hyperthermia,
not too high, however,
that sauna can increase
the release of growth
hormone and other hormones.
And what's so dramatic
about this literature
is the size of the
effects that are reported.
So first of all,
let's talk about these
temperature increases.
And yes, I will refer to
things that people can do
even if you don't own a sauna
because I realized not
everybody has a sauna
in their backyard or
has access to a sauna.
So first of all, recall our study
about exercise where
warming up a few degrees
before the exercise led to
bigger and quicker increases
in growth hormone during
the exercise about itself.
So that already point in the direction
that temperature was important.
Now, the degrees, no pun intended,
that we're talking about
increasing body temperature
is by entering saunas that are somewhere
between 176 degrees Fahrenheit,
so that's 80 degrees Celsius,
and all the way up to like
210, 215 degrees Fahrenheit.
I personally know people
that go even higher than that
but they've trained themselves to deal
with very high heats.
And again, high heat is dangerous.
You must clear this with your doctor.
Now, what happens in high heat?
A couple things happen in high heat.
First of all,
you start getting bigger
stroke volume of the heart.
Kind of like an exercise.
Once you get well-trained
in endurance activity,
your stroke volume and the amount of blood
that your heart can pump
each time gets larger.
You dilate the blood vessels, right?
There are a lot of
things that happen also.
You're sweating.
Your body's trying to unload heat.
Dilation of blood vessels,
arginine, increases in heat.
We're starting to see
and hear a common theme.
But it appears that getting into,
I'm not saying getting the body
up to 212 degrees Fahrenheit,
I want to be very clear,
I'm not talking about getting the body
up to 100 degrees Celsius.
That would be terrible.
You would die.
But entering environments
where it's very hot
for short periods of time,
anywhere from 20 minutes to 30 minutes,
where the temperature
is 80 degrees Celsius
to 100 degrees Celsius or
175 degrees Fahrenheit,
more or less, to about
210 degrees Fahrenheit,
more or less, has been shown to increase
growth hormone release 16 fold.
That's right, 16 fold.
That's 1,600%.
Now, there are also
effects on other hormones,
prolactin, cortisol, et cetera.
So the pattern that was
described in this study
and there've been many studies now.
Endocrine effects of repeated
sauna were done in 17 humans.
This was from doing this repeatedly.
So it wasn't the first time they did this.
They had to do this three days in a row.
And the pattern was to get
into the sauna for 20 minutes,
followed by a 30-minute cooling period.
Remember, you don't want to spend
long periods of time at high heat.
You can cook your brain and other tissues.
Be very careful as you
approach this if you decide to.
But 30 minutes, excuse
me, 20 minutes sauna,
followed by 30 minutes of cooling,
followed by 20 minutes sauna again,
led to a five fold
increase in growth hormone.
And then by doing that
day after day after day,
on the third day, you would
see these huge increases
of like 16 fold, up to 16 fold.
And there are now many studies like this.
This was described a few
years ago, but since then,
there've been a number of
other studies that have pointed
in the direction of
deliberate hyperthermia,
but not too hot that you kill yourself
in order to increase growth hormone.
And I know I keep highlighting
the dangers there,
but again, anytime you're
going to mess with heat,
you have to be cautious,
you have to be careful.
So standard sauna can be useful.
If you don't have access to a sauna,
one way that people do this,
we have to look to our
friends, the wrestlers, right?
They wear plastics, which
are basically bodysuits
that are fairly inexpensive
that you can buy on any
online purchase platform,
I should say.
Some people in the old days
before they had these plastic
things so readily available.
I actually knew people
that wrapped themselves
in garbage bags and then
throw on sweats and a hoodie
and then go out for a jog.
Again, you have to be really careful,
especially on a hot day.
Overheating can equate to death.
But that's another way to heat up.
You don't actually need a sauna.
I've known people who will do this
in hotel rooms while they're traveling.
They'll turn on the heat,
you know, make a hot bath.
They won't actually get in the bath
but they'll fill the
room with steam and heat
and they'll put on a
hoodie and some sweatshirt,
sweat pants, and they'll sit there
with wool socks on and they'll
get warm for 20 minutes,
then they'll take a cool shower,
and then they'll do it again.
I guess when the hotel
is paying the water bill,
you don't worry about it too much.
Some people of course own saunas.
There are a lot of ways to do that.
I have friends who were in the military
who made saunas out of cars
while they were overseas.
All sorts of things.
You do have to be careful.
I know I've said it many, many times.
I just don't want anyone
to hurt themselves.
But these increases in growth
hormone are tremendous.
And what they probably stem from
are increased activity of
neurons within the hypothalamus
that stimulate growth hormone
release from the pituitary.
And that's probably
because the growth
hormone-releasing hormone neurons
in the hypothalamus sit very closely
and may even be intermixed
with some of the neurons
in the hypothalamus that regulate
heat and body temperature.
Remember, metabolism is impart a heat.
It's like a furnace of how
much energy you're consuming
and using for building or
for energy usage purposes.
So sauna can be very, very interesting.
And again, it's 20
minutes, 30-minute cooling,
20 minutes again, proceed
with extreme caution,
but nonetheless, these
are pretty extreme effects
in terms of their abilities
to increase growth hormone levels.
Along the lines of
temperature and hormones,
I just want to mention
a very recent study,
it just came out.
March, April, 2021,
"Endocrine Effects of
Repeated Hot Thermal Stress
and Cold Water Immersion
in Young Adult Men."
Unfortunately, it was just in men,
they didn't look at women,
but nonetheless I think
the data are relevant
to everybody as a general theme.
This is Podstawski et al.
I will put a link to
the study in the caption
and they looked at testosterone,
prolactin, cortisol, et cetera.
And what they found was that the sauna
does indeed lead to a
significant decrease in cortisol,
a stress hormone, a hormone
that you want to be released
early in the day when you wake up.
But sauna definitely led to
significant decrease in cortisol
but did not change testosterone,
DHEA or prolactin levels.
So that's interesting.
And it turns out that the cold did affect
some of these hormones
but the results there
were a little bit more mixed.
So the takeaway here is that heat
seems to have positive
effects on growth hormone,
big effects.
It seems to have positive effects
on reducing cortisol levels.
And it does not seem to have effects
on things like testosterone,
DHEA, or prolactin directly.
You can imagine that
a shift in any hormone
is going to alter the levels of
other hormones down the lines
or have indirect effects
but in terms of direct effects just during
or immediately after the sauna
bath, there were no effects.
So we've talked about
diet, supplementation,
behavioral tools.
And of course, we talked
about the underlying biology and logic.
And hopefully you heard
the safety precautions
for all of those.
Now, I'd like to just briefly talk
about the prescription side of all this.
There are, as we know, many
people taking growth hormone
because it's been prescribed
to them by a doctor.
And presumably there are
people taking growth hormone
even though it has not been
prescribed by a doctor,
which is none of my business.
But the point here is that most all
of the hormones that we
make have been synthesized.
So there are versions of them
in little bottles or little
ampules that people can inject.
Here are a couple of
important things to consider
if you're going to go that route.
First of all, talk to
a physician, all right?
They actually are only legally available
through a physician.
Second of all, anytime
you're injecting something,
you're going to shut
down your own production.
That's the way that the
hormone system works.
If you take thyroid hormone,
you won't make thyroid hormone,
at least in the long run.
If you take testosterone,
you will shut down your own
production of testosterone.
If you take estrogen, the
system's a little more resilient
but eventually you will shut down
your production of estrogen.
And the same is true for growth hormone.
So a decision to go that
route of taking something
is often not always a
decision to do it forever.
However, if you're willing
to sustain a period
of being without a given hormone,
some people can do things
and then stop taking them,
and then wait out the period
in which they're not making testosterone,
estrogen or growth hormone,
and then it will come back,
sometimes and sometimes it won't.
There's a kind of new
area that's developing now
that I think deserves our attention,
not because I'm encouraging it,
but because it is happening.
And in keeping with the
science and in keeping
with trying to keep things
modern, it's worth us discussing.
And those are peptides.
So these days you hear
a lot about peptides.
I'd like to clarify a little
bit about what peptides are.
Peptides is a really huge
category of biological compounds.
Peptides are just strings
of amino acids, right?
So we've talked about
L-tyrosine, arginine, ornithine.
Those are amino acids.
Those are individual amino acids.
And those are put together
into little small peptides
or they're what are called polypeptides,
which are just longer peptides.
It turns out that for any
substance like growth hormone
or growth hormone-releasing hormone,
it's made up of different amino acids
in different sequences,
just like your genes
are made up of As and Gs
and Cs and Ts, nucleotides
in different sequences.
It's like a recipe.
Peptides tend to be short
sequences of amino acids
that resemble a hormone enough or resemble
some other peptide enough that it can lead
to the similar same effects
when you inject them.
So for example, we make growth
hormone-releasing hormone
from our brain which
stimulates growth hormone
from the pituitary.
You're probably getting tired
of me saying that by now.
But people now will take
things like sermorelin,
S-E-R-M-O-R-E-L-I-N, sermorelin,
which is not the entire peptide sequence
of growth hormone-releasing hormone
but it's a subset of those.
And when people inject it
before they go to sleep at night
is typically how it's
done on an empty stomach.
Then that stimulates the
release of growth hormone
from the pituitary.
So this is not taking growth hormone,
this is taking the stimulating hormone
or what's often called a
secretagogue or a mimic, all right?
It causes a secretion of
the hormone that one wants.
People will do this for
thyroid hormone, too.
Some people are doing this
by prescription with a real medical need.
Other people are doing it
for just longevity reasons,
which kind of falls into that gray zone
of they wouldn't die without it,
but they want to enhance their
life and so they're doing that
because they believe
it's the right thing
for them, prescription.
Sermorelin is prescription.
Do they work?
Yes.
Do they shut down your natural production
of growth hormone-releasing hormone?
Well, there, the answer is yes
but some of these peptides
actually have the effect
of changing gene expression.
Remember, way back to the beginning
when I was talking about hormones,
they can actually change gene expression
and they can actually
set pathways in motion
for continued production of a hormone
even if you stop taking the compound.
Now, that can be good or that can be bad
because as you recall, growth hormone,
big increases in growth
hormone that are short-lived
like sauna, or, you know,
I should say exercise
or arginine or sauna, it seems
like has these huge effects.
Or early nights, you
know, first phase of sleep
early in the night, these sorts of things.
Those are transient.
But when one is injecting over
and over at constant level,
you can put into action
gene expression programs
that can be long lived.
And let's say, you have a
particular tumor in the body.
Tumors will grow when
they see growth hormone
even if that tumor is
unhealthy for you, right?
You've got growth of
tissues all over the body.
So again, I'm not saying whether or not
people should do these
things or not doing them.
One thing I do know is that
they are in very prominent use
in the movie industry.
People who want to peel
off body fat quickly,
they do increase recovery time.
They increase healing rates.
People are also injecting
things like gastric peptides.
They're actually stomach peptides
that we talked about in
the previous episode,
things related to the ghrelin pathway
and other things from the
liver that can improve
the rate of tissue and wound healing.
You can bet that in the upcoming Olympics,
lot of people are using
peptides and compounds
and I'm not pointing fingers
at anyone in particular.
It's just this is separate
from hormone augmentation
of like injecting GH or
injecting testosterone.
People are now working
further up the pathways.
Other names of some of
the peptides are things
like ipamorelin, tesamorelin.
Some of these have clinical uses.
Others have just been made as compounds
for people in the kind of longevity field
or the self-augmentation
field, if you will.
So again, not promoting their use
but they're definitely out there.
And so now if you hear about them
or if someone's talking to you about them,
now hopefully you have
a better understanding
about their underlying biology.
And you can think rationally
about whether or not they are
the right decision for you.
Okay, once again, covered an
enormous amount of material.
Hopefully, now you
understand thyroid hormone
and what it does and a little
bit about its mechanism
or maybe a lot and growth
hormone and what it does
and how both of them take
care of our metabolism.
They dictate how many nutrients
we can eat and make use of.
They can pull from body fat stores,
repair muscle, repair cartilage.
They really are incredible compounds.
And they're actionable.
They're things that we can do,
like getting that early phase of sleep,
perhaps supplementing
with arginine, maybe not,
hopefully getting adequate exercise,
warming up properly, not
making the exercise too long
or too intense will help,
maybe sauna or things like it.
You know, deliberate, safe hyperthermia,
with the emphasis on safe,
might be things that are of use.
Regardless, even if you're not interested
in the thyroid or the
growth hormone pathways,
this brings to a close
our month on hormones.
And so now hopefully you understand
not just thyroid and growth hormone
but the logic that
underlies thyroid hormone,
growth hormone, estrogen,
testosterone, why we eat,
why we stop eating,
cholecystokinin, ghrelin.
If these names don't mean anything to you,
then perhaps go back and
listen to those episodes.
But regardless, I hope that you come away
from this with a deeper
understanding about these hormones
which are so powerful in controlling
the way our brain functions
and the interplay between
the brain and hormones
because it is really a
bidirectional conversation.
The brain is telling body
what hormones to make.
The hormones are influencing
all the tissues of the body
but also telling the brain
whether or not to eat more or grow more
or think more, et cetera.
So I really appreciate
your time and attention.
If you like this podcast and
you're finding it useful,
please recommend it to other people.
If you are on YouTube, please subscribe.
Please leave us a comment or feedback
in the comment section.
We do read all of the comments
and we use those comments
as ways to inform future
content of the podcast.
If you listen to it in audio form,
please subscribe on Apple and/or Spotify.
That really helps us.
On Apple, you have the opportunity
to leave us a five star review
and to leave us feedback,
written feedback as well.
I should also mention on YouTube,
hit the subscribe button
but also hit the notifications button.
We release episodes every Monday,
but sometimes we also really
short clips in between.
That way, you're sure to
never miss an episode.
If you want to support us further,
please check out the
sponsors we talk about
at the beginning of the podcast episode,
that really helps us.
We also have a Patreon account.
It's patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
There, you can support the podcast
at any level that you like.
And I mentioned supplements this episode.
I often mention supplements.
They are certainly not necessary,
but for those of you
interested in supplements,
we've partnered with Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E
because Thorne has the
highest levels of stringency
in terms of the quality of the ingredients
and the amount of the
ingredients in each capsule,
tablet, powder, et cetera.
If you want to see the
supplements that I take,
as well as get a discount on any of those
or any of the supplements
that Thorne makes,
it's Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E,
dot com slash the letter U,
slash Huberman.
And you can get 20% off any
of the supplements they make.
I should mention Thorne
works with the Mayo Clinic.
They partnered with them.
They worked with all
the major sports teams.
So really the highest
levels of stringency.
We're quite happy to be working with them.
And last but not least, I thank you
for your time and attention and above all,
for your interest in science.
[guitar music]