- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science,
and science-based tools for everyday life.
- My name is Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology,
at Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring you zero cost to
consumer information about science
and science related tools.
And keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker analyzes
data from your blood
and DNA to help you better
understand your body
and health and health needs.
I've been getting my blood
tested for many years now.
Because, it just turns out that many
of the things that are
important to our health
and wellbeing can only be detected
in a blood test or a DNA test.
InsideTracker makes that really easy.
They can come to your
house to take those samples
if you like, or you can go
to a nearby clinic as well.
The major problem with most blood tests
and DNA tests is that it's
very hard to make sense
of the information you get.
You get a lot of numbers
related to metabolic factors,
endocrine factors, et cetera.
InsideTracker makes it very easy,
to decipher what those levels,
in your blood and DNA mean,
and what to do about them.
They have a very easy to use
dashboard that if you go to it,
it can inform about
lifestyle choices such as,
adding or subtracting certain forms
of exercise or nutrition,
other things related to supplementation.
It's a really powerful
and easy to use program.
If you wanna try InsideTracker,
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman,
and put Huberman at checkout
to get 25% off any of their programs.
That's insidetracker.com/huberman,
and put Huberman at checkout.
The second sponsor of today's
podcast is Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an all-in-one,
vitamin mineral probiotic drink.
I've been using Athletic
Greens since 2012.
And so I'm delighted that
they're sponsoring the podcast.
I started using Athletic Greens
and I still use Athletic Greens,
because I find it very complicated
and almost dizzying to
figure out which vitamins
and minerals I need to take
in order to just cover
my nutritional basis.
Taking Athletic Greens
makes that very easy.
It also tastes very good.
I mix mine with water,
a little bit of lemon
juice, and I really like it.
So I drink it once or twice a day.
The probiotics that are
in Athletic Greens are
also important to me.
Because there are a lot
of data now showing
that the gut microbiome,
which is supported by probiotics,
is important for things
like the gut brain access,
mood, endocrine factors,
metabolism, many, many
biological functions.
And so by taking Athletic
Greens, I get the vitamins,
the minerals and the
probiotics all in one.
Easy to consume, great tasting drink.
If you wanna try Athletic
Greens you can go
to athleticgreens.com/huberman.
And if you do that you'll
also get, a one year supply
of liquid vitamin D three K two.
There are a lot of data now as well,
showing that vitamin D three is important
for immune function, for
mood, endocrine factors,
as well as other systems
in the brain and body.
That's athleticgreens.com/huberman.
And I should also mention
if you do that you won't just get
the vitamin D three K two year supply,
you'll also get five free travel packs
of Athletic Greens.
Mixing up powders
when one is on the road,
either in the car or in a hotel
or on the plane, et
cetera, can be kinda messy.
These little travel packs
make it really clean and easy.
So once again, if you go to
athleticgreens.com/huberman,
you'll get a special offer,
of your Athletic Greens
but you'll also get the year supply
of vitamin D3 K2, and the
five free travel packs.
The third sponsor of
today's podcast is Madefor.
Madefor is a behavioral science company
that makes attaining positive changes
and growth mindset easy,
through a simple set of
steps, and a monthly program.
The company was founded
by former Navy SEAL
Patrick Dossett and Toms
founder, Blake Mycoskie.
I'm the head of their
scientific advisory board.
And the other members
of the advisory board,
include people like the director
of the chronobiology unit
the National Institute of Mental Health,
members of Harvard Medical School,
and many other people who are
serious about taking science
and developing protocols,
that can be applied
towards positive habits,
and growth mindset.
If you wanna check out Madefor,
you can go to getmadefor.com.
And if you purchase any of their products
and put Huberman at checkout,
you'll get 20% off their program.
In addition to that, we
do a monthly Zoom call,
where the members of Madefor get on it.
And Patrick and myself,
sometimes Blake as well,
discuss the Madefor program
and the personal goals
and things that people
are trying to achieve
with the program.
So it's a dialogue back and
forth on Zoom call once a month.
Once again, that's getmadefor.com,
put in Huberman at checkout,
and you'll be able to
get the 20% off as well
as access to the monthly
Zoom calls with us.
Let's talk about neuroplasticity.
More specifically, let's talk about how,
we can optimize our brains.
Neuroplasticity is this incredible feature
of our nervous system that allows it
to change itself, even in ways
that we consciously decide.
That's an incredible property.
Our liver can't decide
to just change itself.
Our spleen can't decide
to just change itself,
through conscious thought,
or through feedback from another person.
The cells in those tissues
can make changes sure,
but it's our nervous system,
that harbors this incredible ability
to direct its own changes,
in ways that we believe, or
we're told will serve us better.
Now, today's a really
special episode because,
while we are going to talk about science
and as always we will
delve into mechanism.
Today's episode is really geared
toward answering your
most common questions
about how to leverage neuroplasticity.
The previous episodes were about focus,
and how to achieve focus
for sake of plasticity.
As well as the last episode which is,
what are some
of the portals into plasticity
that relate to movement,
how behavior can activate plasticity,
as well as how to activate
plasticity for behavior itself.
How to get better at
learning certain movements.
Today's podcast is really directed
toward answering your
most common questions,
and the bigger theme,
of how does one go about
optimizing their brain
or even think about, optimizing the brain?
What is this thing that we're calling
optimizing the brain?
In doing so I'm also
gonna share some of my,
typical routines and tools.
I don't share these because I think
that they are the only ones
that are available out there.
Certainly they're not.
Nor do I share them
because I think that
everyone should do them just
'cause I do them, certainly not.
I share them because many of you,
have asked for very concrete
examples of what I do and when,
and so I'll share those with you
and you can decide whether
or not those protocols are
for you or not.
Everybody's different, but
there are some common features,
of how we are all put together,
at the level of the
nervous system and body,
that direct us
toward particular practices,
particular routines
that can be especially
powerful, for neuroplasticity.
So I wanna open up the discussion today,
by emphasizing something,
that's fundamentally important.
Which is that plasticity, is not the goal.
Plasticity is never the goal.
Plasticity is simply a state,
or a capacity, for our
nervous system to change.
And so, nothing makes me more frustrated,
perhaps then when I hear,
oh, you know, this pill,
this potion, this practice,
it gives you plasticity.
Plasticity is just change.
The real question is what
are you trying to change?
And specifically what end goal
are you trying to achieve?
Specific end goals might
be extremely specific.
Like, you want to learn how
to speak a particular language
or you want to learn a new motor skill
or you want to get very good at calculus,
or you'd like to forget
the bad emotions related
to a particular human being or experience,
or it can be more general.
Like you'd like to be more creative.
And we'll actually talk
about creativity today.
Or you would like to achieve more focus
or you'd like to be less stressed.
So it's very important, that
you understand that plasticity,
and achieving plasticity
is the first step,
in what we call optimizing your brain.
You don't want your brain
to be plastic all the time.
In fact, one of the major questions,
one of the major unsolved
mysteries of neuroscience
is how each and every one
of us wakes up every day,
and knows who we are.
Why should that be?
Well, the brain is plastic.
It has a capacity to change
throughout the lifespan
but it's not so plastic, that every night
when we go to sleep, or in our waking
that the connections get
reconfigured so much so
that we forget who we are, or
how to walk, or how to eat.
It's a good thing that we don't have,
such robust plasticity
or ongoing plasticity,
that we have to restructure
ourselves each day.
It's part of what gives
our life continuity.
So remember, plasticity is
not and is never the goal.
The goal is to figure out
how to access plasticity,
and then to direct that
plasticity, toward particular goals
or changes that you would like to achieve.
And I should just mention,
there's no rule that in life you have
to leverage this incredible
thing called neuro-plasticity.
No one said you had to do that.
This podcast in this episode
is particularly for people,
who are either happy or
unhappy with where they're at
with a particular aspect of their life.
And they wanna shift it,
in some positive way.
And many of you listening might say,
well wouldn't everyone wanna do that?
Well actually, there are a certain number
of people that are pretty
good where they're at
and they don't wanna
change and that's terrific.
And I tip my hat to them and
I think that's wonderful.
If ever they decide
that they wanna leverage
these plasticity mechanisms,
they can, at any stage
throughout the lifespan.
Let's start by talking
about the different systems
within the nervous system,
that are available for plasticity.
And in doing so, I'll
frame them in the context
of what I do on a daily basis,
on a weekly basis, and on a yearly basis.
First of all, there are
several forms of plasticity.
They have names like
long-term potentiation,
long-term depression,
which has nothing to do
with emotional depression, by the way.
And things like
spike-timing-dependent plasticity.
Those names are used to
describe cellular phenomenon.
The actual ways that the
synapses, the connections
between neurons change.
I'll mention those things
and I'll give a little more [indistinct]
to what they are as I mentioned them.
But, that's probably not
the best way to think
about plasticity in terms
of optimizing your brain.
The best way to think about
it is in terms of short term,
medium term, and long-term plasticity.
Short-term plasticity, is any kind
of shift that you want to achieve,
in the moment or in the day,
but that you don't necessarily
wanna hold on to forever.
You might say, well, what
kinds of things are those?
Well, for instance, short-term
plasticity might be,
you wake up earlier than you
would like to catch a flight.
You're not feeling particularly alert,
and you want to use a protocol,
or you decide to use a
protocol which could be coffee
or it could be a certain form of breathing
or it could be some other tool,
to become more alert at a time of day
when normally you aren't that alert.
But, your expectation is
that when you return home,
you will discard with that,
the need to do that at 5:30 AM
because you'll be asleep at 5:30 AM.
So there's short-term plasticity,
behavioral plasticity.
Then there's medium-term plasticity
which are changes, that
you might wanna make.
I call this with respect,
and a little bit of humor,
or at least my kinda humor.
I call this the undergraduate,
pre-med phenomenon.
For those of you that
have worked with pre-meds.
And I have tremendous respect
for medical students and pre-meds,
there is a kind of a stereotype
which I don't necessarily agree with,
but the stereotype is that they wanna know
what they need to know
for sake of the exam,
but they don't really wanna know.
They just want the A.
And I don't think that's always true.
I've worked with a number
of different pre-meds over the years
and there are many of
them that are absolutely,
passionate about the knowledge itself.
And they also wanted the A.
But the pre-med phenomenon
as it's discussed
among professors and
TAs, is that, you know,
you've got these students,
they just wanna know
what they need to know
so they can get the A, right?
It's medium-term plasticity.
They don't actually want it to be embedded
in their memory too long,
or else they would actually
care about the information.
So that's medium term information.
And sometimes that's useful for instance
if you go on vacation to Costa Rica,
and you don't know your
way around Costa Rica.
You wanna learn the different
town and the routes there.
But you don't have any
intention of going back.
It's just medium term.
You wanna just program it in
for sake of your time there
and then you wanna discard it.
Most of the time
when we think about or talk
about optimizing the brain,
we're talking about long-term plasticity.
We're talking about the kinds of changes
that people wanna make
so that their brain
reflexively works differently.
This is what a child does
when it goes from not knowing how to walk
to knowing how to walk.
It doesn't have to think
about it after it learns how to walk.
It becomes reflexive.
Long-term plasticity, is
almost always the big goal.
It's I wanna know how
to speak that language.
I wanna be able to do that skill.
I wanna be able to feel this way,
without having to put much work into it.
And there are tools
and protocols that one
can do to achieve that.
And we are going to talk about those.
We've talked about a few of
them in previous episodes
but I will revisit those protocols today.
I'm gonna frame all this
in the context of the daily
life, the weekly life,
and the yearly life.
And that's because,
neuroplasticity and optimizing your brain,
rides on a deeper foundation,
of this thing that governs plasticity.
In fact, governs all our
life, called autonomic arousal
which is that we're asleep
for part of the 24 hour cycle
and we are awake almost always.
If we push ourselves and
stay awake, we're okay.
We can do that for a night or two,
but almost always we are
asleep for a portion of it
and we are awake for a portion of it.
I've said it before but I'll say it again.
The trigger for plasticity
in learning occurs
during high focus, high alertness states,
not while you're asleep.
And the focus and alertness are both key
because of the neurochemicals
associated with those states.
But, the actual rewiring
and the reconfiguration
of the brain connections happens
during non sleep deep rest,
which we'll talk more about as always.
And, deep sleep.
So you trigger the change and
in sleep you get the change.
So, some of the things
that we'll talk about today
about optimizing the brain,
are centered around not sleep,
but around the autonomic arousal system.
We have this system of
neurons in our brain and body
that's just incredible, that
wake us up and make us alert.
And when we're not accessing that system,
well, we cannot access plasticity.
We can not optimize our brain.
Likewise, if we cannot sleep
well, and we can't rest well,
we will not access plasticity
and rewire our brain
because that's when the
actual configuration
between the connections occurs.
So to set this in context,
I wake up each day, and
I'll be totally honest.
I usually don't feel like
bouncing right out of bed.
I usually don't feel completely rested.
And that's not because I
don't get enough sleep.
It's probably because I'm not terrific
about timing my sleep so well.
Now this month isn't about sleep,
that was the previous month
but I really wanna emphasize a few points.
I wake up, generally more tired,
and groggy than I would like,
because I tend to go to sleep too late.
It's just some thing that I do.
And I tend to get up early
either because I set an alarm,
because I have things to do,
or because I naturally wake up early
because the light coming in and so forth.
Well, what that tells me is
that I'm probably somebody
whose natural circadian rhythm.
You may have heard of chronotypes.
These are genetically programmed things.
But chronotype, is shorter than 24 hours.
It means that the cycle of waking
and alertness for me is
probably shorter than 24 hours.
Which means that getting some light
in the late afternoon will help me shift,
and make my cycle a little bit longer.
It will phase delay me
if that doesn't make any
sense, see a previous episode.
But what it really means
is getting some light
in the afternoon, will allow me
to stay up a little bit later.
But what it means is that,
I'm not really matching
my hard-wired needs
of going to bed probably at 8:30 or 9:00
and waking up at 4:00 AM.
I tend to go to sleep around 10:30, 11:00,
lately around 11:30 or 12:00
and then I wake up at 6:00.
And so of course, I'm gonna feel groggy.
So neuroplasticity will allow
me, to optimize my wakefulness
but I have to do something
in order to access that.
And some of you may
already be anticipating
what I'm about to say, which is,
oh, no he's gonna tell us
to get sunlight in our eyes
in the first 30 minutes of the day.
I am gonna tell you to do that,
but I'm gonna also tell you two things
that I've have not discussed before,
which relate to the plasticity,
between the melanopsin cells.
These sunlight detecting,
bright light detecting cells
in our eye and the circadian clock.
I've never said this
before in this podcast,
but it turns out that the connections
between these melanopsin
cells and the circadian clock,
are plastic throughout the lifespan.
There's a massive configuration
of the connections there.
And a cell type called the astrocytes
which are a glial cell,
are actively removing and
reinforcing connections
between the eye and that clock, every day.
Now this is incredible
because other aspects
of your brain that for instance,
represent you knowing who you are,
when you wake up in the morning,
or what your name is, assuming
that you're old enough
that you've already learned your name.
When the first things kids learn
and something we rarely ever forget.
Those connections, are changing all
the time every 24 hour cycle.
So there's an opportunity
for short-term plasticity.
So that's why I view sunlight
first thing in the day,
it helps me wake up.
The other thing that I do
is that there's a circuit,
that exists between the circadian clock
and our adrenals that I've talked
about before that triggers the release
of cortisol first thing in
the morning, that wakes us up.
Especially when we view light.
So if you're groggy in the morning
that's why viewing light is helpful.
But, the interesting thing is
if you start viewing light
frequently in the morning,
then those connections
between the melanopsin cells
and the circadian clock, become primed
or potentiated we would say,
they become stronger for
the anticipation of light.
And you naturally start waking up earlier,
feeling more alert.
So, what this says is
and what I do is I get that
regular light because I know
that some mornings,
I'm just not gonna feel very alert,
I'll feel, especially tired.
And I might not be able to access sunlight
because it's really
overcast or I'm traveling,
or some other feature.
But the system is plastic
so it shifted in the right direction.
Now it will shift back,
because it's short-term plasticity
after about two, three days.
So you wanna try
and get the sunlight
exposure on a regular basis.
The other thing that I do is
I delay my intake of caffeine,
for the first two hours that I'm awake.
Now, this can be very painful for people.
But, earlier we talked
about, the adenosine system
and how the accumulation of
adenosine makes us sleepy.
And caffeine suppresses adenosine
and it makes us feel alert.
But we know,
that if you ingest caffeine,
immediately on waking,
the signal to the adrenals,
to release cortisol,
which is a healthy release of cortisol,
and the suppression of adenosine
that happens as we come out of sleep,
and in deep sleep the
suppression of adenosine,
if you ingest caffeine too
early, there's a mechanism
by which the adenosine competes
for the receptors et cetera,
so that you have a mid-morning crash.
Because if caffeine, the way it works is
if caffeine is occupying
the adenosine receptor,
then the natural endogenous mechanisms,
for suppressing adenosine,
are not actually gonna have their action.
So the brain to adrenal axis,
is subject to plasticity also.
And so by delaying caffeine
until about two hours after waking,
I'm able to capture, and
reinforce, to potentiate,
the neural circuit that exists
between the circadian clock
and the cortisol released in the adrenals,
as well as, leave those
adenosine receptors,
unoccupied so that I can
then use the caffeine
to get a natural lift,
in alertness and focus
two hours later as opposed
to using it, just to wake
myself up out of sleepiness.
So while I'm sure there are
some eye-rolls out there
and some yawns, about,
oh no, it's the sunlight
in the morning thing again.
It's a powerful tool, for
readjusting these circuits.
So the short-term plasticity.
And the reason
for delaying caffeine
for the first two hours
of the day even if it's painful
to do for the first couple
of days is that then you
naturally start to wake up,
more readily in the morning
without caffeine because,
the adenosine is suppressed
and you don't have these competing.
It's called a competing antagonist,
for the adenosine receptor.
So I wake up, I get sunlight in my eyes.
Lately because I wake up very
early I do use a bright light,
to stimulate alertness.
It's not actually
designed for that purpose.
It's just a light board
that has been about 900 lux.
And then I delay caffeine.
Some of you have asked,
and again I'm not saying
anyone has to do this.
You know, what exactly do you drink?
I'm a big believer in black coffee.
I just happen to like black coffee.
People have asked me about,
and I don't wanna name brand names here
about this type of coffee or,
that type of coffee you
mixed with these other,
kinds of things.
Will that increase focus?
You know, I'm gonna talk today a lot about
the use of diet and
fasting and timing of foods
and certain kinds of foods.
But to be honest, black
coffee is just a simple choice
that's always worked for me.
I also make sure I hydrate
first thing in the morning.
There is plenty of data now
showing that even a slight,
increase in dehydration,
meaning just when you're lacking water,
can make people have headaches.
It can provide some additional photophobia
for those of you that are migraine prone.
Bright light can trigger migraines.
That's no surprise to those of you
that get headaches and migraines.
But dehydration, can compound,
the vulnerability to
migraine and headache.
So I drink water, I drink
black coffee, or I drink mate
which is just because I
have Argentine lineage
which is just a high
caffeine drink first thing
in the morning,
but I delay it until two
hours after I wake up.
And that's because, I want the circuits
between my eye and my circadian
clock and my adrenals,
to be functioning in a particular way,
so that then later the
caffeine is an addition.
It adds more alertness.
Now this is a discussion about
how to optimize your brain.
Many people who wake up quickly,
and just naturally feel
like bouncing out of bed.
I envy these people.
They will do just fine,
by going into a learning
bout or taking care of,
whatever it is that they
need to take care of.
Sometimes that's kind
of more mundane tasks
like email and whatnot.
Here's a more or less a rule
about how the brain
functions, vis-a-vis, focus,
learning and creativity.
And I'm gonna discuss this
much more in future episodes.
Generally states of high alertness,
when we're very very alert,
are great for strategy implementation.
When we already know how to do something.
And it's just simply a matter
of plugging the correct
elements into the correct boxes.
I've talked before about
duration, path and outcome,
as the three things
that the deliberate
conscious brain is trying
to figure out in order
to perform certain tasks,
even cognitive tasks.
This is the sort of thing
that we are very good at
when we're well rested, and we're focused.
In our autonomic arousal
or our alertness rather
is at a high level.
If you are somebody who is
hitting that alertness phase
of your day, very early,
right after you wake up,
that's a great time to move
right into things that,
at least the research says,
you already know, have the strategy
and you just wanna implement the strategy.
This is where I fundamentally depart
from the idea that, oh, you
know, you have to do the hardest
or most critical tasks throughout the day.
Sometimes the hardest
and most critical tasks,
are tasks that require creativity.
And as we'll soon talk about creativity,
and tasks related to it,
oftentimes come to us best
or the brain is best at achieving those,
when we're in states of calm
or even slightly drowsy.
Which is something that's interesting
in what we'll get into.
But for me, for instance,
I get up, I'm not terribly
alert, first thing.
And so I try and just get my brain
and my thoughts organized.
It's not a time for me to be responding
in a very linear fashion to emails
or carrying out calculations.
That comes about two hours later.
And I think many people
out there will relate,
mid-morning is when many people
tend to achieve their peak
in alertness and focus.
Now, many times I get the question and
this what I'm about to
say is directly related
to the hundreds of
questions I got about this.
Should I use, background
music in order to learn?
Should I have, you know,
construction next door?
Is that a good thing or a bad thing?
Is it better to be in
complete silence, et cetera?
Now this will vary.
Some people can tolerate their own noise
within their head much better than others.
Other people find that
having some background noise,
helps cancel that out.
But there's a simple rule
of thumb that one can use,
because at least my experience
is that sometimes background
music, background noise
is very helpful for allowing me to focus.
And other times, it's very distracting.
So what actually governs that?
Well, we have to ask ourselves,
what is at the source,
of the lack of focus?
If our lack of focus is
because our autonomic arousal
or our alertness is very, very high.
We had a little too much coffee,
or if there is such a thing,
slept a little too long
or we're really stressed
or really activated,
and we can't seem to focus.
In that case,
eliminating background noise,
and really just trying to get silence,
so that we can quiet some
of that autonomic arousal,
is going to be best
for learning and for implementation
of things we already know how to do.
For any kind of focus linear task.
Which, basically learning
is a focus linear task
is that you're just not necessarily,
performing well all the time.
Last time we talked about making errors.
So as a rule of thumb,
if you're too keyed up,
then silence and quiet
is going to be helpful.
In fact, if you're very keyed up,
a particular circuit,
related to the basal ganglia,
starts getting triggered more easily.
And this circuit, I'm
gonna talk about in depth.
But, it's called the go, no-go circuit.
We have circuits that
connect our forebrain,
to our structure in our brain
called the basal ganglia
which is actually a
collection of structures.
And the forebrain, which is involved
in rational thought and thinking
and planning and action,
is always trying to plan what should I do,
and then implement that action.
And the basal ganglia
are intimately involved
in that discussion.
There's a reciprocal
loop of communication,
between basil ganglia and cortex.
The basal ganglia has one set
of connections to the cortex,
and the cortex back to the basal ganglia
that facilitates go.
It facilitates action.
And the molecule, the
neuromodulator dopamine,
triggers the activation of go.
It tends to make us
want to do more things.
It tends to make us bias toward action.
By the way that dopamine binds
to something called the D1 receptors.
Just a particular type
of dopamine receptor.
For those of you that wanna know.
The no-go pathway,
the pathway in the basal ganglia,
and cortex that suppresses action,
involves dopamine binding
to this other receptor
called the D2 receptor.
Now D1, D2 receptors,
you can't just consciously decide,
oh, I only want my D1
receptors and my D2 receptors
to be active.
You have to think about,
which sorts of states of mind and body,
facilitate go, and which
ones facilitate no-go.
Now this is critically important,
because doing focused work,
accessing plasticity, and learning,
involve doing certain
things and not doing others.
So here's how it works.
And here's how I apply
it on a daily basis.
Because I tend to be most alert,
first thing, mid-morning or so.
And then I generally will
have my caffeine mid-morning.
My peak of alertness, in
the early part of the day,
is occurring for me sometime
between 9:30 and 11:00 AM.
That's just me.
Other people might experience
that immediately after rolling out of bed.
They might be wide awake and ready to go.
Which case they should be cautious
about throwing caffeine in the mix
and it's gonna make them very, very alert.
There are three sort of levels,
of autonomic arousal of alertness,
that bias us more toward
go, no-go, or both.
And this relates, to a question
that I've gotten now
hundreds of times from you,
in the comment section for this podcast,
which is, is it better for me to listen
to music in the background
while I work and learn,
or should I have complete silence?
And the answer is it depends.
But it doesn't depend
randomly on who you are,
or even necessarily time of day,
it depends, on your overall
level of autonomic arousal.
And it depends because,
autonomic arousal level of alertness,
biases the extent to which,
we are more prone to gos to action,
or to no-gos, to suppress action.
And dopamine is this molecule
that's swimming around
and is going to buy us one
or the other responses.
So here's how it works.
Let's say, I'm very alert.
Maybe I got a particularly
good night's sleep
the night before,
I had a little too much coffee,
and I'm gonna sit down to some work.
The thing to know,
and what I always tell myself
is when I'm very alert,
I am very prone to go, to action,
but I'm also prone to, not no-go, right?
I'm not gonna be very good
at suppressing action.
So those are two different things.
Being biased toward
action and being biased,
toward suppressing action are
two different things, okay?
So those are push pull.
Toward action, suppress action.
So, when you're very alert,
the tendency is for
everything to be a stimulus.
This is why when people say,
well, should I just take a drug
that will increase my level
of epinephrine and alertness?
Will that help me learn better?
No, because it will make you do things,
but it will also make you less good
at suppressing actions
that you need to suppress.
So if I'm very alert,
particularly alert for me
and I recognize what
that state is, of course
'cause everyone will be different.
I know what it is for me.
Then I want silence for learning.
I want it shut down my
internet, which I do.
I sometimes use a program,
that I believe is a free
program called Freedom,
where it actually locks you out
of the internet for a particular time.
They're not a sponsor of the podcast.
I just happen to use it.
There's another version
of Freedom where you go
to the wireless thing and you turn it off.
You disconnect from the wireless.
That's the other one.
Although, many people have a
hard time not reactivating it.
So I'm trying to shut down
the go pathway towards distraction.
And the other thing that I'll do,
is I'll generally turn off my phone,
put the phone outside in the car
or in really extreme cases
I'll throw it up on the roof
which is hard for me to retrieve,
so that I can't get to it.
So if I'm very alert, I'm aware
that I will have a bias toward action.
It will be hard for me
to suppress non-action,
but that it's very nonspecific.
Because, the next kind of
level down of alertness,
or autonomic arousal is
clear, calm and focused
where we have that kind
of sweet spot between,
our willingness to pursue action.
We're in a mode of go, and
it's not always physical action
but it can be pursuing
hard bouts of learning.
But that our ability to
suppress is also very good.
And this is because, and I don't wanna get
into too many details,
because of the way that dopamine competes
for these dopamine one receptors
in the go pathway and
dopamine two receptors
in the no-go pathway.
They're always in this kind of push pull.
And so there is a sweet spot.
And that sweet spot isn't flow,
where it is in some sort
of state where all of a sudden
things come naturally to us.
The state that we're trying
to achieve that's optimal
for learning is one in which,
we have the energy and focus to pursue,
but we also have the energy
and focus to suppress action.
So the basal ganglia are kinda working
in a perfect kind of sing songly manner,
through this parallel pathway.
Now, as we get tired or as we
round out an ultradian cycle
of about 90 minutes,
what happens is our fatigue even
if it's not a physical fatigue
that makes us wanna go to sleep,
but our mental fatigue
starts to accumulate
because these pathways of
go, no-go are actually,
very metabolically consuming.
So what I recognize is that
as they start to falter,
I have a harder time engaging and going
or going toward the goal rather.
I also know that my reflex,
toward actions that are unrelated
to the learning are also
gonna start increasing
because I'm not gonna be
able to suppress action
and activate the no-go pathways.
So if this all sounds like a mouthful,
let's make it very simple for you.
When you are very alert,
the best situation for learning
is going to be silence.
It's going to be complete quiet.
If you are low arousal,
and you're tired and
you're kind of sleepy,
a lot of people find that
having some background chatter
and some background noise,
can help elevate their level
of autonomic arousal.
And that's because our auditory system
and our visual system, are
linked and are part of really
what's called the salience network.
Which is that we're always,
scanning our environment for things.
And when we have a lot of things
in our environment to scan,
generally our level of alertness goes up.
This is why environments
that are very stark
or have very little or
very few objects in them,
tend to make us feel kind of calm,
because our salient
network kinda shuts off.
A lot of people don't like that.
They'll go to a meditation retreat,
or they'll go into an environment
where there's very little
clutter especially city people.
And all of a sudden,
they start feeling really, really anxious.
And that's because their internal level
of autonomic arousal is really high
and it's not being
occupied by all this stuff
to pay attention to.
And so their salience network
starts to turn inward.
They move from exteroception
to interoception.
They're not looking outside themselves,
they're looking inside themselves
and there's a lot of noise in there.
So, as a rule of thumb,
if you tend to be kind of
on the high level of
alertness and kind of anxiety,
and I'm not talking about
clinical levels of anxiety
but you tend to, be pretty high energy,
well then, you are definitely
going to benefit more
in a learning bout,
from learning to go as well
as activate the no-go pathway.
And that requires a lot of energy.
And when you have a lot of
distractions in your environment,
there's a high probability
that you're gonna be distracted
from the learning.
Now, some people are
just naturally more calm.
They're like my bulldog
Costello, who's exceedingly calm.
They're pretty mellow.
They're kind of clear, calm
and focused all of the time.
And those people, actually
are gonna be less flappable.
They're not gonna be yanked
around by background noise
or they're not gonna be around, you know,
bothered from their learning
or from their studying
by a clanging of a pot from
somebody in the kitchen.
So, each one of us
generally tends to ride up
and down this autonomic
ladder, so to speak,
at different times a day.
For most people, three hours after waking.
Those three hours, not
three hours on the mark
but for that three hour
bin tends to be the period
in which they're most
alert throughout the day.
Except I'll tell you later
about a unique time right before sleep
in which you're also very,
very alert, naturally.
So, that morning three
hours is quite vital.
Now, many of you might ask about exercise
and when to exercise.
I think I may have mentioned this
on a previous podcast episode.
But, the research shows that
at least for performance,
afternoon exercise might be better
in terms of avoiding injury, et cetera.
But in terms of rising body temperatures,
and matching body temperature
to have mental alertness, et cetera.
It's pretty clear, that
exercising early in the day,
not only biases us
towards waking up earlier,
but that it also triggers
the release of things
like epinephrine and
other neuromodulators,
that lend itself,
to a situation where we
have heightened levels
of arousal and mental acuity
in the late morning and
even into the afternoon.
Now, this can be very good
because if you wanna restrict
most of your focus learning
to the early part of the day,
exercising early in the day
does set a neurochemical context
or mill you for go.
It tends to trigger
activation of the go pathway.
And so for those of you like myself
who have a hard time kind
of engaging and getting
into action early in the day,
early morning exercise
within an hour of waking,
and certainly no later than
three hours after waking,
will give you quote unquote more energy
throughout the day.
It will make you feel
more biased for action.
You won't feel as lethargic.
So, in can kind of reviewing
what I've set up until now I
do the morning light thing,
I delay my caffeine
two hours after waking,
and then I generally try and get exercise
in the first hour or ideally
within the first three hours of waking up.
And then I'll move into
a focused learning bout.
Now, some of you wrote to me
and said, if I exercise early
in the day, then I feel
a crash afterwards.
If that exercise is very, very intense.
So you're depleting all your glycogen.
So you're doing heavy
deadlifts, et cetera.
Chances are after you eat, you
will start to feel a crash.
So this relates to timing of nutrition.
And in just as a general rule of thumb,
fasted states, and low
carbohydrate states,
I'm not talking about a keto diet around
the clock or all week
but fasted states,
and low carbohydrate states
lend themselves to alertness.
And that's because carbohydrates
are rich in tryptophan,
and they tend to lend
themselves to sleepiness.
Of course, ingesting large
amounts of any kind of food,
any substance that fills
your gut will divert blood
to your gut.
So if you eat a lot of food regardless
of whether or not it's a
lot of carbohydrate or not,
you're going to generally
feel more sleepy.
Now, many people, including
everyone use food,
to modulate their levels
of autonomic arousal.
And typically eating shifts us
more towards a state of calm.
And fasting shifts us more
toward a state of alertness.
And these are hard-wired
circuits that relate
to the need and desire to find
food which requires action,
or the so-called rest and digest system
which diverts our resources
and our energy towards digestion.
It makes us feel calm.
So I personally rely on water, mate,
and black coffee first thing in the day,
in order to exercise and get
into the first round of work.
If I find that I'm too alert,
and then I generally will tend to eat
and kind of bring down
my level of alertness,
and will continue working.
Now this is in district thing.
And since people asked me what I do,
and I'm not dictating that people follow
it exactly of course or even generally,
but I'll just tell you what I do.
It is possible if you're
drinking black coffee,
or mate and you're
ingesting a lot of water,
that you're going to
dehydrate yourself somewhat,
because of excretion of sodium.
Provided you don't have hypertension,
salt is a really good thing.
A lot of people think that they are low
on blood sugar because they're
shaky and they can't think
or they have a headache when
actually they're low in sodium.
And especially if you're
drinking a lot of caffeine.
So I'm a big believer in salt.
So I drink salt water first thing
in the morning because
I drink black coffee.
And that keeps my levels
of alertness really good.
I always thought that I
had messed up blood sugar.
I had shaky hands and I
didn't know what was going on.
I'd drink a little bit of
coffee and feel too amped up.
And turns out that it was a sodium issue.
And if I just drank water
with a little bit of sea salt
and or even just a typical table salt,
then I'd fell rock solid
in terms of my blood sugar.
Now, again, I'm not a
physician, I'm a professor
so I don't prescribe anything,
but I profess lots of things.
So I don't want people who have diabetes
or blood sugar issues to go off the rails.
You're responsible for
your health, not me.
But it's an interesting
parameter to think about
and experiment with, you know,
provided that your doctor says it's okay,
because I think a lot of people,
probably ingest too much sodium
but a lot of people might be
sodium deficient in particular
the people that are fasting.
I typically eat my first
meal right around mid day,
whether or not I've exercised or not.
And the food content there
is actually quite important to me.
I don't know why this is.
I don't have a scientific
mechanism for this
but if I eat hot food for
lunch, I get sleepy after lunch.
So I generally don't
eat hot food for lunch.
I might have a little bit of
soup or something like that.
But in general, I rely on
a low carbohydrate meal.
I'll eat meat or salad
or some variation of that
and nuts and fats and things like that
because of the [indistinct]
content for focus,
because the protein is good in my belief.
And because I believe
in eating fruits and vegetables.
I do that too.
If I've exercised very
hard early in the day,
I do ingest starches like oatmeal or rice
and fruit and things like that.
Now, why am I telling you all this?
Because, 100s if not 1000 people ask me,
is fasting good for focus?
And indeed fasting will
increase alertness,
but if you're so hungry
or preoccupied with food
that you can't focus well,
then it's not gonna be good for learning.
It's only going to be good for agitation.
Now, I'm just gonna mark continue to march
through my day.
And this is, of course what I experienced.
Some people are quite different.
But, what I find is
around 2:00 or 3:00 PM,
I start getting a little groggy.
A little bit sleepy.
I will tend to shift my work
from work that requires a lot
of duration path, outcome,
really careful analysis
and activation of the no-go pathway.
Meaning I'm trying to
suppress the impulse to look
at my phone or answer
email, or do other things.
This is why I haven't
emailed you back until 3:00
in the afternoon.
By the way, or responded
to your text messages,
whoever you are out there.
Around early afternoon,
I find I can do kind of
typical more mundane tasks.
Because, those tasks
require less cognitive load.
And they can be done more or
less, in and out of sequence.
I can answer a couple email here,
maybe answer that email there.
I don't have to do it
in pure linear fashion.
Any kind of linear work
or learning work is gonna
take a lot of focus.
And then typically around 4:00 PM or so,
I do two things.
Sometimes a little earlier.
Sometimes a little later
but I do two things.
One, is I make sure I hydrate.
Because if you're exercising
and you're eating,
you need to digest that food, et cetera.
I make sure I hydrate.
So I drink water.
I try and refrain from drinking
coffee in the afternoon.
This is a new thing for me.
I sometimes do it, but I
try and refrain from that.
And then I always do,
a non sleep deep rest protocol
sometime in the afternoon.
This is sometimes a 10 minute
yoga nidra type protocol,
or a 30 minute yoga nidra type protocol.
These are protocols I
have no relationship to,
no business relationship to whatsoever.
I've been doing them for years now.
They involve listening to a script.
We'll provide the links again
although we've provided them before.
Or I'll do a hypnosis protocol,
from Reveri Health
which is my colleague
David Spiegel's website
that has these free hypnosis apps
or scripts that you can listen to.
And those take me into a
state of really deep rest.
Sometimes so much so that I fall asleep.
And I always set an alarm
so that I don't sleep for
longer than 90 minutes.
But typically this goes
for about 30 minutes.
And I do that because for me
by about 4:30 in the afternoon,
I'm capable of doing basically nothing.
I am just a complete Costello.
I can't think, I can't do,
I can't respond to email.
I've just completely troughed
my ability to function.
I personally find it a mistake,
to that point,
down a double espresso,
and charge really hard.
It just doesn't work for me.
I end up really disrupting
my sleep schedule.
I end up disrupting a
lot of different things.
So for me, I do the non
sleep deep rest protocol.
It really helps me later
when I need to fall asleep.
It helps with all sorts of
things, as I mentioned before.
But I usually emerge
from that a little groggy
or feeling like I have another
whole day, second wind.
Like I could just work.
And then I'll do a
second bout of learning.
I'll do some sort of work
that either involves linear
analysis of something.
So maybe numerical work or
I'm trying to learn something.
I generally try and really use those bouts
of 90 minute focus energy
after the non sleep deep rest.
And as I mentioned in previous episodes,
there's a lot of evidence,
that these non sleep deep
rest protocols can enhance
and accelerate plasticity.
The most I think recent
and striking one is the study
that we referenced last time
in the caption notes.
It was the cell press article,
Cell Reports, great journal.
Was showing that these 20 minute,
kinda shallow naps and
non sleep deep rests,
can facilitate sensory motor learning.
So then I'll go into another learning bout
that's caffeine free.
This learning bout is very
different than the morning one.
This is a work bout or learning bout
that's more in the clear
common focus regime
because I've come out of
this non sleep deep rest.
I'm not ingesting caffeine
because I wanna make sure
that I can sleep later
that night really well.
And, this tends to be more
when I do creative type work.
Now, creativity is a topic
that we're gonna spend
the entire month on coming up soon.
But creativity is a very
interesting state of mind in which,
we're taking existing elements.
Things that we already know,
and rearranging them
in ways that are novel.
And I'd say, well, duh,
that's what creativity is.
But creativity has two parts.
It has a creative discovery
mode where you're kind
of shuffling things around
in a very relaxed way
and kind of being playful
or exploring different configurations.
And then creativity also has,
an absolutely linear implementation mode.
In which you take
the idea or the design you've come up with
and you create something
very robust and concrete.
And so creativity is
really a two part thing.
And the first part
of actively exploring
different configuration,
sometimes in a playful way,
sometimes in a way that's almost random
and just kind of exploring.
That state is definitely facilitated
by being relaxed and almost sleepy.
That is not a state
that I personally can access
very well early in the day.
I've tried to access
it coming out of sleep
because one would say,
well you're still sleepy early in the day
and just doesn't work.
Most of what I write down.
Most of what I do is complete garbage.
And so what I found is there's
this block in the afternoon
of about 90 minutes where, I
can do creative type writing
or creative type imagination of,
scientific ideas or
experiments we might wanna do.
Science might not seem
like a creative endeavor
to many of you, but it is.
Has a lot of imagining what if this,
or we could combine that
and thinking of novel concepts
or ways of arranging things.
So when you find yourself in
that kinda clear common focused mode,
creative works tend to
come about very well
in those regimes.
Now I know there are a lot
of people out there rely
on substances to access creative states.
I'm not a marijuana user.
It's just not the drug for
me, for a variety of reasons.
I'm not a drinker.
It's not the substance for
me for a variety of reasons.
You know, I'm not a cop I'm not out here
to tell people what they
should do or shouldn't do.
The problem with using
substances to access creativity,
is that generally the
substances that relax people,
will allow them to get
into that creative brainstorming mode,
but not so good at the
linear implementation mode.
You know, the other day I was remarking
with a friend that there are
some ads, some advertisements
that I've seen over the years,
that are just incredible.
I'll just tell you what they are.
So there's not cryptic or anything.
I'm revealing my tastes here.
There's a particular perfume
ad that Spike Jones made
that is just amazing.
I'll put a link to it
cause it's just so cool.
I don't want to give away the end
but it has a feature of it that
is particularly interesting
to me as a neuroscientist.
And it's just so cool.
'Cause I grew up in the
skateboarding thing,
I knew a little bit about
Spike's movies and skateboarding
and he's of course made
a lot of very impressive,
popular movies as well,
full length features.
I don't know him personally,
so this isn't a plug.
Not that he needs my
endorsement for anything at all.
But the amazing thing
about this advertisement
is it's a collection of things
that you would never really
think would be combined,
and it involves different speeds
of motion and all sorts of effects.
I mean, it's like a real classic
like Spike Jones kind delivery.
But, what's incredible is when you think
about not just the fact that
someone had to imagine that
but to actually implement the
steps in order to create that,
when you see this you'll
realize that was a ton of work.
You can't just put that together randomly.
And so a lot of people, not Spike clearly,
but a lot of people who have
an incredible mind for ideas
and novel arrangements of things,
they are great at accessing
that state but not so good
at accessing the implementation state.
It's also true that a lot of people
and some who tend to fall on
what we would call the kind of
like more Asperger's or
autism end of the spectrum,
are very good at linear implementation.
Now I'm not talking about all
forms of autism of course.
I'm sensitive to the fact
that there are many forms on the spectrum.
But, some people are very
good at linear implementation.
And that's, a separate
state from a creative state.
So, that afternoon block is when I try
and access the freer
kind of looser mindset
that's associated with the
fatigue that comes later
in the afternoon.
And, for some of you that state
that favors creativity
and creative learning,
might be better in the morning.
I don't know.
You're gonna have to decide.
For some of you you're
gonna be late shifted.
Some of you are gonna be morning shifted.
But where we have alertness,
generally we are good at
linear implementation,
we're good at activating the no-go pathway
and suppressing action,
and we are good at
pursuing particular goals
and strategy implementation.
And where we tend to be more relaxed,
and we tend to be almost
in a kind of sleepy mode.
So for me, coming out
of one of these non sleep,
deep rest modes or sleep,
that's when we tend to be
better at novel configurations
of existing elements, which is creativity.
And this brings about a question
that I get, all the time.
Which is, what about psychedelics?
So, I am going to talk, to
some experts on psychedelics.
I hope to bring some of them in.
Actually speaking on people coming in
or creatures coming.
A creature that's definitely
not on psychedelics
who doesn't need any is
Costello and he just arrived.
He seems to be in a sleepy
state most, all the time.
Hey buddy, how you doing?
You come in, yep.
He's working on his 15th sleep
deep rest episode of the day
which is generally followed
by a 10 to 12 hour deep rest episode,
almost exclusively comprised of REM.
And I know this 'cause his eyes are open
'cause they're so droopy, he
can't close them all the way
and his eyes are going like this.
And he's going down for the count.
So, yeah, nice and big yawn.
Okay so, psychedelics.
First of all, I wanna be very clear.
I am neither a proponent,
nor am I somebody
who rejects the potential
role of psychedelics.
I do however, think that psychedelics,
can be particularly hazardous,
for people who have preexisting
psychological issues,
and are not working
with a board certified,
psychiatrist or physician,
as well as for essentially all kids.
I think that the young brain is basically
in its own psychedelic
state and just naturally.
And all kidding aside,
I think that the young brain
is so subject to neuroplasticity,
that drugs, which like psychedelics
which are very powerful,
can be detrimental to
the developing brain.
That's just my stance.
If anyone disagrees with me,
I'd be happy to chat with you
about it in a polite and discourse.
I'll be happy to listen as well
as tell you more why I believe
that based on the data.
I'm mentioning psychedelics
because many of you asked.
Here's the deal with psychedelics.
At least here's how they work.
In a nutshell, psychedelics were thought
to unleash sensory processing
and to make it less filtered.
We have a lot of different
inputs from our eyes,
from our ears, from our nose,
from our taste, et cetera
that you're coming in
all the time in parallel.
And we have mechanisms that
suppress some of and allow us
to only focus on things
that are happening.
Visually, generally we don't
have synesthesia unless some
of us happen to have synesthesia.
We don't blend what we see
with what we hear in a way,
that is confusing to us.
We know what's making sounds and we know
what is a visual stimulus.
On psychedelics, people report
being able to smell colors
or to, you know, hear trees, et cetera.
And that's because there's
a lot of sensory blending.
Over that's led to the misconception,
that sensory blending itself,
is a creative process.
There's nothing creative
about sensory blending.
You know there's, the essence
of a creative process,
is that some novel
configuration of elements,
whether or not it's notes on a piano,
or whether or not it's words on a page,
whether or not it's numbers
or whether or not it's movement.
That some way in which those
are configured in some new way,
that the algorithm, the way in which,
they are configured makes
sense to the observer.
And this is a key thing.
It seems to me
that when people report their
psychedelic experiences,
it makes a lot more sense
to the person who experiences
it, than to the observer.
And so, creative works by
definition are new ways
of configuring things that lend themselves
to a bigger or greater or
deeper or novel understanding
on the part of the observer.
And just sensory blending is
not gonna accomplish that.
Now it is true and there's a great review
in the journal cell, excellent journal
about how psychedelics work.
And it turns out, they don't just work,
by allowing for more sensory blending.
They do, because of the way
that they activate certain
serotonin receptors et cetera.
They do lend themselves to
more lateral connectivity
between different brain areas,
more novel associations.
So in principle,
in principle, I should say
not necessarily in practice,
but in principle, they
do allow different areas
of the brain.
Maybe even the two sides
of the brain to communicate more broadly
than they would normally.
So that has certain elements
that speak to creativity.
But, it can't simply be the case
that psychedelics are
the portal to creativity.
Because creativity, as I mentioned before,
involves not just novel
associations and a breaking of kind
of space-time rules, it also
involves reconfiguring things,
such that the new space-time
rule that one comes up with,
is interesting, stimulating
and kind of in many cases,
delightful to the observer.
And that's why, many
claims that, you know,
psychedelics open plasticity
or they increase creativity.
That's not sufficient for me personally.
I'm curious about,
does it not just open the
creative thinking process,
this novel configuration process?
But does it also,
lend itself to the
implementation of creative works?
And the answer is, no.
In most cases it has nothing to do
with creative implementation.
Now, I think that, there may come a time
and certainly there are clinical trials
that are happening now,
where psychedelics are leveraged
toward particular clinical goals.
And I wanna tip my hat
to the work at Johns Hopkins
that's happening now,
which really lends itself,
to the idea that early preliminary data
and some of the papers
that are coming out
they're really fantastic.
Showing that there may
be some excellent roles
for certain psychedelics in
certain clinical context.
These are clinical studies done
with a psychiatrist present,
that is authorized to do that.
That can help people through
depression, trauma, et cetera.
And we're gonna spend a lot
of time talking about
that, including with some
of those folks running those studies.
So we can look forward to that.
So all of this is to say that,
no I don't take psychedelics
to access creative states.
That's not where I think the
major role, the important role
of psychedelics might show up
if it's going to for humanity.
I think that it may have
these important roles
in the clinical context.
Provided it's done legally and safely.
I think that,
the creative process being a
two-stage process means that,
I am personally best served
by having this period of
non-linear exploration of concepts.
Whatever it is I happen to be
working on in the afternoon.
But then I'll actually shelve that work.
I'll just set it aside and then
I'll revisit it the next day
or even the next day,
to see whether or not that
the work itself is ready
for deliberate linear implementation
which I would wanna do during one
of these highly focused states.
So, the long and short way
of saying this is that,
when we're very alert, do
linear type of operations.
When we tend to be more
sleepy and more relaxed,
that's when creative works
can first be conceived,
but their implementation requires
high levels of alertness.
Now, that gets us more
to the kind of late afternoon evening.
Now I am, as I mentioned before,
I'm a proponent of getting
sunlight in the evening as well.
This is a critical thing that
I have not mentioned before.
Here's how it works.
Many people now have heard
me say getting light early
in the day is important.
But that will advance one's clock.
It'll make you wanna get
up earlier the next day.
By getting light in the evening
it accomplishes two things for me.
First of all, it makes sure
that I don't get up too early
that I'm not waking up at
3:00 or 4:00 in the morning
because it's going to shift my clock.
It's going to delay it a little bit.
And so this is really important.
If you want to keep your
schedule on a normal routine,
on a regular 24 hour cycle
and not have your circadian rhythms
of sleep and wakefulness
drifting all over the place
and you want some predictability
to how your mind is going to work
in order to optimize
learning and performance.
Well, then you need to get
morning light any evening light.
The morning light is
going to advance my clock.
Make my system wanna get up earlier.
And the evening light is going
to delay my clock a little
bit so that on average
it kind of bookends my
circadian mechanisms.
And I'll basically wanna go to sleep
at more or less the same
time each night and wake up,
more or less at the
same time each morning.
That's how it works.
And that's a hard wired mechanism.
That's not some subjective
thing that I tell myself.
That's a hardwired mechanism.
So, that gets us to the evening.
And generally in the
evening I'll get that light
by going outside
or sometimes I'll do it
by turning up artificial lights brightly,
and then I'll start to
dim them for the evening
'cause as I've mentioned many times before
and I'm not gonna belabor the point.
You wanna minimize your light exposure,
especially overhead bright light exposure,
regardless of whether or
not it's blue light or not.
In the evening from about
10:00 PM to 4:00 AM.
Some of you asked,
wait I thought it was 11:00 PM to 4:00 AM?
Well, it is, but 10:00 PM
to 4:00 AM is even better.
It's just that when I originally
said 10:00 PM to 4:00 AM,
people were like that it's impossible
for most people to adhere to.
So for me, it screens off,
it's dim lights, and that's
what favors falling asleep
in a good night's sleep for me.
Since we were talking about food earlier,
I'll just revisit a little
bit of what I said before.
My evening meal tends to be
more carbohydrate rich more.
If I have proteins,
there'll be like eggs, fish
or chicken or something of
that sort or no protein.
And I eat high carbohydrates.
So I'm not one of these people that's keto
or high meat only, or anything like that.
Remember, fasting and low carbohydrate,
states facilitate alertness.
Carbohydrate rich foods,
facilitate calmness and sleepiness.
They'd stimulate the release
of tryptophan and the transition to sleep.
So that's why I do them late in the day.
Also, if you've exercised
early in the day,
especially if it's weight bearing exercise
or everything's weight bearing exercises.
I suppose unless you're an astronaut.
And you're in space.
But if you're early in the
day, exercising with weights
or you're doing a long run,
sooner or later, you need
to replenish glycogen.
And, I realized
that the ketonisters
out there are gonna say,
well, you know,
gluconeogenesis will allow you
to replenish glycogen, et cetera.
I'm just gonna call out the lie right now,
because I feel like doing it.
And 'cause I think it
just hasn't been stated.
Which is that, not everybody, but a lot
of the people that are proponents
of high meat keto diets, fine.
That's fine if that's what they wanna do.
And as you recall, I do
relatively ketogenic diet
during the day, for alertness or fasting.
But a lot of those people,
can replenish glycogen really well
without ingesting carbohydrates,
so-called gluconeogenesis
and enhance protein synthesis.
Because they are hormone enhanced.
I've been around a while.
I know what this looks like.
They're either thyroid enhanced
or hormone enhanced and I
don't pass any judgment.
But when you look at
people who look amazing
on keto and are able to have a lot
of energy and replenish
their glycogen on keto,
they are in many cases, not all,
but in many cases
they're hormone enhanced.
They're taking exogenous hormones,
that allow them to synthesize,
and repair muscle in ways that people
who aren't taking those
exogenous hormones can't.
This is not just true
of the men by the way.
This is also true of the women.
And this is a whole discussion
into itself probably not directly related
to this month of the podcast.
So, I don't mind that people do this,
but one problem
is when people are following
ketogenic diets all the way
through to sleep and they have trouble
with sleep or they're doing long bouts
of fasting and they're having
trouble falling asleep.
That makes sense.
It's because their
autonomic arousal is tilted
towards epinephrine release,
norepinephrine release,
and dopamine release.
So they have a lot of energy
but they have a hard time calming down
and getting into deep sleep.
I tend to achieve that
state using carbohydrates
and it also replenishes glycogen.
So again, you know, I'm not
trying to draw any fire,
but if I do, I'd be happy
to have a conversation,
about all that.
Again, no judgment, but I think
that most people out there are not aware
of some of the other variables.
Remember, good science is
about isolating variables.
And so oftentimes what we're
seeing in social media,
is we're getting
presented single variables
and we're not seeing the full context
of the other variables
that are being manipulated.
So, I eat pasta and rice
and vegetables and things
like that in the evening.
Also, I just find, maybe I'm becoming one
of the last people that does that.
Although I hope not.
I hope there are others out there like me.
From all the literature speaks to the fact
that carbohydrates not only do that,
but they also help maintain,
healthy thyroid function, et cetera.
So that's my bias.
That's what I do.
I do avoid caffeine and
whatnot in the evening.
I do take supplements and I'll be happy
at some point to put out the complete list
of supplements that I take out there.
But in general, these are
the core things that I do.
And they relate to a lot of the questions
that you've been asking over time.
The next piece of scientific
data that I'm gonna describe
is a very important
piece of scientific data,
for sake of understanding
how to optimize your brain
and access sleep.
It also can help avoid
a lot of anxiety issues.
And these relate to data from
Charles Czeisler, doctor.
He's an MD Charles Czeisler's
lab at Harvard Medical School.
He's run a sleep lab out
of Harvard Medical School.
For a long time now it
has very impressive work.
And what he's shown is
that the peak output,
of the circadian clock for wakefulness,
in other words the peak
of our wakefulness,
and the suppression of the sleep signal,
actually happens very late in the day.
So we have this trough of activity
and body temperatures
lowest right before waking.
Then as we wake up our
body temperature goes up
and into the afternoon
it continues to go up
and then it tends to fall
in the evening and towards bedtime.
But there's a brief blip,
of release of peptides
and other substances from the
sleep centers in the brain,
and the suprachiasmatic nucleus
that the sleep center
is this preoptic area,
that if you wanna look that up.
This preoptic area not far
from the circadian clock
that signals the peak of alertness
and wakefulness about
an hour, before bedtime.
And he say, whoa, that's really weird.
But a lot of people get into bed.
They're ready to go to sleep
and they're wide awake.
And they think this is an unnatural thing
or there's something wrong with them.
And actually it's not.
This it's believed,
I don't know, again, I wasn't
consulted at the design phase.
But it's believed, is a
signal that is helpful
to human beings to start
gathering up resources
and securing themselves
for a night's sleep
during which we, you know,
historically were very
vulnerable to attack
from other humans and
from animals and so forth.
And so that desire to run
around and clean the kitchen
or organize things, or
just a general feeling
of internal anxiety, late in the evening,
that's a natural blip
that naturally passes
after about 45 to 60 minutes.
Now that's often the time
when people start stressing
about the fact that they have
something to do the next day
and they worry about
not being able to sleep
and it can cascade into
a whole set of things.
So another thing that I do
throughout my day is I know
that early day I'm gonna be alert,
afternoon I'm gonna be kinda sleepy.
And then as the evening comes around,
in addition to doing all
the other things I'm doing,
I anticipate, a peak in
alertness in activity.
And I don't worry about it.
I use that perhaps to get
organized for the next day
but basically, I just go through,
if I'm gonna do anything, it's
gonna be very mundane task
like cleaning or things that
require almost zero effort.
And that probably speaks to
my cleaning abilities too.
But, the fact
of the matter is we don't
just go drift off into sleep.
There's this blip of
alertness right before sleep
that I hope just cognitively knowing
about will be helpful to people.
And that raises, yet another theme
that I think is going
to be very important.
Which is, physiological mechanisms.
Like these changes in alertness.
Or using breathing tools.
Something we'll talk
about in future episodes
to shift our levels of autonomic arousal.
Those are concrete, biological phenomenon.
So is fasting.
Fasting will increase alertness that way.
So is caffeine.
Not everybody's susceptible
to caffeine to the same degree of others
But, it's a physiological mechanisms.
We know the receptors.
We know the ligands as they're called
which bind to the receptors.
We know the mechanisms.
They involve cortisol and epinephrine.
Those are the sorts of things
that I personally try and leverage,
toward my learning and
optimization of my brain,
and my activity.
Doing physical activity early
in the day for instance,
tends to give us a longer duration,
wake up signal,
intends to accelerate
waking up early in the day.
That's why working out late
in the day can sometimes
cause people to have
trouble falling asleep.
It will also phase delay.
You make it so that you wanna
wake up later the next day.
It's not just 'cause you're tired.
It's 'cause you shifted your clock
with activity and temperature.
Many people ask me about
subjective tools for plasticity.
What about visualization?
Can we just imagine doing
a particular activity,
will that help us get
better at that activity?
There's some evidence
that visualization can do that, it's true.
But here's the important distinction.
And here's why I personally,
don't do much, deliberate visualization.
First of all, I get my best ability,
or achieve my best ability
to visualize things when I'm
in kind of a sleepy state.
I don't know why
but that's when I'm
able to, direct my brain
towards internal visualization
with my eyes closed.
And generally I fall asleep
and I can't remember anything
that I was thinking about before.
Some people, and these are work
that was done many years ago
by Roger Shephard and by others.
Roger was at Stanford but
and other labs have done
this too, of course,
of rotating objects
physically in their mind,
as a way of improving
or looking at the speed
of spatial calculations and so forth.
Some people are very
good at visualization.
They can close their eyes
and they can just see objects
and rotate them deliberately, et cetera.
A lot of people like me,
when we start doing that,
our mind drifts too easily.
But I like to think I'm a
reasonably focused person
in the waking state.
So, visualization it's interesting
'cause I think people are
very attracted to the idea,
that they can just think
about something and then
get better at it that way.
And it's probably true,
if you can be very linear
in the way that you visualize things.
So I wanna repeat that.
I think visualization
does have certain power.
If you can remain very linear
and deliberate and focused,
in the visualization.
But many people like
myself who are challenged,
with maintaining that linear
focus with eyes closed,
and in visualization,
they don't get much out of visualization.
And I think the data on
performance really supports that.
Now there are examples where for instance,
people will injure one limb
and then they will
exercise the intact limb,
or the non-injured limb rather.
And they will visualize the opposite limb.
Sometimes there's even
the use of mirror boxes.
So that let's say my left limb is injured.
I'm maintaining activity
with my right limb
but I'm using a mirror box
so it looks like my left
limb is working well.
Yes, there's some top-down
or feedback mechanisms,
that support the idea that
the injured limb can rehabilitate
more quickly, et cetera.
But, those are fairly elaborate schemes.
I don't want a mirror
boxes around my house.
I think these are
specialized circumstances.
They're a little bit like
the examples that we see
in the news where, oh,
so-and-so has a stroke
and then spontaneously
speaks a new language.
I don't know what the answer to that is.
It shows that the brain
has associative networks
that are typically suppressed
and those can be unleashed.
But you certainly don't wanna go out
and give yourself a
stroke deliberately to try
and unmask some skill,
because there's no concrete
way to go about that
in a way that you could really know
that you were gonna offset
the detrimental effects of the stroke.
In fact, I think it'd be a terrible idea.
So I think what I'm trying
to describe is how a typical,
I don't know if I'm typical or normal.
I mean, I've been told otherwise,
and certainly not normal.
But in terms of the way
that I structure my day,
I think that's normal.
That's pretty normal.
I tend to wake up right
around, I don't know,
somewhere between 5:30 and 7:00 AM,
depending on what I've been
doing the night before.
I tend to go to sleep
somewhere around 10:30, 11:00.
I tend to have one bout
in the morning where I can
do really focused hard work
and I can really activate the go pathway
while also activating the no-go pathway
so that I can really stay focused.
But I rely on some tools.
I have a period
in the afternoon where I get
sleepy and kinda out of it
like I think most people.
And I tend to come out of that
recognizing the opportunity
of that slightly sleepy
state for creative work
and for thinking about
things in novel ways.
I get light a couple of times a day.
I eat low carb during the day,
and I don't say high, but you know,
higher carbs I eat
starches, in the evening.
So in a way I can sleep.
And then, I really anticipate
that late afternoon peak and alertness.
Excuse me, late night peak and alertness
that many people confuse for insomnia
or challenges when actually
they're really quite normal
in their circadian cycle.
And then I fall asleep.
And if all goes well,
I stay asleep for four or five hours.
Typically it's three or
four and then I wake up.
I think I'm like most people I wake up
during the middle of the night.
Now, one thing that I don't
think has been discussed a lot
but one of my colleagues
at the Stanford sleep
lab tells me is that,
every hour and a half
or so, we all wake up.
Some of you even look
around, believe it or not
and go right back to sleep.
And you don't recognize it.
Waking up periodically
during sleep is the norm.
It is not abnormal.
I don't know
why this hasn't been
discussed more prominently.
I tend to wake up and if
there's a bright light coming
through the blinds, or if
there's some noise upstairs,
if Costello's snoring particularly loud,
I might get up, I might,
go use the restroom.
I might, you know,
pick up a book and read
under low light or something
and then I generally fall
back asleep and wake up,
typical time for me again,
5:30 or 7:00 AM in the morning.
This waking up in the
middle of the night thing
as I mentioned at the beginning
of the podcast episode today,
is not necessarily abnormal.
What it probably reflects,
is that the real time meaning,
the time that I should go
to sleep is probably
closer to eight o'clock.
The word midnight was literally
supposed to mean mid night.
We, many meaning all
of us were meant to go
to sleep and wake up
with the rise, you know,
with the setting and rising of the sun.
And we know this because
this beautiful study
from University of Colorado,
where they took people out
into the wilderness to reset
their circadian clocks,
measured by way of melatonin and cortisol.
They were completely out
of whack from interacting
with screens and staying
up too late, et cetera.
And they basically had
them view the sunrise
and view the sunset each
evening and almost all of them
not all of those
students, but all of them,
got onto a schedule where
they naturally wanted
to go to sleep at sunset
and wake up around sunrise
or just before sunrise, even
when they were brought back
into a normal artificial light setting.
So I think that's the natural pattern
and we've just deviated from
it with artificial lights.
So waking up at 3:00 AM or 4:00
AM doesn't necessarily mean
that there's something
screwed up about you.
Or that you have anxiety or
something, although you might.
What it likely means is
that you were supposed to
go to bed much earlier.
And because of this asymmetry
in the autonomic nervous
system where it's much easier
for us to push, and to
delay our sleep time
than it is to accelerate our wake-up time.
In other words, it's easier to stay up
and hang out at the party even
if you don't wanna be
there than it is to wake up
when you're exhausted and your fast sleep.
Most people are pushing
through, into the late hours
of the evening and night and going
to bed much later than they
naturally would want to.
And so I personally don't
want to go to bed at 8:00 PM.
A lot of good things happen
between 8:00 PM and 11:00 PM.
And so, I wanna enjoy those.
And I push through the evening hours.
But as a consequence, I'm
running out of melatonin.
My melatonin release is basically subsided
by about 3:00 or 4:00 AM
and so it makes sense
that I would wake up.
I don't take melatonin
for reasons discussed
in previous episodes.
I do rely on things
like magnesium glycinate
or magnesium threonate,
things like theanine.
I'm not saying any of
you need to take those.
That's just what I happened to take
in order to facilitate my sleep.
And it's been of great benefit to me.
If I wake up in the middle of the night
and I'm anxious for whatever
reason or my mind is looping,
I have a couple of rules.
One is, I don't trust
anything I think about.
When I wake up in the middle
of the night, any of it.
Unless I've had a magnificent dream
and I wanna write it down,
I'll do that every once in a while.
Typically when I go back and read it,
it's not at all magnificent.
I can't ever remember coming up
with anything really fantastic in one
of my dreams that stuck with
me, or that I implemented.
I don't really trust the
kind of thinking that happens
in those wee hours of the
circadian cycle for me.
There's just nothing either
for me terribly creative,
or worth linear
implementation at that time.
But, one thing that has been very helpful
is to sometimes do one
of these non sleep deep rest protocols
as a way to go back into sleep.
So a hypnosis app or some
of the scripts by Michael Sealey
that I've mentioned before,
or the Reveri Health, or
a yoga nidra protocol.
Those for me have been very
useful at helping me turn off,
kinda looping thinking in
the middle of the night
and fall back asleep.
In reviewing my schedule for you,
just as a context for how
to implement certain types
of tools for optimizing learning.
Realize that, it gives the impression
that there's a 90 minute bout of learning
and work in the morning
and then a 90 minute bout
of creative type work in
the afternoon and that's it.
There are a lot of hours
in between of course,
and I just wanna be very clear.
Those hours for me are occupied
by pretty not mundane tasks
but things that are kinda random.
Those are things like email
or attending to Zoom meetings
or meeting with colleagues and students
and things of that sort.
I sometimes will read just
for sake of my own enrichment.
I mentioned those two 90 minute bouts
because those are the two 90 minute bouts
where I'm trying to expand on,
the mental capacities that I already have.
They're to really where
I'm trying to stretch
and grow what I'm able to do
on a regular basis reflexively.
So I wanna emphasize that the
whole day doesn't just consist
of those two 90 minute bouts.
That's not the way my schedule works
and that's not the way
my lifestyle is arranged.
Which is fortunate
'cause I enjoy all those
other things as well.
And so for many of you out there who are
in school or have family
demands or other demands,
the key is to slot in those
brain optimization segments
of about 90 minutes, one or
two, or maybe more per day.
You're trying to slot those
in wherever you can amidst to your other,
obligations and things
that you need to do.
But, you wanna do that
in an intelligent way
that's anchored to your biology.
And then you wanna do a number of things
which I've talked about today,
in order to optimize those sessions
to get the most out of them.
So as we round up, I acknowledged
that once again I've covered
a huge range of topics,
related to how to optimize learning,
and brain change, and
essentially mental performance.
And I've set that in the context,
of some biological mechanism
like the basal ganglia,
go, no-go pathways,
the circadian autonomic system,
and some of the relationship
between food and fasting
and particular types of food
in alertness or sleepiness.
Linear focus and strategy
implementation is best served
by high alert states,
although not too alert,
and how creative states,
at least the first phase of creativity,
which is the creative arrangement,
kind of brainstorming stage
is supported by states
of kind of relaxation
or even slightly sleepy.
But the creative
implementation is a very linear
and focused and deliberate process,
much like the highly focused
state, that I described.
I described how I do these things so just
to give you a context.
A lot of you asked for, you know,
what I do in order to
set it within a context.
But by no means are these rigid times
and ways of doing things.
But, I think it's fair to say that,
what I do has a circadian logic.
It also has grounding
in biological mechanisms
that are very concrete.
That we know the cells and mechanisms
and neuro-transmitters.
And then some
of them are a little
bit headed out into the,
what we would call, kind
of emerging, or, you know,
I don't wanna say cutting
edge, but maybe front edge
of what neuroscience is
starting to understand
about creativity and so forth.
Those are areas that are just now,
coming to some clarity.
And there is certainly is
still a lot more work to do.
There are a lot of different
ways to arrange one's routine.
But hopefully, the tools
and practices I described,
will be useful to you.
I wanna mention that a lot
of people ask me about
specific tools and practices.
They asked me of Wim Hof
Breathing, about ice baths.
Have talked a little bit
about ice baths before I
think in cold exposure.
About binaural beats and
things of those sorts.
I think the way to look at any tool,
to modulate or measure the nervous system,
is ask whether or not it's
going to move you up or down,
the state of autonomic arousal.
Whether or not it's gonna
can make you more alert
or more calm.
More focused or less focused.
That's kind of the two axes here
that we need to think about.
Sometimes you wanna be
more alert than you are.
And indeed, things like
cold showers, ice baths,
super oxygenation, Wim Hof type breathing,
will bring your level of alertness up.
There's some cautionary notes
associated with each of those.
You need to read
and understand those
cautionary notes, for yourself.
Everybody's different and some
of those carry certain dangers,
under certain conditions.
Others have huge margins for safety.
An ice bath generally wakes you up.
A warmer, hot bath generally
calms you down, right?
Binaural beats, there aren't a lot
of data and quality
peer-reviewed journals.
I did put in the effort
to go search it out.
There are a few.
Binaural beats are
listening to frequencies
of sound that slightly differ
offset for the two ears.
It has been shown, can shift the brain
into particular states.
You'll notice today, I didn't really talk
about alpha or theta or gamma rhythms.
I personally in reviewing the literature,
I don't think it's fair to say
that alpha states are great for X
and theta states are great for Y.
And besides, most of us aren't walking
around our homes and our workplaces,
geared up to EEG machines
or with wires down below our skull.
So we don't know when we're
in those states anyway.
I think the subjective reading of whether
or not one is alert, or calm,
and whether or not that
alertness or calmness matches
the goal or that thing that
we're trying to achieve
in terms of learning, including sleep,
is the most valuable,
internal tool and recognition
that we can all have.
In other words, if I want to be very alert
and I need to be very
alert and I'm exhausted,
there might be tools that
I should use to wake up.
It might also speak to the fact
that I might not have slept
as well as I could have or
should have the night before.
So it's really about a match
between where we are on
that autonomic arousal scale
and what we're trying to achieve.
And indeed, there are gonna be a lot
of tools including supplements
and other prescription drugs
and things that can help,
move us along that autonomic continuum,
up toward more alertness
or toward more calmness.
But ultimately it's about
tailoring that alertness
and calmness to the
specific types of learning
and activities that you are
going to do and perform.
And, it's reciprocal.
Meaning some of those activities
like exercise early in the
day will increase your level
of autonomic arousal and alertness.
Certain foods, will tend to wake you up.
Certain foods will tend
to make you more sleepy
and the volume of food
and the timing of food is a factor also.
So it's a huge parameter space.
It's a huge set of variables,
that impacts whether or
not we're feeling well,
performing well, learning
great, or not learning great.
And the key thing is
to become an observer,
of your own system and what works for you.
And, to recognize that there are two bins
of tools for optimizing,
learning and brain performance.
One, are tools that are really anchored
in biological mechanism
and we are certain of what those are.
I've talked about some of those.
The other, the more subjective tools,
for some of you visualization,
might work terrifically well.
For some of you, one song
might really wake you up
because of the associations
you have with it.
And for me, I might just, you know,
it might repel me from the room.
'Cause I don't like it or
it might put me to sleep.
But of course,
volume is kind of a universal.
Loud music tends to wake people up.
Soft music, doesn't tend to
wake them up quite as much.
So, part of today is really
getting you to think about,
in a scientific way, in a structured way,
about the non-negotiable elements
which are that you're
going to have a period
of every 24 hour cycle when
you tend to be more awake,
and a period when you
tend to be more asleep.
And how to leverage those
so you're not fighting an
uphill battle to wake up
when you actually,
would want to be in and should be sleepy
and not trying to go to
sleep when you are naturally,
going to be most awake.
So a lot of it is really anchors back
to those core mechanisms of biology,
and then you start layering
on the different protocols
of food and supplementation, et cetera.
And I think it's important
to recognize that some people
are just more go and no-go.
And some people,
are just calmer and have
a harder time getting
into action in an activity.
It's just the way that we're wired.
Some of us have autonomic nervous systems
that are more geared towards
parasympathetic, calm states.
One of the reasons I love
bulldogs, not just my bulldog,
is that they are very calm animals.
In fact, they make no
spontaneous movements
unless there's something to respond to.
And I find that incredibly relaxing.
Other animals like pit bulls,
who I also really like and enjoy
and other species, their
tail is always wagging.
And that they're always in a
position to make a movement
at any any second 'cause they tend to ride
at pretty high levels
of autonomic arousal.
They pop up really quickly.
When you say it's time to go for a walk,
Costello does it one limb at a time.
And sometimes he just goes back to sleep.
And so, that there are
people like that too.
And so you have to know where you are
and what particular goals
you're trying to pursue.
As a final closure to this,
I wanna emphasize that today as always,
I've strived to be accurate.
I'm sure if I made mistakes,
some of you will point
out and I appreciate that.
And I'll post a correction,
if we agree that I indeed
misspoke, or misguided something.
But, by no means was I exhaustive.
I mean, I might've exhausted some of you
but the information wasn't exhaustive.
Meaning, there's no way
that I could cover all the ways in which,
we optimize or can optimize
learning and performance.
I think we've touched on a
number of them that I hope,
that you'll find value in
and that you'll explore in your own lives.
We are continuing with this theme
because that's what we
do, for this podcast.
We stay on one theme for an entire month.
For the next episode,
we're going to explore two,
very essential aspects of neuroplasticity.
That actually relate to learning.
Which are pain, pain management,
and neural regeneration.
And for those of you that,
don't have injuries or don't
suffer from chronic pain,
the discussion is still gonna
be a very important one.
Because it's not just going to be
about pain that you're
trying to get rid of.
It's also going to be about how
certain sensory experiences,
within the pain network,
can become amplified,
as well as how we can
use top-down modulation.
We can use our mind, to
suppress the pain response.
We're also gonna talk about some
of the hardwired mechanisms,
that are bottom up,
that exist in our periphery,
in our body to control pain.
And we're also gonna discuss,
a number of interesting interactions
between the pain system
and the learning system.
So again if you're, not
interested in pain per se,
it still is going to be
a very valid conversation
for sake of understanding how
to optimize brain performance.
And neuro-regeneration goes hand in hand,
with that discussion.
So I hope you'll join us for that.
I suppose I'd be remiss
if I didn't mention that,
Costello has been snoring
extremely loudly today.
He had a good long walk this morning
which means up the
driveway down the driveway.
He's an old dog.
So if you've been hearing him
in the background and
it's been distracting,
now you know why.
It probably relates to, where you were
on your level of autonomic arousal.
And I'll leave it
to you to answer that
question for yourself.
Many of you continue
to graciously ask how you
can help support the podcast.
And we really appreciate the question.
The best way is to subscribe
wherever it is you happen
to be listening or watching.
So for those of you that it's YouTube,
please subscribe to the YouTube channel.
If it's Apple, subscribe
to the podcast on Apple
or if it's Spotify, subscribe there.
Maybe you've subscribed to all three.
If you have comments and feedback for us,
suggestions for future podcast,
episodes or topics to cover,
please, place those in the
comment section on YouTube.
Apple also provides a section
where you can give us a rating.
We would love it if you
give us a five star rating
or whatever it is that
you feel that we deserve.
And in general, if you could
tell people about the podcast,
we hope that you would tell them
because you think the
information will be of use
to them of course.
Tell your friends, tell your family,
tell your coworkers, because
as we expand the podcast,
the support for the podcast
just grows along with it.
So that's a terrific way to support us.
As always, check out our sponsors
which were mentioned at the beginning.
And in addition to that,
we've now set up a Patreon account.
Some of you asked specifically,
how you can help support the podcast
but you weren't
interested, in our sponsors
or you were already
engaged with our sponsors.
So, we have a Patreon account.
You can find it at
patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
Finally, in previous episodes today,
and in future episodes,
I mentioned supplements.
Supplements are one way,
certainly not the only way,
but they're one way in
which we can modulate,
our nervous system,
for sake of better of
sleep, learning, alertness,
and several other things as well.
If you're interested in supplements,
we've partnered with Thorne, T H O R N E,
because Thorne supplements
have very high stringency
in terms of, what's in the bottle,
the amounts of the substances that are
in each capsule or pill, et cetera.
And, they have partnered
with other groups such
as the Mayo Clinic, all
the major sports teams.
So there's very high rigor
associated with Thorne
which is why we've decided
to partner with them.
If you'd like to check
out Thorne supplements
and see the supplements that I take,
you can go to Thorne,
thorne.com/u/huberman.
And you'll see a list of some
of the supplements that I take.
As well, you'll get 20% off,
any of the supplements listed there,
as well as anywhere else
on the Thorne website.
So that's Thorne, thorne.com/u/huberman,
for 20% off, any Thorne supplements.
Last but not least, on
behalf of me and Costello,
I wanna thank you for your
time and attention today.
And as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]