- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
[upbeat music]
My name is Andrew Huberman
and I'm a professor of Neurobiology
and Ophthalmology at
Stanford school of medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of my desire
and effort to bring zero
cost to consumer information
about science and science related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme.
I want to thank the first
sponsor of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes blood factors
and DNA related factors
that helps you develop a
personalized health plan.
Many important factors
related to our health
and wellbeing can only be measured
by a blood sample and by a DNA sample.
I've been getting my blood
work done for many years now.
And I use InsideTracker
because InsideTracker makes it very easy
to not only get the blood work done,
someone can come to your house
or you can go to a clinic for instance
but also to interpret
the data that you get.
Oftentimes when we get blood work done
there are all these numbers
and all these levels
of different hormones and
metabolic factors and so forth.
But one doesn't know what
to do with that information
InsideTracker has a
terrific dashboard platform
where you go online and it
makes analyzing all that easy.
And it also provides some very simple
and straightforward directives
in terms of exercise, nutrition
and other lifestyle factors
that can help guide your health
and improve your health.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman
and use the code "Huberman" at checkout
to get 25% off your order.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Headspace.
Headspace is a meditation app
that makes meditating easy.
I've been meditating on and off
for about three decades now.
And typically it's been more off than on.
I think like a lot of people
I find it hard to stick
with a meditation practice.
A few years ago, I started
using the Headspace app.
And when I did that,
I found that I was meditating
really consistently.
First of all, the meditations
in Headspace are backed
by quality scientific
peer reviewed studies.
Second of all the meditations
allow the meditation
to be kind of easy and fun to access.
I started first using
them when I would travel
because on JetBlue flights,
which was the airline I was using
the meditations are
offered as an alternative
to watching a TV or a movie.
And I found that I would arrive
feeling much more refreshed
than had I just sort of zoned
out on the TV the whole time,
or even if I had slept.
And I'll continue to
use Headspace regularly
pretty much every day
for a short meditation.
And I personally derive
tremendous benefits from it.
If you'd like to try Headspace
you can go to headspace.com/specialoffer
and they'll give you one
month of all the meditations
that they have available completely free.
That's the best offer available
right now from Headspace.
So you can go to
headspace.com/specialoffer
and you'll get one month completely free
all the meditations they have.
The third sponsor of
today's podcast is Madefor.
Madefor as a behavioral science company
that is a subscription model
in which you engage in
specific activities each month
for 10 months in order to bring about
positive behavioral
change and growth mindset.
The company was founded by
former Navy seal Patrick Dossett
as well as Toms founder Blake Mycoskie.
I'm the lead advisor of the
scientific advisory board
at Madefor and some of the other members
of the advisory board include
the head of the chronobiology unit
at the national institute of health
as well as psychiatrists
from Harvard, UC Irvine
and many other individuals
who are serious about science
and helped develop the Madefor program.
If you want to try Madefor,
you can go to getmadefor.com
and if you enter "Huberman" at checkout
you'll get 15% off the program.
Today we're talking about neuroplasticity
which is this incredible
feature of our nervous systems
that allows it to change
in response to experience.
neuroplasticity is arguably
one of the most important
aspects of our biology.
It holds the promise
for each and all of us
to think differently, to learn new things,
to forget painful experiences
and to essentially adapt to
anything that life brings us
by becoming better.
Neuroplasticity has a
long and important history
and we're not going to
review all of it in detail.
But today what we are
going to do is discuss
what is neuroplasticity?
As well as the different
forms of neuroplasticity.
We're going to talk about
how to access neuroplasticity
depending on how old you are
and depending on the
specific types of changes
that you're trying to create.
This is a topic for which
there are lots of tools,
as well as lots of biological principles
that we can discuss.
So let's get started.
Most people are familiar with
the word neuroplasticity.
It's sometimes also
called neural plasticity.
Those are the same thing.
So, if I say neuroplasticity
or neural plasticity,
I'm referring to the same process,
which is the brain and
nervous system's ability
to change itself.
There are a lot of reasons
why the nervous system would do this.
It could do it in response
to some traumatic event.
It could, for instance,
create a sense of fear
around a particular place
or a fear of automobiles or planes.
It could also occur when
something positive happens,
like the birth of our first child
or when our puppy does something amusing
or we see an incredible feat
of performance in athleticism.
The word neuroplasticity
means so many things to
so many different people
that I thought it would be important
to just first put a little
bit of organizational logic
around what it is and how it happens,
because nowadays if you were to go online
and Google the word neuroplasticity,
you would find hundreds of
thousands of references,
scientific references
as well as a lot of falsehoods
about what neuroplasticity is
and how to access it.
As I mentioned before,
we're going to talk
about the science of it
and we're going to talk about the tools
that allow you to engage
this incredible feature
of your nervous system.
And that's the first point,
which is that all of us were
born with a nervous system
that isn't just capable of change,
but was designed to change.
When we enter the world,
our nervous system is primed for learning.
The brain and nervous system of a baby
is wired very crudely.
The connections are not precise.
And we can see evidence of that
in the fact that babies
are kind of flopping,
they're like a little
potato bug with limbs.
They can't really do much in
terms of coordinated movement.
They certainly can't speak
and they can't really do
anything with precision.
And that's because we come
into this world overconnected.
We have essentially wires,
those wires have names
like axons and dendrites.
Those are the different
parts of the neurons
discussed in episode one,
but those little parts and
those wires and connections
are everywhere.
Imagine a bunch of roads
that are all connected to one
another in kind of a mess,
but there are no highways.
They're all just small roads.
That's essentially what the
young nervous system is like.
And then as we mature, as
we go from day one of life
to 10 years old, 20
years old, 30 years old,
what happens is
particular connections get
reinforced and stronger
and other connections are lost.
So that's the first important principle
that I want everyone to understand,
which is that developmental plasticity,
the neuroplasticity that
occurs from the time we're born
until about age 25 is mainly a process
of removing connections that
don't serve our goals well.
Now, of course, certain events happen
during that birth to 25 period
in which positive events
and negative events
are really stamped down
into our nervous system
in a very dramatic fashion,
by what we call one-trial learning.
We experience something once
and then our nervous
system is forever changed
by that experience.
Unless of course, we go through some work
to undo that experience.
So, I want you to imagine in your mind
that when you were
brought into this world,
you were essentially a widely
connected web of connections
that was really poor
at doing any one thing.
And that through your experience,
what you were exposed to by your parents
or rather caretakers,
through your social interactions,
through your thoughts,
through the languages that you learn,
through the places you
traveled or didn't travel,
your nervous system became customized
to your unique experience.
Now, that's true for
certain parts of your brain
that are involved in what we call
representations of the outside world.
A lot of your brain
is designed to represent the visual world
or represent the auditory world
or represent the gallery of smells
that are possible in the world.
However, there are aspects
of your nervous system
that were designed not to be plastic.
They were wired so that plasticity
or changes in those
circuits is very unlikely.
Those circuits include things like,
the ones that control your heartbeat,
the ones that control your breathing,
the ones that control your digestion,
And thank goodness that those
circuits were set up that way
because you want those circuits
to be extremely reliable.
You never want to have to think about
whether or not your heart will beat
or whether or not you
will continue breathing
or whether or not you'll be
able to digest your food.
So many nervous system
features like digestion
and breathing and heart
rate are hard to change.
Other aspects of our nervous system
are actually quite easy to change.
And one of the great gifts of childhood,
adolescence and young adulthood,
is that we can learn through
almost passive experience.
We don't have to focus that hard
in order to learn new things.
In fact, children go
from being able to speak
no language whatsoever
to being able to speak many many words
and comprise sentences
including words they've never heard before
which is remarkable.
It means that
the portions of the brain
involved in speech and language
are actually primed to learn
and create new combinations.
What this tells us is that the young brain
is a plasticity machine.
But then right about age 25
plus or minus a year or two,
everything changes.
After age 25 or so,
in order to get changes
in our nervous system,
we have to engage in a completely
different set of processes
in order to get those changes to occur
and for them more
importantly to stick around.
And this is something that
I think is vastly overlooked
in the popular culture
discussion about neuroplasticity.
People always talk about
fire together, wire together.
Fire together wire together is true.
It is the statement of
my colleague at Stanford,
Carla Shatz
and it's an absolute truth
about the way that the
nervous system wires up
early in development.
But, fire together wire together
doesn't apply in the
same way after age 25.
And so we have these little
memes and these little quotes
that, you know circulate on the internet
like fire together, wire together
or there's a famous quote
from the greatest neurobiologist
of all time, Ramón y Cajal.
I think it goes something like, you know
should somebody wish to
change their nervous system
they could be the sculptor
of their nervous system
in any way they want, something like that.
And that sounds great.
I mean, who wouldn't want to
change their nervous system
any way they want,
but what's lost in those statements
is how to actually accomplish that.
And we're going to cover that today
but please understand
that early in development
your nervous system is
connected very broadly
in ways that make it very
hard to do anything well.
From birth until about age 25
those connections get refined
mainly through the removal
of connections that don't serve us
and the incredible
strengthening of connections
that relate to either powerful experiences
or that allow us to do
things like walk and talk
and do math, et cetera.
And then after age 25,
if we want to change those connections,
those super highways of connectivity,
we have to engage in some
very specific processes.
And those processes, as
we'll soon learn are gated.
Meaning you can't just
decide to change your brain.
You actually have to go
through a series of steps
to change your internal state
in ways that will allow
you to change your brain.
I just want to acknowledge that
Costello is snoring
particularly loud today.
Some of you seem very keen
at picking up on his snoring,
others of you can't hear his snoring.
It's very low rumbling sound
and whether or not you can or you can't
probably relates to the
sensitivity of your hearing.
We're actually going to talk
about perfect pitch today
and range of auditory detection.
And so if you can hear
Costello's snoring enjoy,
if you can't, enjoy.
I want to talk about how
the nervous system changes.
What are these changes?
Many of us have been captivated
by the stories in the popular press
about the addition of new neurons.
This idea, oh, if you go
running or you exercise,
your brain actually makes new neurons.
Well, I'm going to give you the
bad news first which is that,
after puberty, so after
about age 14 or 15,
the human brain and nervous
system adds very few
if any new neurons.
The idea that new neurons
could be added to the brain
is one that has a rich history
in experimental science.
It's clear that in rodents
and in some non-human primates
new neurons, a process
called neurogenesis,
can occur in areas of the brain,
such as the olfactory bulb,
which is of course involved in smell
as well as a region of our hippocampus,
a center of the brain involved in memory
called the dentate gyrus
of the hippocampus.
And there is strong evidence
that new neurons can be
added to those structures
throughout the lifespan.
In humans, the evidence is a
little bit more controversial.
It's clear that we can add new neurons
to our olfactory bulb.
In fact, if any of you have ever
had the unfortunate experience
of being hit on the head too hard,
the wires called axons from
those olfactory neurons
that live in your nose
can get sheared off
because they have to
pass through a bony plate
called the cribriform plate.
And the cribriform plate
can shear those axons
and people can become
what's called anosmic,
they won't be able to smell.
But over time, those neurons
unlike most all central
nervous system neurons
can grow those connections back
and even reestablish new neurons
being added to the olfactory bulb.
They come from elsewhere deep in the brain
and they migrate through a pathway called
the rostral migratory stream.
You can Google these words
and look up some of the
descriptions of this
if you'd like to learn more.
So indeed there is some evidence
that the neurons responsible for smell
can be replaced throughout the lifespan.
Certainly, in very young individuals
from birth till about age 15 or so.
Whether or not they're new
neurons added to the hippocampus,
the memory center of the
human brain isn't clear.
Many years ago, Rusty Gage's
lab at the Salk Institute
did a really important study
looking at terminally ill cancer patients
and injecting them with a label,
a dye that is incorporated
only into new neurons.
And after these patients died,
their brains were harvested.
The brains were looked at and
there were new neurons there,
there was evidence for new neurons.
Those results I think stand over time
but what was not really discussed
in the popular press
discussion around those papers
was that it was very few
cells that were being added.
And a number of papers have
come along over the years
mainly from labs at UCSF,
although from others as well,
showing that if there are new neurons
added to the adult brain,
it's an infinitesimally
small number of new neurons.
So that's the depressing part,
we don't get new neurons.
After we're born, we pretty
much have the neurons
that we're going to use our entire life.
And yes, as we get older
and we start to lose certain
functions in our brain,
we lose neurons.
But all is not lost, so to speak,
because there are other
ways in which neurocircuits
can create new connections
and add new functions
including new memory, new abilities
and new cognitive functions.
And those are mainly through the process
of making certain connections,
which of course are those
things we call synapses,
between neurons making
those connections stronger.
So they're more reliable,
they're more likely to engage
as well as removing connections.
And the removal of connections is vital
to say moving through a grieving process
or removing the emotional load
of a traumatic experience.
So even though we can't add new neurons
throughout our lifespan,
at least not in very great numbers,
it's clear that we can
change our nervous system,
that the nervous system
is available for change,
that if we create the
right set of circumstances
in our brain, chemical circumstances,
and if we create the right
environmental circumstances around us,
our nervous system will
shift into a mode in which
change isn't just possible
but it's probable.
As I mentioned before,
the hallmark of the child
nervous system is change,
it wants to change.
The whole thing,
everything from the chemicals
that are sloshing around in there
to the fact that there's a lot
of space between the neurons.
A lot of people don't know
this, but early in development
there's a lot of space
between the neurons.
And so the neurons can
literally move around
and sample different
connections very easily
removing some and keeping others.
As we get older, the
so-called extracellular space
is actually filled up
by things called extracellular
matrix and glial cells.
Glial means glue.
Those cells are involved in a
bunch of different processes
but they start to fill in all the space
kind of like pouring
concrete between rocks.
And when that happens,
it becomes much harder
to change the connections that are there.
One of the ways in which
we can all get plasticity
at any stage throughout the lifespan
is through deficits and impairments
in what we call our sensory apparati,
our eyes, our ears, our nose, our mouth,
and there are some very dramatic
and somewhat tragic examples of people,
for instance who have genetic mutations
where they're born without a nose
and without any olfactory
structures in the brain
so they cannot smell.
In that case areas of the brain
that normally would represent smell
become overtaken by areas of the brain
involved in other things like
touch and hearing and sight.
In individuals that are blind from birth,
the so-called occipital cortex,
the visual cortex in the back,
becomes overtaken by hearing.
The neurons there will
start to respond to sounds
as well as braille touch.
And actually there's a one
particularly tragic incident
where a woman who was blind since birth
and because of neuroimaging studies,
we knew her visual cortex
was no longer visual,
it was responsible for braille
reading and for hearing,
she had a stroke that actually took out
most of the function of her visual cortex.
So then she was blind, she
couldn't braille read or hear.
She did recover some aspect of function.
Now, most people they don't end up in that
highly unfortunate situation.
And what we know is that for instance,
blind people who use their visual cortex
for braille reading and for hearing,
have much better auditory
acuity and touch acuity.
Meaning they can sense
things with their fingers
and they can sense
things with their hearing
that typical sighted
folks wouldn't be able to.
In fact, you will find a much greater
incidence of perfect pitch
in people that are blind.
And that tells us that the brain
and in particular this
area we call the neocortex,
which is the outer part,
is really designed to be a map
of our own individual experience.
So these, what I call
experiments of impairment or loss
where somebody is blind from
birth or deaf from birth
or maybe has a limb development impairment
where they have a stump
instead of an entire limb
with a functioning hand,
their brain will represent
the body plan that they have,
not some other body plan.
But the beauty of the situation is that
the real estate up in the
skull, that neocortex,
the essence of it is to be a
customized map of experience.
Now, it is true however,
that if let's say I were
to be blind when I'm 50,
I'm 45 right now, I've
always been sighted.
If I was blind at 50,
I'll probably have less opportunity
to use my formerly visual cortex
for things like braille
reading and hearing
because my brain has changed,
it's just not the same brain
I had when I was a baby.
So there's actually a
principle of biology,
not many people know this,
it's actually a principle neurology
which is called the Kennard principle,
which says, if you're going
to have a brain injury,
you want to have it early in life.
And of course better to not
have a brain injury at all
but if you're going to have it
you want to have it early in life.
And this is based on a
tremendous number of experiments
examining the amount of recovery
and the rate of recovery in humans
that had lesions to their brain
either early in life or later in life.
So the Kennard Principle says
better to have injuries early in life.
Now, that's reassuring
for the young folks,
it's not so reassuring
for the older folks.
But there are aspects of neuroplasticity
that have nothing to do with impairments.
I mean earlier I said
we're all walking around with this map,
this representation of the world around us
so we can see edges, we can see colors,
except for folks that are
color blind of course,
and we also have a map
of emotional experience.
We have a map of whether or not
certain people are trustworthy,
certain people aren't trustworthy.
A few years ago I was at a course
and a woman came up to me and she said,
you know, I wasn't teaching
the course, I was in the course
and she said, "I just have to tell you
that every time you speak,
it really stresses me out."
And I said, "Well I've heard that before
but do you want to be more specific?"
And she said, "Yeah, your tone of voice
reminds me of somebody
that I had a really
terrible experience with."
I said, "Well, okay, well,
I can't change my voice
but I really appreciate
that you acknowledge that
and it also will help explain why
you seem to cringe every time I speak",
which I hadn't noticed until then
but after that I did notice.
She had a very immediate
and kind of visceral
response to my speech,
perhaps some of you are
having that right now.
But in any event, over the
period of this two-week course,
she would come back every
once in a while and say,
"You know what I think,
just by telling you
that your voice was really
difficult for me to listen to,
it's actually becoming
more tolerable to me."
And by the end we actually
became pretty good friends
and we're still in touch.
And so what this says is that
the recognition of something
whether or not that's an emotional thing
or a desire to learn something else
is actually the first
step in neuroplasticity.
And that's because
our nervous system has two
broad sets of functions.
Some of those functions are reflexive.
Things like our breathing, our
heart rate, our obvious ones,
but other aspects are reflexive
like our ability to walk.
If I get up out of this chair
and walk out of the door,
I don't think about each
step that I'm taking
and that's because I learned
how to walk during development.
But when we decide that
we're going to shift
some sort of behavior or some reaction
or some new piece of information
that we want to learn,
it's something that we want to
bring into our consciousness,
that awareness is a remarkable thing
because it cues the brain
and the rest of the nervous system
that when we engage in
those reflexive actions
going forward,
that those reflexive actions
are no longer fated to be reflexive.
Now if this sounds a little bit abstract,
we're going to talk about
protocols for how to do this.
But the first step in neuroplasticity
is recognizing that you
want to change something
and you should immediately say, well,
kids don't go into school and say,
oh, I want to learn language
or I want to learn social interactions,
and that's the beauty of childhood.
The whole brain has this switch flipped
that is making change possible
but after that we have to be deliberate.
We have to know what it is
exactly that we want to change.
Or if we don't know exactly what it is
that we want to change,
we at least have to know that
we want to change something
about some specific experience.
In this case, I believe
that she came and told me
that my voice was really
awful for her to listen to
not to make me feel bad
or for any other reason
except that she wanted
it to not be the case.
And she knew I wasn't
going to stop talking.
So she decided to call
it to her consciousness
and mine as well.
So that's important.
If you want to learn something
or you want to change your
nervous system in any way,
whether or not it's
because of some impairment
or because of something
that you want to acquire,
a cognitive skill, a motor
skill, an emotional skill,
the first thing is recognizing
what that thing is.
And that often can be the
hardest thing to identify
but the brain has the self
recognition mechanisms
and those self recognition mechanisms
are not vague, spiritual or mystical
or even psychological concepts.
They are neurochemicals.
We're going to talk next
about the neurochemicals
that stamp down particular behaviors
and thoughts and emotional patterns
and tell the rest of the nervous system,
this is something to pay attention to
because this is in the
direction of the change
that I want to make.
So I'll repeat that, there
are specific chemicals
that when we are consciously aware
of a change we want to make
or even just that we
want to make some change,
chemicals are released in the brain
that allow us the opportunity
to make those changes.
Now, there are specific protocols
that science tells us We have to follow
if we want those changes to occur.
But that self-recognition is
not a kind of murky concept.
What it is is it's our fore brain,
in particular our prefrontal cortex,
signaling the rest of our nervous system
that something that we're about to do,
hear, feel or experience is
worth paying attention to.
So we'll pause there and then
I'm going to move forward.
One of the biggest lies in the universe
that seems quite prominent right now
is that every experience
you have changes your brain.
People love to say this.
They love to say, your brain
is going to be different
after this lecture
or that your brain is going to
be different after today's class
than it was two days ago.
And that's absolutely not true.
The nervous system doesn't just change
because you experienced something
unless you're a very young child.
The nervous system changes
when certain neurochemicals are released
and allow whatever neurons
are active in the period
in which those chemicals
are swimming around,
to strengthen or weaken the
connections of those neurons.
Now, this is best illustrated
through a little bit
of scientific history.
The whole basis of neuroplasticity
is essentially ascribed
to two individuals,
although there were a lot more people
that were involved in this work.
Those two individuals
go by the name David
Hubel and Torsten Wiesel.
David Hubel and Torsten Wiesel
started off at Johns Hopkins,
moved to Harvard medical school.
And in the seventies and eighties,
they did a series of experiments,
recording electrical
activity in the brain.
They were in the visual cortex,
meaning they put the electrodes
in the visual cortex,
and they were exploring how vision works
and how the visual brain
organizes all the features
of the visual world to give us these
incredible things We
call visual perceptions.
But Hubel was a physician.
And he was very interested in what happens
when for instance, a
child comes into the world
and they have a cataract,
the lens of their eye,
isn't clear but it's opaque.
Or when a kid has a lazy eye
or the eyes have what's called strabismus,
which is when the eyes either
deviate outward or inward.
These are very common things of childhood,
especially in particular
areas of the world.
And what David and Torsten
did is they figured out
that there was a critical period
in which if clear vision did not occur,
the visual brain would
completely rewire itself,
basically to represent
whatever bit of visual
information was coming in.
So they did these experiments
to kind of simulate a droopy
eye or a deviating eye
where they would close one eyelid
and then what they found
is that the visual brain
would respond entirely to the open eye.
There was sort of a
takeover of the visual brain
representing the open eye.
Many experiments in many
different sensory systems
followed up on this.
There are beautiful
experiments for instance,
from Gregg Recanzone's lab up at UC Davis
and Mike Merzenich's lab at UCSF
showing that for instance
if two fingers were taped
together early in development,
so they weren't moving independently,
the representation of those two fingers
would become fused in the brain
so that the person couldn't
actually distinguish
the movements and the sensations
of the two fingers
separately, pretty remarkable.
All of this is to say that
David and Torsten's work,
for which they won a noble prize,
they shared it with Rogers Barry,
their work showed that
the brain is in fact a customized
map of the outside world,
we said that already.
But that what it's doing is it's measuring
the amount of activity for
a given part of our body,
one eye or the other, or our fingers,
this finger or that finger
and all of those inputs are competing
for space in the brain.
Now this is fundamentally important
because what it means is that
if we are to change our
nervous system in adulthood,
we need to think about not
just what we're trying to get,
but what we're trying to give up.
We can't actually add new connections
without removing something else.
And that might seem like kind of a stinger
but it actually turns out
to be a great advantage.
One of the key experiments
that David and Torsten did
was an experiment where
they closed both eyes,
where they essentially
removed all visual input
early in development.
Now this is slightly
different than blindness
because it was transient,
it was only for a short period of time.
But what they found is when they did that
there was no change.
However, if they would close just one eye
there was a huge change.
So when people tell you,
oh at the end of today's lecture,
or at the end of something
your brain is going to
be completely different,
that's simply not true.
If you're older than 25
your brain will not change
unless there's a selective
shift in your attention
or a selective shift in your experience
that tells the brain it's time to change.
And those changes occur
through the ways I talked about before
strengthening and weakening
of particular connections,
they have names like
long-term potentiation,
long-term depression,
which has nothing to do
with emotional depression by the way,
spike-timing-dependent plasticity.
I threw out those names
not to confuse you,
but for those of you that would like
more in-depth exploration of those,
please you can go google
those and look them up,
there are great Wikipedia pages for them
and you can go down the paper trail.
I might even touch on them
on some subsequent episodes.
But the important thing
to understand is that
if we want something to change,
we really need to bring an
immense amount of attention
to whatever it is that we want to change.
This is very much linked to
the statement I made earlier
about, it all starts with an awareness.
Now, why is that attention important?
Well, David and Torsten
won their Nobel prize
and they certainly deserved it.
They probably deserved two
because they also figured
out how vision works.
And I might be biased
'cause they're my scientific
great-grandparents
but I think everybody in the
field of Neuroscience agrees
that Hubel and Wiesel, as they're called
H&W for those in the game,
absolutely deserved a
Nobel prize for their work
because they really unveiled
the mechanisms of brain change
of plasticity.
David passed away a few years
ago, Torsten is still alive,
he's in his late 90s,
he's still at the Rockefeller university.
He's sharp as a tack.
He still jogs several miles a day.
He's really into art and
a number of other things.
He's also a super nice guy.
Hubel was a really nice guy as well,
also he was a great
Frisbee player I discovered
'cause he beat me in a game of
ultimate when he was like 80,
which still, it has me a little bit irked.
But anyway, Hubel and Wiesel
did an amazing thing for science
that will forever change
the way that we think about the brain.
However, they were quite wrong
about this critical period thing.
The critical period was this idea that
if you were to deprive the
nervous system of an input,
say closing one eye early in development
and the rest of the visual cortex is taken
over by the representation
of the open eye,
that you could never change that
unless you intervened early.
And this actually formed the basis
for why a kid that has
a lazy eye or a cataract
why, even though there's some issues
with anesthesia in young children,
why now we know that you
want to get in there early
and fix the cataract or fix the strabismus
it's what ophthalmologists do.
However, their idea that
you had to do it early
or else there was no opportunity to rescue
the nervous system deficit later on
turned out wasn't entirely true.
In the early 90s, a graduate student
by the name of Gregg Recanzone
was in the laboratory
of a guy named Mike Merzenich at UCSF.
And they set out to test this idea
that if one wants to change their brain,
they need to do it early in life
because the adult brain
simply isn't plastic
it's not available for these changes.
And they did a series of
absolutely beautiful experiments,
by now I think we can say proving
that the adult brain can change
provided certain conditions are met.
Now, the experiments they did are tough.
They were tough on the experimenter
and they were tough on the subject.
I'll just describe one.
Let's say you were a subject
in one of their experiments.
You would come into the lab
and you'd sit down at a table
and they would record
from or image your brain
and look at the
representation of your fingers
the digits as we call them.
And there would be a spinning drum,
literally a like a stone drum
in front of your metal drum
that had little bumps.
Some of the bumps were
spaced close together,
some of them were spaced far apart.
And they would do these experiments
where they would expect their
subjects to press a lever
whenever for instance, the
bumps got closer together
or further apart and these
were very subtle differences.
So in order to do this you
really have to pay attention
to the distance between the bumps
and these were not braille readers
or anyone skilled in doing
these kinds of experiments.
What they found was that as people paid
more and more attention to the
distance between these bumps
and they would signal
when there was a change
by pressing a lever,
as they did that there
was very rapid changes
plasticity in the
representation of the fingers.
And it could go in either direction.
You could get people very
good at detecting the distance
between bumps, that the
distance was getting smaller
or that the distance was getting greater.
So people could get
very good at these tasks
that you're kind of hard to
imagine how they would translate
to the real world for
a non braille reader.
But what it told us is
that these maps of touch
were very much available for plasticity.
And these were fully adult subjects.
They're not taking any specific drugs.
They don't have any impairments
that we're aware of.
And what it showed, what it proved
is that the adult brain is very plastic.
And they did some beautiful
control experiments
that are important for
everyone to understand
which is that sometimes
they would bring people in
and they would have them touch these bumps
on this spinning drum but
they would have the person
pay attention to an auditory cue.
Every time a tone would go off,
or there was a shift in
the pitch of that tone,
they would have to signal that.
So the subject thought
they were doing something
related to touch and hearing
and all that showed was that
it wasn't just the mere action
of touching these bumps.
They had to pay attention
to the bumps themselves.
If they were placing their attention
on the auditory cue on the tone,
well then there was plasticity
in the auditory portion
of the brain but not on the
touch portion of the brain.
And this really spits in
the face of this thing
that you hear so often
which is every experience
that you have is going to
change the way your brain works.
Absolutely not.
The experiences that you pay
super careful attention to
are what open up plasticity
and it opens up plasticity
to that specific experience.
So the question then is why?
And Merzenich and his
graduate students and postdocs
went on to address this question of why.
And it turns out the answer
is a very straightforward
neurochemical answer.
And inside of that
answer is the opportunity
for any of us to change
our brain at any point
throughout our lifespan,
essentially for anything
that we want to learn,
that could be subtracting an emotion
from an experience we've had,
it could be building a
greater range of emotion,
it could be learning new information
like learning a new language.
It could be learning new motor
skill, like dance or sport
or it could be some
combination of cognitive motor.
So for instance, an air traffic
controller has to do a lot
with their mind in addition
to a lot with their hands.
So it's not just cognitive,
it's not just motor but combined.
So we're going to talk
about what that chemical is
but to just give you an important hint,
that chemical is the
same chemical of stress.
This is not a discussion
about stress per se.
In a future podcast episode,
we'll talk all about stress
and tools to deal with stress,
something my lab works
on quite extensively.
And it's a topic that I enjoy discussing.
But this is a topic about brain change.
And what I just told you
is that in order to change the brain
you have to pay careful attention.
And the immediate question
should be well, why?
Well, the answer is that
when we pay careful attention
there are two neurochemicals,
neuromodulators as they're called,
that are released from
multiple sites in our brain
that highlight the neural circuits
that stand a chance of changing.
Now it's not necessarily the case
that they're going to change,
but it's the first gate that has to open
in order for change to occur.
And the first neurochemical is
epinephrin, also adrenaline.
We call it adrenaline
when it's released from the adrenal glands
above our kidneys, that's in the body,
we call it epinephrin in the brain,
but they are chemically
identical substances.
Epinephrin is released from
a region in the brainstem
called locus coeruleus.
Fancy name, you don't need to
know it unless you want to.
Locus coeruleus sends
out these little wires
we call axons such that
it hoses the entire brain
essentially in this
neurochemical, epinephrin.
Now it's not always hosing
the brain with epinephrin.
It's only when we are in
high states of alertness
that this epinephrin is released.
But the way this circuit is
designed, it's very nonspecific.
It's essentially waking
up the entire brain
and that's because the
way that epinephrin works
by binding particular receptors
is to increase the likelihood
that neurons will be active.
So no alertness, no neuroplasticity.
However, alertness
alone is not sufficient.
As we would say, it's necessary
but not sufficient for neuroplasticity.
We know this is true also from
the work of Hubel and Wiesel
where they looked at brain plasticity
in response to certain experiences
in subjects that were
either awake or asleep.
And I hate to break it to you
but you cannot just simply
listen to things in your sleep
and learn those materials.
Later I'll talk about how
you can do certain things
in your sleep that you're unaware of
that can enhance learning of
things that you were aware of
while you were awake.
But that is not the same as
just listening to some music
or listening to a tape while you sleep
and expecting it to sink in, so to speak.
Epinephrin is released
when we pay attention
and when we are alert.
But the most important
thing for getting plasticity
is that there'll be epinephrin
which equates to alertness,
plus the release of this
neuromodulator, acetylcholine.
Now acetylcholine is released
from two sites in the brain.
One is also in the brainstem
and it's named different things
in different animals, but in humans
the most rich site of
acetylcholine neurons
or neurons that make acetylcholine
is the parabigeminal nucleus
or the parabrachial region.
There are a number of different names
of these aggregates of neurons.
You don't need to know the names,
all you need to know is
that you have an area
in your brainstem and
that area sends wires,
these axons up into the area of the brain
that filters sensory input.
So we have this area of the
brain called the thalamus
and it is getting bombarded with all sorts
of sensory input all the time.
Costello snoring off to my right,
the lights that are in the room,
the presence of my computer to my left,
all of that is coming in.
But when I pay attention to something
like if I really hone
in on Costello snoring,
I create a cone of attention
and what that cone of attention reflects
is that acetylcholine is now
amplifying the signal of sounds
that Costello is making with his snoring
and essentially making that signal greater
than all the signal around it,
what we call signal-to-noise goes up.
So those of you with an
engineering background
will be familiar with signal-to-noise.
Those of you who do not have
an engineering background,
don't worry about it.
All it means is that one
particular shout in the crowd
comes through, Costello's
snoring becomes more salient,
more apparent relative to
everything else going on.
Acetylcholine acts as a spotlight
but epinephrin for alertness.
acetylcholine spotlighting these inputs.
Those two things alone are
not enough to get plasticity.
There needs to be this third component.
And the third component
is acetylcholine released
from an area of the forebrain
called nucleus basalis.
If you really want to get technical,
it's called nucleus basalis of Meynert.
For any of you that
are buddying physicians
or going to medical school,
you should know that.
If you have acetylcholine
released from the brainstem,
acetylcholine released from
nucleus basalis and epinephrin,
you can change your brain.
And I can say that with confidence
because Merzenich and Recanzone
as well as other members
of the Merzenich lab,
Michael Kilgard and others
did these incredible experiments
where they stimulated
the release of acetylcholine
from nucleus basalis
either with an electrode
or with some other methods
that we'll talk about.
And what they found was when you stimulate
these three brain
regions, locus coeruleus,
the brainstem source of acetylcholine
and then the basal forebrain
source of acetylcholine.
When you have those three things
whatever you happen to
be listening to, doing
or paying attention to
immediately in one trial
takes over the representation
of a particular area of the brain.
You essentially get rapid
massive learning in one shop.
And this has been shown
again and again and again
in a variety of papers
also by a guy named Norman
Weinberger from UC Irvine.
And it is now considered
a fundamental principle
of how the nervous system works.
So while Hubel and Wiesel
talked about critical periods
in developmental plasticity,
it's very clear from the work of Merzenich
and Weinberg and others, that
if you get these three things,
if you can access these three things
of epinephrin, acetylcholine
from these two sources,
not only will the nervous
system change, it has to change.
It absolutely will change.
And that is the most important thing
for people to understand if
they want to change their brain.
You cannot just passively
experience things
and repetition can be important,
but the way to use repetition
to change your brain
is fundamentally different.
So now let's talk about
how we would translate
all the scientific information and history
into some protocols that
you can actually apply,
because I think that's what
many of you're interested in.
And I'm willing to bet that
most of you are not interested
in lowering electrodes
into your nucleus basalis
and frankly, neither am I.
In episode one of the
Huberman Lab Podcast,
I described the various
ways that people can monitor
and change their nervous system.
Those ways include brain
machine interface, pharmacology,
behavioral practices,
and those behavioral practices of course
can include some dos, do this
and some don'ts, don't do that, et cetera
In thinking about neuroplasticity,
I want to have a very frank conversation
about what one can do
but also acknowledge
this untapped capacity
that I'm just not hearing about out there,
which is one can also
combine behavioral practices
with pharmacology.
One can combine behavioral practices
with brain machine interface,
and you don't have to do that.
In fact, I'm not recommending
you do anything in particular.
As always, I'll say it again,
I'm not a physician, so I
don't prescribe anything.
I'm a professor, so I
profess a lot of things.
What you do with your health
and your medical care is up to you.
You're responsible for
your health and wellbeing.
So I'm not going to tell you
what to do or what to take.
I'm going to describe what
the literature tells us
and suggests about ways
to access plasticity.
We know we need epinephrin,
that means alertness.
Most people accomplish this
through a cup of coffee
and a good night's sleep.
So I will say you should
master your sleep schedule
and you should figure out
how much sleep you need
in order to achieve alertness
when you sit down to learn.
All the tools and more
science than probably
you ever wanted to hear about sleep
and how to get better at
sleeping and timing your sleep
et cetera and naps and all of that
is in episodes two, three, four, and five
of the Huberman Lab Podcast.
So I encourage you to refer to those
if your sleep is not where
you would like it to be.
Your ability to engage in
deliberate focused alertness
is in direct proportion to
how well you are sleeping
on a regular basis.
I think that's kind of an obvious one.
So get your sleep handled.
But once that's in place,
the question then is how
do I access this alertness?
Well, there are a number of ways.
Some people use some pretty elaborate
psychological gymnastics.
They will tell people that
they're going to do something
and create some accountability.
That could be really good.
Or they'll post a picture
of themselves online
and they'll commit to
learning a certain amount
losing, excuse me, a
certain amount of weight
or something like this.
So they can use either
shame-based practices
to potentially embarrass themselves
if they don't follow through.
They'll write cheques to
organizations that they hate
and insist that they'll cash them
if they don't actually follow through
or they'll do it out of love,
you know, they'll decide
that they're going
to run a marathon or learn
a language or something
because of somebody they love
or they want to devote it to somebody.
The truth is that from the
standpoint of epinephrin
and getting alert and activated,
it doesn't really matter.
Epinephrin is a chemical and
your brain does not distinguish
between doing things out of
love or hate, anger or fear.
It really doesn't, all of
those promote autonomic arousal
and the release of epinephrin.
So I think for most people
if you're feeling not
motivated to make these changes
the key thing is to identify not just one
but probably at kit of reasons,
several reasons as to why
you would want to make
this particular change
and being drawn toward a particular goal
that you're excited about can be one,
also being motivated to not
be completely afraid, ashamed,
or humiliated for not following through
on a goal is another.
I just want to briefly
mention one little aside there
because I've got a
friend who's a physician,
he's a cardiologist who has
a really interesting theory.
This is just theory, but
I think it will resonate
with a lot of people, which is that,
you've all heard of this molecule dopamine
that gives us the sense of reward
when we accomplish something.
Well, we also want to be
able to access dopamine
while we're working towards things,
enjoy the process as they say,
'cause it has all sorts
of positive effects
gives us energy, et cetera.
With my friend, what he says is, you know,
there's many many instances
where someone will come to him
and say, "You know what,
I'm going to write a book."
And he says, "Oh, that's great.
I'm sure the book's going to be terrific
and you really should write a book."
And then they never go do it.
And his theory is, if
you get so much dopamine
from the reward of people saying,
Oh yeah, you're absolutely
going to be able to do that,
you might not actually go after the reward
of the accomplishment itself.
So be aware these positive
reinforcements also.
I'm not saying people
should flagellate themselves
to the point of victory in
whatever they're pursuing,
but motivation is a tricky one.
So I suggest that everyone asks themselves
what is it that I want to accomplish?
And what is it that's
driving me to accomplish this
and come up with two or three things.
Fear-based perhaps, love-based perhaps
or perhaps several of
those in order to ensure
alertness, energy and
attention for the task.
And that brings us to the attention part.
Now it's one thing to
have an electrode embedded
into your brain and increase
the amount of acetylcholine.
It's another to exist in the real world
outside the laboratory
and have trouble focusing.
Having trouble bringing your attention
to a particular location in
space for a particular event.
And there's a lot of discussion
nowadays about smartphones
and devices creating a
sort of attention deficit,
almost at a clinical
level for many people,
including adults.
I think that's largely true.
And what it means, however,
is that we all are responsible
for learning how to create depth of focus.
There are some important
Neuroscience principles
to get depth of focus.
I want to briefly talk
about the pharmacology first
because I always get asked about this.
People say, "What can I
take to increase my levels
of acetylcholine?"
Well, there are things you can take.
Nicotine is called nicotine
because acetylcholine binds
to the nicotinic receptor.
There are two kinds of
acetylcholine receptors,
muscarinic and nicotinic,
but the nicotinic ones are involved
in attention and alertness.
I have colleagues, these
are not my, you know
kind of like bro, science
buddies, I have those friends too,
this is a Nobel prize winning colleague
who chews Nicorette while he works.
He used to be a smoker.
He quit smoking because
of fear of lung cancer,
seemed like a smart choice,
but he missed the level of focus
that he could bring to his work.
This is somebody who has
had very long career.
And if you ever meet with him,
unfortunately I can't name him.
If you ever meet with him
what you realize is he chews
about five pieces of Nicorette an hour,
which I am not suggesting people do.
But when I asked him,
"Why are you doing this?"
He said, "Well, increases
my alertness and focus."
And also his theory and I
want to really underscore
that it's theory not
scientifically supported yet,
is that it offsets
Parkinson's and Alzheimer's.
It is true that nucleus basalis
is the primary site of
degeneration in the brain,
in people that have
dementia and Parkinson's
and it's what leads to
a lot of their inability
to focus their attention, not
just deficits and plasticity.
So he might be onto something.
Now I've tried chewing Nicorette,
it makes me super jittery.
I don't like it because
I can't focus very well.
It kind of takes me too far up
the level of autonomic arousal.
I've got friends that
dip Nicorette all day,
some of whom are scientists,
writers and artists
and musicians are familiar
with the effects of nicotine
from the era where a lot of people smoked
and fortunately fewer people smoke now.
So if you're interested
in the pharmacology,
there are supplements and things
that can increase cholinergic
transmission in the brain.
I'm not suggesting you do this
but if you're going to go down that route,
you want to be very
careful how much you rely
on those all the time.
Because the essence of
plasticity is to create a window
of attention and focus that's distinct
from the rest of your day.
That's what's going to
create a mark in your brain
and the potential for plasticity.
Things that increase acetylcholine,
besides nicotine or Nicorette,
the nicotine could come
from a variety of sources
or things like alpha-GPC or choline.
There are a number of these things.
I would encourage you to go
to examine.com, the website
and just put in acetylcholine
and it will give you a list of supplements
as well as some of the
dangers of these supplements
that are associated with
cholinergic transmission.
But I would be remiss and I would be lying
if I didn't say that there
are a lot of people out there
who are using cholinergic drugs
in order to increase their level of focus.
And since we're coming up on the Olympics,
I don't want to get anyone in trouble
but I'm well aware that
the fact that the sprinters
are really into cholinergic drugs
because not only is acetylcholine
important for the focus
that allows them to hear the gun
and be first out the
blocks on the sprints.
That's a lot of where the race is won,
hearing that gun and being
the quickest on reaction time.
So they take cholinergic agents for that
as well as acetylcholine is the molecule
that controls nerve to muscle contraction.
So your speed of reflexes
is actually controlled
by this nicotinic transmission as well.
So lots to think about
in terms of acetylcholine
in sport and mental acuity,
not just plasticity.
Now for most of you,
you probably don't want to chew Nicorette,
definitely don't want to smoke cigarettes
or take supplements for
increasing acetylcholine.
So what are some ways that you
can increase acetylcholine?
And there, it's going to sound
like a bit of a circular argument
but you to increase focus.
How do you increase focus?
You know, people are so
familiar with sitting down,
reading a couple pages of a book
and realizing that none of it sunk in
or talking to someone and
seeing their mouth move,
maybe even nodding your
head subconsciously
and none of it sinks in.
This can be very damaging
for school, work performance
and relationships as many of you know.
Costello incidentally never
seems to pay attention
to anything I say while
looking directly at me,
which contradicts what I'm about to say,
which is that the best way
to get better at focusing
is to use the mechanisms of
focus that you were born with.
And the key principle
here is that mental focus
follows visual focus.
We are all familiar with the
fact that our visual system
can be unfocused, blurry or jumping around
or we can be very laser focused
on one location in space.
What's interesting and vitally important
to understanding how to
access neuroplasticity
is that you can use your visual focus
and you can increase your
visual focus as a way
of increasing your mental
focus abilities more broadly.
So I'm going to explain how to do that.
Plasticity starts with alertness.
And as I mentioned before,
that alertness can come
from a sense of love,
a sense of joy, a sense
of fear, doesn't matter.
There are pharmacologic ways
to access alertness too.
The most common one is of course caffeine
which if you watch the sleep episodes,
you know reduces this molecule
that makes us sleepy called adenosine.
I drink plenty of caffeine.
I'm a heavy user of caffeine.
I don't think abuser of caffeine.
I think in reasonable amounts
provided we can still
fall asleep at night,
caffeine can be a relatively safe way
to increase epinephrin.
Now, many people are
now also using Adderall.
Adderall chemically looks
a lot like amphetamine
and basically it is amphetamine.
It will increase epinephrin
release from locus coeruleus,
it will wake up the brain
and that's why a lot of people rely on it.
It does have a heavy basis for use
in certain clinical syndromes prescribed
such as attention deficit.
However, it also has a
high probability of abuse
especially in those who
are not prescribed it.
Adderall will not increase
focus, it increases alertness.
It does not touch the
acetylcholine system.
And if those of you that
are taking Adderall say,
"Well, it really increases
my focus overall",
that's probably because your
autonomic nervous system
is just veering towards what
we call parasympathetic.
You're really just very sleepy
and so it's bringing your
levels of alertness up.
As I mentioned, Adderall
is very problematic
for a number of people as
it can be habit forming.
Learning on Adderall
does not always translate
to high-performance off or
on Adderall at later times.
And the Adderall
discussion is a broader one
that perhaps we should have
with a psychiatrist in the room
at some point because it is
a very widely abused drug
at this point in time.
The acetylcholine system
and the focus that it brings is available
as I mentioned through pharmacology,
but also through these
behavioral practices.
And the behavioral practices
that are anchored in visual
focus are going to be the ones
that are going to allow
you to develop great depth
and duration of focus.
So let's think about
visual focus for a second.
When we focus on something
visually, we have two options.
We can either look at a
very small region of space
with a lot of detail
and a lot of precision
or we can dilate our gaze
and we can see big pieces
of visual space with very little detail.
It's a trade-off.
We can't look at everything
at high resolution.
This is why we have these,
the pupil more or less relates
to the fovea of the eye
which is the area in which
we have the most receptors,
the highest density of
receptors that perceive light.
And so our acuity is much better
in the center of our visual
field than our periphery.
It's a simple experiment
you can do right now.
If you're listening to
this, you can still do it.
You can hold your feet or your
hands out in front of you.
Provided that you're sighted
you should be able to see
how many fingers you have in front of you.
For me, it's five.
I still got all five
fingers, amazingly enough.
If I move my hand off to the side,
I can't see them with precision,
but as I moved them back into
the center of my visual field
I can see them with precision.
And that's because the density,
the number of pixels in the
center of my visual field
is much higher than it
is in the periphery.
When we focus our eyes,
we do a couple of things.
First of all, we tend to do that
in the center of our visual field
and our two eyes tend to align
in what's called a vergence eye movement
towards a common point.
The other thing that happens
is the lens of our eye moves
so that our brain now no longer
sees the entire visual world
but is seeing a small
cone of visual imagery.
[door banging]
If it...
That was the dog bumping
into the wall, forgive me.
That small cone of visual imagery
or soda straw view of the
world has much higher acuity,
higher resolution than if I
were to look at everything.
Now you see, of course,
this makes perfect sense
but that's about visual
attention, not mental attention.
Well, it turns out that focus in the brain
is anchored to our visual system.
I'll talk about blind people in a moment
but assuming that somebody is sighted,
the key is to learn how
to focus better visually,
if you want to bring about
higher levels of cognitive
or mental focus, even if you're
engaged in a physical task.
Now there's a remarkable
phenomenon in animals
where animals that have their
eyes on the side of their head
are scanning the entire visual
environment all the time.
They're not focused on anything.
Think you're grazing animals,
your cows, your sheep
your birds, et cetera.
But think about a bird
picking up seeds on the beach
or on concrete.
That bird's head is up here.
It's up about a foot off the ground,
or if it's a small bird about
six inches off the ground
and its eyes are on the side of its head
and yet it has this tiny beak
that can quickly pick up these
little seeds off the ground
with immense precision.
Now, if you try to do that by staring off
to the sides of the room
and picking up items
in front of you with high
precision at that tiny scale,
little tiny objects, you
will miss almost every time.
They do it perfectly and
they don't smash their beak
into the ground and damage it,
they do it with beautiful
movement acuity also.
So how do they do it?
How do they create this
focus or this awareness
of what's in front of them?
It turns out as they lower their head,
their eyes, very briefly move inward,
in what's called a vergence eye movement.
Now their eyes can't actually
translocate in their head,
they're fixed in the skull,
just like yours and mine are.
But when we move our eyes slightly inward,
maybe you can tell and do it's like so
basically shortening or making
the inter pupillary distance
as it's called smaller.
Two things happen.
Not only do we develop
a smaller visual window
into the world, but we
activate a set of neurons
in our brainstem that trigger the release
of both norepinephrine,
epinephrin and acetylcholine.
Norepinephrine is kind
of similar to epinephrin.
So in other words, when our
eyes are relaxed in our head
when we're just kind of looking
at our entire visual environment,
moving our head around,
moving through space we're in optic flow,
things moving past us
or we're sitting still,
we're looking broadly at
our space, we're relaxed.
When our eyes move slightly inward
toward a particular visual target
our visual world shrinks, our
level of visual focus goes up
and we know that this relates
to the release of
acetylcholine and epinephrin
at the relevant sites in
the brain for plasticity.
Now, what this means is that
if you have a hard time focusing your mind
for sake of reading or for
listening, you need to practice
and you can practice
focusing your visual system.
Now this works best if you practice
focusing your visual system
at the precise distance,
from the work that you intend
to do for sake of plasticity.
So how would this look in the real world?
Let's say, I am trying to
concentrate on something
related to, I don't know, science,
I'm reading a science paper
and I'm having a hard time,
it's not absorbing.
I might think that I'm
only looking at the paper
that I'm reading.
I'm only looking at my screen,
but actually my eyes are
probably darting around a bit.
Experiments have been done on this.
Or I'm gathering information
from too many sources
in the visual environment.
Now, presumably because it's me,
I've already had my coffee, I'm hydrated.
I'm well rested, I slept well.
And I still experienced
these challenges in focusing
spending just 60 to 120 seconds
focusing my visual attention
on a small window of my screen,
meaning just on my screen
with nothing on it,
but bringing my eyes to
that particular location
increases not just my visual
acuity for that location
but it brings about an
increase in activity
in a bunch of other brain
areas that are associated
with gathering information
from this location.
So put simply, if you want to
improve your ability to focus
practice visual focus.
Now, if you wear contacts
or you wear corrective
lenses, that's fine.
You of course would want to use those.
You don't want to take those
off and use a blurry image.
The finer the visual image
and the more that you can hold
your gaze to the visual image,
the higher your levels
of attention will be.
Many times on Instagram
and here I've been teased
for not blinking very often.
That's actually a practiced thing.
We blink more as we get
tired, which as you hear it
you'll probably just say, duh.
As we get tired, the
neurons in the brainstem
that are responsible for alertness
and that hold the eyelids open
start to falter and our
eyelids start to close.
This is why it's hard, the words,
"I could barely keep my eyes open"
which may be how you feel right now.
But assuming that you're paying
attention and you're alert,
when you're very alert,
your eyes are wide,
your eyes are open.
And as you get tired, your
eyelids start to close.
Blinks, actually reset our
perception of time and space.
This was shown in a beautiful
paper in Current Biology.
I'll be sure to post the
reference in the notes.
And blinking of course is
necessary to lubricate the eyes.
People blink because
their eyes might get dry.
But if you can keep
focused by blinking less
and by focusing your eyes
to a particular location
that's probably pretty
creepy for you to experience
as I'm doing this.
But the more that you can do this
the more that you can
maintain a kind of a cone
or a tunnel of mental focus.
And so I'm sort of revealing my practice
which is that I've worked very
hard through blinking contest
with my 14-year-old niece
who still beats me every time
and it really bothers me,
but also just through my own self practice
of learning to blink less
and focus my visual attention
on a smaller region of space.
Now for me, that's important
because I'm mainly learning
things on a computer screen.
If you're going to be doing
sport, it's quite a bit different
and we can discuss how you might
translate to that to sport.
In fact, in the next episode,
I'm going to talk all about
how plasticity and the
focus mechanisms relate
to learning of movement practices
and coordinated movements.
It's an entire discussion unto itself
but the same principle holds.
So we need alertness.
You can get that through
mental tricks of motivation,
fear or love, whatever it is,
pharmacology, please do it healthfully.
You know, caffeine if
that's in your practice,
certainly want to be well hydrated
that increases actually
will increase alertness.
Well, having a very full
bladder will increase alertness
although you don't want
your alertness to be so high
that all you can think about
is the fact that you have to go urinate
'cause that's very distracting.
You don't want your alertness
to go through the roof.
You need focus and visual
focus is the primary way
in which we start to deploy
these neurochemicals.
Now you may ask, well,
what about the experiment
where people were feeling
this rotating drum
or listening to the auditory cue
that doesn't involve vision at all?
If you look at people
who are learning things
with their auditory system,
they will often close their eyes.
And that's not a coincidence.
If somebody is listening very
hard, please don't ask them
to look you directly in the eye
while also asking that they listen to you.
That's actually one of the worst ways
to get somebody to listen to you.
If you say, now listen to
me and look me in the eye.
The visual system will take over
and they'll see your mouth move,
but they're going to hear their thoughts
more than they're going to
hear what you're saying.
Closing the eyes is one of the best ways
to create a cone of auditory attention.
And this is what low vision
or no vision folks do.
They have tremendous capacity
to focus their attention
in particular locations.
Incidentally does anyone
know the two animals
that have the best hearing in the world?
The absolute best hearing
is many orders of magnitude
better than humans.
It turns out it's the elephant.
That might not surprise
you, they have huge ears
and the moth which
probably will surprise you.
I didn't even know that moths could hear.
but now it explains why
they're so hard to catch.
If you are not sighted,
you learn how to do this
with your hearing.
If you're somebody who braille reads,
you learn how to do
this with your fingers.
If you look at great piano
players like Glenn Gould,
they often times will turn
their head to the side.
You think about some
of the great musicians
like Stevie Wonder that were blind, right?
He would look away
because he had no reason
to look at the keys, but
oftentimes they'll orient an ear
or one side of their head
to the keys on the piano.
As I mentioned before,
people who are non-sighted
have better pitch.
So we have these cones of
attention that we can devote.
And for most people,
vision is the primary way
to train up this focus of
building these cones of attention.
So you absolutely have to focus
on the thing that you're trying to learn.
And you will feel some agitation
because of the epinephrin in your system.
If you're feeling agitation
and it's challenging to focus
and you're feeling like
you're not doing it right
chances are you're doing it right.
And you can practice this ability to stare
for long periods of time without blinking.
I know it's a little
eerie for people to watch,
but if your goal is to
learn how to control
that visual window for sake
of controlling your focus,
it can be an immensely powerful portal
into these mechanisms of plasticity,
because we know it engages
things like nucleus basalis
and these other brainstem mechanisms.
I get a lot of questions
about attention deficit
hyperactivity disorder, ADHD,
and attention deficit disorder.
Some people actually have
clinically diagnosed ADD and ADHD.
And if you do, you should certainly work
with a good psychiatrist
to try and figure out
the right pharmacology and/or
behavioral practices for you.
Many people, however, have given
themselves a low grade ADHD
or ADD because of the way that they move
through their world.
They are looking at their
phone a lot of the time.
It's actually very easy
to anchor your attention
to your phone for the following reason.
First of all, it's very
restricted in size.
So it's very easy to limit
your visual attention
to something about this big.
It's one of the design
features of the phone.
The other, is that just
as you've probably heard
a picture is worth a thousand words,
well, a movie is worth 10,000 pictures.
Anytime we're looking at
things that have motion,
visual motion, our attentional system
will naturally gravitate towards
them, towards those movies.
It's actually much harder
to read words on a page
than it used to be for many people,
because we're used to seeing
things spelled out for us
in YouTube videos or videos
where things move in a very dramatic.
It is true that the more that we look
at those motion stimulate,
the more that we're
seeing movies of things
and things that are very
dramatic and very intense,
the worst we're getting
at attending to things
like text on a page or
to listening to something
like a podcast and
extracting the information
so much so that I think
many people have asked me,
"Hey you know what, why aren't
you providing intense visuals
for us to look at?"
Well, frankly, it's
because a lot of people
are consuming this content
through pure auditory,
through, it's by listening.
And I want them to be able
to digest all the material.
But in addition to that,
if you think about the areas of life
that dictate whether or
not we become successful,
independent, healthy individuals,
most of those involve the
kind of boring practices
of digesting information on a page.
Boring because it's not as
exciting in the moment perhaps
as watching a movie or
something being spoonfed to us.
But the more attention that
we can put to something,
even if it's fleeting and we feel like
we're only getting little bits and pieces,
shards of the information as
opposed to the entire thing,
that has a much more powerful effect
in engaging this cholinergic
system for plasticity
than does, for instance, watching a movie.
And that's because when we watch a movie,
the entire thing can be
great, it can be awesome.
It can be this overriding experience
but I think for all those experiences,
if you're somebody who's
interested in building your brain
and expanding your brain
and getting better at various things,
in feeling better,
doing better, et cetera,
one has to ask how much of
my neurochemical resources
am I devoting to the passive experience
of letting something,
just kind of overwhelm me
and excite me,
versus something that I'm
really trying to learn
and take away.
And now there's another
I enjoy movie content and
TV content all the time.
I scroll Instagram often.
But we are limited in the extent
to which we can grab a hold
of these acetylcholine release
mechanisms or epinephrin.
And I think that we need to be careful
that we don't devote all our
acetylcholine and epinephrin,
all our dopamine for that matter
to these passive experiences of things
that are not going to
enrich us and better us.
So that's a little bit of
an editorial on my part
but the phone is rich with movies,
it's rich with information.
The real question is
is the information rich
for us in ways that grow us
and cultivate smarter,
more emotionally, you know
emotionally evolved
people, or is it creating
what's it doing for our physical
wellbeing for that matter?
So I don't want to tell
people what to do or not to do
but think carefully about
how often you're focusing
on something and how good
you are or poor you are
at focusing on something
that's challenging.
So once you get this
epinephrin, this alertness,
you get the acetylcholine released
and you can focus your attention.
Then the question is for how long?
And in an earlier podcast,
I talked about these ultradian cycles
that lasts about 90 minutes.
The typical learning about
should be about 90 minutes.
I think that learning about will no doubt
include five to 10
minutes of warmup period.
I think everyone should
give themselves permission
to not be fully focused in
the early part of that about.
But that in the middle of that about
for the middle hour or so
you should be able to maintain focus
for about an hour or so.
So that for me means
eliminating distractions.
That means turning off the wifi.
I put my phone in the other room.
If I find myself reflexively
getting up to get the phone
I will take the phone and
lock it in the car outside.
If I find myself going to get it anyway,
I am guilty of giving away
the phone for a period of time
or even things more dramatic,
I've thrown it up on my roof before
so I can't get to it
till the end of the day.
That thing is pretty compelling
and we come up with all sorts of reasons
why we need it, to be in contact with it
but I encourage you to try experiencing
what it is to be completely
immersed in an activity
where you feel the agitation
that your attention is drifting
but you continually bring it back.
And that's an important point
which is that attention drifts,
but we have to re-anchor it.
We have to keep grabbing it back.
And the way to do that, if
you're sighted is with your eyes.
That as your attention
drifts, and you look away
you want to try and literally
maintain visual focus
on the thing that you're trying to learn.
Feel free to blink, of course,
but you can greatly increase
your powers of focus
and the rates of learning
which is anchored
in all the work of Merzenich,
Hubel and Wiesel and others.
Now that's the trigger for plasticity,
but the real secret is
that neuroplasticity
doesn't occur during wakefulness.
It occurs during sleep.
We now know that if you
focus very hard on something
for about 90 minutes or so,
maybe you even do several
bouts of that per day.
If you can do that, some people can,
some people can only do one
focus about of learning,
that night and the following
nights, while you're asleep
the neural circuits that
were highlighted if you will
with acetylcholine
transmission will strengthen
and other will be lost,
which is wonderful because
that's the essence of plasticity.
And what it means is that
when you eventually wake up
a couple of days or a week later,
you will will have acquired
the knowledge forever
unless you go through some
process to actively unlearn it.
And we will talk about
unlearning in a later episode.
So mastering sleep is key
in order to reinforce
the learning that occurs.
But let's say you get a
really poor night of sleep
after a about of learning.
Chances are, if you sleep the next night
or the following night
that learning will occur.
There's a stamp in the brain
where this acetylcholine was released.
It actually marks those
synapses neurochemically
and metabolically, so
that those are synopses
are more biased to change.
Now, if you don't ever get that deep sleep
then you probably won't get those changes.
There's also a way in which
you can bypass the need
for deep sleep at least
partially by engaging
in what I call Non Sleep Deep
Rest, these NSDR protocols.
But I just want to
discuss the signs of this.
There was a paper that was
published in Cell Reports
last year that shows that if people did,
it was a spatial memory task,
actually quite difficult one
where they had to remember
the sequence of lights
lighting up and if they're
just two or three lights
in a particular sequence it's easy
but as you get up to 15 or 16 lights
and numbers in the sequence
it actually gets quite challenging.
If immediately after,
and it was immediately after the learning
the actual performance of this task,
people took a 20 minute Non
Sleep Deep Rest protocol
or took a shallow nap, so lying down,
feet slightly elevated perhaps,
just closing their eyes, no sensory input,
the rates of learning
were significantly higher
for that information than
where the two just had
a good night's sleep the following night.
So you can actually accelerate learning
with these NSDR protocols
or with brief naps,
90 minutes or less.
So the key to plasticity in
childhood is to be a child.
The key to plasticity in
adulthood is to engage alertness,
engage focus and then to
engage Non Sleep Deep Rest
and deep sleep while you're in
your typical about of sleep.
I always get asked,
"How many bouts of
learning can I perform?"
Well, I know people that train up
these visual focus mechanisms
to the point where they can do
several 90 minute bouts
throughout the day,
as many as three or four.
And some of them are also inserting
Non Sleep Deep Rest as well.
Now that can get pretty tricky.
A lot of people find that
they can recover best
from these intense bouts
of focused learning
by doing some motor activity
where you get into
self-generated optic flow.
And that should make sense
if you've ever heard
me lecture about stress
which I've done a little
bit in various podcasts.
When we are in a mode of
self-generated optic flow
like walking or running or cycling
and things are just floating
past us on our retina,
we're not really looking
anywhere in particular,
so this is the opposite of
a tight window of focus.
When we do that,
there are areas of the
brain like the amygdala
which are involved in releasing epinephrin
and create alertness.
At the extremes, it creates
fear but certainly alertness,
those are all shut down.
So it's its own form
of non sleep deep rest.
So some people find it much
more pleasurable and practical
to engage in a focused about of learning
and then go do some activity that involves
what we would essentially
call worldlessness
where you're not really
thinking about much of anything.
And so for those of you that listen
to audio books or podcasts while you run
you may want to consider whether or not
that's how you want to
spend your time right now.
I'd love it if you were
listening to this podcast
while you run or cycle, but
I'm much more interested
in you actually getting the
benefits of neuroplasticity
than just listening to me for
the sake of listening to me.
So for many people letting the mind drift
where it's not organized in thought
after a period of very
deliberate focused effort
is the best way to accelerate learning
and depth of learning.
And there are good scientific data
to support these sorts of things,
including the Cell Reports paper
that I mentioned a few moments ago.
I want to synthesize
some of the information
that we've covered up until now.
This entire month is
about neuroplasticity.
Today's episode has covered a lot,
but by no means has it
covered all of the potential
for neuroplasticity and
protocols for plasticity.
We will get into all of it.
But today I want to make
sure that these key elements
that form the backbone of neuroplasticity
are really embedded in people's minds.
First of all, plasticity
occurs throughout the lifespan.
Early, from birth until 25,
mere exposure to a sensory
event can create plasticity.
That could be a good thing or a bad thing.
We're going to talk about
unlearning the bad stuff,
traumas, et cetera in a
subsequent episode this month.
If you want to learn as an
adult, you have to be alert.
It might seem so obvious
but I think a lot of
people don't think about
when in their 24 hour
cycle, they're most alert.
There are four episodes
devoted to that 24-hour cycle
and the cycles of alertness and sleep.
I encourage you to listen to those
if you haven't had the opportunity to yet
or just ask yourself when
during the day do you typically
tend to be most alert?
That will afford you an advantage
in learning specific things
during that period of time.
So don't give up that period of time
for things that are meaningless, useless,
or not aligned with your goals.
That'd be a terrible time to
get into passive observance
or just letting your time
get soaked away by something.
That is a valuable asset, that epinephrin,
released from your brainstem
is going to occur more readily
at particular phases of your
24-hour cycle than others,
during the waking phase of course.
You should know when those are.
And then you could start to think about
the behavioral practices, maybe
the pharmacologic practices
like caffeine, hydration, et cetera
that will support heightened
levels of alertness.
Attention is something that can be learned
and attention is critical
for creating that condition
where whatever it is
that you are engaging in
will modify your brain in a way
that you won't have to spend
so much attention on it
going forward.
That's the essence of plasticity,
that things will eventually
become reflexive.
The language that you're learning,
the motor movement, the cognitive skill,
the ability to suppress
an emotional response
or to engage in emotional response
depending on what your goals are
and what's appropriate for you.
Increasing acetylcholine
can be accomplished
pharmacologically through nicotine.
However, there are certain dangers
for many people to do
that as well as the cost,
financial cost,
learning how to engage
the cholinergic system
through the use of the visual system,
practicing how long can you maintain focus
with blinks as you need them,
but how long can you maintain
visual focus on a target,
just on a piece of paper set
a few feet away in the room
or at the level of your computer screen.
These are actually things
that people do in communities
where high levels of
visual focus are necessary.
Now, the other way to get
high levels of visual focus
and alertness is to have a panic
or to have a situation
that's very, very bad.
You will be immediately
focused on everything
related to that situation,
but that's unfortunate.
What we're really talking
about here is trying to
harness the mechanisms of attention
and get better at paying attention.
You may want to do that
with your auditory system,
not with your visual system,
either because you're
low vision or no vision,
or because you're trying
to learn something
that relates more to sounds
than to what you see.
But for most people they're
trying to learn information,
cognitive information, or
they're trying to learn how to
hear the nuance in their
partner's explanations
of their emotionally
challenging events, et cetera.
And just remember, by the
way, what I said earlier,
which is that if you really
want somebody to listen to you
and really hear what you're
saying and what's underlying it,
you should not, and cannot expect them
to look directly at you while you do that.
That's actually going to
limit their ability to focus.
I'm trying to rescue a few folks out there
who might be in this struggle.
I of course have never
been in this struggle.
And that was supposed to be a joke.
I'm very familiar with that struggle
but I know that one can
get better at listening,
one can get better at learning,
one can get better at all sorts
of things by anchoring
in these mechanisms.
Now, of course you can
also combine protocols.
You can decide to combine pharmacology
with these learning practices.
Many people in communities do that.
Many people are doing that naturally
by drinking their coffee
right before they do their learning.
But I would also encourage
you to think about
how long those learning bouts are.
If you think you have ADD or ADHD,
see a clinician but you
should also ask yourself
are you giving up the best period of focus
that you have each day naturally
to some other thing like social media
or some other activity
that doesn't serve you well
or are you devoting that period
to the opportunity to learn?
You should also ask
yourself whether or not
you're trying to focus too much
for too long during the day.
I know some very high
performing individuals,
very high-performing in
a variety of contexts
and none of them are focused all day long.
Many of them take walks down the hallway,
sometimes mumbling to themselves,
they're not paying
attention to anything else.
They go for bike rides, they take walks.
They are not trying to engage their mind
at maximum focus all the time.
Very few people do that
because we learn best
in these 90 minute bouts
inside of one of these ultradian cycles.
And I should repeat again, that
within that 90-minute cycle,
you should not expect yourself to focus
for the entire period
of one 90-minute cycle.
The beginning and end are
going to be a little bit
flickering in and out of focus.
How do you know when one
of these 90-minute cycles
is starting, or typically when you wake up
os the beginning of the
first 90-minute cycle,
but it's not down to the minute.
You'll be able to tap into your sense
of these 90-minute cycles
as you start to engage in
these learning practices
should you choose.
And then of course getting
some non sleep deep rest
or just deliberate disengagement,
such as walking or running,
or just sitting, eyes closed or eyes open
you kind of mindlessly
it might seem in a chair,
just letting your thoughts move around
after a learning about will accelerate
the rate of plasticity
that's been shown in quality
peer reviewed studies.
And then of course, deep sleep.
And so what we can start to see is that
plasticity is your natural
right early in life.
But after about age 25
you have to do some work
in order to access it.
But fortunately, these
beautiful experiments
of Hubel and Wiesel and Merzenich
and Weinberger and others
point in the direction of what allows us
to achieve plasticity,
it points to the neurochemicals
and the circuits.
And we now have behavioral protocols
that allow us to do that.
I also really want to emphasize
that there's an entire other
aspect of behavioral practices
that will allow us to engage in plasticity
that don't involve intense
focus on emotionality
but involve a lot of repetition.
So there's another entire
category of plasticity
that involves doing what seemed
like almost mundane things
but doing them over and
over again repeatedly
and incorporating the reward
system that involves dopamine.
So today I talked about
the kind of plasticity
that comes from extreme focus.
You would get that extreme
focus and alertness naturally
through a harder, difficult
event that you didn't want.
That's the kind of stinger
but your brain is
designed to keep you safe
so it wants to get one trial learning
from things like touching a hot stove
or engaging with a really horrible person.
You can get incredible plasticity
of positive experiences
of things that you want by
engaging this high focus regime
and then rest, non sleep
deep rest, and sleep.
And there's another aspect of plasticity
which we will explore next episode
as well as when we explore
movement-based practices
for enhancing plasticity and
plasticity of movement itself.
And those are not of the high attention
kind of high emotionality
or in the intensity of the experiences
that I described today.
Those are more about repetition
and reward and repeat,
repetition, reward, repeat,
and they are used for a
distinctly different category
of behavioral change more
of which relate to habits
as opposed to learning of
particular types of information
that allow us to perform physically,
cognitively or adjust
our emotional system.
So I'm going to stop there.
I'm sure there are a lot of questions.
Please put your questions
in the comment section below
and please remember that this entire month
we're going to be
exploring neuroplasticity.
So this discussion/lecture,
I wish it was more of a back and forth,
but this is what the format offers us.
So please do put your questions
in the comment section
and I will address them in
the other episodes coming soon
on neuroplasticity.
As I say that I'm reminded
that many of you are listening
to this on Apple or Spotify
and therefore there isn't an opportunity
to leave comments aside from
the rating section on Apple.
So if you have specific topics
related to neuroplasticity
that you would like me to cover
in the subsequent episodes this month
please go to the YouTube, subscribe,
but as well please put your
question in the comment section
for this episode and I'll be
sure to read them and respond.
Many of you have very graciously asked
how you can help support
the Huberman Lab Podcast.
Best way to do that is
to subscribe on YouTube.
You might want to also hit
the notification button
so that you don't miss
any upcoming episodes.
Leave a comment,
as well if you go to Apple,
you can give us a 5-star rating
and there's a place there where also
you can leave a comment.
And if you prefer to listen on Spotify
subscribe and download on Spotify.
In addition, it's always helpful
if you recommend the podcast
to your friends and family
and others who you think might
benefit from the information
and as well, please
check out our sponsors.
That's a great way to help us.
Today and in previous episodes,
I've talked a number of
times about supplements.
I'm very pleased that we're
partnering with Thorne,
T-h-o-r-n-e supplements
because Thorne has the very
high levels of stringency
in terms of product quality and precision
about how much of given
supplements are in the bottle
which is vital and not
all supplement companies
have stood up to the test on that one.
If you want to check out Thorne
and go to Thorne that's
thorne.com/u/huberman.
And if you do that, you'll get 20% off
any supplements that you purchase.
I've also listed there
a gallery of supplements
that I take, including
magnesium glycinate.
I know in previous episodes,
I talked about magnesium threonate
as a sleep aid that I take.
magnesium glycinate
and magnesium threonate
are essentially interchangeable.
Thanks so much for your
time and attention,
and as always thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]