[upbeat music]
- [Andrew Huberman] Welcome
to The Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
- I'm Andrew Huberman
and I'm a professor of
Neurobiology and Ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate from
my teaching and research
roles at Stanford.
It is however part of
my desire and effort,
to bring zero cost to consumer information
about science and science related tools.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Inside Tracker.
Inside Tracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I'm a big believer in
blood tests and DNA tests
for the simple reason
that many of the factors
that are important for
your short-term and long-term
health and overall wellbeing
can only be analyzed
from blood and DNA tests.
Things like metabolic
factors and hormone levels,
really can only be assessed
accurately from blood and DNA.
The thing I like about Inside Tracker is
you don't just get back
levels of different hormones
and metabolic factors and so forth,
you also get directives.
It has a dashboard that's very easy to use
that tells you based on your data,
what sorts of foods you might want to eat
more of or less of.
What forms of exercise
you might want to do more of or less of.
It's really a wonderful way to assess
how your behaviors and lifestyle choices
are interacting with what's going on
deep within your biology.
Inside Tracker makes all of
that super easy to understand.
It's also really easy to
get the blood tests and DNA tests taken.
You can go to a local location or
they can send somebody to
your home if you prefer that.
If you'd like to try Inside
Tracker you can visit
insidetracker.com/huberman to get 25% off
any of Inside Trackers plans.
Use the code Huberman at checkout.
That's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off any off any
of Inside Tracker's plans
and use the code Huberman at checkout.
Today's episode is also
brought to you by Helix Sleep.
Helix Sleep makes mattresses and pillows
that are designed to
meet your sleep needs,
in order to optimize your sleep.
I've done several episodes of this podcast
and there's a ton of information out there
pointing to the fact that
getting really deep
restful sleep each night
is vital for mental and physical health.
And the mattress that you sleep on
and the pillow that you
use is very important
for getting optimal sleep.
Helix Sleep has a brief two
minute quiz that you can take.
It asks you questions like,
"Do you sleep on your side,
or your back or your stomach
or maybe you don't know?
Do you tend to run hot
or cold as you sleep
or maybe you don't know?"
That two minute quiz matches you
to a mattress and pillow
that's ideal for your sleep needs.
I took this quiz,
I matched to the mattress
they call "The Dusk," D-U-S-K.
And I've been sleeping
on "The Dusk" mattress
for many months now
and I've been sleeping better
than I ever have before.
It's really wonderful
to have a really good night's
sleep on a consistent basis.
It's a total game changer.
So if you're interested in
upgrading your mattress,
you can go to helixsleep.com/huberman.
Take their two minutes sleep quiz
and they'll match you to
a customized mattress.
And you'll get up to $200 off
any of their mattress
orders and two free pillows.
So that's helixsleep.com/huberman.
Take the two minutes sleep quiz
they'll match you to a mattress.
And if you order one of their mattresses,
you'll get up to $200 off
any of their mattresses
and two free pillows.
They have a 10 year warranty
and you get to try out the mattress
for 100 nights risk-free
and if you don't like it
they'll pick it up and take it away.
If you love it, then you keep it.
And I think there's a very good chance
that you're going to love it,
I certainly loved mine.
And today's episode
is also brought to you by Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an all-in-one
vitamin mineral probiotic drink.
I started using Athletic
Greens way back in 2012.
And so I'm delighted that
they're sponsoring the podcast.
I started using Athletic
Greens because I found it
rather confusing to figure out
what vitamins and minerals to take.
And in Athletic Greens,
I get all the vitamins and minerals
I need to cover my bases.
As well probiotics are really important.
Probiotics have been shown
now in numerous studies
to be important for the gut microbiome,
which impacts the gut brain axis,
as well as various
aspects of bodily health.
So in Athletic Greens
I get vitamins, minerals and probiotics.
I also really like the way it tastes.
It's a greens drink,
so you mix it with some water.
You could mix it with something else
like juice if you like.
I mix mine with water and lemon juice
and I drink it once or twice a day.
If you want to try Athletic
Greens you can go to
athleticgreens.com/huberman.
And if you do that,
you'll claim their special offer,
which is to get a years
supply of vitamin D3 K2.
There's now also a wealth of data
showing that Vitamin D3 is important
for various aspects of
brain and body health.
So that's athleticgreens.com/huberman
for Athletic Greens and a
years supply of Vitamin D3 K2.
You'll also get five free travel packets.
The travel packets are just
a really convenient way
to take Athletic Greens
when you're on the road,
in the car or on a plane
or just moving around.
You just empty one of the packets
into a water bottle or a glass
and mix it up really quickly.
It saves any kind of mess
or anything of that sort.
So once again athleticgreens.com/huberman
to get Vitamin D3 K2.
That's a year supply and
the five free travel packs.
It's a new month,
which means it's a new topic
here at the Huberman Lab Podcast.
For the next four or so episodes,
we're going to be talking all about
hormone affects on the brain and body.
So that's a huge number
of different topics.
We're going to talk about sex.
We're going to talk about reproduction.
We're going to talk about
puberty a little bit more.
We talked about that
in a previous episode.
We're going to talk about menopause.
We're going to talk about birth control.
We are going to talk about
aggression, competition, winning, losing.
Basically, we're going to
cover as much about hormones
as we possibly can in this month
and in doing so
we are going to go deep
into tools and protocols.
We are also going to talk about a lot of
tools that relate to things
that you might not want to do in order to
optimize hormone health,
regardless of stage of life
or your goals et cetera.
So it's sure to be a month
rich with discussion,
rich with tools and you're
going to learn a lot of
neuroscience and endocrinology.
There's actually a field
of neuro-endocrinology.
It's actually where I
started my graduate work.
I did a masters in it.
Which has only to say
that I love the topic.
I have a lot of friends
that work on this topic,
many of whom I've consulted
for these episodes.
And I'm really excited to
share the information with you.
Before we dive into today's episode,
"All About Emotions and Sex."
I want to just to have a few announcements
that are designed to point
you to some useful resources.
Last episode, "Talking
About The Science of
Emotions and Relationships."
I mentioned the Mood Meter app.
The Mood Meter App was developed by
people out at Yale University who study
the biology and psychology of emotions.
It's a really wonderful app.
However, many of you quickly told me
that the Mood Meter App
isn't available in your area.
You went to the link we posted
and it just was saying not
available in your area.
The situation was actually
a lot worse than that.
The situation was that,
when we recorded the episode
the Mood Meter App was working.
I know 'cause I downloaded a
fresh copy of it to my phone.
And then in the ensuing weekend,
they took the Mood Meter
App down for some repairs.
The Mood Meter app is now up.
It is available.
I want to be really clear.
It's not an app I'm affiliated with.
I'm just mentioning it to you.
They don't know me.
I know them, but they don't know me.
So we don't have any kind
of business relationship.
They do charge 99 cents for the app.
I think the free version has disappeared
in the last year or so.
So that's Mood Meter app.
We'll provide the link again
and the link should be working.
Hopefully they won't take it down again,
in between this announcement
and the release of this episode.
Also just want to take
a step back for a moment
and talk a little bit about the logic
of how to make the most of the information
on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
I tend to throw out a lot of information
about a given topic.
Many of you have pointed out however,
that I don't cover certain things.
And once again I'll just say
the goal is always to be accurate,
but there's no way I can be exhaustive.
There's no way I can cover everything
for a particular topic.
The good news is we have time.
My goal, at least in the first year
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
is to give you a basis,
a foundation in these different topics
of neuro-plasticity, focus,
sleep, hormones et cetera.
And of course, to provide
tools along the way.
We are going to host guests,
I've actually started recording
with some of these guests already.
And even those episodes will include
a little what we call primer.
A little description of
the basics of a given topic
so that you can get more
information from those topics.
My goal really is to
educate you in these topics,
give you a foundation in these topics
and allow you to start exploring them
here in the episodes
with our future guests,
but also in other podcasts and books
and other sources of information.
So for those of you that are saying,
"It's too much information."
I just encourage you
to remind yourself that
you have a pause button
you can return to it.
Everything's timestamped.
For those of you that feel,
it's not enough information
I'm not covering enough.
Just know that this is just the beginning.
We didn't intend to do
this for a very long time
and we will be thorough over time.
So thanks for your patience
and please be patient with yourselves.
There's no reason why you have to digest
all the information in one swoop.
The other thing is that
I've been told both that
I speak too fast and speak too slow.
So there's a wonderful solution to this.
If I speak too fast or too slow
you can adjust the speed in YouTube.
If you're listening in a different format,
I think you also can adjust
the speed of playback.
So that's something that
wouldn't be possible in the classroom,
but you may find useful.
And then last but not least,
I want to point people again to this NSDR,
non-sleep deep rest protocol,
that the folks over at Madefor
have put out as a free resource.
It does, as many of you pointed out,
bear resemblance to things like
yoga nidra and other forms of meditation.
But what we've done is we've stripped out
intentions or any kind of
the verbiage related to
what some people might perceive as
kind of related to the yoga community or
specific to kind of new
age-y type techniques.
Not because we don't like yoga nidra.
In fact, I've done yoga nidra
daily for almost the last
goodness, eight years of my life.
I love yoga nidra,
but sometimes the complicated language
can be a separator and
can discourage people
from taking on these protocols
that are extremely useful.
So NSDR is intentionally generic.
It's designed to bring you into a state of
deep relaxation through a combination of
breathing and body scan.
There's the you too script over at Madefor
which is linked in the caption.
And many people find that they prefer that
to scripts like yoga nidra.
Scripts where they're doing intentions
and they're hearing a lot of
kind of unusual language
around the process.
This is just very basic and
I hope you'll enjoy it.
And if you prefer the more
typical yoga nidra scripts
then go with those.
There are many of them available
on the internet and elsewhere.
And last but not least I
want to point out that,
all our episodes now are subtitled
both in English and in Spanish.
So for those of you that prefer
to digest this information in Spanish,
that's now available to
you in the subtitles.
Today we're going to talk about
The Science of Sex.
In particular, sexual differentiation.
Now that's a complicated topic because
sex is both a adjective,
a noun and a verb,
depending on the context.
Today we're going to talk about
the hormonal effects
and the neural effects
of particular events that
happen during development
and how those guide
adolescent and adult behavior,
including sexual preference.
It's an area that's
fascinating and for which,
there are actually very
solid textbook findings.
So textbook findings means,
that there are many studies
that have been aggregated over decades.
That point to what we now know to be
absolute truths in terms of
how hormones affect brain development,
how the brain impacts hormonal development
and how those interact to
control behavior for instance.
We are also going to
talk about reproduction,
the verb sex.
And of course, sex the verb,
can also be carried out
independent of reproduction.
It's not always,
in particular in humans,
just to produce offspring.
So that's going to be
covered in the next episode,
but you absolutely need to understand
the information in this episode,
in order to make sense of the information
in the next episode.
So, today we're going to explore hormones.
What they are, how they work,
what leads to masculinization
or feminization
of the brain and body?
I'll just throw out one
really interesting fact
that perhaps most of
you didn't realize that
hormones have direct effects on the body.
Most people know that because there are
hormone differences and
sex differences in bodies
in terms of genitalia and body hair,
distribution of body hair et cetera.
But there are also effects of
hormones on the brain directly
and believe it or not
there're also effects
on the spinal cord.
On the neurons and structures
within the spinal cord
that impact in a very direct way,
what sorts of behaviors are possible.
So it's a fascinating area,
you might notice I'm going to go
a little bit more slowly
through this topic
than I normally do.
I want to be extremely
careful with my language.
Some of these topics,
some of you may be thinking
are extremely sensitive, right?
And of course,
any discussion about sex and reproduction
is a sensitive one.
But today we're just
talking about the biology.
We're not getting into
the cultural constraints
or the cultural dialogue.
What we're trying to do
today is really get to
the biology, the physiology,
the endocrinology
and the behavior.
So let's start by talking about
what hormones are just to remind you
and what they do.
Hormones by definition,
are a substance, a chemical that's
released in one area of the body.
Typically from something we call a gland,
although they can also
be released from neurons.
But they're released often from glands,
that travel and have
effects both on that gland
but also on other organs
and tissues in the body.
And that differentiates hormones
from things like neurotransmitters,
which tend to act more locally.
So that's important.
A hormone is a substance secreted
at one location in the body, travels,
and has impact on things
elsewhere in the body.
Examples of tissues that
produce hormones would be
the thyroid, the testes,
the ovaries et cetera.
And then of course there
are areas of the brain
like the hypothalamus and the pituitary,
which are closely related to one another
and release hormones
that cause the release
of yet other hormones out in the body.
So we're going to cover all this.
If you don't know anything
about endocrinology,
you're still going to be able to
understand today's discussion.
And we're going to start
with a discussion about,
what hormones actually do,
to create this thing that we call
masculinization or feminization.
So let's start with development.
Sperm meets egg.
Everything that happens before that
is a topic of the next episode.
But, sperm meets egg.
This is mammalian reproduction.
And that egg starts to duplicate,
it starts to make more of itself.
It makes more cells.
And eventually some of
those cells become skin.
Some of those cells become brain.
Some of those cells become muscle.
Some of those cells become fingers.
All the stuff that makes
up the brain and body plan.
In addition, there are hormones
that come both from the mother
and from the developing baby,
the developing fetus.
That impact. whether or
not the brain will be
what they call organized
masculine or organized feminine.
And as I say this,
I want you to try and discard
with the cultural connotations
or your psychological connotations,
of what masculinization
and feminization are.
Because we're only
centering on the biology.
So typically, people have
either two X chromosomes,
and the traditional language around that
is that person is female, right?
Or an X chromosome and a Y chromosome
and that person will become male.
Now it's not always the case.
There are cases where it's XXY,
where there two X chromosomes
plus a Y chromosome.
There are also cases where it's XYY.
Where they're two Y chromosomes.
and these have important biological
and psychological impacts.
So the first thing we
need to establish is that
there is something called chromosomal sex.
Whether or not they're two X chromosomes,
or an X and Y chromosome,
is what we call chromosomal sex.
But the next stage of
separating out the sexes,
is what we call gonadal sex.
Typically not always, but typically
if somebody has testes for their gonads,
we think of them as male.
And if somebody has ovaries,
we think of them as female.
Although that's not
always the case either.
But let's just explore
the transition from
chromosomal sex to gonadal sex,
because it's a fascinating one
that we all went through
in some form or another.
So this XY that we typically think of as
promoting masculinization of the fetus.
We say that because on the
Y chromosome there are genes
and those genes have particular
functions that suppress
female reproductive organs.
So on the Y chromosome there's a gene,
which encodes for something called
Mullerian Inhibiting Hormone.
So there's actually a hormone
that's programmed by the Y chromosome
that inhibits the formation
of Mullerian Ducts,
which are an important part of the female
reproductive apparatus.
That's critical because,
already we're seeing
the transition between
chromosome Y chromosome and gonad.
And other genes on the Y chromosome
promote the formation of testes.
So there are genes like the SRY gene
and other genes that promote
the formation of testes,
while they also inhibit the formation
of the Mullerian Ducts.
So the transition from
chromosomal sex to gonadal sex
is a very important distinction.
It's kind of a fork in the road
that happens very early in development
while fetuses are still in the embryo.
Now what's interesting as well,
is that just because
there's a Y chromosome
that can suppress Mullerian Duct formation
and there are other genes
on the Y chromosome that
promote testes development.
The placenta itself is an endocrine organ.
I think most people don't know this
but the placenta is an
endocrine organ as well.
The mother, which of course
is carrying the fetus
has an adrenal gland which
can produce testosterone.
There are instances for example,
where a mother has either a tumor
or for some other reason is
secreting large levels of testosterone
while carrying a fetus that is XX.
And that leads to what
we would call masculinization
of certain aspects of the fetus.
Typically, that will be enlarged clitoris.
There also some examples
of other phenotypes on
the body that are created
even though it's a purely
XX chromosomal baby.
So we have to distinguish between
chromosomal sex, gonadal sex.
And then there's what
we call hormonal sex.
Which is the effects of
the steroid hormones,
estrogen and testosterone
and their derivatives,
on what we call morphological sex
or the shape of the baby and the human
and the genitalia and the jaw
and all these other things.
And so it actually is quite complicated.
So you know, it's a long distance from
chromosomes to gender identity
and gender identity has a lot of
social influences and roles.
This is an area that
right now is very dynamic
and in the discussion
out there as you know.
But just getting from chromosomal sex
to what we would call gonadal sex
and hormonal sex and morphological sex,
involves a number of steps.
So today we're going to
talk about those steps.
And there's some fascinating things that
do indeed relate to tools.
Do indeed relate
to some important behavioral choices.
Important choices about things
to avoid while pregnant.
And for those of you
that are not pregnant,
things to avoid if you're thinking about
eventually having children.
And that is not to drive development
in one direction or another,
but there are examples where
there are some deleterious
things in our environment
that can actually negatively impact
what we call sexual development overall,
regardless of chromosomal background.
So let's get started with that.
Let's talk a little bit
more about what hormones do.
Hormones generally have
two categories of effects.
They can either be very fast
or they can be very slow.
There are hormones like
cortisol and adrenaline,
which act very fast.
Adrenaline can increase your heart rate
very fast when secreted into the body.
Cortisol can be a little bit slower,
but it also can have
some very fast effects.
And then there are hormones like.
Like testosterone and estrogen,
which we refer to as the
sex steroid hormones.
The sex steroid hormones can have
quick effects through signaling.
Meaning they can attach to cells
and make those cells do different things.
They can have a actually quite
quick effects on the brain.
A lot of people don't know this,
but there are some very fast effects of
estrogen and testosterone as
well as long-term effects.
These molecules, for those
of you that are interested,
are what it called lipophilic.
Which just means that
they like fatty stuff,
they can actually pass
through fatty membranes.
And because the outside of cells,
as well as the what's
called the nuclear envelope.
Where all the DNA contents
and stuff are stuffed inside,
are made of lipid, of fat.
These steroid hormones can
actually travel into cells
and then get into the DNA.
Basically interact with the DNA of cells
in order to control gene expression.
So they can change
the sorts of things that cells will become
and they can change the
way that cells function
in a long-term way.
And that's actually how
the presence of these genes like SRY
and Mullerian inhibiting hormone,
lead to reductions or
elimination I should say,
of things like the Mullerian Ducts
and promote instead what's called in males
the Wolffian Ducts.
Or promote the development of
testes rather than ovaries.
So all you need to know is that
hormones have short-term
and long-term effects.
And the long-term effects are actually
related to their effects on genes
and how those genes are
expressed or repressed,
in order to prevent them from having
particular proteins made.
So these hormones,
these steroid hormones
are exceedingly powerful.
And if we're going to
have a discussion about
masculinization or feminization et cetera,
you also need to think
about the counterpart.
It's not just about masculinizing the body
or feminizing the body and brain,
it's also about demasculinize
the brain in many cases,
as a normal biological function
of typically of XX females.
And de feminization,
the suppression of certain
pathways that are related
to feminization of the body and brain.
But there are some really
fascinating twists in this story.
So I've just thrown a lot
of biology at you, but
this is where it all starts
to get incredibly surprising.
You would think that it's
straightforward, right?
You have a Y chromosome
you suppress the female
reproductive pathway
like the Mullerian Ducts.
You promote the development of testes
and then testes make testosterone.
And then it organizes the brain male
and it wants to do male like things.
And then in females you get estrogen
and it wants to do female like things.
And air quotes here for all of this.
It turns out that isn't
how it works at all.
Here's where it's interesting.
We have to understand
that there are effects of these hormones,
testosterone and estrogen.
on what are called primary
sexual characteristics.
Which are the ones that you're born with.
Secondary sexual characteristics,
which are the ones that
show up in puberty.
And these are happening in the brain
and body and spinal cord.
And so I'm going to
disentangle all this for you
by giving you some examples.
First, let's talk about the development of
primary sexual characteristics.
The ones that show up at birth.
And one of the more
dramatic examples of this
comes from the role of testosterone
in creating the external genitalia.
Now you might think it's
just straight forward.
If there's a testes, 'cause
there's a Y chromosome.
You know, you've got a gene that codes for
the development of testes,
you get testosterone
and the penis grows
and the baby is born with a penis.
You know, one of the
first things that happens
when the baby comes out
is they look at the genitalia,
and they try and make an
assessment on whether or not
it's a quote boy or it's
a quote girl, right?
That's been done for a very very long time
throughout human history.
It turns out that it's not
testosterone that's responsible
for the development of the penis
in a baby that has an X
chromosome and a Y chromosome.
It's a different androgen.
Androgen is just a category of hormones
that includes testosterone,
but testosterone is converted in the fetus
to something called dihydrotestosterone.
And that's accomplished through
an enzyme called 5-alpha-reductase.
Now dihydrotestosterone
has important effects
later in life too.
We will talk about those.
In fact, if you just want to know,
dihydrotestosterone is what we would call
the dominant androgen in males.
It's responsible for aggression.
It's responsible for a
lot of muscular strength.
It's involved in beard growth
and male pattern baldness.
We're going to talk about all of that.
But dihydrotestosterone
has powerful effects
in determining the genitalia,
while the baby is still in the embryo.
So this ends.
There's testosterone that's made.
And that testosterone gets converted
by this enzyme 5-alpha-reductase
in a little structure called the tubercle.
That tubercle will
eventually become the penis.
So you say, "Okay, straight forward."
This testosterone is converted
to dihydrotestosterone.
And then if there's dihydrotestosterone
it controls penis growth.
And indeed that's the case.
So that's a primary sexual characteristic.
That baby will then grow
up and later during puberty
there will be the release of a molecule.
I talked about this last
episode called Kisspeptin.
K-I-S-S-P-E-P-T-I-N kisspeptin,
which will cause the release
of some other hormones
Connatural releasing
hormone, Luteinizing hormone
will stimulate the testes
to make testosterone.
So in puberty, testosterone
leads to further
growth and development of the penis,
as well as the accumulation
of or growth of pubic hair,
a deepening of the voice,
all the secondary sexual
characteristics, okay?
So dihydrotestosterone
creates what we would call
the typical masculine phenotype for
primary sexual
characteristics and produces.
Testosterone excuse me, produces
secondary sexual
characteristics during puberty.
There's a very interesting phenomenon
that was published in The
Journal of Science in the 1970s,
for which now there's a
wealth of scientific data.
And this relates to a genetic mutation,
where 5-alpha-reductase
the enzyme that converts
testosterone to
dihydrotestosterone doesn't exist.
It's mutated in a way into a
genome that it doesn't exist.
And this actually was first identified
in the Dominican Republic.
It has shown up elsewhere.
It's quite rare, but where
it shows up it's robust.
What happens is baby is born.
Typically when a baby is born
they don't measure chromosomes.
They don't look at
chromosomal sex XX or XY.
That's not typically done nowadays.
Baby is born.
If you were to look at that baby,
it would look female.
There would be very little
or no external penis.
And so people would say, "It's a girl."
And they might, you know,
have the celebration it's a girl.
And I guess now they call
them "Gender Reveal Parties"
or something like that.
I don't know about this, but anyway.
They would reveal.
The baby would reveal
its external genitalia
simply by being there and
being naked when it's born.
It has nothing to do with gender,
it has to do with genitalia and sex.
That baby would be born.
And what was observed is that,
from time to time,
that baby after being raised as a girl,
perfectly happy as a girl
would around the age of 11 or 12 or 13,
would suddenly start to sprout a penis.
There's actually a name for this,
it's called Guevedoces.
Which the translation is
more or less, penis at 12.
And as strange as this might sound,
it makes sense if you understand
the underlying mutation.
What happens in these
children, these Guevedoces,
is that the child is born.
It has testes which are not descended,
so up in the body.
They're not making a lot
of testosterone early on.
They weren't able to
convert testosterone
to dihydrotestosterone
because they lack this
enzyme 5-alpha-reductase.
As a consequence,
the primary sexual characteristic
of external male genitalia, penis,
doesn't develop.
And then what happens is
the baby grows up as a
young child essentially
is treated as a girl.
Generally they report being
pretty comfortable as girls,
although not always.
And then testosterone
starts getting secreted
from the testes 'cause
kisspeptin in the brain
signals through gonadotropin
and luteinizing hormone
and travels down to the testes,
the testes start churning out testosterone
and there's a secondary
growth of the penis.
And all of a sudden there's a penis.
And this leads to some
very complicated situations
in families and culturally.
And actually the outcomes
in terms of whether or not
these children decide to self
identify as males or females
and how people treat them
actually varies quite a lot.
There's actually been kind of an
adopting of a third
category of sex and gender
in these Guevedoces for
in order to just offer
them the opportunity to
explore not just what
would be a typical kind of
girl or woman or boy or man phenotype,
but something in between.
Something that some people
call intersex although
intersex and pseudo hermaphroditism
is actually a separate thing altogether.
So it's fascinating and the point here
is that dihydrotestosterone
not testosterone
is responsible for this
primary growth of the penis.
And that testosterone later is involved in
the secondary sexual characteristics
deepening in the voice, et cetera.
Now this is where the information
gets even more interesting
and applies to essentially everybody.
You might think
that testosterone because
it masculinizes the body
in the secondary sexual
characteristic way.
And because dihydrotestosterone
another androgen,
masculinizes the primary
sexual characteristics.
The growth of the penis early on,
that testosterone must
masculinize the brain.
And there are in fact aspects of
masculinization of the brain and body,
that are independent of genitalia.
Now it might be obvious to some of you,
but some people probably
don't realize that.
Yes indeed the brain has
receptors for testosterone.
It also has receptors for estrogen.
But the fascinating thing is that
if you look at the brains of
people that have Y chromosomes
and that have testes
and that make testosterone,
and you look at the brains of people
that don't have Y chromosomes or testes
and therefore make far less
testosterone in general,
what you realize is that
the cells in the brain
that differ between what
I'll call males and females,
but between XY, and XX
have receptors for testosterone,
but the masculinization of the brain
is not accomplished by testosterone.
I want to repeat this.
The masculinization of the brain
is not accomplished by testosterone.
It is accomplished by estrogen.
Testosterone can be
converted into estrogen
by an enzyme called aromatase.
This is vitally important to understand.
Testosterone can be
converted into estrogen
by something called aromatase.
I'll give an example of where this happens
later in life,
to just illustrate the principle
and really embed it in your mind.
During puberty in boys,
XY chromosome individuals.
It's not uncommon for there to be
transient or sometimes long
lasting breast bud development.
Testosterone goes up during puberty,
for the reasons we talked about before.
And some of that testosterone
gets converted into estrogen
by an enzyme called aromatase.
Aromatase is made by
several sources in the body.
One of the main sources is body fat.
So it can make a lot of aromatase.
Sometimes you'll even see
fairly dramatic breast development
in males during puberty.
Sometimes it's transient,
sometimes it's not.
The other place where you see this
is in athletes and bodybuilders
that take a lot of anabolic steroids.
That take high levels of androgens.
So they'll be taking testosterone
at super physiological doses.
Sometimes not always.
They will convert some of that
testosterone into estrogen
and they'll get what's
called gynecomastia.
Which is the development
of male breast tissue.
Sometimes they'll get
it cut out surgically.
Other times they'll start trying to take
estrogen blockers in order
to try and suppress it
or they'll try and block prolactin.
It's a topic that we're going
to get into in more detail.
But what's important here
is to understand that
testosterone can be converted
to estrogen by aromatase.
Aromatase is not just made in body fat.
There are neurons in the
brain that make aromatase
and convert testosterone into estrogen.
And it is testosterone
converted into estrogen.
In other words,
it's estrogen that
masculinizes XY individual.
That masculinizes the brain.
And this has profound effects
on all sorts of things.
On behavior, on outlook
in the world et cetera.
But I think most people don't realize
that it's estrogen that
comes from testosterone
that masculinizes the
male brain, the XY brain.
Not testosterone nor dihydrotestosterone.
So I just want to mention some tools.
You might be asking yourself,
"How could tools possibly come up
at this stage of the conversation
where we're talking
about sexual development
and we're talking about
the differentiation of
tissues in the body."
Well, this is true both for children
and parents and adults.
I want to emphasize that
there are things that are environmental
and there are things that people use
in their homes sometimes
that actually can impact
hormone levels and can impact
sexual development in
fairly profound ways.
And I want to be very clear,
this is not me pulling from
some rare journal have never heard of it.
This is pulling from textbooks.
In particular, today I'm guiding
a lot of the conversation
on work that on
"Behavioral Endocrinology,"
is a book by Randy Nelson
and Lance Kriegsfeld.
True experts in the field.
I'm going to talk about some
of the work from Tyrone Hayes
from UC Berkeley
about environmental toxins
and their impacts on
some of these things like
testosterone and estrogen.
I'm going to touch into them.
I'm going to give some anecdotal evidence
that's grounded in studies,
which we will provide in the caption
or that I'll reference here.
One of those that's
actually really interesting
but helps illustrate the principle
that we've been talking about is.
A few years ago, there
was a lot of excitement
about Evening Primrose Oil.
Evening Primrose Oil
is in a lot of products
that typically are associated
with skin beauty and skin health.
And so I'm generalizing here.
But typically it was mothers
or sisters that were using it.
And there were actually
examples starting to crop up
of young boys getting
accelerated breast bud development
from skin contact with women were using
Evening Primrose Oil.
So Evening Primrose Oil is
chemically a lot like estrogen
and it has a lot of estrogenic compounds.
There are a number of
things out there like this.
So believe it or not
things like pine pollen
look very much like
testosterone structurally.
They are more or less are testosterone.
Their bioavailability in
humans isn't as clear.
Evening Primrose Oil
has a lot of estrogenic
elements to it.
Just structurally how it's built.
And so there were cases where boys were
understandably you know,
being hugged by their mom
or maybe even like showering and taking.
you know using the Evening
Primrose Oil solution.
Those things will actually
change levels of estrogens
in boys and girls.
And so this wasn't just
an issue for young boys.
This is also an issue for young girls.
So it's not that Evening
Primrose Oil is bad,
it's just that many of
you have probably heard
about the dangers of Soy Isoflavones
and things like that.
The impact of soy on estrogen levels is,
there are some decent
evidence to support that.
However, there's a lot of other factors
that are more severe.
And one of those is this
Evening Primrose Oil.
So regardless of age,
let's just put it this way
because people might be
wanting to drive their
hormones more estrogenic
or more androgenic.
How could I know which
what your preference is?
I don't know.
But in any case,
things like pre Evening
Primrose Oil can actually
promote estrogenic pathways in the body
and some of it can go transdermal.
Likewise, because testosterone
replacement therapy
is fairly widespread nowadays.
And some people accomplish
that through cream.
It's pretty well understood that,
if someone's taking that
they want to avoid contact
with anyone.
Skin contact with anyone
that is trying to promote
more estrogenic activity in their body.
And especially in children.
So that's one.
The other is this issue
of environmental factors.
Now this, you know,
again I'm just going to highlight,
when one starts talking
about environmental factors
and how they're poisoning
us or disrupting growth
or fertility rates
it can start to sound a little bit crazy.
Except when you start to actually look at
some of the real data,
Data from quality research labs funded by
Federal government funded,
not from companies or other sources,
that are really aimed at understanding
what the underlying biology is.
And for that I really,
we should all be grateful to
Tyrone Hayes at UC Berkeley.
I remember way back when
I was a graduate student
in the late nineties,
goodness. at UC Berkeley.
And I remember him, he was studying frogs.
He was talking about developmental
defects in these frogs
that live in different waters around
it was California, but also elsewhere.
And he identified a substance,
which is present in a lot of waterways
throughout this country
and other countries.
So US and beyond.
Certainly not just
restricted to California,
which is atrazine.
This is A-T-R-A-Z-I-N-E.
Again, this is the stuff of textbooks.
And it causes severe
testicular malformations.
So again, atrazine exposure is serious.
And what's interesting is
if you look at the data,
what you find is that
at sites in Western
and Midwestern sections
of the United States 10
to 92% of male frogs.
These were frogs mind you,
had testicular abnormalities.
And the most severe
testicular malformations
were in the testes
rather than in the sperm.
So it's actually the organ
itself, the gonad itself.
Now it's very well known now
that atrazine is in many herbicides.
And so you know, whereas I would say in
the 80's and 90's the discussion around
herbicides and their negative effects
was considered kind of
like hippy-dippy stuff
or the stuff you hear about at
you know, your local community markets
and these kind of new age communities.
Now there's very solid data,
from Federally funded
labs at major universities
that have been peer reviewed and published
in excellent journals,
showing that indeed
many of these herbicides
can have negative effects,
primarily by impacting the
ratios of these hormones
in either the mothers or in the testes,
altering the testes of the fathers
or direct effects on
developing young animals
and potentially humans.
And so you ask, "Well, what about humans?
Frogs are wonderful,
but what about humans?"
So here are the data on what's happening
and this isn't all
going to be scary stuff.
We're also going to talk about
tools to ameliorate and
offset some of these effects.
One would be,
be cautious with Evening Primrose
as well as testosterone creams,
depending on whether or
not you want to be more
androgenic or estrogenic
depending on your needs.
But across human populations,
sperm counts are indeed declining, okay?
So in 1940, the average,
the average density of human sperm was
113 million per milliliter of semen.
That's how it's measured.
How many sperm per milliliter of semen.
In 1990 this figure has dropped to 66.
So it went from 113 million per milliliter
to 66 million per milliliter
in the United States and Western Europe.
So this is not just a US thing.
Researchers also estimated that
the volume of semen produced by men
has dropped 20% in that time,
reduced sperm count per
generation even further.
So between 1981 and 1991,
the ratio of normal spermatogenesis
has decreased from 56.4% to 26.9%.
So there's a lot that's happening
primarily because of these herbicides
that are in widespread use
to reduce sperm counts.
And these are going to
have profound effects
not just on sperm counts,
but on development,
sexual development at the level of
the gonads and the brain.
Because you need testosterone to get
dihydrotestosterone for
primary sexual characteristics.
You need estrogen that's
come from testosterone
to masculinize the brain.
And of course,
we're not just focusing
on sperm and testosterone.
You of course also know
that many of these
herbicides are disrupting
estrogens in a similar way.
Or are leading to hyper
estrogenic, excuse me,
states which might explain why
puberty is happening so much earlier
in young girls these days.
So there are a lot of
things that are happening.
Now does this mean that
you have to run around
and neurotically avoid
anything that includes
things like atrazine and
should you be avoiding
all kinds of herbicides?
I don't know that's up to you.
But it does seem that these
have pretty marked effects,
in both the animal studies
and in the human studies.
You know, you can open up a textbook like
the endocrinology textbook
and find things like Vinclozolin.
V-I-N-C-L-O-Z-O-L-I-N,
which is a fungicide and
it's an anti-androgen.
You give it to animals, to rats.
And instead of forming a
penis, they don't form a penis.
They basically, it's not
that they form a clitoris,
they just don't form a penis.
So let's talk about
female sexual development.
And as always what we'll do is,
we'll talk about the normal biology.
Then we'll talk a little bit about
a kind of extraordinary
or unusual set of cases,
but we'll talk about them because
they illustrate an important principle
about how things work under
typical circumstances.
So there is a mutation called
androgen insensitivity syndrome.
And understanding how androgen
insensitivity syndrome works
can help you really
understand how hormones
impact sexual development.
So here's how it works.
There are individuals who are XY,
so they have a Y chromosome,
that are born that make testosterone.
They have testes and they
don't have Mullerian Ducts
because on the Y chromosome is this
Mullerian inhibiting hormone.
However, these individuals
look completely female.
And in general, they report feeling
like girls when they're young,
women when they're older.
But there's something unusual
that's happening in these individuals
because they have an XY
chromosomal type and not XX.
So what's happening?
Well what's happening is
the testes are making testosterone,
but the receptor for
testosterone is mutated.
And therefore the testes never descend.
They don't have ovaries, they have testes
but the testes are internal.
And so typically these
individuals find out
that they are actually XY chromosomes.
so that you know, their
chromosomal sex is male.
If you will.
And their gonadal sex is male,
but the gonads, the testes
are inside the body.
They don't actually develop a scrotum.
They don't make ovaries.
And when they don't menstruate
around the time of puberty
that's a sign that something is different.
And so they never
menstruate around puberty.
And if they look into this deeply enough,
what you find is that
they are actually XY.
They make testosterone
but their body can't make
use of the testosterone
because they don't have the receptors.
And the receptors are
vitally important for some,
for most all of the secondary
sexual characteristics
that we talked about.
Body hair, penis growth
during puberty et cetera.
They live fairly happy lives as females.
Although of course they
can't conceive, right?
They don't have a uterus,
they don't have ovaries.
They also in general, don't produce sperm
in quantities enough
that they could actually
reproduce with somebody else,
although sometimes they can.
And believe it or not,
and I'm not going to name names
but there are actually
reports of several people,
fairly prominent people throughout history
who have had this androgen
insensitivity syndrome
or people suspected they did.
And the reason to not name names is that,
it gets right to the
heart of whether or not
they are male or female.
How could you say right?
They have XY chromosomes
but gonadally they have
testes that are inside.
And yet, if you looked at their bodies
if you looked at their faces,
you would say almost with certainty
that they appeared female.
And that naturally occurring experiment,
points to the fact that
testosterone that shows up in the body
and impacts the things that
the levels of the receptor
has a profound effect on phenotype.
On the external or body plan.
So again, we're talking about this
in order to illustrate the principle that
in order to have its effects,
a hormone doesn't just have to be present.
That hormone actually has to
be able to bind its receptor
and take action on the target cells.
And once again, I'll just
throw out the example of
where people are using
performance enhancing drugs.
Although that's a pretty broad statement,
nowadays there's a lot of excitement about
the so-called SARMs.
Who are more on the receptor side.
And so we'll talk about
this in a future episode.
And I just say that as a teaser because
the SARMs and what's happening right now
in augmenting sports performance,
both with testosterone directly
but also testosterone derivatives
and then also altering things at
the level of the receptor
is exceedingly interesting
and is revealing to us
the many ways in which
hormones can impact brain and body.
In ways that we didn't suspect.
Perhaps the simplest way to understand
how estrogen and testosterone impact
masculinization or feminization
of the brain and behavior
is from a statement.
It's actually the closing
sentence of an abstract
that my colleague Neuronal Shaw
at Stanford school of medicine published.
Which is that estrogen,
again it's estrogen that is
aromatized from testosterone
by aromatase,
sets up the masculine
repertoire of sexual,
and in animals and in humans,
territorial behaviors.
So it sets up the circuitry in the brain.
Estrogen does that.
Estrogen sets up the masculine
circuitry in the brain
and testosterone is then what controls
the display of those
behaviors later in life.
And I find that incredibly interesting.
You would think it was just testosterone
did one thing and estrogen did another,
but it turns out that nature is
far more interesting than that.
Okay, so what are some things
that impact sexual development
early in life and later in life.
Let's talk about cannabis.
Let's talk about alcohol
and dare I say let's
talk about cell phones.
Something that I never
thought I would ever do,
either in this podcast
or in the classroom.
But, these days there are
really interesting data.
And I think you should be aware of them.
First of all, cannabis, marijuana, THC.
I realize that there are
now a lot of different
variance it's on this.
There are a lot of different
strains of cannabis.
I personally am not a pot smoker.
It's just not for me.
I'm not talking about the
moral or legal implications,
in some States it's decriminalized,
in other places it's really illegal
and other places it's basically legal.
You have to check,
you know where you live
and understand the laws.
That's not what this is about.
What we do know however,
is that with the exception of one study
there are many studies
that point to the fact
that THC and other things in cannabis
promote significant increases
in aromatase activity.
Now pot smokers aren't going to like this,
especially male pot smokers
aren't going to like this
but it's the reality.
Remember, what you're
hearing in the background
is Costello snoring really loud?
Should we put them on screen?
He's not a cannabis smoker,
but you can imagine why.
Come here Costello.
Come here buddy, come here.
He's asleep.
Come here.
He's my [indistinct], there you go.
This dog definitely
does not need cannabis.
This is his state for most of the time.
He is highly...
Oh he's asleep still.
So some of you have asked to see Costello
if you're just listening on audio,
maybe he'll gives a
[Costello grunts]
Oh, okay.
We're going to let him get back to sleep.
He's always here,
some of you have asked to see him.
Costello's not a pot smoker either.
He did have a dog sitter that
was a pot smoker years ago.
It was his favorite dog sitter but,
I'm not a pot smoker.
Again, no judgment.
But here's the deal.
That cannabis,
and it's not clear if it's THC itself
or other elements in the marijuana plant,
promote aromatase activity.
Now, this has been observed anecdotally
where pot smokers have a
higher incidence of developing
something I mentioned before gynecomastia,
breast bud development.
Or full-blown breast development in males.
There may be some women
who want to increase
their estrogenic activity.
Remember females make testosterone.
It comes from the adrenals, right?
They don't have testes.
So it comes from the adrenals
and that testosterone
can also be aromatized.
Although typically
most of the aromatase activity
that we're referring to
in these examples is in males.
So testosterone can increase
estrogenic activity.
So you might say, "Oh you know, therefore
does testosterone reduce sexual behavior?
Does it create all sorts of things
that are related to low testosterone?"
Not necessarily, not necessarily.
And here's why,
estrogen itself in males and females
is important for things like
libido and sexual behavior.
I'm going to repeat that.
If estrogen is too low in males,
it can actually inhibit
libido and sexual behavior.
So you don't want estrogen
too high or too low.
Whether or not you're male or female.
Now of course in females,
estrogen levels tend to
be higher than in males.
I'm speaking very generally here.
You just think back to
the chromosomal sex.
That's what I'm referring to
when I say male or female,
although there's nuance there of course.
In females, the testosterone
that comes from the adrenals
has a powerful effect on
libido and desire to reproduce.
And in the next episode,
we're going to talk about how that works
and its relationship to birth control,
its relationship to menopause.
We're also going to talk about how that
whole thing works in males as well.
But cannabis and other
aspects of the marijuana plant
can impact levels of
testosterone and estrogen
by increasing aromatase.
And so people should be aware of that.
As well, there are good data.
I was able to find
several studies on PubMed,
pointing to the fact that
smoking marijuana during pregnancy can
shift the pattern of hormones
in the developing fetus,
such that it promotes
more estrogenic outcomes.
Now earlier I said that
estrogen is what masculinized
is the male brain,
in utero that's true,
but the way that cannabis seems to work,
at least from the studies I
was able to identify is that
it promotes circulating
estrogen in the body
and therefore can counteract
some of the masculinizing effects of
things like testosterone
and dihydrotestosterone,
on primary and secondary
sexual characteristics.
So I mention this because,
you know I think nowadays marijuana use
is far more widespread
and certainly during puberty
it can have profound effects
on these hormonal systems.
And so we'll do another episode,
that goes really deep into this.
But yes, cannabis promotes
estrogenic activity
by increasing aromatase.
Almost everyone can appreciate that
drinking during pregnancy,
is not good for the developing fetus.
Fetal alcohol syndrome
is a well-established
negative outcome of pregnancy.
And it's something that
there are cognitive effects
that are really bad.
There's actually physical
malformation, et cetera.
So drinking during pregnancy, not good.
Probably drinking during
puberty, not good either.
Because alcohol, in particular
certain things like beer
but other grain alcohols can
increase estrogenic activity.
Now, this isn't just about protecting
young boys from estrogenic activity.
It's also protecting girls from
excessive or even hypo
estrogenic effects of alcohol
in puberty.
Now, many teenagers drink.
College students drink
and it's important to point out that
puberty doesn't start on one
day and end on another day,
puberty has a beginning
a middle and an end,
but development is really
our entire lifespan.
This idea that you know,
puberty you know has this open and close.
That's just false.
Okay, so we talked about cannabis.
We talked about alcohol.
Let's talk about cell phones.
First of all, I use a cell phone.
I use it very often.
And I do not think they are evil devices.
I think that they require some discipline
in order to make sure that
it does not become a
negative force in one's life.
So I personally restrict
the number of hours
that I'm on the phone and in
particular on social media.
I only answer email at
particular times of day.
But what about the cell phone itself?
You know, when I was a junior professor.
I was a pre-tenure early professor.
I taught this class on
neural circuits in health and disease.
And one of the students asked me,
you know are cell phones
safe for the brain?
And you know, all the data
point to the fact that they were.
Or at least there were no
data showing that it wasn't.
I still don't have the
answer on that, frankly.
I don't see a lot of studies about it.
I'm not personally aware of any evidence
in quality peer reviewed studies
showing that cell phones
are bad for the brain
or that holding the
phone to the ear is bad
or that Bluetooth is bad or any of that.
I'm just not aware of any quality studies.
If you are aware of quality
studies, peer reviewed study
please reference them, put
them in the comment section.
Send them to me, however you like.
I'd love to see them.
I'm not aware of them.
However, I was very interested
in a particular study
that was published back in 2013 on rats.
It was basically took a cell phone
and put it under a cage of rats
and looked at basically testicular
and ovarian development in rats and saw
minor but still statistically
significant defects
in ovarian and testicular development.
Since then and now
returning to the literature,
I've seen a absolute explosion of studies.
Some of which are in quality journals,
some of which are in what I would call
not to blue ribbon journals.
Identifying defects in testicular
and or ovarian development
by mere exposure to cell
phone emitted waves.
Let's just call that,
we don't know what they are.
And this sounds almost crazy, right?
Anytime somebody starts talking about
EMS and things like that,
you kind of worry like,
is this person okay?
But look, the literature are
pointing in a direction where
chronic exposure of the gonads
to cell phones could be
creating serious issues
in terms of the health
at the cellular level
and then in terms of the output.
So the output for the testes
would be sperm production.
Swimming speed in sperm
is an important feature of sperm health.
In the ovaries it would
be estrogenic output.
How regular the cycles are.
So in animals,
the cycles are a little bit
different than in humans.
They don't have a menstrual cycle.
They have an estrous cycle,
which is a generally around four days.
I think that it's to say
based on the literature,
that there are effects of
cell phone emitted waves
on gonadal development.
The question is,
what is the proximity of the
cell phone to the gonads?
Now, I've taken the
literature as I observe it.
And that of course we'll
point you to in the captions.
And I don't like to have my
cell phone on and in my pocket,
I'm well past puberty, but nonetheless
some of these effects were
seen in adult animals.
There are effects now that have
been demonstrated in humans.
So let's just talk about
a couple of those effects.
So a paper published in the
journal, "Clinical Biochemistry"
from S. Gander et al.
Looked at hormone profiles
in people based on
proximity to their phone
and frequency of phone use,
where they stored their
phone on their body.
Aa well as proximity
of where they lived to,
I guess they're called these
radio-frequency towers.
So the base stations.
And they were looking at
effects of radio frequency radiation RFR
on human hormone profiles.
And they show significant
decreases in cortisol.
You might say, "Well, that might be good."
But you need that morning cortisol bump
in order to wake up.
Morning cortisol is good.
But also thyroid hormones
were significantly reduced.
Prolactin in young females,
that's definitely concerning
and testosterone levels
in males and females.
And so, there are now quite
good data showing that
being close to the phone
too much of the day
and how close is an interesting question
or living near one of these base stations
apparently can have effects
on hormone profiles.
And when you see a study like this
one should always ask,
"Well, what are the other things
that could also have effects
on these hormone profiles?"
Right? Cause you could imagine that
if you ran the same study
of people that live close to a waterway,
or close to a highway
where there's a lot of
exhaust from buses and cars,
you might see similar effects.
So you have to take these sorts of studies
with a grain of salt.
But I think it's very interesting.
And given that the last time
I looked into these data
were way back when I
was a junior professor
and there was like one or two
studies that I could find.
One of the studies pointed to
increases in testosterone in rats,
where they were had
close proximity to these
radio-frequency radiation waves.
And then in the other case,
it showed decreases in testosterone.
So there really wasn't any
conclusion to takeaway from that.
Now, there's pretty
impressive amount of data
pointing to the fact that
there are effects of
these things on hormones.
I don't know what to do
with that information.
I'm not going to stop using my phone but,
in light of the work from Tyrone
Hayes and others looking at
sperm counts and looking
at the decrease in
testosterone levels and
sperm counts and fertility
over the last 20, 30 years,
perhaps it's you know, not surprising.
Although there again,
cell phones and smartphones
have really been
in prominent use mostly within
the last 10 or 11 years.
And so it's hard to explain
all of those declines
simply on the basis of cell phone use.
There's some interesting
effects of hormones
that actually you can observe
on the outside of people,
that tell you something about
not just their level of hormones,
but also about their underlying genetics.
And these relate to beard
growth and baldness.
And it's fascinating.
The molecule, the hormone
dihydrotestosterone,
made from testosterone,
is the hormone primarily
responsible for facial hair,
for beard growth.
As well, it's the molecule,
the hormone primarily responsible for
lack of hair on the head, for hair loss.
So how does that work?
Well, DHT circulates in the body
and it binds to DHT receptors in the face
to promote hair growth.
But it binds to DHD receptors on the scalp
to promote hair loss.
Not incidentally,
the drugs that are designed
to prevent hair loss
are 5-alpha-reductase inhibitors.
So remember 5-alpha-reductase
from the Guevedoces?
Well, the people that
discovered the Gevedoces,
went on to do a lot of research
on the underlying biochemistry
of this really interesting
molecule dihydrotestosterone.
They identified 5-alpha-reductase.
and 5-alpha-reductase inhibitors
are the basis of most of the
anti-hair loss treatments
that are out there.
And so there's some
interesting things here.
First of all, the side effect profiles
of those treatments for hair loss
are quite severe in many individuals.
Remember DHT is the primary androgen
for libido, for strengthened
connective tissue repair,
for aggression.
Even if that aggression of
course is held in check,
but just sort of ambition and aggression
is related to dopamine,
but within the testosterone pathway,
less so pure testosterone,
although pure testosterone
has its effects.
But DHT is, at least in primate
species including humans,
is the dominant androgen for
most of those sorts of effects.
And if you look at somebody,
everyone can predict whether or not
they're going to go bald
based on looking at their,
we're always taught our mother's father.
So if your mother's father was bald,
there's a higher probability that
you're going to go bald.
The pattern of DHT receptors on the scalp,
will dictate whether or not
you're going to go bald everywhere
or just in the front or the
so called crown type baldness.
And the density of the
beard tells you about
the density of DHT receptors.
Now this varies by background,
by genetic background.
And actually around the world nowadays,
because people travel and people
form couples and have kids with
so many different people of
different mixed cultures.
You're seeing this starting to disappear.
But there are areas areas of the world
where all the men seem to
have the same pattern of baldness,
like a strip of baldness down the center,
with hair still on the
sides and and full beards.
That's because these
patterns of DHT receptors
are genetically determined.
Elsewhere, testosterone
levels can still be very high,
DHT levels in the blood can be very high
and yet people will have very
light beards or no beards.
And that's because
they don't have a lot of
DHT receptors in the face.
And in still other cultures
you'll see people with huge beard,
tons of beard.
Their beards are growing
all the way up to their eyes
and they have huge heads of hair.
And that's because they have a lot of
DHT receptors on the face
and not on the scalp.
So there are a lot of effects of DHT
that you can just see in male phenotypes.
And it's interesting that
these hair loss drugs
that are,
or to prevent hair loss drugs,
are directly aimed at preventing
the conversion of testosterone
into dihydrotestosterone.
And that's why they to some
extent prevent hair loss,
but also to some extent have,
a bunch of side effects that
are associated with low DHT.
Along these lines there's a particular
sports supplement that a lot
of people use called Creatine.
Creatine, now there's a lot
of research showing that
Creatine can bring more
more water into the muscle.
It can support strength.
It does a number of other things.
Might even have some
important cognitive promoting.
Cognitive enhancement
effects, although mild.
The studies there show
that it can be significant.
Some people, not all it's more anecdotal,
report that creatine promotes hair loss.
It differs by individual.
For some people that's
true, for others no.
But yes it does appear,
based on the studies I was
able to find on PubMed,
that creatine does promote
5-alpha-reductase activity
and therefore the
conversion of testosterone
into dihydrotestosterone.
And so it makes sense
that it might promote
some degree of hair loss,
as well as beard growth,
as well as the other effects of DHT.
I recall in junior high
school and middle school,
going home one Summer
it was seventh grade,
coming back in the eighth grade
and a kid that I knew
that I was friends with,
went from being like a young kid to,
he was like a grown man,
he had a full beard.
It was amazing.
It was like he would
completely transformed.
And in puberty as I've said before,
is without a doubt the most accelerated
rate of development
that we will go through
at any point in our lives.
Even faster than infancy
just in terms of the
huge number of different cognitive changes
and physical changes.
Not surprisingly that same individual
was mostly or bald by his early twenties.
And that's because he must have had
just exceedingly high levels of DHT.
I also played soccer with this kid
and he was basically like
dribbling past everybody.
It who was like a grown man,
playing soccer with a
bunch of little kids.
Full beard you know, bald at 20.
And so the rate of
maturation, the rate of aging
is very interesting.
It's hard to know rate of aging.
There's some genetic tests that now
can allow you to do that.
Things like Horvath Clocks
and things of that sort.
Beautiful work of David
Sinclair at Harvard and others
has pointed to this.
The speed of entry and
exit from puberty might be,
I'm putting it out there as a hypothesis.
Might be an interesting window,
into how fast one is going through
their aging or developmental arc.
Because development of course,
doesn't just start at birth
and end after puberty.
It continues your entire life.
So I think it's interesting.
You will often see that
people, boys and girls.
I should say boys or girls,
will develop secondary
sexual characteristics
at different rates.
And sometimes it's sequential.
You know you might see a kid will,
she'll grow very tall
or she'll have a big growth spurt,
but then breast development
will come a little bit later.
And then other features will
come a little bit later.
You can also see this in boys.
The person that I referred to earlier,
my friend that developed a full
beard, you know, went bald.
He was also quite muscular,
he was a great athlete.
So he went through
puberty exceedingly fast.
Other people go through it more slowly.
Some people will go
through puberty at age 14,
but they won't start to
accumulate facial hair
until much, much later.
Or their voice will
change first, very early.
And then they won't get
the other secondary sexual characteristics
until much later.
And so, we don't really
know how that impacts
or relates to overall
trajectory or rate of aging.
But it's an interesting
thing to think about
for each and every one of us.
I'm going to offer you the opportunity
to do an experiment today,
while listening to the podcast.
But first I want to tell you a story about
hyenas, professional baseball
and clitoris's the size of penises.
So when I was a graduate
student at UC Berkeley,
we had a professor in our department,
phenomenal scientist named Steve Glickman.
Steve Glickman, had a colony
of hyenas, spotted hyenas
that lived, within caged
enclosures of course,
in Tilden Park behind
the UC Berkeley campus.
The enclosures are actually still there.
I run past there fairly often.
The hyenas are no longer there.
This was a Federally Funded field station.
These animals were
brought over from Africa
or were bred there.
And the reason why they
were hyenas in Tilden Park,
enclosed in Tilden Park.
Was because hyenas exhibit
an incredible feature
to their body, their hormones
and their social structure.
Hyenas, unlike many species,
have a situation with
their genitalia where
the male penis is actually smaller
than the female clitoris.
And I should say that
the male penis itself,
having seen a fair
number of hyena penises,
is not particularly small.
Which means that the hyena
clitoris's are extremely large.
This was well known for some time.
It turns out that in these spotted hyenas
the females are dominant.
So after a kill
the females will eat, then
they're young will eat.
And then the male hyenas will eat.
As well,
when the female hyena gives birth,
she gives birth, not
through the vaginal canal
that we're accustomed to seeing,
but through a very enlarged
clitoris's like phallus.
Although it's not a
phallus, it's a clitoris.
And it literally splits open.
So many fetuses die during the course of
hyena development and birth.
These animals have this,
what could only be described as
a very large or giant clitoris.
Although for a hyena it's
not giant, it's normal.
And it splits open and the
baby actually comes through.
The baby hyena actually
comes through the tissue
and it's it's a very traumatic birth.
A lot of tissue is torn away, et cetera.
And as I mentioned, a
lot of baby hyenas die.
It was a mystery as to how
the female hyenas have this
we'll call it masculinization,
but it's really a androgen jet.
Excuse me, androgenization
of the periphery.
Of the genitalia.
And it turns out, through
a lot of careful research
done by Steve Glickman,
Christine Drey and others.
That it's androstenedione.
What is essentially a pro
hormone to testosterone?
It's androstenedione at very high levels
that's produced in female hyenas
that creates this enlargement
of their genitalia.
So if you want to read
up on androstenedione.
Androstenedione is made into testosterone
through this enzyme 17-beta-hydroxy
steroid dehydrogenase
it's a complicated pathway to pronounce.
It's a fairly straightforward
pathway biochemically.
You may recall during the 90's and 2000's
there were a lot of performance
enhancing drug scandals,
in particular in Major League Baseball.
And it was purported,
although I don't know
that it was ever verified.
But it was purported that the major
performance enhancing drug
of abuse at that time,
in particular players whose
names we won't mention
but you can Google it
if you want to find out.
Was androstenedione.
And I actually recall long ago,
when you could buy androstenedione
in the health food stores.
And so it was sold over the counter.
So a lot's changed since then.
But it's interesting that these hyenas,
with these highly androgenized genitalia
accomplish that through
high levels of androstenedione
in the females.
Now if that's unusual,
what might be even more unusual is that
a graduate student that I
was working with at the time.
Alongside we didn't share research.
Her name was Nicola Sitka.
She is actually a trained behavioral,
animal behavioral expert.
She had trained ferrets for
that show the "BeastMaster."
And she had trained wolves
for television shows
and was a dog trainer.
She had these two large dogs that,
unlike my dog would actually listen to her
when she would give them commands.
A remarkable scientist.
She was studying a species of mole
that also lived in Tilden Park.
People are going to start
to wonder about Tilden Park,
what's in Tilden Park?
But this particular mole that lived there
had testes for part of the year
and had the capacity
to trans differentiate
its testes into ovaries
in order to balance out the ratio
of males and females in the population
to keep reproduction at appropriate levels
for that certain population.
So some animals are actually able
to adjust whether or not
they have androgenized
or estrogenized gonads,
in order to adjust the ratios of offspring
or the males and females in
therefor promote offspring.
And the last little anecdote about this,
which is also published in
the scientific literature,
which is weird but I do find interesting.
Hormones are so fascinating,
they're just incredible to me is
going back to the marijuana plant.
You know, the marijuana plant
has these estrogenic properties.
And I asked a plant biologist
whether or not this was unusual.
And I asked because
there's all this stuff out there about,
"Oh, you know, Soy does this.
And these plants are highly
estrogenic, et cetera."
Although we should probably point out that
a lot of factory meats
are also estrogenic.
So this isn't a meat versus plants thing.
But this plant biologist told me,
"Oh yeah, there are plants that make
what is essentially the
equivalent of testosterone
like pine pollen as it looks
a lot like testosterone.
And there are other plants that make
what is essentially estrogen.
And I said, "Well, why
would they do that?"
Well and you know plants,
at least as far as I know,
don't have a consciousness.
They don't have a brain.
They don't have neurons even but,
his answer was fascinating.
He said that, one of the
reasons why some plants
have evolved this capacity
to increase estrogen levels
in animals that smoke, not smoke it
but then animals that consume them.
I'm guessing that animals
aren't smoking marijuana.
Although I don't know, send me the paper
if you've heard of this.
Is that plants have figured out ways.
They've adapted ways to
push back on populations
of rodents and other species
of animals that eat them.
So plants are engaged in a kind of
plant to animal warfare
where they increase the estrogen
of the males in that population
to lower the sperm counts,
to keep those populations
clamped at certain levels
so that those plants can
continue to flourish.
Even if those animals are
reproducing very robustly.
And I find this just fascinating.
And hormones therefore,
aren't just impacting tissue
growth and development
within the individual
and between the mother.
Remember the placenta
is an endocrine organ,
and the offspring,
but plants and animals
are in this communication.
And today we're in this communication,
I'm telling you that
there are certain herbicides
that humans are using
for which there's very good data,
are disrupting the endocrine pathways.
And so it's fascinating that
humans and other animals,
we're always in this interplay
with plants and the other
things in our environment.
And hormones and adjusting
the hormone levels
of animals and plants is one way in which
the environment kind of pushes back
or pushes forward if you will,
in terms of promoting their
well-being and longevity,
as well as you trying to promote
your wellbeing and longevity.
If anyone wants to see
the incredible paper
by Steve Glickman and colleagues.
It was published in the proceedings
of the national Academy.
First in 1987, that's Glickman et al.
That was the hypothesis that
it was androstenedione .
And then if you just Google
Glickman hyenas science magazine,
there's a beautiful
cover article and feature
all about that important discovery,
it's a fascinating one.
And I should mention also
that those discoveries,
both the moles and the hyenas weren't just
impactful for the world of animal behavior
and endocrinology,
they've also strongly
impacted understanding
of conditions that show up in the clinic,
which we haven't talked about today.
Which is actually pseudo hermaphroditism.
Occasionally babies will be
born where it is unclear,
if they are boys or girls
based on the genitalia.
And this has a very important
ethical and other issues.
Do you raise them as a boy or a girl?
It's not super uncommon
for this to happen.
And there have been terrible
cases where people have
gone against the chromosomal sex.
And the person was very unhappy
with the the choice that their
parents had made for them.
There were also cases where
they've gone with a chromosomal sex
and the person was very
happy about the outcome.
There've been cases where
they've been treated with hormones
and there been cases where they have not
been treated with hormones.
It's a complicated literature and
it has to be sorted out on
kind of a case by case basis,
but it is something that does happen.
And the studies on
androstenedione in hyenas
and in these very interesting moles,
pseudo-hermaphroditic moles
that live in Tilden Park,
have impacted not just the science
but the therapeutics around
those important issues.
So now last but not least,
I want to discuss the effects of hormones
while you and I were separately in utero
and the effects that
that had on who we are,
who we select as mates.
So mate choice, sexual preference.
And all other aspects
of what you would call
sexual development.
Now this is something that's
gotten a lot of popular press
and it has to do with
how exposure to androgens in particular
while we were in utero,
impacted whether or not people report
as homosexual, heterosexual,
identify as male or female.
I'm very familiar with this work
because I was a graduate student
in the department that
first published this work
and I'm an author on the paper.
I was not the main driver of the work,
but I was involved in the work.
And I certainly know the
people that did this work.
First it starts with a story.
There was a researcher
who's still going now.
His name is Dennis McFadden.
I believe he was at UT Austin back then.
And he was studying the auditory system.
And people would come into
his clinic and he would,
or his laboratory.
And he would look at hearing
and he would explore different aspects
of what they call the
psychophysics of hearing
and understanding hearing thresholds
and frequency thresholds.
And he made several observations.
And those observations were that
young males tended to have
what are called auto acoustic emissions,
more often than young females did.
Auto acoustic emissions,
as the name suggests,
are the ears actually making sounds.
Now these sounds have to be picked up
by a special apparatus,
because they can hear into that frequency.
But it turns out that your ears don't just
take sound waves and convert them into
this thing we call hearing.
But they also in some cases make sound.
So your ears are making sounds.
Strange right?
So it turns out that there's a
sex difference in auto acoustic emissions.
It turns out also that people
that self-report as lesbians,
they also have auto acoustic emissions
significantly more than females
that don't self-report as lesbian.
And Dennis noticed this
and published this.
And it was an important discovery because
it was one of the first discoveries
that pointed to the fact that there are
sex differences in biology
that are independent of sex.
I mean, this is hearing and
auto acoustic emissions.
And just to really illustrate what that.
What the former problem was
and why this study was so important?
You know, a lot of people had explored
for instance whether or not,
homosexuals had lower testosterone
for instance in males.
And actually the result
often was the opposite.
That gay men or men
that self-report is gay,
often had much higher testosterone.
And those studies then
became controversial
because people said,
"Well, sexual behavior can
relate to testosterone,"
et cetera.
And so it became very controversial.
And then there were some studies
that attempted to look at
the equivalent phenomenon in
people that self report as lesbian.
Or self-report as heterosexual.
And so it became very complicated.
But this was an identification
of a phenomenon,
auto acoustic emissions,
that was independent of
anything that had to do with
sexual or even social behavior.
1998 rolls around.
And I'm a graduate student at UC Berkeley
and a guy by the name of Mark Breedlove.
Kind of an ironic name,
given that he worked on.
He worked and still works
on sexual dimorphism
in the brain and in the spinal
cord and nervous system.
And Mark, who's a phenomenal scientist
comes running down the hall.
I'll never forget this.
And he said, "Give me your hands."
I was like, [indistinct].
He's like, "Give me your hands."
And he pulls out a ruler
and he starts measuring my fingers.
And he takes down a couple of measurements
and then he goes away.
And I was like, "What was that?"
Well, I was in a course
that Mark was teaching
at that point.
And soon after, we did a
study that Mark directed
exploring the finger length ratios.
And I'll explain what those are.
Of males and females,
and people that self-reported
as homosexual or heterosexual.
So let's just get to the basic,
what we'll call sex differences first.
These are averages.
I want to point out.
Anytime you get into this kind of topic,
people assume it's causal,
but it's not causal.
These are averages that
I'm about to report.
It is the case that the ratio
of what's called the D2 to D4 digits.
So the D2 is your index finger.
So your thumb is D1.
Then D2 would be your index finger
that you would point with.
Middle finger is D3,
which you whatever with.
And then D4 is the so-called ring finger.
Okay and D5 is the pinky.
It is the case that
the D2 to D4 ratio is greater
in self-reported females
than it is in males.
What does that mean?
It means that digit D4 and
D4 are more similar in length
in females than in men males.
And that effect is
particularly, excuse me,
pronounced on the right hand.
Although not always, okay?
And it does not have
to do with handedness.
This D2 to D4 difference has
to be measured correctly.
You can't just look at
somebody who's hands and say,
"Oh, their ring finger and
index finger are very similar.
And therefore they are female you know.
Or they were exposed to very
little testosterone in utero."
You can't look at somebody and see that
their index finger is much
shorter than their ring finger
and say, "Oh, they must've been exposed
to a lot of androgen."
You have to actually measure it
and you have to measure it correctly.
You have to measure it from
the base of the finger where
there's that first crease,
all the way to the tip past the.
You can't include the fingernails.
If you're growing fingernails,
it'd be logical here folks.
So you can't normally see it
from the back of the hand.
Although, I don't know if
this'll show up here but
if you look at the back of the hand
sometimes you can see it.
You know, in my case for instance.
Let me see if I can do this.
So my D4 is a little
bit longer than my D2.
In some people it's more pronounced
and that's on my right hand.
On the other hand,
the difference actually
is far less pronounced.
Is it's a little bit.
it's a little bit pronounced
there, but not so much okay?
So that's sort of the typical
ratio that you would see.
It turns out that in mice and in humans,
the more androgen that you
were exposed to in utero,
the smaller the D4 D2 ratio.
Meaning that the ring finger tends to be
slightly longer than the pointer finger.
And in females because they're exposed to
less androgen in utero typically.
Then those fingers tend to
be more equal in length.
And these are subtle differences
and these are averages.
I invite you to look up the paper.
This was published in Nature in 2000
and it's been replicated six times.
Now, here's where it gets
even more interesting.
And potentially precarious,
so we're going to step cautiously here.
If you look at the finger length ratios
of men that self-report as homosexual,
they have either the typical
male pattern of D2 to D4 ratio
or a hyper masculinized D4 to D2 ratio.
Now this can't be something
that's established or
modified by behavior.
This has to be something that
was established in utero.
And in fact, it's present at birth okay?
So it completely divorces
the interactions between
hormones and behavior.
And that's an important theme
that we've been talking about.
And we're going to talk about even more.
Next episode is that
hormones impact behavior
but behavior also impact hormones.
But this is a case of hormones impacting
what really should be considered
a primary sexual characteristic.
Because it doesn't show up in puberty,
it shows up before puberty.
It's actually established in utero.
And in people that self-reported lesbians.
And I remember going out there
and collecting these data with,
with the collaborators on this work.
Again, I wasn't the
main driver on the work.
But I participated in
some of the analysis.
People that self-report as lesbians
also tend to have a
smaller D2 to D4 ratio.
So this is consistent with the
auto acoustic emission study
that Dennis McFadden had published.
And it points to the fact that
early exposure to androgens
may have an impact,
not just on androgenization
of the body plan,
but also separately on sexual preference.
Now, this raises all sorts
of interesting questions
about biological basis
of sexual preference.
I'll tell you about another study.
A guy named Simon LeVay who was at UCLA.
Who trained under Hubel and Wiesel.
If any of you remember early
episodes on "Plasticy,"
David Hubel and Torsten Wiesel
my scientific great-grandparents
won the Nobel Prize
for discovery of critical
periods for brain plasticity.
They defined some of the
most important aspects
of how we see and brain plasticity.
Simon LeVay trained with them.
And then Simon went on to discover that
in the brains of people
that self-report homosexual
there is a brain difference.
And the brain difference
is in an area called
the Interstitial Nucleus of
the Anterior Hypothalamus.
So it's the INAH.
And so there are published reports.
That was published in Science.
The other work I refer to
as published in Nature,
and then replicated no
fewer than six times.
And the McFadden results that point to
strong biological correlates
of mate choice, of sexual preference.
And these tie directly to
things like androgenization
or estrogenization.
Meaning we could call it
maleness or femaleness,
but that's sort of tricky territory.
Because of the way that we described
the huge range in which
sex can be defined earlier.
So, if you want to
measure your D2 D4 ratio
you're welcome to,
but you also have to understand that
it's not predictive of anything, right?
It's just a window into the possible
androgen exposure that
you had early in life.
There are plenty of men
who report themselves
as heterosexual who are out there
who have similar or have
D2 D4 ratios to females.
And there are plenty of
females whose index fingers
are shorter than their ring fingers.
And they're perfectly happy
where they say they're perfectly happy.
And we are inclined to believe
them being heterosexual.
So there's variation.
In fact, Mark tells a really good joke.
If you want to know whether or not
somebody is homosexual or heterosexual,
simply look at their hands,
look at their D2 D4 ratio
and guess heterosexual.
And you'll be right 96% of the time.
Because 96% of the time
people report themselves
as heterosexual on average.
Those numbers might be changing.
So the joke really is a
joke on science because,
that falls within the realm
of statistical significance.
And yet it really
illustrates the fact that
none of this is causal.
But it's nonetheless very interesting
because it means that
hormones are organizing
the brain early in
development in ways that
can potentially impact
same or opposite sex partner
choice later in life.
Now of course, there are
other things that can impact
opposite sex or same-sex
partner choice later in life.
The study did not look at
people who reported bisexual.
There hasn't been a lot
of studies on that yet.
One thing that's very interesting,
for which there are some
good scientific data
but there's also some controversy is that,
it appears that the
probability of a male human
self-reporting as homosexual,
increases with the number of
older brothers that he has.
Now, that doesn't mean if
you have an older brother
or even if you have 10 older brothers,
that you are sure to
self-report as homosexual.
But statistically it becomes
more likely that somebody will
with each successive older
brother that they have.
And the idea that starting to emerge,
in the developmental
neuroendocrinology landscape
is that there's a record within the mother
of how many male fetuses she's carried,
because male fetuses are
secreting certain things,
dihydrotestosterone, other things,
that can feed back on to the genome.
So these could be epigenomic effects
or onto the placenta itself,
so that there's a higher probability
in subsequent pregnancies
that offspring will
self-report as homosexual.
So it's a fascinating area of biology.
And as you've noticed today,
none of this deals with
the current controversies around gender
and how many genders and sex, et cetera
That's a separate conversation that is
by definition grounded
in the kind of concepts
we've been talking about today
and needs to take place,
taking into consideration
all of the aspects of sex
and the effects of hormones,
both on the body, on the brain.
We didn't talk a lot about spinal cord,
but we will in the next episode.
But we can just say on the
brain and the periphery,
early effects, late effects,
acute effects, meaning
effects that are very fast
of levels of hormones going up or down.
Something that absolutely happens during
and across the menstrual cycle.
As well as long-term effects
like the effects of these
hormones on gene expression.
So today, as always,
we weren't able to cover
all things related to sex and hormones
and sexual differentiation or development.
There's no way we could.
But we have covered a lot of material.
We talked about some effects
of environmental toxins.
We talked about potential
effects of cell phone radiation.
Something I never thought
that I would be talking about,
especially not in a podcast.
But for which there are
interesting emerging data.
We talked about considerations about
Evening Primrose Oil and
its estrogenic effects.
About Creatine and its pro DHT effects.
About cannabis, alcohol.
About plants exerting warfare on animals
by increasing aromatase.
The conversion of
testosterone to estrogen.
We talked about hyenas
with giant clitoris's.
And we talked about moles that can revert
from having ovaries to testicles.
And throughout this Costello
has been snoring nonstop.
He missed all of it.
Although he might be
learning it in his sleep
for all I know.
And I do understand it's
a lot of information,
a lot of detail as always.
I just want to remind you,
you don't have to absorb
all the information at once.
Next episode, we are
going to be talking about
the science of sex, the
verb, actual reproduction.
We're also going to be talking about
effects of hormones on
various aspects of behavior
and ways to modulate hormones,
through the use of
behavior, supplementation.
Also we'll touch on diet
and nutrition a bit.
And we're going to talk about
interactions between
those things and behavior,
as they relate to important themes
like sex and reproduction.
Like workplace performance.
Like motivation and
drive and even anxiety.
There's a very interesting
relationship between
hormones and anxiety and the
desire to explore novelty.
So just to remember as we go forward that,
hormones affect behavior and
behavior affects hormones.
But that doesn't mean that
cutting off your index finger
will increase your testosterone.
Many of you have asked how you
can help support the podcast.
And we thank you for the question.
There are several ways to do that.
The first one is to subscribe on YouTube.
If you haven't subscribed to
the YouTube channel already,
please do so.
As well, please hit the subscribe button.
So you're sure not to
miss any of the episodes.
We do release episodes every Monday,
but we also occasionally
release short clips in between.
As well, if you could subscribe
on Apple and or Spotify,
that's very helpful.
And on Apple you have the opportunity
to leave us up to a five star review
and to leave a comment.
On YouTube, please do leave
us comments and suggestions
for future episodes.
We really appreciate the feedback
and we appreciate those suggestions.
Also ask us any questions
you have about the material.
Those questions help
guide our office hours,
this discussion about your questions
that we hold from time to time,
as well as inform future content.
Also, if you could tell
people about the podcast.
Please tell your family,
your friends, your coworkers
anyone that you think might
benefit from the material.
That really helps us get the word out.
As well, if you're
interested in supplements.
We've partnered with Thorne.
T-H-O-R-N-E.
And we've partnered with Thorne because,
Thorne has the highest level of stringency
with respect to the ingredients
that they put in their products.
As well as the precise
amounts of those contents.
You know, a lot of
supplement brands out there
claim to have X amount of some supplement,
but then when people have measured
the amount in capsules and tablets,
it's turned out to be very different.
Thorne is very precise about this.
They partnered with important
and stringent institutions
like the Mayo Clinic, all
the major sports teams.
So that's why we partnered with Thorne.
If you want to try any
of Thorne's products,
if you want to see what I take
you can go to Thorne that's
thorne.com/u/huberman
And if you do that you can see
any of the products that I take.
You can get 20% off any of those.
As well as 20% off any
of the other products
that Thorne makes.
So that's thorne.com/u/huberman.
Please also check out our sponsors.
Check out the sponsor links.
That's perhaps the best way to support us.
And of course, I want to point out,
that any of the ways that support us,
whether or not they are cost-free
like subscribing and leaving comments
or whether or not you're
interested in the products
that I've referred to, those all help us.
And so we really appreciate it.
So once again, I want to thank you
for embarking on this
journey through neuroscience
and today neuroendocrinology with me.
And as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]