- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
[upbeat music]
My name is Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a Professor of Neurobiology
and Ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor today is Theragun.
Theragun is a handheld
percussive therapy device
that releases deep muscle tension.
I was first introduced to Theragun in 2017
while on a laboratory expedition.
We were in the middle of the Pacific Ocean
filming great white sharks
for my laboratory studies on
fear using virtual reality
we were working very hard around the clock
and I and other people on the
trip were picking up a lot
of aches and pains and just
kind of chronic soreness.
Couple of people had
injuries that were flaring up
because of all the hard
work and lack of sleep.
Someone had a Theragun
and pretty soon it was
getting passed around.
It became the most
coveted device on board.
Everyone was using it to work
on these different sites of soreness.
And I really fell in love
with the thing so much
so that when I got back, I
immediately purchased one
and I've used it almost daily ever since,
I use it on muscles that are sore,
I use it on areas that
I'm really working on to
release tension and improve
tissue quality and so forth.
The great thing about
Theragun is it's really quiet
so you can use it while you're
in a conversation or while
you're watching a movie
and it doesn't disrupt
those activities at all.
If you want to try Theragun
you can try Theragun by going
to theragun.com/huberman
to get your gen four
Theragun, they start at $199.
But if you think about it, a
massage, which is an hour long
or 90 minutes long is typically
in that range of costs.
And this is something
you can use every day
whenever you want, and even
while enjoying other activities.
So that's theragun.com/huberman.
The second sponsor of today's
podcast is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a personalized nutrition
platform that analyzes
data from your blood
and DNA to help you better
understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
The great thing about InsideTracker
is that it gives you data
that you can make sense of.
I've long been a believer in
getting blood samples taken
and more recently I've become a believer
in getting DNA samples taken
in order to understand what's going
on at the level of
hormones, metabolic factors
and other things that profoundly
influence our immediate
and long-term health.
The problem always has been
getting those samples taken
and making sense of those samples.
InsideTracker makes all
of that really easy.
They'll even come to your
home to take the samples.
Then you get the information back.
And while typically after
getting information back
there's these long lists of numbers
and nobody knows what to do with them,
InsideTracker makes it really easy to
interpret what those numbers mean.
And it points to things
in terms of lifestyle, exercise,
nutrition, and so forth
that can help you adjust some
of the numbers that
you might need to bring
down or up to put into the
appropriate normal range.
So I find this whole process
to be immensely valuable
for guiding my health
choices and also just
for giving me peace of
mind about how my body
and the rest of my health
are doing internally.
Something you just can't know
without a blood and DNA test.
If you want to try
InsideTracker, you can go
to insidetracker.com/huberman,
and you'll get 25% off any
of their programs, you want
to put Huberman at checkout.
So that's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off any
of InsideTracker's plans and
put Huberman at checkout.
The third sponsor of today's
podcast is Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an
all-in-one vitamin mineral
probiotic drink.
I started using Athletic Greens in 2012.
So I'm delighted that they're
a sponsor of the podcast.
The reason I started using Athletic Greens
and the reason I still take
it once or twice per day,
is that I find it very
hard to know what vitamins
and minerals I need to take.
And by drinking Athletic
Greens, I get it all in one
easy to consume great tasting formula.
I really do like the way it tastes.
I mix mine with water
and a little bit of lemon or lime juice.
And to me it's delicious.
The other thing about Athletic Greens
that I really like are the probiotics
there are so much data
out there now telling us,
and I certainly believe based
on the data that I've seen
that probiotics are really
important for support
of the gut microbiome, the gut
brain axis, the immune system
and many other aspects of our biology.
So with Athletic Greens,
I get the vitamins
the minerals and the
probiotics that I need.
If you want to try Athletic Greens
you can go to athletigreens.com/huberman.
And if you do that, they'll
also give you a year supply
of vitamin D3K2.
Vitamin D3 we also know
is really important
for things like immune
system and metabolic support.
So that's
athleticgreens.com/huberman to get
Athletic Greens and a year's supply
of vitamin D3K2.
And they'll give you
five free travel packs.
Today we're talking all about emotions,
and emotions are central to
our entire experience of life.
Whether or not we're happy or sad
or depressed or angry
is our life experience.
And yet I think with all the importance
we've placed on emotions.
Very few people actually
understand how emotions arise
in our brain and body.
And I mentioned brain and body
because as you'll see today
emotions really capture the
brain body relationship.
We cannot say that emotions
arise just from what
happens in our head.
It also involves events, biological events
chemical events within our body.
The other thing about emotions
is that there's no real agreement
as to what's a good
emotion or a bad emotion.
Today we're gonna talk about the biology
of the chemicals and pathways
that give rise to emotions.
And I'm going to equip you with several,
if not many tools that
will allow you to regulate
and change and steer your
emotions should you want,
but not using the typical advice.
You know, everyone's
probably heard of this thing.
Oh if you're feeling
depressed, just smile,
you know, it's impossible to
be depressed while smiling.
Look, if that were true
we wouldn't have any depressed people
because depressed people
don't want to be depressed.
And it is not the case
that simply smiling will
reverse depression or sadness.
And it's simply not the case
that smiling can inhibit sadness.
It just doesn't work that way.
However, it is the case
that certain things that are happening
in our body influence
how our brain functions
and the chemicals that are released.
And today we're gonna talk
a lot about how the brain
and body interact to create
these things called emotions
in the context of food and nutrition.
And the reason we're doing that is not
because I am beating the drum
about particular diet
regimens or anything.
In fact, I'm not gonna do any of that.
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna review some
of the most important
scientific data that point
to how ingesting certain
nutrients, both macro nutrients
like proteins, fats, and carbohydrates,
as well as micronutrients
can impact the chemicals
in our brain that give rise
to the feelings of being happy
or sad or sleepy or alert
when you want to be sleepy
or sleepy when you want to be alert.
So this is sure to be a broad discussion
and yet we're gonna get very specific
about what emotions are,
how they arise in the body,
tools that one can use in order
to better control their emotions,
tools that people can
use to believe it or not
feel happier or feel calmer.
And that's because in
the last 20 years or so
there's been an explosion
of scientific studies
exploring how the brain and body interact
to support certain neurochemicals
that give us these feelings
of being alert and happy
or depressed or certain
that our life is gonna be terrible
or certain that our life
is going to be great.
So as mysterious as all that might sound
and confusing as all that might sound
we're gonna make it very clear today.
And you're gonna come away
from this conversation
with a lot of tools that
you can act on immediately.
And those tools are
grounded in scientific data.
We are gonna provide links
to several of the studies,
and I'm gonna mention
several of those studies as we go along.
But overall, the goal today is
for you to understand how
moods and emotions arise
and the different pathways in your brain
and body that allow them to happen
and how you can use those
pathways to change those emotions
and the tools that you can rely
on in very specific ways to shift
from being, say, slightly
depressed, to feeling happier.
There actually are ways to do that,
or from feeling too alert and
anxious to feeling calmer.
And these are tools that are distinct
from the tools I've talked
about in previous episodes.
The discussion around emotions has a long
and rich history going back to Darwin.
And even long before Darwin,
this is a conversation that philosophers
and scientists have
been having for hundreds
if not thousands of years.
The idea that Darwin put forth
and that was really attractive
for about the last hundred years was
that emotions are universal and that some
of the facial expressions
around emotion are universal
and other people have
capitalized on that idea.
And to some extent it's true.
I mean, I think that the
two most robust examples
of that would be when we see something
or we smell something or we
taste something that we like,
there does tend to be
a postural leaning in.
We tend to inhale air at
that time, we tend to bring
in more of whatever chemical
substances there is.
We tend to these mm's and kind
of lean in closer to things
that are attractive to us.
And when we see and experience
things that we don't like
sometimes it's a mild aversion.
We just kind of lean back or look away.
Other times it's an intensive version
of disgust and we tend to cringe our face.
We tend to avoid inhaling
any of the chemicals.
This probably has roots
in ancient biological mechanisms
that are to prevent us
from ingesting things that are bad for us,
chemical compounds and tastes
that might be poisonous.
So much of the foundation
of any discussion
about emotion has to center
around this kind of push pull
of attraction to things
or aversion from things.
Now that's a very basic way
of thinking about emotions
but if you think about
it, it works for a lot
of different circumstances
and in the brain everywhere
from the deep circuits of
the brain to the more kind
of what we call higher order
evolved centers of the brain.
We have this push pull thing where
either a previous episode,
I talked about go,
the circuits that allow
you to emphasize action
and then no go circuits, the
circuits and the basal ganglia
that allow you to de-emphasize
action and prevent action.
We talked about how that's a push pull.
So aversion and attraction
is a push pull too.
Delight or happiness or
excitement are attractions
to certain things and ideas,
songs, people, places, foods
aversion is a leaning out.
It's a disgust, it's an avoidance.
And so we can break down the
discussion about emotions
into these simpler versions of themselves,
but at the core of that
of attraction or aversion
is an important theme that
you might realize already.
But most people tend to overlook
which is that there's an action there
you're either moving forward
or you're moving away from something.
And any time you're talking about action
in the nervous system, you're
talking about motor behaviors.
You're talking about
literally the contraction
of muscles to move you
toward or away from things.
And any time you're talking about nerve
to muscle and action, you're
talking about the brain
and the body, because the
brain can't move itself
that the brain has a body so
that the organism can move.
And the body has a brain so
that the organism, you,
can move toward or away
from things that you deem
to be good or bad for you.
Now, some of these things that
we're attracted to and some
of them that we avoid are what
we call innate or hardwired.
You know, when we taste bitter compounds,
I'm not saying about bitter
like a little bit of a
bitters in your drink
or something like that, but
really bitter compounds.
We tend to avoid those
because they're associated with poisons.
When we taste things that
are sweet or that are savory
we tend to pursue more of those.
We tend to lean toward those so to speak
and we tend to not avoid them.
So there are circuits in the brain
for aversion and for
attraction toward things.
And the body is governing a lot of that.
And so immediately in this conversation
I want to raise an important point
which is about a nerve pathway that many,
many people have heard of that
gets discussed all the time.
And that is one of the
most kind of oversold
for the wrong reasons and
undersold, unfortunately,
for its real power,
which is the vagus nerve.
So the vagus nerve is one, not the only,
but one way in which our brain
and body are connected and
regulates our emotional states.
Now, many of you have probably
heard about polyvagal theory.
I'm gonna talk about this today.
Polyvagal theory was
popularized by Stephen Porges
and it's an interesting theory,
certain aspects of it, frankly,
hold up to the science,
some of it doesn't.
And I'm gonna discuss all of that today.
A lot of the vagus and the excitement
about the vagus, V-A-G-U-S,
is because it's somehow got
into the mind of the public
that the vagus is involved
in calming us down.
So what is the vagus nerve?
Okay, we're gonna make this really simple,
in particular for those
that are just listening,
you can just imagine this,
for those are watching I'll
point to the various areas,
but basically vagus is
the 10th cranial nerve
which basically means that the neurons,
the control center of
each of those neurons
in the vagus lives just kind
of near the neck, right?
And a branch of the vagus
goes into the brain.
They send a little wire into the brain.
The other branch goes into the periphery
but not just the gut.
It goes into the stomach, the intestines
the heart, the lungs,
and the immune system.
So this vagus nerve is incredible
because it's taking information
from the body and it has two directions.
The first is what we call sensory.
So it's sensing things that
are happening in the gut
in the lungs, everything,
for example, in the lungs
when our lungs are distended,
the vagus nerve senses that
and sends that information
up into the brain.
It also consents things in
the gut like how distended
or empty your stomach happens to be,
it can sense heart rate.
It can sense your immune
system, whether or not
you have bacteria or things
invading you in your body.
So it sends that
information up to the brain.
So it's a two-way street
and sensory information
is going up to the brain.
That's all vagus.
So it's like a super
highway sensory information
going one way and in the other
direction is motor control.
So the vagus is not
just for sensing things.
It's actually for controlling things.
It's got a sensory pathway
and a motor pathway.
So that's the first thing I
think everyone should know
about the vagus.
In fact, it's so important
that I feel like this is as
important as people knowing
that walking involves
flexors and extensors.
And if you don't think that's
important, it's as important
as walking, frankly,
because the vagus is the way
in which you can govern
the brain body connection.
And in which you can steer
various aspects of your mood
and wellbeing, but most people
just don't understand how to use it.
So first you got to understand what it is.
So you've got sensory information coming
from all these different organs
of the body up to the brain.
You've got motor information going
from the brain back to the body.
And so you've got this
super highway within you.
Now what actually regulates the vagus.
Oftentimes you'll hear things
like, oh this particular behavior
rubbing your face at a
particular location or breathing
in a particular way, or
a warm bath or something
stimulates the vagus.
Well, right now, I want
everyone to know that,
quote unquote, stimulating
the vagus broadly speaking
is a terrible way to think about the vagus
because do you know what,
if you have a contaminant inside your body
the vagus senses that and
projects that information
to your brain, and you
start to generate a fever
you start to try and kill
that contaminant in your body.
So I don't know that you want
to stimulate the vagus just
as a general theme today,
we're going to get specific
about how you can activate
particular circuits,
certain pathways from
certain organs to the brain
in order to feel better or
relieve certain conditions.
But you certainly don't want
to just stimulate the vagus.
Now excitement about the vagus in part
is because of what quite honestly,
was a fairly pioneering
theory about the vagus
which is his polyvagal theory.
So polyvagal, the word poly means many,
is cool because it acknowledges
that the vagus has a lot
of different branches.
It's not just one thing.
And so I really liked that.
I liked the naming polyvagal.
The idea that Porges has
put forward was that there's
a dorsal vagus, which is
kind of runs in the back
of the spinal cord, which
is involved in alertness
and activation and kind of
fight or flight type stuff.
And that there's a ventral pathway
and that that's involved in
more kind of empathic behaviors.
That is not quite in agreement
with the modern anatomy,
but he was doing the best
with what he had at the time.
So, okay.
The problem I have with
the polyvagal theory
is the way that it's
discussed people often say,
oh if your dorsal vagus is too active
then you tend to be someone
who's a little too keyed
up and people who are kind
of in a state of freeze
or kind of flacid and kind of
like just not really active
and they're just lethargic.
Well, then that pathway is hypoactive.
It should be more active.
So there are a lot
of theories about how
psychology maps onto the vagus.
That as far as I know, don't
map to any real physiology.
Now, the other problem with this kind
of the way that the
polyvagal theory is discussed
probably not by the real
experts, but by a lot of people
is that people start to
diagnose different psychological
and physical manifestations
through the vagus.
They would say things like, Oh
this person is hyper
flexible at the joints
and therefore their dorsal
vagus isn't active enough
or something like that.
And it's really kind of gone
way outside the lane lines.
So today we're gonna
clean up a lot of that.
Let's make it really simple
about how the vagus actually works.
At least as we understand
it today in 2021.
First of all, as I mentioned,
you have sensory information
the same way that you
detect light with your eyes
or you hear sounds with
your ears, you have sensors
in your gut that sense how
full or empty your gut is.
It can also sense how acidic your gut is.
It can sense various
things within your gut.
Your heart is doing the same.
It's informing the brain how
fast your heart is beating,
how full your lungs are
has been communicated
and then the status of your immune system.
So the way to think
about the vagus is the
same way I would think
about the eyes.
The eyes are looking at colors,
they're looking at motion
they're looking how bright it is.
And each one of those things,
those features is telling the
brain something different.
So the brain can decide
when to be awake or asleep
whether or not it's looking
at somebody's attractive or unattractive.
The vagus nerve is also
analyzing many features
within the body and informing the brain
of how to feel about that and what to do.
So a really good example that
I think is an exciting one is
as it relates to sugar.
So we all know that sweet
things generally tastes good.
I'm not particularly a
fan of very sweet things.
You know, I'd much rather have
cheese or pizza or hamburger or steak.
I like savory fatty foods,
but I do like sweet foods.
And most people find sweet
foods to be attractive.
They want them, they might
or they might not be able
to regulate their behavior
around them, but they want them.
And what's really interesting
is that for hundreds of years
people have thought that that's
because of the way that sweet foods taste.
So that makes sense, right?
You eat something that tastes sweet.
You want more of it.
Well, it turns out
that it's much more interesting than that.
When you eat something sweet
within your stomach,
you have cells, neurons,
that sense the presence of sugary foods
independent of their taste
and signal to the brain.
So those sensors, those
neurons send information
up the vagus to your brain
goes through a series of stations.
And then you release dopamine.
This molecule that makes you want more
of whatever it is that you just ingested.
In fact, this pathway is so powerful
that they've done experiments
where they completely numb all the taste
and feeling in somebody's
mouth they're blindfolded.
So they don't know what they're eating
and they're eating a food.
That's either sugary or not sugary.
And what they find is
that even though people
can't taste the sugary food
they crave more of the
food that contains sugar
because of the sensors in
the gut, that sense sugar.
So to put this differently,
you actually have sensors
within your body that make you crave sugar
independent of the sweet
taste of those things.
Now that's incredible.
And what it does, and what it tells us is
that we have circuits in
our body that are driving us
towards certain behaviors
and making us feel good
even though we can't perceive them.
Now, for those of you
that are really interested
in gut intuition and kind of gut feelings
this is a gut feeling except
this is a chemical gut feeling.
This is a particular set of
neurons detecting that something
in your body has a particular feature,
in this case the presence of sugars,
and sending information to the brain
essentially to control your behavior.
And I find this remarkable,
because what it means is
that what we call attractive
isn't always coming from our thoughts
about that or our feelings,
or even our perception.
We are drawn to particular
foods and we're drawn
to perhaps also to
particular people, places
and other things because of information
that's coming from our body.
And we're gonna talk about
what one can do with this information.
I know many people are thoughtful
or concerned about sugars
these days thinking we
all ingest too much sugar.
There's sugar snuck into
all the things we eat.
And indeed, that's true.
I mean, this should completely
reframe the way that we think
about the sort of so-called
hidden sugars in foods.
What this means is that even
if a food is very savory
like a piece of pizza or a piece of bread
or even like a salad dressing
if there's sugar snuck into
that and you can't taste it
you will still crave more of that thing
without knowing that you
crave it because it has sugar.
In other words,
you might find yourself
wanting certain foods
and not knowing why you want those foods.
So I find this to be a fascinating aspect
of our biology and yes, it
relates to mood and emotion.
And we'll talk about
how that is in a moment.
So let's just back up a
bit and ask the question
why do we eat certain things?
And why do certain
foods make us feel good?
And other foods actually
make us feel anxious.
I think some people may
be familiar with this.
Other people might not,
but most people don't realize
that as you approach eating
there's an anxiety associated with that.
It's an alertness.
Remember in the previous discussions,
or even if you don't and
you haven't seen those,
all of your moods and feelings
of wellbeing are anchored
on this continuum of
alertness versus calmness.
And we hear so often
about rest and digest.
You know that, oh, after
we eat, we feel really nice
and full, hopefully comfortably
full and not too full.
And we're relaxing.
And we feel satiated, it's
associated with serotonin
this molecule of satiation.
That's all true.
But what most people don't
know is that there's an area
of the hypothalamus.
So deepen the brain kind of
in the middle deep portion
of the brain called the
lateral hypothalamus.
And the lateral hypothalamus
is really interesting
because it controls feeding,
but it inhibits feeding.
It stops us from feeding.
And there's another area in the brain.
If you want names, I'll give them to you.
If you don't want names, just ignore them,
delete them from your
memory and awareness,
called the locus coeruleus,
now the locus coeruleus sits back further
in the brainstem and it
releases norepinephrine
which is essentially adrenaline.
It makes us feel alert.
Now, locus coeruleus has a
lot of different functions
in the brain, but when we are going to eat
let's say we walk into a
restaurant, we sit down
or we're preparing a meal,
locus coeruleus is known
to release noradrenaline in the brain.
It's creating a kind of alertness.
This has ancient utility, but
it's creating this alertness.
And for many people, they experience
that as they approach
food as stress as anxiety.
But what's interesting is
that as we approach food
locus coeruleus is releasing
all these molecules
that make us feel more anxious and alert
sometimes it's felt as excitement.
And that asks probably to do
with how we feel about food
generally, are we happy with
our relationship with food?
Are we trying to restrict
our relationship to food,
are people coming over for
dinner, all that will play
in of course, but there's a certain stress
and anxiety upon approach to food.
And as we approach food
and we feel that anxiety
locus coeruleus activates
the lateral hypothalamus
in a way that inhibits feeding
that makes us not want to eat.
So a lot of people who have kind
of pre-meal anxiety or anxiety around food
and they can't seem to just calm down
and have a good meal to access
that later rest and digest.
A lot of that is because
of this heightened stress upon
approach to food and a lot
of the tools that are out
there, both for eating disorders
and for just kind of the general
public who isn't suffering
from eating disorders, things
like mindfulness around meals.
You know, they always tell you
you should never eat when stressed.
I'm sorry, but my life is not organized
in a way that I can do that.
I would never eat.
Right because I eat when I'm awake
and I don't know if I'm stressed,
but I don't think I am but I tend to
run around a lot during the day.
I don't generally take time to do two
or three deep breaths before I eat.
I generally will just eat.
That can be healthy
or unhealthy depending on the
quality of your digestion.
I think using digestion
as a guide is good,
but a lot of people aren't
aware that this interaction
between locus coeruleus
and lateral hypothalamus
is a basic mechanism
where we are supposed to
get a little bit alert and
anxious around mealtime.
And then as we eat, the mechanisms
for calming and satiation
are supposed to kick in
and those mechanisms involve
as I mentioned earlier, two things.
One is how things taste,
digestion starts in the mouth.
Of course, we taste our food.
Everyone tells us we
should chew our food more.
Yes, that can improve digestion.
We're not supposed to drink
too many fluids as we eat.
That's true too, but a lot
of how we feel while we eat
and after we eat is because
of this vagus sensing
of what's in our gut.
It's sending information all the time.
Is there sugar?
Are there fats?
Are there contaminants?
There are a lot of information.
These so-called parallel
pathways that are going
up into our brain that regulate whether
or not we want to eat
more of something or not.
And there are accelerators,
things that make us want to
eat more, like sugar and fats
because those are nutrient dense.
And they helps generally,
at least in the short term
support the survival of animals,
but also amino acids.
And this is very important.
There are a lot of data,
but much of what comes from
the data on what people eat
and how much they eat is
from a subconscious detection
of how many amino acids
and what the array,
meaning the constellation of
amino acids is in a given food.
And it's fair to say that the sum total
of these studies pointing
in a direction where
people will basically eat, not
until their stomach is full
but until the brain perceives
that they have adequate
intake of amino acids.
Now, this is a conversation
that comes up in the context of
you know, the meat, only the keto,
the kind of zone diet,
the Mediterranean diet, the vegan diet.
I'm largely going to ignore
the kind of strict camps today.
I will talk a little bit about it,
because I think each one
of them actually taps
into something important about this brain
body relationship that
the other ones don't.
But I don't want to get
into a discussion about
the ethics of different foods
of animal based or non animal based.
'Cause that's not the topic today.
It's really about nutrient
sensing and amino acid sensing.
So we generally will eat
until our gut tells our brain
that we have adequate amounts
of these amino acids.
Amino acids of course are important
because they are the building
blocks of sure, muscle,
and the other things in
our body that need repair.
But what most people don't realize
is that amino acids are
what the neurochemicals
in the brain are made from.
Now, this is vitally important.
Okay, so we've heard
dopamine is this molecule
that makes you feel good.
Actually dopamine is a molecule
It's released within the brain.
And it does feel very good
when you have dopamine release,
dopamine releases caused
by surprise, excitement,
events that you're looking
forward to and they turnout well,
it is inhibited by events
you're looking forward
to that don't work out when someone says
they're going to call that you're really
really excited to talk
to, and then they don't,
or you thought a movie
was gonna be really great
and it's not, or you expect a
meal to be really delicious.
And it's kind of, eh, and we actually
there's a name for that.
It's called reward prediction error.
And you can actually
use this in the context
of meals and plans in a
way that's very useful
with yourself and people you know,
essentially if you expect
something to be really terrific
it really does place a higher expectation
at the chemical level.
So if you don't get as much dopamine
as you're expecting from something,
so you you hear about a
really great restaurant
or a place that has a really, in my case,
I have, I wouldn't call it an addiction.
I would call it more of an
affliction for croissants.
The best vegetable of
course, is the croissant.
And I get really excited
about the fact that someone will tell me,
oh there's this place and they
have incredible croissants.
You gotta go there.
So I get really excited, and I'll go.
And just them telling me
that it's gonna be really terrific
raises an expectation,
a dopamine expectation.
And unless those croissants are amazing
chances are I'm going to experience them
as less good, less satisfying.
I will truly release less
dopamine than I would
had they just said, oh yeah,
I think that there are
croissants down the street.
Or if I just tried one at random,
and that's because of this
reward prediction error
your expectation of
something releases dopamine
and the actual event releases dopamine.
And if the event related dopamine does not
exceed the expectation or
at least match it, there's
a much higher tendency
that you won't pursue that thing again.
So dopamine is really powerful
and it's not just the molecule of reward.
It is the molecule of desire.
It's the molecule of wanting
not just the molecule of having.
And a book, since people often
ask for book recommendations.
I don't know the author
personally, but I love the book.
It's called "The Molecule Of More".
It's a terrific book.
I wish I had written it, frankly,
but if you want to learn more
about dopamine reward prediction error
and how dopamine regulates
various aspects of your emotional
and motivational life,
it's a terrific read.
Dopamine is what's going to
lead us to want to eat more
of something or to not
want more of something,
because dopamine really is about craving.
It's about motivation
and it's about desire.
And as I mentioned,
these amino acid sensors
in our gut are detecting
how many amino acids
but they're also detecting
which amino acids.
And there's a particular
amino acid called L-tyrosine
which comes from food.
You can look up online, which
foods contain L-tyrosine.
It is in meats.
It is in nuts.
It is also in some plant-based foods.
L-tyrosine is the precursor
to a couple other molecules
like L-DOPA, et cetera,
that make dopamine.
And so there's a misconception
out there that most
of the serotonin is in our gut.
And most of the dopamine is in our gut.
And therefore our mood is in our gut.
That's not quite the way it works.
Okay. we'll talk about
serotonin in a moment
but dopamine is synthesized
from the amino acids that you eat.
However, the dopamine
neurons that give rise
to these feelings of good or wanting more
or desire and motivation,
those reside in the brain.
So we don't want to get too confused.
We want to respect and honor the power
of the gut and this vagal
pathway, but it's really neurons
within your brain that drive the pursuit
and decision-making,
so what does this mean?
Well, some people make
too little dopamine.
Some people make so
little dopamine that they
need prescription dopamine.
They need L-DOPA, people
with Parkinson's take L-DOPA
and other compounds to increase dopamine
because Parkinson's is associated
with deficits in movement,
starts as a tremor,
actually starts with some other
things that are interesting.
We'll talk about in a moment,
but Parkinson's is a depression.
It's a blunting of motivation
and mood and effect, and it's a tremor.
And then eventually in severe conditions
it's challenges in speaking and walking so
that some famous examples
would be Muhammad Ali,
Michael J. Fox, the great
boxing trainer, Freddie Roach,
like these people have
Parkinson's and they
at least later in their life
had challenges speaking.
Now it's not just fighters
that develop Parkinson's as far
as I know, Michael J.
Fox wasn't a fighter.
People can develop Parkinson's
and Parkinson's is a depletion
of dopamine neurons in the brain.
And it's not just movement challenges.
It's challenges with mood.
Now, hopefully most of you
all of you don't have Parkinson's,
but it's clear that dietary L-tyrosine
supports the healthy production
of things like dopamine
and as well as other
factors within the brain.
Now, some people immediately ask,
well should I supplement L-tyrosine?
So let's just talk about that
because that's gonna come up.
Full disclosure, I
sometimes take L-tyrosine.
I'm not taking it right now,
but I take it only occasionally,
you can buy this in capsule form.
It does increase kind of a mood
and elevation and alertness.
It is over the counter.
You have to check with your doctor.
I'm not responsible for your healthcare
and I'm not a doctor, whether
or not it's safe for you,
people with preexisting
hyper dopaminergic conditions
like mania should probably
not take L-tyrosine.
The other thing
about taking L-tyrosine
is there is a crash, okay?
It's not a massive crash if you take it
at appropriate doses
and it's right for you
but it can produce a crash and a lethargy
and a kind of brain fog
after the next day or so.
And so L-tyrosine however
can be ingested through foods
or through supplementation
to increase dopamine levels.
That's well-known, taken
chronically however,
it can disrupt those dopamine pathways.
Now there are other drugs
that will increase L-tyrosine
and dopamine as well.
But those are severe enough
that they generally tend to
have addictive properties.
So things like methamphetamine,
things like cocaine are terrible
because they really ramp
up the dopamine system so much
that people really can't
achieve dopamine release
through any other mechanisms.
But food and the ingestion
of L-tyrosine has a profound effect
on our levels of dopamine.
It takes a little while
but that really will impact level of mood.
Certain antidepressants fall
into the category of
dopaminergic antidepressants.
One of the most famous ones
of course is Wellbutrin.
Wellbutrin with developed
because a lot of the other antidepressants
tend to make people feel kind of lethargic
or they had side effect profiles
that people didn't like.
So they developed this thing that,
the generic name is different,
but it's generally called Wellbutrin.
Wellbutrin activates dopamine
and epinephrin, which is
a substrate of dopamine.
And both of those are involved
in motivation and alertness and effort.
So you might say, wow, this
sounds like a great drug.
However, this drug,
the side effect profile
tends to be the things
that are associated with
elevated mood and alertness.
So this isn't like taking some L-tyrosine.
This isn't like eating
some tyrosine rich foods.
This is really a much greater release
of dopamine and epinephrin,
and it increases things
like anxiety, sweating, the pupils dilate.
It has certain effects
on, in particular people
with epilepsy, it's been
used somewhat successfully
for smoking cessation, but
again, it's not for everybody
and I'm not here to encourage
the use of these things.
I'm just describing the biology
and the rationale for why
these drugs were developed.
So let's back up a second.
Let's just kind of take
stock of where we're at.
We have a brain body connection.
There are many of them, but one
of the main ones is the vagus nerve.
The vagus collects information
about a lot of things,
breathing, heart rate stuff
that's happening in the gut, et cetera,
and gut by the way, includes
the stomach and the intestines,
sends that information up to the brain.
The brain is using that information
to decide one of two things,
move toward something or move away.
It can also pause,
but essentially pausing
is not moving toward.
So that's the dopamine
pathway and foods rich
in L-tyrosine generally
give us an elevated mood
and make us want to do more
of whatever it is that we
happen to be doing as well
as other things, motivation, generalizes
to other things it's not
unique to just ingesting foods
but foods that give us a big pulse
of dopamine will make us
crave more of that food.
It will make us crave more
of the activity that led to
the ingestion of that food.
And as I mentioned earlier,
a lot of that is happening
at a subconscious level that
you're not even aware of.
And this is why I think the
concern about hidden sugars
and over ingestion of sugars
is serious because it's not just
that the sugars are impacting
our blood glucose in negative ways.
Although often it is,
it's not just the obesity
crisis that's happening.
It's also the fact
that it's disrupting our dopamine systems.
Now that doesn't mean all sugar is bad.
Some people have a quite
healthy relationship to sugar
but I think most people are just not aware
that sugar isn't just
operating at the level
of taste it's operating at the level
of neurochemicals and it's
doing it subconsciously.
So I'd like to talk about
some of the other pathways
between brain and body that
regulate our moods and emotions
but also are actionable.
So the other neuromodulator
that's really interesting
in the context of the vagus is serotonin.
Serotonin, just to remind
you is a neuromodulator
therefore it creates a bias
in which neural circuits
which neurons in the brain and
body are going to be active
and it makes it less likely the other ones
are going to be active.
I think it's fair to say
without ever having measured it
that my bulldog Costello, just his brain
and body must be swimming in serotonin,
because he's very calm and he eats a lot
but he generally feels pretty sated.
He's kind of an animal that's
obsessed with comforts.
He's a bit of a hedonist, and
serotonin when it's elevated
tends to make us feel really comfortable
and kind of blissed out wherever we are.
And that contrast with
dopamine and epinephrin
which mainly put us in pursuit of things.
Motivation is pursuit.
Serotonin is more about
feeling really comfy
where we are.
The conversation around the
brain body relationship and mood
and serotonin for many years
was, well, you eat a big meal.
The gut is distended.
You've got all the nutrients you need
you rest and digest and
serotonin is released.
That's sorta true, but
there's a lot more going
on and a lot more that's interesting
and actionable that's going on.
First of all, some of you,
but perhaps not all have heard that more
than 90% of the serotonin
that we make is in our gut.
And indeed we have a lot
of serotonin in our gut.
We have neurons in our
gut that makes serotonin.
brain that make serotonin,
but here's the deal.
Most of the serotonin
that impacts our mood
and our mental state is not in our gut.
Most of it is in the neurons of the brain
in an area called the
raphae nucleus of the brain,
there are a few other locations too,
and those are the neurons that control
whether or not we feel satiated or not.
Whether or not we feel happy and calm.
You can't have a
discussion about serotonin
without having discussion
about antidepressants.
Because during the late
eighties and early nineties
there was this explosion
in the number of prescription
drugs that were released.
Things like first one and most
famous one is Prozac, Zoloft
and Paxil, a number of other
ones that are so-called SSRI
selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors.
That's a long acronym, but
basically those drugs work
by preventing the gobbling
up of serotonin or re-uptake
of serotonin into neurons
after it's been released
which leads to more serotonin overall
which means to elevate serotonin.
And indeed those drugs
were and can be very useful
for certain people to feel better in cases
of depression and some other
clinical disorders as well.
So I really don't want to dismiss them
as useless or dangerous for everybody.
They can be quite useful for many people.
Not everyone responds well to them
as I'm sure you've all heard.
And their side effect profile has affects
like blunting affect.
It can make people feel kind of flat,
kinda meh, it can reduce
appetite for food.
It can reduce appetite for sex.
It can do all sorts of things,
or it can work really well.
Sometimes it's a dose-related
issue, et cetera.
Serotonin is fascinating however,
because how well those neurons
in the raphe work is impacted
by some events within the gut.
Although you might be surprised to find
out what those events are.
So let's go a little
bit deeper into the gut.
And again, the gut includes the stomach
and then the small intestine
in the large intestine
and ask like, what is going
on with serotonin in the gut?
How is it impacting
serotonin in the brain?
And let's think about this in the context
of how some of us might want to increase
or decrease our serotonin levels.
So as far as I know, there
aren't any really good
at home blood tests for things
like serotonin and dopamine.
There's some commercial
products out there.
But to me, just to me, I'm
not particularly impressed.
You know, it's not the same
as getting your hormones levels measured
or your metabolic factors
measured, that's can be daunting.
It can be done rigorously.
There are tests out there.
There are even some, believe it or not.
There's some questionnaires that,
and I think actually
last year it made some
of the bigger newspapers,
are you more of a dopamine or a serotonin?
Are you a this or that?
I find that stuff to be a little silly
although I do appreciate,
and like the fact
that people are thinking about and talking
about neuromodulators there aren't really
great ways to measure these
things outside the clinic.
There's some great clinical
tools that you can get inside
of a hospital or from a
proper endocrinologist
or neurologist, but no great at-home tool.
So maybe that's a call to arms
for some of you entrepreneurial folks
out there to create these
tests, accurate tests please,
that could be done at home.
But some people feel
like they're too anxious
or they're always in a motivated state
and they're trying to
adjust their serotonin.
Many people adjust their
serotonin by just eating more food
and carbohydrate rich foods
will increase serotonin.
I've talked about this
on a previous podcast
but I personally am a big fan
at least for me is I usually fast
and exercise in the early part of the day
I eat a relatively high protein
and moderate fat zero carb
or low carb meal at lunch in
the afternoon to stay alert
because those foods tend to
favor dopamine production
acetylcholine production,
epinephrin production and alertness.
My mood is generally pretty
good most of the time.
And then as evening comes
around and I'm concerned
about sleep and a good
night's sleep, not concerned
in an anxious way, but I want
to get a good night's sleep.
I will ingest foods that
promote serotonin release
because they contain a lot of tryptophan.
So if I do eat meat,
it would be like a
white meat, turkey meat.
I don't tend to, I've never liked turkey.
I don't mind the animal
but I don't like ingesting the meat,
but starchy carbohydrates
will increase serotonin.
Some people also will take serotonin.
You can now buy 5-HTP supplements.
This is a little bit tricky.
5-HTP supplements can of
course increase 5-HTP.
It is 5-HTP or serotonin
but that sometimes can create problems
in endogenous or self-made
production of serotonin.
So I'm never a fan
of taking things very
close to the chemical
you're trying to increase for
very long periods of time.
Maybe for occasional use.
I have the problem that
if I take serotonin supplements,
5-HTP, I fall asleep.
The sleep I have is very intense
and I wake up three or four hours later.
And we know based on sleep
studies with good measurements
in the lab that serotonin
release tends to be
in the later part of the night.
And so by taking it early in the night
it really can disrupt the pattern
of sleep in the depth of sleep.
Nonetheless, some people are interested
in taking serotonin to get some
of the more blissed out effects.
You can achieve that with foods.
As I mentioned, that
are carbohydrate rich.
So as you're seeing this
isn't really a discussion
about nutrition per se.
This is discussion about food
which contains amino acids, amino acids
being the precursors to
neuromodulators and neuromodulators
having a profound effect
on your overall state
of alertness or calmness,
happiness, sadness, and wellbeing.
So there are a number of
things that one can take.
As I mentioned, one of
them being 5-HTP itself.
Now I'm not recommending
people take anything,
but if you're interested
in what this does and
you want to explore this
of course you'd want
permission from your doctor.
You can go to this free website.
I love this resource.
They don't pay me to say that,
but I just love this resource.
I've followed it for a long
time called examine.com.
Thank you folks at examine.com
for putting this free resource
out on the web that has links
through what they call
the human effect matrix.
So it's links
to all the PubMed studies
for particular effects
of particular compounds that one combined
and just incredible as well
as important health warnings.
So I'm not gonna read through everything
but if you were to go to
examine.com as I have now
and you put in 5-HTP
they're only looking at things
that have strong evidence.
PubMed articles,
articles that are in the PubMed archive.
So for instance, I didn't know this,
but 5-HTP produces a notable
decrease in appetite,
three studies.
And this appetite suppression
makes sense, of course,
because we ingest foods to get serotonin.
And if we have enough serotonin
then there's no reason
to ingest more foods.
It tends to have a blunting of appetite.
It probably does that also
through other mechanisms.
So I'm not saying you should do this
but if someone's trying to blunt
their appetite could
be a interesting route,
although I don't recommend chronic use,
not surprisingly there's
a decrease in body weight
as a consequence, an increase in cortisol.
So that's kind of important to note
that when you typically
in biology, if you pull
on one string really
hard and other one moves
it's a little bit like a puppet in there.
It's more than one string on the puppet.
So it does seem to
increase cortisol though
they report as a minor effect.
Again, links to all those are there
which is why I'm not listing
them out in our caption notes.
You can go and get them at examine.com,
put in serotonin and you'll find that.
So I find it fascinating
that nowadays there are
things that are somewhere
between doing nothing, getting serotonin
from tryptophan and foods
and prescription drugs.
There's this other category
of supplements that are really interesting
for modulating these
chemicals in the body.
And I should mention before I move on,
because I mentioned L-tyrosine
I neglected to mention earlier
in our discussion about
dopamine, if you're interested
in the dopamine pathway,
go to examine.com,
put in Mucuna pruriens, it's M-U-C-U-N-A,
separate word, P-R-U-R-I-E-N S.
It is a velvet bean that grows from vines
and is very itchy to touch due
to serotonin on its surface.
Amazing, this bean has
serotonin on its surface
and indeed serotonin at
if you were to put it
on your skin would cause
some irritation of the skin, amazing.
Inside the bean is L-DOPA,
Mucuna pruriens is not
just something that
promotes dopamine release
because of some weird mystical
ancient thing or whatever, or sorcery.
It is chemically L-DOPA
the precursor to dopamine.
It contains some other molecules as well
and low levels of other psychoactives.
This stuff is available over the counter.
Incredible. I personally
find it incredible.
Its effects are really interesting.
I'm not gonna read them all off
but I mentioned these effects
not because I'm encouraging you to take it
but because you get a window
into what dopamine, acute
dopamine increase does
in the non-Parkinsonian context.
And you can start to think
about foods that are rich
in L-tyrosine as biasing
certain effects or not others.
So when you hear food is medicine,
food isn't really medicine.
Food is food, but food has
these chemical effects as well.
So first one listed is three studies
with very high rigor that
overall have a minor effect
on of all things, sperm quality.
So it appears that sperm motility itself,
I'm assuming when they say sperm quality
I don't know what features
of sperm of quality
they looked at with sperm,
that's not discussion I want to have,
but I'm assuming it's motility
because I know enough
about reproductive biology
to know that sperm ability to swim depends
on some proteins that are present
in the front of the sperm, et cetera
things like contractions
and sperm motility
is generally associated
with sperm quality.
Sperm that don't move are
generally not very useful sperm.
Symptoms of Parkinson disease are
are notably degraded with Mucuna pruriens.
So fascinating. That's not surprising.
And there are a lot of other effects here.
Feelings of subjective wellbeing,
testosterone, reductions in
prolactin, not surprising.
Prolactin is a hormone that's involved
in milk letdown, it's
in lactating mothers.
It's involved in feelings
of peace and generally
is antagonistic to sexual
desire in both men and female.
So it's really interesting that
things like Mucuna pruriens
which are L-DOPA reduce prolactin,
increased sperm motility,
increased testosterone,
subjective wellbeing.
So you're starting to see a theme, right?
Dopamine really makes us motivated.
Feel in pursuit, makes us feel good.
Serotonin makes us feel
more relaxed and calm.
Now this whole month is about emotion.
So you might be thinking, well, wait
where are we going with all
this as it relates to emotions.
But in the last episode I said something
I'm gonna repeat it now
briefly, which is that much
of what we talk about is good
emotions or bad emotions.
There's a context to that.
There's a social context.
We can't really say an
emotion is good or bad.
Grieving at a funeral is healthy.
Being happy at a funeral,
assuming you loved the person that died
is most people probably
wouldn't think that was healthy.
So we can't really say that certain
emotions like sadness or
happiness are healthy.
It's context is important.
Cultural context is important.
Many of you have asked
for book recommendations.
This is an opportunity to raise
a mention of another book.
Again, I don't have any
financial affiliation or anything
but if you want to read
more about emotions
and how the context and cultural
things impact our emotions
I'm a huge fan of Lisa Feldman Barrett.
I learned about her from
the Lex Fridman Podcast.
I've had discussions with
her on my Instagram Live,
she's at Northeastern University,
a world expert in emotions.
Her first book is "How Emotions Are Made"
This is not a book she sent me.
I paid for this with
my own money years ago,
bought it, read it, loved
it long before I met Lisa,
I'm just delighted
that we've got to known
each other a little bit.
It's a really interesting
read into the psychology
of emotions and some of the
subjectivity of emotions.
So, whereas I'm talking about
mainly the biology of emotions
this gets a little bit
more into the psychology
and the biology as well.
And Lisa's just terrific.
She's also putting a lot
of information out into
the world about emotion.
So if you want to learn more about that
check out her work, again,
it's Lisa Feldman Barrett.
And that book is "How Emotions Are Made"
Hopefully she'll continue
to write many more books.
So now you understand the relationship
I hope between foods and
dopamine, foods and serotonin
and that they're both being communicated
to the brain via the vagus, right?
We ingest these foods,
these supplements are things people take,
they don't put them
directly into the brain.
They put them in our gut.
So yes, there's a gut brain connection
but it's not about the serotonin
in the gut that makes
you feel calm and placid.
It's not about the dopamine in the gut.
It's just been oversold that way
because I think there's
something really attractive.
And I understand about the idea
that because certain
things about our experience
of life and our emotions
is happening in our body.
That maybe we have a
little more control, right?
Because this thing is a hard container.
We can't just stuff
some dopamine in there.
I could probably take
a Mucuna pruriens bean
and stuff it in my ear,
please don't do that.
It'd make my ear itchy
because of the serotonin on the outside.
But you can't get stuff in there.
What you have to do is ingest
things that are metabolized
in certain ways that
communicate to the brain
or so maybe they pass
into the brain themselves
across what's called
the blood brain barrier.
I'll talk about the blood
brain barrier in a minute.
It's actually called the BBB.
So it ends up sounding like baby, BBB.
I guess that's like BB, anyway,
BBB, but they're also nerves
in the gut that are sensing
the nutrient contents of food
and then saying, oh, you should
feel better and want more.
Oh, that's got a lot of
bitterness and acid taste to it.
You should want less of that.
So as I transitioned out
of the discussion about dopamine
and serotonin in the gut
hopefully you've got some
actionable items there
under your belt, pun intended,
where you can understand how certain foods
and certain nutrients
and you can look these up,
might impact your mood.
If you're somebody who's really
anxious and really wired.
Well, then the dopamine adrenaline pathway
epinephrine pathway is
probably not one that you
want to lean on any harder.
If you tend to be someone
who's pretty passive
and you're having trouble with motivation.
Well then think about ramping
up the dopamine pathway through,
I always think behaviors
and proper food choices
is the best way to start.
And behaviors include things
like exercise, et cetera.
But one of the problems
with the discussion
around mood and exercise
or mood and meditation is
that it's so subjective.
It's like, I love certain forms
of exercise and not others.
Certain ones are aversive to me.
Certain ones are attractive to me,
and it's never really clear.
No one's ever told me.
Okay, you have to do 10 minutes
on the bike at X number
of RPM at so-and-so
or on the skier in order
to get your dopamine up.
But we can actually say, if
you ingest more L-tyrosine
there's a high probability
that you're going
to make more dopamine.
And I'm talking about ingesting it
through food or through
supplementation if you like.
Mucuna pruriens, I've tried.
I should just mention it
was too dopaminergic for me.
I got really, really jazzed up
and then a severe crash
for me the next day.
But that's, I think because
I tend to ride pretty high
on the kind of alertness
and motivation scale.
I'm always being told by
Costello and other people
in the podcast studio
to slow my speech down.
This is me uncaffeinated,
and I could probably
afford a little more serotonin in my life.
So, whereas Costello,
he can afford to wake
up every couple of days
and just say hello to us.
This dog sleeps more
than any other creature.
It's remarkable.
So there are things that we
can do and they're actionable.
And they are in some
ways they're quantitative
because you can regulate dosages
and you can regulate amounts
and you can regulate timing.
And everyone has to play with these things
and figure out what's right
for them in terms of feeding.
And everyone has to explore
and understand what's
safe and right for them.
But, and of course, exercise
is still very important.
I talked about social
connection in the last episode
super important for
activation of serotonin
but when it comes to this gut brain,
body brain relationship,
what we eat really matters
in terms of the
neurochemicals that we make.
So let's talk a little bit more
about things that we ingest
in our body and then allow
our body to inform our brain
to shift our mood.
And this is something
I've been doing for years.
And I just want to say
I've found to be a complete game changer.
There's excellent science to support it.
And I think most people are familiar
with it in a different context
but I don't think most
people know this simple fact
which is that the omega-3
to omega-6 fatty acid ratio
has a profound effect on depression.
It has a profound effect
on mood so much so
that in a double-blind
placebo controlled study
that I will provide the link too,
this was a study first published in 2008
but there've been many others as well.
First of all, an
experiment done in animals.
They found there's a model
of learned helplessness in animals.
It's not very kind to the animals,
but they put rats or mice in a jar.
They let them swim and they'll swim, swim,
swim to try and save their life.
And eventually they give up,
it's a learned helplessness.
They don't let them
drown, they take them out.
Adjusting the omega-3 omega-6 ratio so
that the omega-3's are higher led to less
learned helplessness,
meaning these animals
would swim longer.
Now that's an animal.
That's a rat, not a
particularly kind study,
but that same study was
essentially done in humans
although they didn't have
them swim to the point
of near drowning.
What they did is they took
people who were clinically
depressed, major depression.
Major depression is
severe maladaptive state
meaning it inhibits job,
relationships, appetite,
all sorts of negative health effects.
And they did a comparison of
a thousand milligrams a day of EPA.
So EPA is one of the elements
that contains high levels
of omega-3's that's in
things like fish oil,
I'll talk about other
sources in a little bit
but it wasn't a thousand
milligrams of fish oil.
It was a thousand milligrams of EPA.
Compared that to 20
milligrams of Fluoxetine
which is Prozac, okay.
Really increases serotonin.
And in this study of
60 individuals, again,
I'll provide the links to the study.
They found that they
were equally effective
in reducing depressive symptoms.
So imagine that,
a food-based compound that
you can't make without,
right, this is not a situation
where you can make your own omega-3s.
You have to get them from food sources
or from supplementation, was
as effective as 20 milligrams
of fluoxetine over the
course of eight weeks.
And what was really
interesting in addition
to that is that the combination
of a thousand milligrams
of EPA and Fluoxetine
had a synergistic effect
in lowering depressive symptoms.
I find this remarkable.
I heard about this when it first came
out and I wasn't sure what to make of it.
'Cause there are a lot
of studies that come out
and I generally like to
focus my changes in behavior
around things where there's
a large center of mass.
There's a lot of information.
A couple years later, I did in fact
start taking a thousand milligrams
per day of EPA in fish oil.
Now there are a few side
effects of fish oil.
People who have blood, who are bleeders
who have Factor V Leiden mutations
or in women who are taking birth control,
which can affect blood clotting and things
of that sort really
should talk to your doctor
make sure it's okay for you.
Fish oil also can give people fishy breath
which is pretty gross, frankly,
but there are now fish oils that
either because of the
Encapsulations or because
they put some lemon flavoring in there
doesn't have that effect.
In any event, a thousand
milligrams per day of EPA.
I started ingesting that regularly.
I just felt better.
I wasn't clinically
depressed, but I generally,
I did feel at least for me, an
increase in mood and affect.
And a number of other things
it's supposed to reduce inflammation.
The cardiovascular
effects are controversial
for a long time everyone
thought the effects
on platelets were really terrific.
Then there were articles that came
out in major newspapers
saying maybe not so much
but the effects on mood
are really profound.
And now there are lots of studies.
If you go into PubMed
and you were to put EPA
or fish oil and depression
you would find that there were a number
of really impressive results showing
that it's at least as effective
as certain SSRI antidepressants
at these dosages
and it can amplify or improve the effect
of low dosages of some of these SSRIs.
So I feel like more people
should know about this.
This is nutrition, but it's
profoundly affecting mood
and depression is terrible, right?
Depression can have a component
of anxiety in some cases where people are
they feel lousy and very uncertain.
That's kind of how I talk
about depression with anxiety
is you talk to someone who is anxious
and you can tell them
everything's gonna be okay.
And they're always concerned
about what they might not know.
You don't really know the
plane isn't gonna crash.
You don't really know that
life is gonna go okay.
And in some sense, they're right,
no one has a crystal ball
or can predict the future,
but they tend to perseverate
or fixate on the uncertainty.
And then of course there are the versions
of depression that involve certainty.
People are lethargic and
they're certain they say, yeah,
I'm certain, I'm never
gonna get another job.
gonna meet anyone new.
I'm certain I'm gonna fail.
So there's this kind of
a divide in the sphere
of depression around
certainty and uncertainty.
But what's interesting is this
thousand milligrams per day
or more of EPA has been shown
to relieve both forms of depression.
Now, does that mean it's
gonna work for everybody?
No, I'm not here to try
and play psychiatrist.
I want to point you in the
direction of these manuscripts
so that you can make informed
choices for yourself.
You can discuss it with your doctor
and family and make the
choices that are right for you.
But here's what's especially interesting
about the heart effects,
because we've heard that these omega-3s,
which of course you can
get from other sources too,
you can get from fatty fish,
they're in flax seeds, hemp seeds.
There are a number of chia
seeds, these kinds of things
but the levels of EPA that
are required are quite high.
So this thousand milligrams
per day is that's pretty
hard to get from food
although it can be done depending
on what you're eating.
What's interesting is that the
heart effects that are solid
that really stand up in the literature
have a lot more to do
with something we talked
about in a previous episode.
And I'll mention again, which
is heart rate variability.
So we know that having a
heart rate that's really high
or heart rate, that's really low.
Neither of those are good.
A lot of people think, oh
you just want a low heart
rate, big stroke volume.
You know, if you're running a lot
you may have 30 or 40 beats per minute.
That's great to be in shape
but you still want heart rate variability.
It has a lot to do with the tone
of the autonomic nervous
system talked about last time.
How, when you inhale,
it speeds up heart rate.
When you exhale, it decreases heart rate.
That's called respiratory
sinus arrhythmia.
That's the basis of
heart rate variability.
We'll maybe do a short post about this.
So you can get all the mechanism
and the behaviors that spill
out of that that might be useful for you.
But the point is heart rate variability.
HRV is good.
And what's interesting
is that there was a study
in 2009 that showed that people
who eat a diet where they
fail to supplement in a way that there's
a high omega-6 to three ratio,
so not enough omega-3s,
not only are there markers
of an inflammatory cytokines,
elevated things like IL-6
and TNF-alpha,
but they tend to be
non-responders to antidepressants.
Shifting that omega-3 omega-6
ratio did a couple things.
First of all, increasing the amount
of EPA shifted the ratio.
So it was higher omega-3 to
omega-6 ratio, which was good,
lowered the inflammation markers,
and then allowed antidepressants
to have their effect,
even at low doses.
And here's the really interesting thing.
It worked by increasing
heart rate variability,
and you think, well, how in
the world would this happen?
But you know how I mean,
that's a ton of effects
but the way it works is because
of the way that these things
are impacting the gut and
the autonomic nervous system.
Remember earlier, I said, the
vagus includes connections
from the heart signaling
about sensory information
about how fast the heart
is beating to the brain
not just stuff on the lungs,
but information from the heart
and the brain then adjusts heart rate
by heart rate variability.
So it's incredible that
there's a way that one
can use the gut, the ingestion
of more of these EPA's,
either through food or supplementation
to increase rate variability
and thereby to improve symptoms,
meaning reduce symptoms of depression,
and to even make low
levels of antidepressants
that wouldn't otherwise work work.
And I think I like this study so much
because a, it's super cool.
It bridges the brain body access.
It incorporates nutrition and
micronutrients in the brain
but also because it
really points to something
that we hear all the time,
which is our body is a whole system.
It's working as a whole system
and the brain isn't working
in isolation up there in the skull.
It's reacting to things that
are happening in the body
in the gut and in the heart
rate and heart rate variability.
And that the things we ingest can have
a profound effect on them.
Now, of course, I really
want to emphasize something
which is that no one compound or nutrient
or supplement or drug or
behavior for that matter
is going to be the be all end all
of shifting out of depression
or improving one's mood
or improving sleep.
It's a constellation of things.
And this is especially true
when people start to get excited
about supplements and drugs
of all kinds and their
potential for various things.
Right now, there's a lot of
excitement about psychedelics
and their therapeutic uses.
And I think great, but
as a good friend of mine
who's a physician clinician says
better living through chemistry
still requires better living.
You cannot expect to take a compound
regardless of source or potency
and have it completely shift
your experience of life
without having to continue to engage
in the proper behaviors,
all the things we know
proper sleep, exercise, social
connection, food, et cetera.
There are many others as well.
So I still find that this collection
of studies about omega-3 to omega-6 ratios
to be profoundly important so
much so that it's completely
changed the way that I think about food,
the foods I eat, I do supplement.
I don't necessarily that
think that's for everybody
but I really think it's incredible
that there are these compounds
that have these robust effects
on our feelings of wellbeing.
And there are others too.
So that thousand milligram per day
threshold of fish oil that's beneficial
requires that one take a reasonable amount
of these things, either through food
or through supplementation.
I acknowledge that not everyone
wants to take fish oil.
There are a couple of reasons
why one might want to avoid that.
One would be for ethical reasons.
You have an emotional
relationship or a relationship
to the environment that makes you not want
to ingest fish related products.
There's krill oil.
Krill is still an organism.
It's a little tiny thing
that whales eat a lot
of and people generally
eat very little of.
So krill is out there,
I personally, just me,
I don't know why, I didn't
react well to krill.
It didn't make me feel very good.
I had some like kind of skin
itches and things like that.
And they stopped when I stopped taking it
but I don't want to bias you against it.
If that's your preference.
Some people really like krill oil
as a source of omega-3s.
I did mention some of the other sources
like chia seeds and flax
seeds, but as you'll notice
these are not things that
we tend to ingest a lot
of on a regular basis.
It is possible to get omega-3s from meats.
If the animals have grazed
on grasses that contain a lot of omega-3s.
So for those of you that ingest meat
you're the source of those meat is gonna
be very important as
it relates to omega-3s.
Even within the category of fish oil
there's a concern sometimes
about mercury and other contaminants.
You want to go with a
brand that emphasizes
that they've gone to really good sources
and that they decontaminate regardless.
And so you have to
search out those brands.
There is a test that you can do as
to whether or not the fish
oil is a rancid or not.
Some people take it in liquid form.
Some people take in capsule form.
The liquid form is gonna
be more affordable.
The capsule form is more
is a little easier and
a little more portable.
You can actually just chew
one of the gel tablets.
And if it tastes really
fishy kind of rancid,
you'll know it's disgusting.
You want to spit it out.
And if it doesn't and it's tolerable
then you'll know that that it's okay.
Unfortunately you have to buy
it first in order to do that.
Although, I don't know, maybe
you can get them to open
up the bottle for you in the store
and tell them you want to try it.
Someday perhaps fish oil and omega-3,
it'll be like tasting wine
at a restaurant where you
can send it back for now.
I think you have to purchase it first,
but find a brand you trust in
like, and then work with them.
If you decide to go that route of course.
There are other compounds
that are also interesting
for mood elevation that
are essentially like foods
or are supplement based
that now, fortunately,
there are really good data
from peer reviewed studies.
And the next one I want to mention
because I think it's really
interesting is L-carnitine.
Now, L-carnitine has
been around a long time
and it's been discussed in the context
of heart health and a
number of other things.
It was actually being touted
as a bit of a weight loss agent
in the early nineties,
but L-carnitine actually
has some really impressive
effects on depression.
And again, we will look to PubMed
because looking at examine.com
is essentially for me anyway
looking at PubMed, what
is L-carnitine okay.
L-carnitine is most prevalent in meat
and in beef in particular.
Now for the vegans, please
know that L-carnitine
is available through
non-meat sources as well.
Although it's not as
enriched in non-meat sources.
It's a really interesting
molecule because acetylcarnitine
is essentially what's
made from L-carnitine
but it's acetylated.
If you're interested in the biochemistry,
you can look that up,
it's acetylated into a form that can cross
the blood-brain barrier.
The blood-brain barrier
or BBB is a barrier.
It's a wall around the brain
and you have this barrier
because the brain is so important.
And it has this feature
that the neurons there
don't recreate themselves after injury,
like other organs of the body.
There's not a lot of
turnover of cells despite
what you might've heard.
And so nature has created this BBB,
this blood brain barrier to
make sure that certain molecules
in particular, large
molecules don't get across
the blood-brain barrier.
'Cause it can be damaging
to those tissues.
Incidentally,
you also have a very
rigid or stringent barrier
around other organs, which are the gonads.
So the ovaries and the testes
and the brain are the organs
of the body that nature has gone out
of its way to protect,
give this additional layer
of the blood-brain barrier
or as you might imagine for the testes
and the ovaries, it's going to be
the blood gonadal barrier.
So these barriers exist
to make it such that just
because you eat something,
just because you ingest
it doesn't mean it's going
to cross the blood-brain barrier,
but L-carnitine when taken is
acetylated and converted into this form
that gets across the blood-brain barrier.
And it has a lot of effects, it's involved
in mitochondrial activation
of long chain fatty acids
which that's a big mouthful,
that we'll get into some time when
we're talking about metabolic,
but it has some interesting
effects on the neuro side.
So if you decide to check
it out on examine.com
you'll see some really interesting things,
lots of effects on ammonia,
C-reactive proteins,
things of that sort, blood
glucose is lowered, et cetera.
That's all stuff that's the
level of blood and periphery,
slight effects in lowering cholesterol.
Here's some interesting ones.
Rates of pregnancy go way up when people
are taking L-carnitine both
the father and the mother
but the source of sperm and
the source of egg are affected
in ways that favors pregnancy.
It does increase,
here we go again with sperm
quality sperm motility
in males and it seems
to have positive effects
on females that have
polycystic ovary syndrome.
So check that out.
You know, the effects are very strong.
There are three studies listed there.
Again, I'm not promoting this,
but that that people take L-carnitine,
especially if you're
trying to get pregnant
but check it out because the effects there
and the studies that are
mentioned are published
in peer reviewed rigorous journals.
In terms of the neural effects.
Those are quite interesting.
The effects on depression
are still emerging
but they do seem to exist
that people feel a notable
decrease in depressive symptoms.
There are seven studies
listed on examine.com
that it has a notable benefit
in a variety of circumstances
where participants
have heightened depression already.
They start taking L-carnitine
and they start feeling better.
And they talk about dosages
in those various studies.
It also has been shown to
have a notable decrease
in the symptoms of autism,
which I find fascinating.
Also again, the things we ingest impact
the chemicals in our brain
and how they impact the rest of our body.
There's other things that's
been used to treat certain forms
of alcohol dependence.
I think this is going to be a
very exciting emerging area.
We're gonna do a whole
month about addiction.
I've got a great guest
lined up for that month,
but there's now an emerging
field about what people can take
and supplement to help ease the cravings
and the withdrawal when
trying to quit drugs of abuse,
like cocaine, alcohol, heroin, and smoking
and things of that sort.
So really interesting area.
This is, I like to think is the early days
and we're gonna discover a lot more.
There's a huge list of things here.
Since we talked about
pain on a previous episode
and I know a lot
of people have written
to me about fibromyalgia.
It does L carnitine has been shown
to reduce symptoms of fibromyalgia.
Again, all the links to
studies are on examine.com,
totally free site.
And that was my bulldog
being a battering ram.
There's nothing graceful
about this bulldog.
He's decided he wanted to leave
to go get a drink of water.
And so please forgive the noise.
Okay.
So now let's turn to another aspect
of the gut-brain relationship
that will surprise you,
in some cases might shock you.
And that has some really
cool and actionable biology.
And that's the gut microbiome,
probiotics and prebiotics.
I know today we're talking
about emotions and not pain
but I'd be remiss if I
didn't mention another effect
of acetylcarnitine that's been reported
and that you can find listed with link
to study on examine.com
which is its effect in reducing
the symptoms of migraine.
This was a randomized controlled trial
with 133 participants who
had frequent migraines.
They were taking 500 milligrams
of L-carnitine or nothing for 12 weeks.
So the control is a little bit,
the control experiment
there is a little bit tricky
but it had a significant effect
on reducing the number of
migraine attacks per month.
So I find that really interesting
and there's a lot more
listed there about the study.
And I think these compounds are powerful.
They carry risks for certain
people, not for others.
So again, you have to find
out what's right for you
but I do think they are super interesting
as potential therapeutics
for various people.
So what's the deal
with the gut microbiome
and the gut brain axis.
Today we've actually been
talking a lot already about
the gut brain axis that has
nothing to do with microbiomes.
We've been talking about this vagus nerve
that connects providing
sensory information
from the body to the brain.
And then the brain also
sends in the same nerve motor
information to control the
motility that got the heart rate
how fast we breathe and
deployment of immune stuff
killer cells and things of that sort.
But oftentimes when we hear
about the gut brain axis
these days, it's a discussion
about the gut microbiome.
And once again, we're in a situation where
there's incredible biology,
I'm very happy there's so much discussion
about the gut microbiome.
I am somewhat dismayed
and concerned that most
of what I hear out there is
either false or partially false.
So we're gonna clear up some
of the misconceptions, first
by understanding the biology.
And then we're going to talk
about some of the actionable items.
It is true that we have
a lot of these little
microorganisms living in our gut.
They're not there because
they want to help us.
They don't have brains,
they are adaptive however,
they try and find and create environments
that make it easier for
them to proliferate.
So they don't care about you and me
but they are perfectly
willing to exploit you
and me in order to make more
of themselves the same way viruses are,
viruses don't have a
mind, they infect cells,
they hijack the genome,
and they use that genome
to make more of themselves.
The microbiota that live in us
vary along the length
of our digestive tract.
But let's just take a step back
and think about how our body plan is made.
We are actually a series of tubes.
Our brain is actually a tube.
You see, it's all squishy on the outside.
And then it's got that long thing.
The spinal cord that goes
down to the base of the spine.
That's the central nervous system
that all started out as a tube.
It just looks like a
cauliflower on the other end
up in the brain because the tube is so big
and it has to be crammed into the skull.
So it gets all wrinkled up.
But if we were to splay it out
you'd find that it's just one big tube.
Similarly, our digestive tract
and our airways are
essentially one big tube.
It starts with our mouth, also our nose.
And then we have all these other tubes.
They go down through our throat and then
into our stomach and then
into our various intestines.
And then the tube ends out the other end.
So we are one long tube for digestion.
And inside of that tube
is a mucosal lining.
It's these little microvilli,
tiny, tiny, tiny little
like velvety ends of cells
that are able to move
and move things along and mucus mucosa.
And the conditions
of that mucosal lining set a
number of different things.
It sets the rate
of our digestion and the
quality of our digestion.
It sets for instance, our immune system.
Most people probably don't
realize this, but most infections
in the environment have to
get into our body somehow.
Some of them are inhaled.
A lot of them go into our mouth
and lodge in the mucosal
lining of the mouth.
And then infection start there.
You probably had the
experience, unfortunately,
of you know, feeling like you
have a tick in your throat,
like something's irritating your throat.
And then it kind of
migrates up into a head cold
or runny nose.
Sometimes it'll start as headache.
Sometimes it won't, but
things that are inert
can migrate down into the gut.
So we're ingesting things all the time.
Think about air, bacteria, viruses,
they're making their way into our gut.
And some of those
bacteria live in the gut.
And some of those bacteria
bias the mucosal lining
in the gut, stomach and intestines
to be more acidic or more basic
so that they can make more of themselves
so they can replicate.
They like a particular comfort.
It's like they like a particular kind
of bedding to lie down in and
create more of themselves.
Now, some of those those mucosal linings
that they promote make us feel better.
They make us feel more alert.
They bolster our immune system
and others make us feel worse.
So first rule, the
microbiome isn't good or bad.
Some of these little bugs
that live in us do bad things to us.
They make us feel worse.
They lower our immunity.
They affect us in negative ways.
Some of them make us feel
better and they do that mainly
by changing the conditions
of our gut environment.
In addition to that, they do impact
the neurotransmitters and the
neurons that live in the gut.
And that signal up to the
brain to impact things
like dopamine and serotonin
that we've been talking about previously.
So there's a vast world now
devoted to try and understand
what sources of food
what kinds of foods are good or not good
for the gut microbiome?
So let's just talk about some
general rules of thumb related
to the research quality
research that's peer reviewed.
And then in a future episode
we will go far deeper
into the gut microbiome
and gut brain axis.
But here's a few things
that I think you might find surprising.
First of all,
supporting a healthy gut
microbiome is good for mood,
great for digestion and great
for immune system function.
However, that does not mean maxing out
or taking the most probiotic
and prebiotic that you
can possibly manage.
As I mentioned many times before
I do believe in probiotics,
I take probiotics
but there are studies that show that
if you take lots and lots
of certain probiotics
like lactobacillus and you
really ramp up the levels more
it is not a case of more is better.
There are things like brain
fog that can come from that,
brain fog is just this inability to focus.
People feel really not well generally.
Some of those studies are
a little bit controversial
but I think it's fair to say
that if people really increase the amount
of probiotic that they're
taking beyond a certain amount
then they start feeling foggy in the mind.
Now what's too much?
Well I get probiotics
I mentioned before from Athletic Greens,
you can get them from fermented foods
like sauerkraut, pickles, kimchi natto,
these are different sources
from around the world.
Actually, I'd love to hear some
of the other sources that
people know other foods
from around the world.
I'm fascinated by the way
in which different
cultures have all arrived
at these foods that provide
and support healthy microbiomes
because they're fermented.
I have a colleague at
Stanford, Justin Sonnenberg,
and he and I have talked about this.
I don't want to quote him inappropriately,
but we've had discussions about it,
and they've published that the ingestion
of fermented foods is one
of the best ways to support healthy levels
of gut microbiota without
exceeding the threshold
that would cause things like brain fog.
So foods and fermented foods
are going to be the best source.
And there are a number
of different ways that one could do that.
Some people don't like fermented foods,
however some people supplement it.
So it isn't a case of more is better.
So we know that.
The other is that it is true
that healthy gut microbiota
have been shown to
improve symptoms of certain
psychiatric illnesses
as well as certain conditions
like particular features
along the autism spectrum,
which is interesting.
And those effects are probably
due to not just improvement
of immune system function,
but to the the conditions
in which the neurons
that sense nutrients convey
information to the brain
and increase levels of
serotonin and or dopamine.
So gut microbiome provides
kind of a foundation
for healthy gut and
healthy gut brain access
so much so that some people report
that when they start eating small bits
'cause it doesn't require
a lot of fermented foods,
that their overall mood is better,
not unlike the effects of EPA.
Although I don't think it's been looked
at directly in the context
of clinical depression yet.
And if someone knows of a study
please mention it in the comments.
That would be terrific.
There are some things
that you can do to really
damage your gut microbiome.
And this is where there's
a huge misconception
that I want to clear up.
There was a study that
was published in "Nature",
which is among the three top journals
that we have in science.
You know, "Nature", "Science"
and "Cell" are considered the top tops,
but excellent journal that showed
that artificial sweeteners
but a particular artificial sweetener
which was saccharin can
disrupt the gut microbiome
in ways that is detrimental
to a number of different health markers,
increasing inflammatory cytokines
and all the other bad
things that happen when
the gut microbiome is thrown off kilter.
That study was widely discussed
but there were a few things that were not
mentioned there that are really important.
That study was about
saccharin in particular.
Saccharin is not the
most typical artificial
sweetener that's used, the most typical
artificial sweeteners
that are used are things
like aspartame, so-called
NutraSweet or Sucralose,
or these days Stevia, there's
monk fruits, to my knowledge
and please correct me if
anyone knows of any studies,
to my knowledge, the negative effects
of these artificial sweeteners
on the gut microbiome were
restricted to saccharin.
Now there is enough chemical similarity
between saccharin and some
of the other ones that I
mentioned, but not all of them.
For instance, Stevia,
monk fruit are distinct
in their chemical makeup so
that they probably don't have
if they have any, have lower
effects, negative effects
on the gut microbiome, but
it should still be tested.
So saccharin is really,
it was shown in this study
and several other studies
can really negatively
impact the quality of the gut microbiome.
Interestingly, the narrative
around artificial sweeteners
and gut microbiome is incorrect.
Most people thought,
oh, saccharin is bad for the microbiome.
It must kill the microbiome.
And so you hear people saying,
oh, artificial sweeteners
kill the microbiome.
That's not true at all.
In fact, in that very same
study published in nature
they showed that the negative affects
of saccharin on the
microbiome could be blocked
or eliminated by giving antibiotics.
So what happens is certain
artificial sweeteners
in particular saccharin
disrupt the microbiome
and make the environment
within the gut that mucosal
lining more favorable
to bacteria microbiota that
are not good for the organism.
This is an important distinction.
It's not just a language
thing where people say,
oh, you know, it kills the microbiome.
It doesn't kill the microbiome.
It shifts the microbiome and shifts
in the microbiome can be
good or they can be bad.
And that takes us to another topic
that's a bit of a hot button topic
but I'm willing to go there.
'Cause I think it deserves conversation,
which is nowadays there
are many examples out there
where people have switched
from a kind of standard diet
or even a vegetarian diet to
a vegan diet, to a keto diet.
Now keto doesn't necessarily have to mean
the ingestion of meats, but it can.
And they experience positive
effects for themselves.
Not everybody.
And I've talked previously
about some of the
kind of the incorrect,
what I believe is
incorrect marketing of keto
as it relates to the cosmetic effects
and some of the challenges with
sleep that some people have
but some people love keto
and it works great for them.
But the ketogenic diet is interesting
because when one shifts
to the ketogenic diet
there is a shift in the gut microbiome.
And some people end up feeling better.
Some people end up feeling worse.
Likewise, some people go from
ingesting animal products
including meat or they're
vegetarian and they go to vegan
and they experience positive
shifts in mood and affect.
And we know that the transition to a more
plant-based diet and especially
the enrichment of fiber
that's present in those diets
also creates dramatic shifts
in the gut microbiome.
Some people feel better doing that.
Some people feel worse.
And of course, it's
gonna depend on whether
or not you're ingesting a lot
of processed foods or not.
There was a paper published in "Cell",
"Cell Press" journal
obviously, excellent journal,
showing that ingestion of processed foods,
regardless of whether or not they come
from animal sources or non-animal sources
the processed foods themselves
tend to create activity
within the body and this surely has roots
in the nervous system that lead
to over-consumption of
calories and weight gain.
Even some weight gain
that couldn't be explained
by increased calories.
In other words, processed
foods are bad, regardless of
whether or not you're
talking about animal products
or non animal products,
probably not surprising
given what you know
about these sugar sensing
and other amino acid sensing cells
in the gut that we talked about earlier.
So the point of all this is
that when I say you have to
find what's right for you,
that's not a throwaway statement.
Some people's microbiome and the lining
of their mucosa, excuse me,
their mucosa lining of their throat,
of their gut, of their nose,
everything is improved by diets
that are heavily meat based
and don't have many plants.
Other people do much better
on a plant-based diet
without many meat products
or animal products.
It's highly individual.
And this probably has
roots in genetic makeup.
This probably has roots
in what people were raised
on because remember the
nervous system of course
is set up by your genetic, your
genes, your genetic program
but your nervous system adapts early
in life to your conditions.
That's what it's for,
the reason you have a
nervous system is to move
your body appropriately
towards things that are good
for you and away from things that are not.
But also it was designed to adapt.
The early life period
has this incredible thing
about plasticity that
we spent a whole month
on so that it can change so that yes
indeed some people may like certain foods
and react to certain
foods better than others
because of the way that their
nervous system was wired.
This enteric as it's called nervous system
that lines the gut and the
communicates with the brain.
So most of what I've talked
about today is kind of black and white.
These are things that
are present in all of us,
the sugar sensing neurons of the gut,
the way the vagus is wired.
The fact that omega-3
omega-6 is tend to improve.
The ratios tend to impact
mood with high omega-3.
omega-6 ratios improving mood.
We talked about all sorts
of things in the gut brain
and body brain axis, but when
it comes to the microbiome
the key thing is that we
all have a microbiome.
You want a microbiome, but you want to
promote the microbiome
that is right for you.
And that can be shifted and steered
by ingesting certain categories
of foods and not others.
And one thing that really
frustrates me is when
the people show up with an agenda,
like all meat agenda or a vegan agenda
or a keto agenda, and they talk
about these positive effects
on the gut microbiome.
And it's all true, frankly.
And so it's highly individual.
Now this doesn't get to
any of the ethical issues
around animals or the planet,
and you hear rabid debates
about that on both sides.
And I am not qualified or equipped to talk
about whether or not
regenerative agriculture,
animal products, or farming
or any of these things,
how those actually impact the environment,
that is not my expertise,
but when it comes to your
health and your microbiome
you want to support the microbiome.
It's very clear
that these fermented foods
support the microbiome
that we should be ingesting
at least two servings per day.
Which is quite a lot that supplementation
at low levels can be good.
Supplementation at high levels
can create this brain fog
even though some people say
that result is controversial.
I've experienced this
myself and the data looked
to me pretty darn solid.
So that's one thing to
think about as well.
And the other thing
about the gut microbiome
is that it's highly contextual based
on other things that you're doing.
So even things like exercise
and social well-being
and connection, those
things are also impacting
the gut microbiome.
So find the diet that's right for you.
And that works for you in the
context of the other ethical
and lifestyle choices
that are important to you.
That's my advice.
A note about fasting.
I have a colleague at
Yale, who's an expert
in the gut microbiome.
And he told me something
really interesting,
which is when we fast,
we actually digest certain components
within our dietary tract.
It actually depletes a good
amount of the gut microbiome.
And this is interesting.
I've had good results
from I guess you would call
it intermittent or kind
of circadian type fasting where
I've never done long fast,
but where I push out my
first meal by a few hours
my first meal is generally
around lunchtime or so
but the longer periods of
fasting that go for a day
or two or three days are known to deplete
the gut microbiome in major ways.
But that's not always
necessarily a bad thing
because when it's replenished,
it often is replenished
at levels that exceeded
its previous level.
But I think that some of
the GI tract and even some
of the mental effects of
returning to eating after feeding
sometimes people don't feel so
good when they start eating.
They really want food, but
then they start eating again.
They don't feel as good
as they did on the fast.
Some of that may be
related to the depletion
of the microbiome that
occurs during long fast.
So again, this is something
to think about and talk about
with your doctor, but
the idea that fasting
across the board is good.
There may be some merits
to that, and certainly
in some cases, but it does
deplete the microbiome
and that depletion of the
microbiome is significant
because it means when you return
to eating, you're actually
not in the same position to digest
and assimilate those foods.
And those foods are not
in the same position to
impact your brain and body the same way
they were prior to the fast.
And this is, I think why
people suggest a kind
of gradual transition back
to consuming nutrients after a fast.
So as we round up, I want to
share some results with you
That without question will
impact the way that you respond
to food mentally and even physically.
And I know that because
that's the central theme
of the studies I'm
about to tell you about.
I have a colleague at Stanford, Alia Crum,
who's done some remarkable
experiments on mindset.
And some people could think
about these as placebo effects
or belief effects,
but they actually go
way beyond those terms.
And there are a number
of different examples
of this that Aaliyah's lab
and her coworkers have demonstrated.
But two that are particularly
interesting to me
I Want to share with you now
because they really emphasize how
our beliefs can really
impact the way that our brain
and body work together.
I think the most famous of
these is an experiment they did
where they had two groups of individuals.
They were each given a milkshake
and they had some factors
measured from their
blood by an IV while they
ingested the milkshake.
And then afterwards as well.
And one of the factors
that they were looking
at was something called
grehlin, G-H-R-E-L-I-N.
Grehlin is a peptide that
increases with hunger.
So the longer you haven't
eaten that grehlin goes up.
And I know some of you say,
well, I fast, I fast, I fast
and I eventually lose my appetite.
Well, grehlin still goes
up and then it drops.
So if you were one of these
people that eats every three
hours regularly, grehlin
kind of gets a little pulse
as you get to that two
hour and 50 minute mark.
So it's a little bit of a timer as well.
It's really interesting peptide.
In any event, what they did is
they gave people milkshakes,
two groups, one group got
a shake that they were told
it was a low calorie, healthy shake.
The other got a milkshake
that they were told
it was the very decadent
high calorie shake.
I think it was something
like two or maybe even two
and a half times as many
calories as the other.
Perhaps even more, I
don't recall the details,
but you got a high calorie
and a low calorie condition.
And then they drank the shake
and then they measured grehlin
in these subjects' blood.
And what they found was
that the high calorie shake
had a much more robust effect
on blunting grehlin and reducing grehlin.
But the interesting thing you
probably guessed already is
that it was the exact same
shake given to both groups.
So people's belief about the content
of something impacted their physiology.
And this speaks to the so-called top
down mechanisms or
modulation of our physiology.
In a previous episode about pain
we talked about the effects of obsessive
believe it or not, it was
an obsessive infatuation
and love on pain responses
and pain thresholds.
This is yet another example where beliefs
or subjective feelings
can impact physiology
at the level of the periphery,
because grehlin is released
in the periphery in the body.
Now, these beliefs affects
extend beyond examples like this,
another good example
that I'd like to share
is Alia, Dr. Crum,
and her colleagues did an experiment where
they took housekeepers,
they were essentially hotel workers,
divide them into two groups.
They had them watch a short film.
In one case, the film was about how
their work was important to
help people feel comfortable
in the hotel, et cetera, et cetera.
The other group heard that
the activity that they were
doing cleaning and taking care
of the hotel was good for them.
It was good for their
health, et cetera, et cetera.
They controlled very nicely in the study
for health parameters, for
individual differences.
And for the behaviors of
these people in the period
that followed this short tutorial.
And what they found was eight weeks later,
the group that had been told
that the activity was good
for them showed lower blood pressure.
They had lost a significant
amount of body fat
and they reported enjoying
their work far more
than the other group.
The same work, simply biased mentally
by the information that they were given,
but their physiology
followed that information.
And so this is not just
the placebo effect.
This is an incredible set
of findings that illustrate
the extent to which whether
or not we believe a food is gonna be good
for us or not good for us.
Well, we can't escape the reality.
You can't tell yourself that
a poison is gonna be good
for you and ingest that poison
and expect it to not kill you,
nor can you tell yourself
that eating 12 croissants,
I confess I've done it,
it was after a very long
run, a long time ago
but you can't tell yourself
that that's necessarily going to be good
for you or that it's gonna
make you lose weight.
These belief effects are not about lying
to yourself in these
cases, in these experiments
as you'll notice that subjects
didn't have prior knowledge
about grehlin or about the effects
of their daily routine on
weight loss and blood pressure.
So in order for them to work
you have to be naive to
the information, right?
You can't simply lie to yourself
and tell yourself what you want to believe
and that's important, but also
important is that the mind
and the body are in this
fascinating interplay.
And today we've talked
mainly about how the body
and things that we put inside this tube,
that runs from our mouth to
the other end to our rectum,
basically is impacting all these cells,
these neurons, microbiota
in their mucosal lining,
heart, lungs and how all
that information is feeding
up to the brain to impact
how we feel up here.
But also how we feel up here is impacting
how our body reacts at levels
of very core physiology that
you couldn't just tell yourself
that this was gonna work,
but what you believe
about certain substances, certain foods,
certain nutrients does
have a profound effect
on the magnitude of their impact
and sometimes even the quality
and direction of that impact.
Well, first of all,
I want to thank everybody for
their support of this podcast.
The response that we've
received since releasing
at the beginning of the new
year has been tremendous.
And we're so grateful for it.
I know some of you and people I've said,
well, it's a lot of information.
It's like a college lecture.
Indeed, there's a lot of information,
but I believe very strongly
that if you learn mechanism
and maybe even if you
hear it several times over
eventually those
mechanisms become embedded
into the way that you
view an entire topic.
As well, I always try and put tools
as I go along that you
can look to immediately.
Some of them might be right for you.
Others might not,
try them if you like and
don't if you don't want to,
and if they don't work for
you, then discard them.
If however, you are finding benefits
from the information and
from the tools and you know
others that you think
could benefit from it,
please pass along information
about the podcast.
Please subscribe to the YouTube channel
if you haven't already,
please subscribe to us
on Apple and Spotify,
if you haven't already.
Please leave a review
in the comment section here on YouTube.
Also, if you feel we deserve it
please give us a
five-star review on Apple.
All those things really help us.
In addition, if you'd like to
support the podcast further
we've set up a Patreon account.
It's patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
It allows you to support the
podcast at a variety of levels.
We have the 5-HTP
serotonin for $5 a month,
the Costello, $10 a month
in honor of Costello, et cetera.
You don't have to but if you'd like to,
that would be terrific.
In addition, please check out our sponsors
that we've mentioned at the
beginning of the podcast.
That's one of the best
ways to help support us.
And we do believe in all
the products that we support
and our sponsors very much otherwise
we wouldn't be working with them.
So much so that when I
mentioned supplements
and I talk about supplements
throughout the course
of the episodes, I don't
mention specific brands,
but I would be remiss if
I didn't mention the fact
that we have partnered
with Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E.
And we've done that because we know
that Thorne uses the highest levels
of stringency in terms of
the products they produce.
What they say is in each capsule
and tablet actually is,
they're used by the Mayo Clinic,
by all the major sports teams
because of their level
of stringency and rigor.
If you want to know
what supplements I take
you can go to thorne.com/u/huberman.
And you can see the
supplements that I take
and you can get those as well
as any of the other supplements
and products that Thorne
makes for 20% off.
So it's thorne.com/u/huberman to get 20%
off any supplements that Thorne makes.
So in today's episode,
we took a full journey
into the brain body relationship
and discussed a lot of the mechanisms
and the actionable items
that you can approach
if you want to explore this aspect
of your biology and psychology further.
Last, but certainly not least,
I want to thank everybody
for your time and attention today,
and as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]