- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science based tools
for everyday life.
[cheerful music]
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today, we are discussing aggression.
I'm going to explain to you that there are
several different types of
aggression, for instance,
reactive aggression versus
proactive aggression.
Meaning sometimes people
will be aggressive
because they feel threatened
or they are protecting
those that they love,
who also feel threatened.
There's also proactive
aggression where people
go out of their way to
deliberately try and harm others.
And there is indirect
aggression, which is aggression,
not involving physical
violence, for instance,
shaming people and things of that sort.
It turns out that there are
different biological mechanisms
underlying each of the
different types of aggression.
And today I will define those for you.
I'll talk about the neural
circuits in the brain and body
that mediate each of the
different kinds of aggression.
Talk about some of the
hormones and peptides
and neurotransmitters involved.
I promise to make it
all accessible to you,
even if you do not have any
biology or science background,
I will also discuss
tools, psychological tools
and biological tools that one can use to
better control aggression.
Now, right here at the outset,
I want to acknowledge that any
discussion about aggression
has to have an element
of context within it.
To be fair, human beings
invest a lot of money,
a lot of time, and a lot of energy,
and indeed can even derive
pleasure from aggression.
Later I'll talk about neural
circuits in the brain and body
that reinforce, in other words,
reward through the release
of chemicals that make people feel good.
Acts of aggression.
However, what I'm mainly referring to
is the context in which
human beings will pay money
in order to derive what we
call vicarious aggression,
put it simply people spend
an enormous amount of money
and time and energy watching
other people engage in,
for instance, aggressive sports.
And we know that observing
your team winning
over another team causes the
release of neurochemicals
in your brain and body
that make you feel good.
And yes, that can make
you feel more aggressive.
We also know of course that
most governments invest
many billions if not trillions of dollars
in infrastructure,
technologies and human beings
in order to engage in
aggression if needed,
so-called military warfare, et cetera.
So today's discussion will
include a description of
aggression in the pathological sense.
We'll actually talk about an
explosive aggressive disorder
that most of you probably
haven't heard of,
but is actually far more
common than perhaps, you know,
we'll talk about the role of
things like attention deficit,
hyperactivity disorder,
and how that can relate
to aggression through
the relationship between
impulsivity and aggression.
And we'll talk about verbal aggression,
physical aggression, proactive aggression,
as mentioned before,
and reactive aggression.
I'm certain that by
the end of the episode,
you will come away with a much
more thorough understanding
of what this thing that we
call aggression really is.
And when you see it in other people,
I think it will make more sense to you.
And when you observe it in
yourself or the impulse to engage
in aggression, verbal,
or physical or otherwise,
I hope that you'll
understand it better as well.
And of course, the tools
that I will describe
should allow you to modulate and control
aggressive tendencies or
predispositions to aggressiveness
and just generally to be
able to engage with people
in a more adaptive way overall.
Before we begin, I'd like to
emphasize that this podcast
is separate from my teaching
and research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an
all-in-one vitamin mineral
probiotic drink that's designed to meet
all your foundational health needs.
I started taking Athletic
Greens way back in 2012.
So I'm delighted that they're
sponsoring this podcast.
The reason I started
taking Athletic Greens
and the reason I still
take Athletic Greens
once or twice a day is that
it covers all of my basic
vitamin mineral and probiotic needs.
The probiotics are
especially important to me.
There are now abundant data
showing that the gut microbiome,
which is basically a
community of trillions
of little bacteria that live
in our guts are beneficial
for our immune system, for brain function,
for mood and many other
aspects of our health.
The gut microbiome thrives on
probiotics and Athletic Greens
contains the proper array of probiotics
to optimize the gut microbiome.
Athletic Greens also has
adaptogens for recovery
from physical and mental exertion,
digestive enzymes for gut
health, vitamin C, zinc,
as I mentioned before, all the
other vitamins and minerals
that you need in order to cover
your basic needs each day.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and claim a special offer.
That'll give you five free
travel packs that make it easy
to mix up Athletic Greens
while you're on the road
and a year supply of Vitamin D3K2.
There's now a wealth of
data showing that vitamin D3
is important for many
aspects of our immediate
and long term health.
Many people, even if they
get out in the sunlight
are not getting enough Vitamin D3,
and the K2 is thought to be beneficial
for calcium regulation and
a number of other things
important to our health.
So again, if you go to
athleticGreens.com/huberman,
you can claim the
special offer of the five
free travel packs and the
year's supply of vitamin D3K2.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by ROKA.
ROKA makes sunglasses and eyeglasses
that are the absolute highest quality.
The company was founded by
two All-American swimmers
from Stanford and everything
about their eyeglasses
and sunglasses were designed
with performance in mind,
I've spent a lifetime
working on the biology
of the visual system, I can
tell you that your visual system
has to contend with some
pretty tough challenges
as you move throughout the day.
For instance, if you go
from a brightly lit region
to a dimmer region, your
visual system has to adjust.
ROKA eyeglasses and
sunglasses were designed
with those sorts of adjustments in mind.
So for instance, if you're
outside in the shade,
you move into the sun and
then back into the shade,
you don't have to take
your sunglasses on and off.
Their glasses were initially designed
for sports performance
and the great thing is
they could be used for
that, but also they have
a terrific aesthetic, so you can wear them
to work or out to dinner.
I wear readers at night
and when I drive at night
and I wear sunglasses, if I'm out a lot
on really bright days.
The terrific thing about
ROKA glasses is that even
if you get sweaty, they won't fall off.
So you can run with them,
you can cycle with them.
Or as I mentioned before, you can just
wear them out and about.
If you'd like to try ROKA,
you can go to roka.com,
that's R-O-K-A.com and
enter the code "Huberman"
to save 20% off your first order.
Again, that's ROKA roka.com
and enter the code "Huberman" at checkout.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Helix Sleep.
Helix Sleep makes mattresses
and pillows that in my opinion
are the very best you'll find.
I started sleeping on a Helix mattress
a little over a year ago,
and it's the best sleep
I've had ever since.
If you go to the Helix site,
they have a terrific sleep quiz
that just takes a few minutes,
ask you questions like,
"Do you tend to sleep on your side,
your back or your stomach?"
Maybe you don't know
because you're asleep,
but many people do know.
And even if you don't know that's okay,
it will also ask you questions like,
"Do you tend to run hot or cold?"
Do you tend to wake up in the
middle of the night or not?
And by taking that brief
quiz, they will match you
to the specific mattress
that's ideal for you
and your sleep needs.
And that's really what sets
Helix Sleep mattresses apart.
Everybody's unique, and they know that.
So if you take this
quiz, you'll get matched
to a particular mattress.
For me, it was the
"Dusk" mattress D-U-S-K,
but again, that's just me,
and you may match to that one,
or you may match to a different one.
If you're interested in
upgrading your mattress
and sleeping much better, go
to helixsleep.com/huberman.
Take that two minute sleep
quiz and they'll match you
to a customized mattress and
you'll get up to $200 off
any mattress order and two free pillows.
I also love their pillows.
I've always had this issue with pillows
that they heat up too much.
I'm always looking for the
pillow that can cool itself.
Somehow the pillows stay nice and cool.
They're also not too big,
so I'm not propped up,
not getting the Text Neck
in the middle of the night,
where I'm letting my chin push my chest,
nor am I falling back and
having trouble breathing
in the middle of the night.
They're designed just right.
They also have a 10 years warranty
and you get to try it out for
a hundred nights, risk free.
They'll even pick it up for
you if you don't love it.
But I think that you will.
Again, if you're interested, you can go
to helixsleep.com/huberman
for up to $200 off
and two free pillows.
Let's talk about aggression.
I think that many people
out there are put off
by aggression, although
others are drawn to aggression
both in themselves and when
observing it in others.
The reason to talk about aggression is,
that as mentioned before,
the context of aggression really matters.
So there are instances where
aggression is adaptive.
For instance, a mother
protecting her children
if she's being attacked,
or if her children are being threatened.
I think most people would
agree that so-called
maternal aggression of that sort,
provided the context is
right, is a great thing.
Protecting our young is
after all one of the primary
adaptive drives of our species,
and thank goodness it is.
Of course, other forms of aggression
like unprovoked, proactive aggression,
somebody simply being
violent to somebody else,
even when unprovoked, most of us cringe
when we see that kind of behavior,
it can even evoke aggression in people
when they observe that kind of behavior.
So again, context really matters,
but a more general and perhaps
an even more important reason
to think about and understand aggression
is that by understanding the biology
and psychology of aggression, you will be
in a much better position to understand
how all emotional states come to be,
both in yourself and in others.
For instance, many of you have
probably heard the statement
that I believe arises from pop psychology,
not from formal academic psychology,
that aggression is just sadness.
It's a form of sadness that's amplified
and it shows up as aggression.
But when we look at the underlying biology
and the peer reviewed literature on this,
nothing could be further from the truth.
We have distinct circuits
in the brain for aggression
versus grief and mourning,
those are non-overlapping.
Now that doesn't mean that you
can't be sad and aggressive
or in a state of mourning and
aggressive at the same time,
but the idea that sadness and aggression
are one in the same
thing is simply not true.
And by understanding that,
or perhaps by understanding
that irritability and aggression
are not the same thing,
you'll be in a much
better position to apply
some of the tools that we will
talk about in this episode
in order to be able to
reduce or eliminate,
or if it's adaptive to you
to modulate aggression.
And yes, there are cases where
modulating your aggression
in some cases, even amplifying
aggression can be adaptive.
Now this of course is
not the first discussion
about the biology of aggression
or the psychology of aggression.
And we really can look to the
beginning of the last century
as the time in which the formal study
of aggression really began.
One of the names that's most
associated with the formal
study of aggression is none
other than Konrad Lorenz.
Some of you may be
familiar with that name,
others of you may not be
familiar with that name.
Konrad Lorenz studied
so-called imprinting behaviors
and fixed action pattern behaviors.
He's most famous, at least
in scientific circles,
for getting geese to believe
that he was their parent.
And if you were to put into
Google Conrad with a K, Lorenz,
just as it sounds, Konrad Lorenz, geese,
you're going to see a
lot of photos of Conrad
walking down roads with a
lot of geese following him
or swimming in lakes with a
lot of geese following him.
He had a habit of geese adopting him
because of the behaviors
that he partook in.
So he would swim out on a lake
in front of a bunch of
little geese and then
they would think that he was the parent
and they would imprint on him.
He even lived with these
animals and they lived with him,
sort of a strange
character from what I hear.
But nonetheless, all
this work was deserving
of a Nobel prize because
what he discovered
were fixed action patterns.
That is patterns of behavior
that could be evoked by a single stimulus.
Okay. This is really important.
The idea that you can get a
whole category of behaviors,
like swimming behind a parent,
or looking to somebody for
comfort, and only them,
the idea that you could
get a huge category
of different behaviors in a
bunch of different contexts
triggered by just the presence
of that person is remarkable,
because what it suggested
and what turns out to be true
is that there are neural circuits,
not just individual brain
areas, but collections
of brain areas that work together
to engage a pattern of behaviors.
And that's the first fundamental principle
that we need to define today,
that when we talk about aggression,
we are talking about
activation of neural circuits,
not individual brain
areas, but neural circuits
that get played out in
sequence like keys on a piano,
but that playing out in sequence means
that aggression is a verb.
It has a beginning, a middle
and an end, and it's a process.
It's not an event.
And as you'll see, that turns
out to be very important
in terms of thinking about
how one can halt aggression,
prevent it from happening
before it's initiated,
or maybe even prolonging aggression,
if that's what's needed.
Now, Konrad Lorenz had no real
knowledge of neural circuits.
I mean, obviously he
knew there was this thing
that we call a brain and a nervous system,
and he knew that there
were chemicals in the brain
and hormones and things of that sort
that were likely to play a role,
but he really didn't take
any measures to define
what the neural circuits were,
frankly, he didn't need to.
He had his Nobel prize and he
did all this beautiful work.
He's known for an abundance of work,
but he did think about what
sorts of underlying processes
could drive something like aggression.
And he talked about one particular feature
that's especially important,
and that's this notion of a pressure.
The idea that yes, certain
hormones will bias somebody
or an animal to be aggressive,
certain neural transmitter
states, and you'll learn
what those are today will bias somebody
to be more or less aggressive,
maybe even submissive and passive,
maybe outright proactively
aggressive towards anyone
or anything in front of them.
And yes, of course there
will be historical features
based on their childhood,
et cetera, et cetera.
He understood that there will
be a constellation of things
that would drive people to be aggressive.
And he described a so-called pressure,
almost like a hydraulic pressure.
Just think about fluid
pressure in a small container
being pushed, pushed,
pushed until the can,
or the container is ready to explode
and how multiple features,
multiple variables
could impinge on that
and create that pressure.
It turns out that's exactly
the way the system works.
There is no single brain area
that flips the switch for aggression.
Although we'll soon talk
about a brain structure
that generally houses the propensity
and the output of aggression.
This notion of a hydraulic
pressure that can drive us
toward aggressive behavior
or conversely can be
very low pressure and keep us
in a state of non-reactivity,
maybe even passivity or submissiveness
is a very important feature
because it really captures
the essence of how neural circuits work
when we're talking about
primitive behaviors generally.
And you can start to notice
this in yourself and in others,
you can start to notice
when you are veering
toward aggression or
when someone is veering
toward aggression, verbal or physical.
Now that veering is the buildup
of this hydraulic pressure
that Lorenz was referring to,
and it really does have an
underlying biological basis.
Now it was some years later
that the first experiments
came along, which really
started to identify
the brain areas and the
biological so-called pressures
that can induce aggressive behavior.
And the person that really
gets credit for this
is a guy by the name of Walter Hess,
who at that time was working on cats.
And I know that when say working on cats,
a lot of people will cringe.
A lot of people have cats as pets,
and certainly cats can be delightful.
Some people like them more,
some people like them less.
Most people cringe at the idea
of doing experiments on cats.
I should say that these days,
very few laboratories work on cats.
Most laboratories that
work on animal models
will work on flies, Drosophila fruit flies
for their capacity to do genetics,
on laboratory mice, sometimes
rats, but usually mice.
And occasionally you'll find a
lab that still works on cats.
Back in the time of Hess,
very few laboratories
worked on mice, most laboratories
worked on cats or rats.
And the reason for that is
nowadays most laboratories
use mice if they use animal models
because of the genetic
tools that exist in mice
to knock out this gene or
knock in this gene, et cetera,
which can't be done in
humans or non-human primates,
at least not very easily
at this point in history.
So when I say he was working on cats,
I realized that probably
evokes some negative emotions
in some of you, maybe even
aggression in some of you,
what we can do, however,
is look at the data
and make use of the data in
terms of our understanding.
What Hess did was he
had cats that were awake
and he was able to lower
a stimulating electrode
into their brain.
Now keep in mind that the brain
does not have any pain sensors.
So after a small hole
is made in the skull,
electrodes are lowered into the brain.
This is what's done commonly
in human neurosurgery.
And he was able to stimulate
different brain areas
and he was sort of poking around.
And when I say sort of,
he was doing this with
some logical intent and purpose,
he wasn't just poking
around in there for fun.
He was trying to identify brain
regions that could generate
entire categories of
behavior, ALA Lorenz, right?
These fixed action pattern behaviors.
Eventually his electrode landed in a site
and he provided electrical
stimulation to the cat
that caused this otherwise
passive purring relaxing cat
to suddenly go into an absolute rage.
So arched back, hissing hair up.
So called piloerection,
where the hairs go up,
animals try to make
themselves as big as possible
often when they're aggressive.
Drooling, maybe even
spitting, believe it or not,
cats and other animals can do this.
And the cat tried to
attack him or anyone else,
and anything else, even inanimate objects
when he stimulated this
particula brain area.
So Hess obviously took notice
of this incredible
transformation in behavior.
And the fact that when he
turned off the stimulation
of this particular brain area,
the cat very quickly within seconds,
went back to being passive calm kitty.
Now, of course, he repeated
this experiment in other animals
because he had to confirm that
it wasn't just happenstance,
that there wasn't something
unique about this one cat
that perhaps he had stimulated an area
that had been built up during
the kittenhood of this cat
and had been reactivated.
Maybe this kitten had been
traumatized early in life
or scared and reactivation
of a particular circuit,
unique to that cat created
this aggressive behavior.
That wasn't the case,
every cat that he looked at
and stimulated this particular brain area,
the cat would immediately
go into an aggressive,
almost rage type behavior.
Now, of course we can't anthropomorphize.
We don't know what the cat was feeling.
For all we know the cat could be happy,
although that seems pretty unlikely
and later experiments done in mice,
but also in humans confirm that indeed,
stimulation of this brain area evoked
not just behavioral aggression,
but also subjective feelings
of aggression and anger.
So what was this incredible brain area,
or rather, I should say,
what is the brain area
that harbored this incredible capacity
to generate aggressive
behavior in Hess's experiments?
Well, for those of you
that are regular listeners
of this podcast, you'll
probably be relieved to know
that today we're going to talk
about some new neural circuits,
oftentimes we'll center
back on the amygdala
or the prefrontal cortex,
and those names will come up.
And for those of you that
haven't heard them before,
don't worry, I'll make it clear as to what
those brain areas are and what they do.
But today we're going to talk a lot about
the so-called VMH or
ventromedial hypothalamus.
The ventromedial
hypothalamus is a nucleus,
meaning a small collection of neurons...
What are neurons?
Nerve cells, and that
small collection of neurons
that we call the ventromedial
hypothalamus is truly small.
It's only about 1,500 neurons
on one side of your brain
and a matching 1,500 neurons
on the other side of your brain
and that combined 3000 neurons
or so, it's not exactly 3000,
but 3000 neurons or so
is sufficient to generate
aggressive behavior of the sort
that Hess observed in the
cat, and believe it or not,
when you see somebody
who's in an act of rage
or in an act of verbal aggression
or in an act of defensive aggression,
protecting their family or loved
ones or country, et cetera,
almost certainly those neurons
are engaged in that behavior.
Those neurons are perhaps
even generating that behavior.
And next I'll describe some
experiments that were done
just recently within
the last 10 years or so,
but leading right up until this year
and even last month that keep confirming
again and again and again,
that it is the activity of neurons
in the ventromedial hypothalamus
that are both necessary
and sufficient to
generate the full catalog
of aggressive behaviors.
Now, before I go further to describe
the beautiful recent studies on the VMH,
the ventromedial hypothalamus,
and the important role of testosterone,
and more importantly, estrogen,
in the activation of aggressive
behavior, that's right.
That's soon to be clear to
you why that's the case.
I want to emphasize that the
ventromedial hypothalamus
is something that we
should all care about.
Why?
Well, it turns out that many categories
of psychiatric disorders,
developmental disorders,
and psychological challenges,
things like schizophrenia,
PTSD, post-traumatic stress
disorder, depression,
borderline personality disorder,
and even certain forms of
autism can include elements
of aggression and even violence.
Now it's certainly not the case
that aggression and violence
are present in all people
who suffer from schizophrenia
or PTSD or depression or autism
or borderline personality disorder.
I'm absolutely not saying that.
However, it can be a feature of those.
And it's a well described feature
in terms of trying to
understand the constellation
of challenges that people suffer
from when they have those.
So thinking about the VMH goes
way beyond just understanding
basic aggression in the
context of adaptive aggression.
So, you know, when
earlier I use the example,
maternal aggression, that's one
adaptive form of aggression.
It also can be pathologic aggression,
meaning it can harm ourselves or others.
So keep this in mind as we go forward,
because later we're going
to talk about specific tools
designed to modulate or prevent
aggression in, for instance,
people with attention deficit
hyperactivity disorder,
and especially kids with ADHD.
In the meantime, let's return to the VMH,
this relatively small
collection of neurons.
And the reason I say
relatively small is, well,
your brain has many hundreds
of billions of neurons,
maybe even trillions of neurons,
the exact number of
neurons isn't really clear,
but it's a lot.
And it certainly is a lot
relative to the number of neurons
this 3000 or so neurons
living in your hypothalamus
that can evoke this aggressive response.
Experiments done by David
Anderson's lab at Caltech
were really the first to
parse the fine circuitry
and to really show that the
ventromedial hypothalamus
is both necessary and sufficient
for aggressive behavior.
These are important experiments
and they're worth knowing about.
What they did was they
identified, first of all,
where the ventromedial
hypothalamus was in the mouse,
that was pretty straightforward
to do was sort of known
before they started these experiments.
And then they analyzed which
genes, meaning which DNA,
which of course becomes RNA
and RNA becomes protein,
which DNA and therefore
which proteins are expressed
in particular cells of the
ventromedial hypothalamus.
And it turns out that
there's a particular category
of neurons in the
ventromedial hypothalamus
that make an estrogen receptor.
And it is those neurons in
particular that are responsible
for generating aggressive behavior.
How did they know this?
Well, they used a tool that's
actually been described
by a previous guest of this podcast.
We had an episode with the
psychiatrist and bioengineer
and my colleague at
Stanford School of Medicine,
Karl Deisseroth, he and
others have developed tools
that allow people to control
the activity of neurons
essentially by remote control,
by shining light on those neurons.
So in the context of an
experiment on a mouse,
which is what David's
lab did, and these were
the beautiful experiments of Dayu Lin
who's now in her own laboratory
at New York University,
put a little fiber optic
cable down into the brain
into the hypothalamus
that is of the mouse.
The mouse is able to move around
in its cage freely moving,
even though it has a little
tether, this little wire,
it's a very thin wire.
And that little thin wire is actually
a little what we call optrode.
And the experimentalist
in this case, Dayu,
was able to stimulate the turning on
of a little bit of blue
light and that blue light
activated only those
estrogen receptor neurons
in only the ventromedial hypothalamus
and the way she was able to do that,
is she had introduced a
gene that had been developed
by our friend, Karl
Deisseroth that allows light
to trigger electrical
activity in those neurons.
So if any of that is confusing,
or if all of that is confusing,
here's the experiment.
There's a mouse in a cage.
It has a little wire
coming out of its head.
It doesn't notice, believe it or not.
We know this 'cause it's
still eating and mating
and doing all the things
that mics like to do
on a daily basis and sleeping, et cetera.
And the mere pressing of
a button will activate
a little bit of light released
at the end of that wire,
that light activates particular
neurons in this case,
it's the estrogen receptor
containing neurons
in only the ventromedial hypothalamus.
When that mouse is in a
cage with another mouse,
a couple of things happen depending on
what the other mouse is, or we could say
who the other mouse is.
If it's a male mouse and you put in there
with a female mouse, the male
mouse will attempt to mate
with a female mouse
provided that the male mouse
has gone through puberty.
He will try to mount and
mate with the female mouse.
Now female mice are either
in a receptive phase
or a non-receptive phase of
their so-called estrous cycle.
They don't have a menstrual 28 day cycle
They have an estrous cycle.
And on particular days
of the estrous cycle,
they are not happy to mate.
They will basically
keep their hindquarters
away from the male mouse at all costs.
They'll even attack the male mouse.
On certain days of the
estrous cycle, however,
the female mouse will undergo
what's called lordosis,
which is an arching of her
back and she'll allow the male
to mount and mate with her.
So a large number of
experiments were done,
but the first experiment really
was to put the male mouse
in with a female mouse
who's in the so-called
receptive phase of estrus.
That is, she will allow mating
and he starts mating with her
and they go through
the standard repertoire
of mating behaviors that
you observe in mice:
mounting, thrusting,
intromission as it's called
in the mouse sex world.
Well, I guess I don't know
what the mice call it,
but that's what the experimenters call it.
And then afterwards that
he will dismount, okay.
So they observe this kind
of mounting and sex behavior
is very typical, but about
halfway through the behavior,
Dayu turned on the light to stimulate
these estrogen receptor containing neurons
only in the male mouse
and what she observed
was incredibly dramatic.
The male mouse ceases from trying to mate
with the female mouse
and immediately tries
to kill the female mouse.
He starts attacking her.
Then she turns off the
light, the male stops
and goes back to trying to
mate with the female mouse.
So I'm sure all of this was very confusing
and disturbing to the female mouse.
Nonetheless, that was the repertoire.
They would mate.
She would stimulate these
ventromedial hypothalamus neurons.
The male mouse would
immediately try and attack
and kill the female mouse.
And then she would stop the stimulation
and he would stop trying
to attack and kill
the female mouse, return
to the attempt, at least,
to mate with the female mouse.
These are such dramatic shifts in behavior
triggered only by the
activation of only the small set
of neurons within the
ventromedial hypothalamus.
And for those of you that think
that you can watch this sort of thing
without being disturbed, I
encourage you to go to YouTube.
We will provide a link
where you can see a video
of this type of behavior.
It's incredibly dramatic.
The shift in behavior
is almost instantaneous,
occurs within seconds,
if not milliseconds,
thousandths of a second.
The next experiment that she
did was to put a male mouse
with this stimulation
with light capability
in its ventromedial
hypothalamus into a cage alone,
but with a rubber glove
filled with air or water.
Mouse, walking around sniffing, peeing,
which is what male mice seem to do.
They seem to urinate
everywhere, that's actually
an interesting, perhaps
interesting feature of male mice
and actually many male
animals, perhaps even humans.
We don't know, or maybe we do know,
basically this has been an
observed time and time again
in experiments, mainly
by Lisa Stowers's lab
at the Scripps Institute,
that's characterized this.
If you put female mice
into an arena or a cage,
they always urinate in a very
small corner of that cage.
Whereas if you put mail mice
into an arena or a cage,
the urinate everywhere,
they have this obsession
with spraying their urine everywhere,
you can transpose that to
human behavior if you like.
In any event, Dayu put the
mouse in the cage alone,
but with this rubber glove,
the mouse is walking around
urinating, et cetera,
doing whatever is that mice do,
then she stimulates the activation
of these ventromedial
hypothalamus neurons,
and the mouse immediately
tries to kill the glove.
It goes into a rage, attacking the glove
as if it were another mouse
or some other animate object.
But of course it's an inanimate object.
It's just a rubber glove.
She stops the stimulation and the mouse
immediately goes back
to being completely calm
or at least not attacking.
Again, we don't know what
the mouse was feeling.
So these are very dramatic videos.
Again, you can see them
by following the link
that we'll provide in the caption.
If that sort of thing
is going to disturb you,
by to see, for instance, the attack,
one mouse attacking another,
please just don't watch them.
I'm not interested in traumatizing anybody
or you traumatizing yourself, that is.
A number of different variations
were done on this experiment.
For instance, stimulating
the VMH in female mice,
as opposed to male mice,
putting the female mice
in with other female mice
or with other male mice,
no matter what variation
one carries out, so it doesn't matter
if it's male with female, male with male,
female with female, et cetera,
stimulation of the
ventromedial hypothalamus
in a male mouse or a female
mouse evokes this very dramatic,
almost instantaneous aggressive behavior,
physically aggressive behavior.
Subsequent experiments done by Dayu Lin
in her own laboratory
and other laboratories
have shown that the ventromedial
hypothalamus connected
with a bunch of other brain
areas that are interesting,
And I'll talk about some
of those in a little bit,
but one of them that
I want to call out now
is the so-called PAG, the
periaqueductal gray nucleus.
This is a large structure
in the back of the brain
that houses things like neurons
that can create opioids.
We all know of the opioid
crisis, but these are neurons
that can produce endogenous,
means made by the body,
chemicals that can cause pain relief.
You could understand why that might occur
in a circuit for aggression, right?
Even if one is the aggressor, it's likely
that they may incur some physical damage
and they'd want some pain relief.
The PAG also is connected to a number
of neural circuits that eventually,
through several processing
stations, excuse me,
arrive at things like the jaws.
And in fact, stimulation of
the ventromedial hypothalamus
can evoke biting and
aggressive biting behavior.
Now aggressive biting behavior
is particularly interesting
because in humans and
especially in human children,
biting is something that,
while young children might do
as a form of aggression,
tends to disappear
pretty early in childhood.
And if it doesn't, it's often
seen as a mark of pathology.
I have a story about this,
actually, when I was a kid,
I went to a summer sports camp
and I'll never forget this,
so we're playing soccer and
in a rare stroke of luck
or accident, I happened to score a goal.
I wasn't a particularly
good soccer player,
especially not at that stage of my life.
They later figured out
that it was just better
to make me a fullback, 'cause
I could just wait there
and do what fullbacks do.
I was better at taking
the ball or the person out
than I was putting the ball in the goal.
Nonetheless, I, again,
by chance, scored a goal
and I was trotting back
to my side of the field,
and all of a sudden I felt
this sting in my back,
a kid, not to be named, although
I do remember your name,
I'm not going to tell
you what his name was.
A kid jumped on my back and
bit me on the top of my back.
And this of course resulted
in a discussion and a timeout
and all the usual things and
parents I think got involved.
I don't recall, I didn't
think much else of it,
but I recall that this was
considered especially troubling
behavior because he bit
me as opposed to hit me
or shoved me down or something that sort,
and it does seem as if
the tendency to use biting
as an aggressive behavior is associated
with a more primitive circuitry.
Now here I'm truly anthropomorphizing.
I don't know what this other
kid happened to be thinking
or feeling at the time, how could I?
And I certainly am not going to say
that biting in every case
reflects a pathology,
although I think there
is general agreement
in the psychology community,
in the psychiatric community
that past a certain age,
the using of one's teeth to
impart aggression and damage
on others is a particularly
primitive and troubling
or at least for the observer
or the person experiencing
is a pretty disturbing event.
Dayu's lab has shown that activation
of the ventromedial hypothalamus triggers
a downstream circuit in
the periaqueductal gray
which then triggers a whole
other set of circuits of fixed
action patterns.
Here we are back to Lorenz
with fixed action patterns,
including swinging of the
limbs, right punching.
And this wouldn't necessarily
be controlled punching,
but also biting behavior.
So it's remarkable to me,
at least that we have circuits
in our brain that can evoke
violent use of things like
our mouth or violent use of
things like our limbs.
That of course could be used
for things like singing or
kissing or eating or, you know,
gesticulating in any kind
of polite or impolite way.
The point here is that neural circuits,
not individual brain areas
evoke the constellation
of behaviors that we call aggression.
Now, many of you are probably
puzzled or at least should be
because I've been talking about
this highly specialized brain area,
the ventromedial hypothalamus
and this highly specialized
subcategory of neurons in the
ventromedial hypothalamus,
these neurons that make
estrogen receptors.
And yet the activation of those cells
triggers dramatic and
immediate aggression,
both in males and in females and both
against males and against females.
So what's going on here?
Most of us think about
estrogen and we don't
immediately think of aggression.
Most of us hear testosterone and we might
think about aggression,
although other things as well.
In order to understand this, I
just want to briefly refer back
to a conversation that I had
on a previous episode of
the Huberman Lab Podcast.
And that was with my colleague,
the great Robert Sapolsky
of course, is a professor at Stanford
who studied testosterone
and its impacts on behavior
as well as estrogen and other hormones
and their impacts on behavior.
To make a long story short and to dispel
a still unfortunately very common myth.
Testosterone does not
increase aggressiveness,
testosterone increases
proactivity and the willingness
to lean into effort in
competitive scenarios.
Sometimes this is referred to
as the challenge hypothesis,
but to make a long story short,
if people are given testosterone,
or if you look at people
who have different levels,
excuse me, of testosterone,
endogenously that they naturally make.
What you'll find is that
testosterone tends to increase
competitiveness, but not
just in aggressive scenarios.
So if somebody is already aggressive,
giving them testosterone
will have the tendency
to make them more aggressive.
If somebody however is very
benevolent and altruistic,
giving them testosterone will
make them more benevolent
and altruistic, at least up to a point.
Now, of course there are certain forms
of synthetic testosterones that
are known in sports circles
and in other circles to
increase aggressiveness
because of the way those particular forms
of synthetic testosterones work.
But in general, most of the experiments
that I'm referring to have
not been done using those,
they've been done using
the let's call them
the more traditional biological
forms of testosterone
or that resemble the biological
forms of testosterone.
In fact, Robert Sapolsky described
a really interesting experiment in which,
if you look at testosterone
levels or you administer
additional testosterone to people
who are doing philanthropy,
giving money to organizations
and so they're essentially doing good
because these are
organizations doing good.
What you find is that
increased testosterone
or further increasing
testosterone makes people
more willing to compete,
to give more money
than the other person
in the room in order,
you know, to put it in air quotes,
"To Alpha out the other
person," by giving more money.
So this is an act of altruistic
or benevolent philanthropy.
It is not an act of aggression.
Of course, we don't know what the people
are feeling underneath all that.
Again, we can't
anthropomorphize or project
onto other people what they're feeling.
But the point is that testosterone itself
does not make people more aggressive.
And in the experiments that
we've been talking about
up until now, it's actually the activation
of estrogen receptor containing neurons
that makes these animals more aggressive.
And it turns out there's
evidence that in certain context,
estrogen can make people more aggressive.
So what's going on here?
Well, what's going on is that
testosterone can be converted
into estrogen through a
process called aromatization.
There's an enzyme called aromatase.
Anytime you have word that ends in A-S-E,
at least if it's in
the context of biology,
it's almost always not always,
but almost always an enzyme.
So the aromatase enzyme converts
testosterone into estrogen,
and it is actually
testosterone, aromatized,
converted into estrogen and then binding
to these estrogen containing neurons
in the ventromedial hypothalamus
that triggers aggression.
I want to repeat that, it
is not testosterone itself,
that triggers aggression.
It is testosterone aromatized
into estrogen within the brain
and binding to these estrogen
receptor containing neurons
in the ventromedial hypothalamus
that evokes aggression
and dramatic aggression at that.
Now this effect of estrogen
causing aggression in the brain
is very robust, so much so
that if you take a mouse
that lacks the aromatase enzyme or a human
that lacks the aromatase
enzyme, and they do exist,
then there is a reduction
in overall aggression,
despite high levels of testosterone.
And if people who or mice who
have the aromatase enzyme have
that enzyme blocked, well,
then it doesn't matter
how much you increase testosterone
or any of its other derivatives.
You do not observe this aggression.
So this runs counter to
everything that we know and think
about the role of testosterone.
Again, testosterone
increases competitiveness.
It can increase the desire
to work under challenge.
I've said it before, and I ran this
or pressure tested this
against Robert Sapolsky
who's been working on
testosterone and it's role
in the brain and behavior
for many decades now.
It is fair to say that
testosterone has the net effect
of making effort feel good,
or at least increasing
the threshold at which effort
feels bad or unsustainable.
And it does that by way
of changing the activity
or the threshold for
activation of brain structures,
like the amygdala and
other brain structures
associated with anxiety.
So the next time somebody says,
testosterone makes people aggressive.
You can say, "Ah, no,
actually it's estrogen
that makes people aggressive,
and animals aggressive
for that matter.
Now of course it is the
case that because males
have relatively less estrogen circulating
in their brain and body
than females, right?
Because they have testes, not ovaries,
that testosterone is
required in the first place
in order to be converted into estrogen,
to activate this aggressive
circuit involving
these estrogen receptor containing neurons
in the ventromedial hypothalamus.
But nonetheless, it is estrogen
that is the final step.
It is the hormone on
which aggression hinges.
And I think for most people,
that's a quite surprising finding.
And yet this is perhaps one
of the more robust findings
in both the animal and human
literature, as it relates
to hormones and psychological
states and behavior.
Now, of course it is the case
that if testosterone is low,
that a person or an animal will exhibit
less aggressive behavior, but that's not
because of reduced testosterone per se.
It's because of the subsequent
reduction in testosterone,
meaning if there's no
testosterone to aromatize
into estrogen, estrogen
will also be lower.
So we've established that
it's not testosterone,
but testosterone converted into estrogen
that activates these
circuits for aggression.
But nonetheless, it's
still surprising, right?
I mean, most of us don't
think about estrogen
as the hormone that stimulates aggression,
but it turns out it's all contextual.
There are beautiful data
showing that whether or not
estrogen stimulates aggression,
can be powerfully modulated
by whether or not days are
short or days are long.
In other words, whether or not
here's a lot of sunshine or not.
Now, obviously brain is encased in skull.
So it doesn't really know
if there's a lot of sunshine
out there even though you can
see the sun with your eyes,
you can feel it on your skin.
Day length is converted
into hormonal signals
and chemical signals
and the primary hormonal
and chemical signals involve
melatonin and dopamine
and also the stress hormones.
So to make a very long story short,
in the long days where
we get a lot of sunlight,
both in our eyes and on our skin,
melatonin levels are reduced.
Melatonin is a hormone
that tends to produce
states of sleepiness and quiescence.
It also tends to activate
pathways that tend to reduce
things like breeding and sexual behavior.
In long days, dopamine is increased.
Dopamine is a molecule associated
with feelings of wellbeing
and motivation and the desire to seek out
all sorts of things, all
sorts of motivated behaviors.
And in long days provided
we're getting enough sunlight
on our skin and to our
eyes, the stress hormones,
especially cortisol, and some of the other
stress hormones are reduced in levels.
If estrogen levels are
increased experimentally
under long day conditions,
it does not evoke aggression.
However, in short days,
if estrogen is increased,
there's a heightened
predisposition for aggression.
And that makes perfect sense.
If you think about what short days do
to the biology of your brain and body.
In short days, the
melatonin signal goes up.
There's more melatonin circulating
for more of each 24 hour cycle.
Stress hormones are circulating more.
Why? Short days tend to
be associated with winter.
In winter, we are bombarded
with more bacterial viruses
because bacterial viruses actually survive
better in cold than they do in heat.
In fact, in my laboratory, we work with
a lot of viruses and
bacteria and when we want
to keep them alive, we
put them in the freezer.
If we want to kill them, if
we want to inoculate them,
we put them under UV light.
Like you would see from the sunlight.
So shorter days are
conducive to aggression.
Not because days are short per se,
but because stress
hormone levels are higher
and because dopamine levels are lower.
Now, here's where all of
this starts to converge
on a very clear biological picture,
a very clear psychological
picture, and indeed
a very clear set of tools that
we can think about and use.
Under conditions where cortisol is high,
where this stress hormone is
elevated and under conditions
where the neuromodulator
serotonin is reduced
there is a greater propensity for estrogen
to trigger aggression.
Now, again, I know I've said it before,
but for males who make
a lot of testosterone
relative to estrogen, you
have to swap in your mind
this idea that if testosterone is high,
that means that estrogen is low because
while that can be true in
the periphery in the body,
if testosterone is high,
there is going to be
some aromatization, that conversion of
testosterone to estrogen.
So anytime you hear that
testosterone is high,
you should think testosterone
is high in the body
and perhaps estrogen is low in the body.
But that means that there's
going to be heightened levels
of estrogen in the brain and therefore
increased propensity for aggression.
In females who generally
make less testosterone
relative to estrogen, there
is sufficient estrogen
already present to trigger aggression.
So both males and females
are primed for aggression,
but that's riding on a
context and that context
of whether or not you get a
tendency for aggression or not.
depends on whether or not
cortisol is high or low,
and I'm telling you that if
cortisol is relatively higher
in any individual, there's
going to be a tilt,
an increase in that hydraulic
pressure that Lorenz talked
about toward aggression.
And if serotonin, the
neuromodulator that is associated
with feelings of wellbeing and sometimes
even of slight passivity,
but certainly of wellbeing,
if serotonin is low, there's
also going to be a further shift
towards an aggressive tendency.
So if we return to Lorenz's
hydraulic pressure model
of aggression in other internal states,
we realize that external
stimuli, things that we hear,
things that we see, for instance,
someone saying something upsetting or us,
seeing somebody do something
that we don't like to others
or to us, as well as our internal state,
our subjective feelings of wellbeing,
but also our stress level,
our feelings of whether or
not we have enough resources
and are content with what we have.
All of that is converging on this thing
that we call internal state and creating
this pressure of either to be
more aggressive or less aggressive.
And now we have some major players feeding
into that final pathway.
That question of whether or not
will we hit the other,
person, will we say the thing
that is considered aggressive?
Will we not say it?
If somebody says something
or does something
aggressive to us, will
we respond or will we be
submissive or even passive?
Again, there are many things
funneling into that question
and dictating whether
or not the answer is,
"Absolutely I'll fight back,"
or, "I'm going to attack
them even unprovoked."
Or if they say this, I'm going to do that,
or no matter what they do,
I'm not going to respond.
These kinds of things are very complex.
And yet we really can boil them down
to just a few common elements.
And I'm telling you that those
elements are whether or not
cortisol levels are relatively
lower or relatively higher.
Again, relatively higher is going to tend
to make people more reactive.
Why?
Because reactivity is really a function
of the autonomic nervous system,
which is sort of like a
seesaw that oscillates
between the so-called sympathetic arm
of the autonomic nervous system,
which tends to put us
into a state of readiness
through the release of adrenaline.
Cortisol and adrenaline
when they're circulating
the brain and body, make
us more likely to move
and to react and to speak.
It's actually what will induce
a kind of low level tremor,
which is an anticipatory tremor to be able
to move more quickly, right?
A body in motion is more
easily set into further motion,
that is, and the neuromodulator serotonin
is a neuromodulator that
in general is associated
with feelings of wellbeing in response
to what we already have.
So when we are well fed,
serotonin tends to be released
in our brain and body,
in particular, well
fed with carbohydrates,
the precursor to serotonin is tryptophan.
And indeed there are nice studies
exploring the types of
diets, nutritional programs
that can reduce aggressive
behavior, both in children
and in adults and tryptophan-rich diets
or supplementation with tryptophan.
So for tryptophan rich diets,
things like white turkey meat,
but then there are also
a number of carbohydrates
you can look up.
It's very easy to find foods
that contain lots of tryptophan.
Those foods contain the
precursor to serotonin.
Now it isn't simply the
case that eating more foods
with tryptophan will tend
to reduce your aggression.
I suppose it could do that,
if you ate it in abundance,
it could make you tired
and then you're less likely
to be aggressive, I don't
recommend that strategy,
but the idea here is that
when it's been explored,
increasing levels of tryptophan
either by supplementation
or by food or drugs, prescription drugs
that increase serotonin.
So for instance, fluoxetine
sometimes called Prozac
or Zoloft or any number of the other SSRIs
tend to reduce aggressive behavior.
Now, not always, but in
general, that's the case.
Similarly, because elevated cortisol tends
to shift the whole
system, again, create more
of a hydraulic pressure
towards aggressive states.
If cortisol levels are
reduced, well then the tendency
for aggressive behavior is reduced.
This is supported by a number
of peer reviewed studies.
We'll provide links to some of those
in the caption show notes.
And we're going to return to
these a bit later in the context
of specific studies that have
looked at genetic variants
in different individuals that cause them
to make more or less serotonin,
or at least to metabolize
serotonin differently.
This is also the case for so-called
intermittent explosive disorder
that can often be associated
with gene variants that control
how much serotonin is made
or how it's metabolized or
how much cortisol is made
and how much it's metabolized.
In thinking about tools
that are a number of things
that one could consider.
First of all, there are a
number of decent studies
exploring how supplementation
with the Omega-3 fatty acids,
which are precursors of some
of the transmitter systems,
including serotonin that can
modulate not directly mediate,
but modulate mood and emotional
tone supplementation with
the omega 3 S has been shown
to reduce impulsivity and
aggressiveness in certain
contexts in things like ADHD
or in individuals who
have a predisposition
for aggressive type behavior
or aggressive thinking.
Now that doesn't necessarily
mean that the omega 3
fatty acids are going directly
to the ventromedial hypothalamus
and changing the activity
of neurons there more likely they are
causing or modulating
an overall shift in mood
through the immune system,
through hormone systems that are
changing the overall tone or
the propensity for neurons
in the ventromedial
hypothalamus to be activated.
How much omega 3 fatty acid, what source?
Well, we've talked about
this on the podcast before.
You can, of course get omega 3 fatty acids
from a number of different foods.
Getting them from whole foods
is probably the best way
to do it, but many people,
including people with depression
will often supplement
with one gram or more
of omega 3 fatty acid per day.
Some people including myself
will take them every day
as just a general mood enhancer.
I don't suffer from depression,
but I've found it be
beneficial for my health.
And so some people do that,
and I've talked about before,
how in double blind
placebo controlled studies,
people taking one to three
grams of omega 3 fatty acids
per day, typically in the form
of a high quality fish oil,
although there are other sources as well,
algae and so forth, can
experience improvements in mood
that are on par with some of the SSRIs,
the selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors.
And of course, if you're
prescribed an SSRI
by your psychiatrist or other
doctor, please do take that
and don't cease to take it
just simply to take omega 3s.
However you might mention to
them, and you can find links
to the studies in our previous
episodes on depression
that supplementation
with omega 3 fatty acids
of at this one gram or
more of EPA specifically,
so getting above that one gram threshold,
as high as three grams per day
of the EPA has allowed people
to take lower doses of SSRIs
and still keep their mood
in a place that's beneficial for them.
And in terms of keeping cortisol
in a range that's healthy
and doesn't bias someone toward
high levels of aggression
and irritability, that's
again, going to be set
by a number of larger
modulators or contextual cues.
And I've talked about some
of those on the podcast,
but I'll just briefly recap them now,
obviously getting sunlight in
your eyes early in the day,
and as much sunlight as
you safely can in your eyes
throughout the day is
going to be important.
Again, because of this effect
of estrogen in long days,
not increasing aggression,
however, in shorter days,
estrogen increases aggression
because of the increase
in cortisol observed in short days.
Another way to reduce cortisol
was discussed in our episode
on heat and the use of sauna
and heat, but also hot baths.
It turns out that hot baths and sauna
can be very beneficial
for reducing cortisol.
All the details on that are
included in the episode on heat
and it's timestamped, so
you can go directly to that
if you want to learn
about the temperatures
and the various durations,
but to just give
a synopsis of that, a 20
minute sauna at anywhere
from 80 to a hundred degrees
Celsius is going to be
beneficial for reducing cortisol.
If you don't have access to a sauna,
you could do a hot bath,
adjust the temperature
so you don't burn yourself.
I think 80 to a hundred degrees Celsius
is going to be too hot for many people
if it's a hot bath, whereas
many people who can't tolerate
that hot bath can tolerate the sauna.
So safety first always, and of course,
but hot baths reduce cortisol,
hot saunas, reduce cortisol
of a duration about 20 or 30
minutes is going to be beneficial.
And of course, some of you
may be interested in exploring
the supplementation route and
for reductions in cortisol,
really the chief player
there is ashwagandha,
which is known to decrease
cortisol, fairly potently.
I should just warn you
that if you're going to use
ashwagandha in order to
reduce cortisol, first of all,
check with your doctor
or healthcare provider
before adding or subtracting anything
from your supplementation
or health regimen.
Of course, I don't just
say that to protect us.
I say that to protect you,
you are responsible for your health,
what you take and what you don't take.
Chronic supplementation with
ashwagandha can have some
not so great effects of disruption
of other hormone pathways
and neurotransmitter pathways.
So the limit seems to be
about two weeks of regular use
before you'd want to take
a break of about two weeks.
So ashwagandha again, a very
potent inhibitor of cortisol,
but with some other effects as well,
don't use it chronically
for longer than two weeks.
But if your goal is to reduce cortisol,
let's say you're going
through a period of increased
irritability and aggressive tendency,
maybe you're also not
getting as much light
as you would like, and
perhaps also, if there are
other circumstantial
things leading you towards
more aggressiveness and
your goal is to reduce
aggressiveness, that can
be potentially helpful.
And in light of all this stuff
about cortisol and estrogen
and day length, I should
mention that there are in fact,
some people who have a
genetic predisposition
to be more irritable and aggressive,
and there are a couple of
different gene pathways
associated with this.
We never like to think about just one gene
causing a specific behavior.
The way to think about genes
is that genes generally code
for things within our biology.
In the context of today's
discussion, things like
neural circuits or the
amounts of neurotransmitters
that are made, or the amounts
of hormones that are made,
or the amount of neurotransmitter
hormone receptors
or enzymes, et cetera,
that shift the activity
of our biology in a particular direction.
They bias our biology.
And in fact, there is a
genetic variant present
in certain people that adjusts
their estrogen receptor sensitivity,
and that estrogen receptor
sensitivity can result
in increased levels of aggression,
sometimes dramatic increases, however,
and also very interestingly, photo period,
meaning day length, is a strong
modulator of whether or not
that aggressiveness turns up or not.
Whether or not that person with
the particular gene variant
is more aggressive or not,
depends on how long the day is
and how long the night is.
One particular study that
I like that references this
is Trainer, et al, the
title of the study is
"Photo period reverses
the effects of estrogens
on male aggression, via genomic
and non-genomic pathways."
This was a paper published
in the proceedings
of the National Academy of Sciences.
We'll put a reference to
this in the show notes,
if you'd like to explore it further,
but it really points to the
fact that rarely, sometimes,
but rarely, is it the
case that just one gene
will cause somebody to
be hyper aggressive.
Almost always there's
going to be an interplay
between genetics and environment
and as environment changes
such as day length changes and
the length of night changes,
so too, will the tendency for people
with a given genetic variant
to be more aggressive or not.
Now, of course, in the absence
of detailed genetic testing
for this particular
estrogen receptor variant,
most people, I'm guessing
you, are probably
not walking around knowing
that you have this gene or not.
Regardless, I think it's
important to pay attention
to how you feel at
different times of year,
depending on whether or not summer,
whether or not it's winter,
whether or not you're
getting sufficient sunlight,
meaning viewing sufficient
sunlight or not,
whether or not you're getting
sufficient sunlight exposure
to your skin or not, whether or not
you're indoors all the time.
Generally those things
correlate with season,
but not always.
You can go through long bouts of hard work
in the summer months when days are long,
but you're indoors a lot and
getting a lot of fluorescent
light exposure late in the evening.
And perhaps that's when you're
feeling more aggressive.
So we have to be careful
about drawing a one-to-one
relationship between
any biological feature
and certainly psychological
or behavioral feature
like aggressiveness, but
it's, I believe, helpful
to know that these genetic biases exist,
how they play out again,
they shift our biology
in a general thematic direction.
They don't change one thing.
They change a variety of things
that bias us toward or away
from certain psychological
and behavioral outcomes
and the various things that we can do
in order to offset them.
And we described those
earlier in terms of trying
to keep cortisol low by
getting sufficient sunlight
regardless of time of year, and
regardless of whether or not
you happen to have this
particular genetic variant.
So earlier I talked about
how it is testosterone
converted into estrogen
that's activating aggression
in the ventromedial hypothalamus,
not testosterone itself.
However, there are some
studies carried out in humans
that have evaluated the
effects of testosterone
and how levels of testosterone
correlate with aggressiveness
in the short term.
I'm just going to detail
a few of those studies
because I think they are
interesting and important.
First of all, there is a
study that has explored
levels of testosterone in
men of different professions.
Now, before I tell you the data,
I want to be very clear here,
with a study such as this,
one never knows whether or not these men
went into a particular profession because
they had a testosterone
level of a given value
or whether or not the work itself
altered their testosterone levels or both.
And I think it's fair to
assume that it's probably both.
So be very careful in assuming
that a given testosterone
level is causal for
choosing a particular career
or that a particular career is causal
for creating a particular
testosterone level.
This study used salivary
testosterone levels
as the measure, which to
be fair is not the best way
to measure testosterone.
Typically blood draw would be the best way
to measure testosterone,
but nonetheless, provided
the appropriate methods are
used, salivary testosterone
can be a reasonable
measure of testosterone.
The different occupations
that were looked at were,
and here they just looked at
men in this particular study
were ministers, salesmen, they didn't say
what particular types
of salesmen, firemen,
professors, of all things,
physicians and NFL players.
And what they discovered was
that the testosterone levels
were essentially in that
order from low to highest.
So minister, salesman, fireman,
professor, physician, NFL player.
Now we could micro dissect
all the different stereotypes
and all the different features
of each of these jobs.
For instance, we don't know
whether or not the fact
that the firemen happened,
at least in this study
to have lower testosterone
levels on average
than the professors or the physicians
was because firemen have
lower testosterone levels
or because they have a
much more stressful job
and their cortisol levels
are higher than the professor
or the physician and cortisol
and testosterone, not always,
but generally are in somewhat
antagonistic push-pull mode
because they derive from the
same precursor, et cetera.
Typically, when cortisol is high,
testosterone tends to
be lower and vice versa.
So we don't know what's
causing these effects.
And again, this is just one
study and just six occupations,
but I think it's relatively
interesting given the fact
that each of these professions
involves different levels
of competitiveness, right?
So we don't necessarily
just want to think about
the level of physical
exertion that's required,
but also the level of
competitiveness because it's known
that competitive interactions
can cause increases
in testosterone, in
particular, in the winners
of competitive interactions,
a topic for a future podcast.
Meanwhile, studies that
have analyzed also again,
salivary testosterone in
prisoners, in this case,
female prisoners, so these
are incarcerated individuals,
have looked at levels of testosterone
according to whether or
not the person committed
a non-violent or a violent crime in order
to arrive in prison.
And higher levels of salivary
testosterone were related
to those that had arrived in prison
because of conviction of a violent crime,
as opposed to a nonviolent crime.
Likewise, when they analyzed
prison rule violations,
so an indirect measure of
aggressiveness, but in this case,
it was strongly associated
with aggressiveness
because they knew what
the violations were,
they found were for
prisoners that had none,
no prison violations, prison
rule violations I should say,
their testosterone
levels tended to be lower
than the testosterone levels
of women that had some,
even one, or more aggressive
violations of prison rules.
We'll provide links to these
studies in the show notes
if you'd like to go into them further,
obviously studies like
this need to be taken
with a grain of salt
because there are so many
different factors, different
prisons have different degrees
of violence to begin with and
competitiveness to begin with.
But just as a final pass
at examining the role
between testosterone and aggressiveness,
there was a very interesting
study from Goetz, et al,
G-O-E-T-Z published in
2014, that looked at serum,
so in this case, blood
levels of testosterone.
30 minutes after application
of a gel-based testosterone
that goes transdermal
so that the testosterone
can go very quickly into the bloodstream,
and then did brain imaging
to evaluate the activity
of neurons in the so-called
corticomedial amygdala,
the cortico, the medial
amygdala is one of the areas
of the amygdala complex as we
call it because it's complex,
it's got a lot of different nuclei,
you know, know what nuclei
are, low clusters of neurons.
It's got a lot of different
ones, but that medial
and that cortico medial
amygdala in particular,
is known to be associated with
aggressive type behaviors.
It's linked up with as part
of the larger circuit that
includes the ventromedial
hypothalamus and other brain areas
that we referred to
earlier, such as the PAG.
What is remarkable about this
study is that it showed that
just 30 minutes after
application of this so-called
AndroGel, this testosterone that seeps
into the bloodstream,
there was a significant
increase in of course, testosterone
and corticomedial amygdala activation.
So testosterone can have acute effects,
immediate effects on the
pathways related to aggression.
And I think this is something
that's not often discussed
because many of the
effects of steroid hormones
like testosterone, and
estrogen are very slow acting.
In fact, steroid hormones,
because they have a certain
biochemical composition can actually pass
through the membranes of
cells, so the outside of a cell
and into the nucleus of the cell
and change gene expression in the cell,
you think about puberty,
the kid that goes home
for the summer and then comes back
looking completely different.
Well that's because of a
lot of genes got turned on
by steroid hormones like
testosterone and estrogen,
but the steroid hormones can also
have very fast acting
effects and with testosterone
in particular, those can
be remarkably fast acting
and one of the most apparent
and well documented fast acting
effects is this effect: the
ability to activate cells within
the amygdala, so you might say,
"Well, I thought the amygdala
was associated with fear?"
Wouldn't testosterone then cause fear? No.
Turns out that the amygdala
harbors, both cortisol,
corticosteroid receptors
and testosterone receptors,
and they each adjust the activity
in the amygdala differently,
such that testosterone tends
to activate amygdala circuitry
for inducing states of mind and body
that are more action based
and indeed in animals
and in humans, testosterone
application and activation
of this corticomedial amygdala pathway
will make animals and
humans lean into effort.
This is why I say testosterone
makes effort feel good,
or at least biases the organism
toward leaning into challenge.
So if you recall, there's not
just one type of aggression,
there's reactive aggression,
which is triggered when one
is confronted with something
that sometimes is inevitable, right?
One needs to fight for their life
or for somebody else's life,
but also proactive aggression
and proactive aggression
involves activation
of those go-pathways in the basal ganglia
and a leaning into effort to overcome
whatever state one happens
to be in to begin with.
And so this is very important
because it points to the fact
that yes, estrogen is
activating aggression pathways
that are in the ventromedial hypothalamus,
but it's very likely the case
that testosterone is acting
to accelerate or to bias
states of mind and body
toward those that will lead to aggression.
Again, aggression is not
like a switch, on and off.
It's a process.
It has a beginning, a middle and an end.
Remember that hydraulic pressure
that Conrad Lorenz hypothesized?
Well, think of testosterone
as increasing the pressure
toward an aggressive
episode and then estrogen
actually triggering
that aggressive episode
in the ventromedial hypothalamus.
So if somebody tells
you that testosterone,
endogenous or exogenous
makes people aggressive,
tell them no, testosterone tends to make
people lean into effort.
And if that effort
involves being aggressive,
either reactively aggressive
or proactively aggressive,
well then it will indeed
lead to aggression.
But the actual aggression
itself is triggered by estrogen,
not testosterone.
Now, thus far, we really
haven't talked too much
about the social context
in which aggression occurs.
And that's because there
is a near infinite,
if not infinite number of variables
that will determine that.
So for instance, violent
aggression is entirely appropriate
at a professional boxing match provided
it's occurring inside the ring and only
between the competitors
and within the bounds
of the rules of the sport, et cetera.
However, there are some
things that tend to bias
certain social context
toward being more aggressive
or less aggressive and not
always physical aggression.
And those generally come in two forms
that many of you are familiar with,
which are alcohol and caffeine.
Let's discuss caffeine first.
Why would caffeine increase
aggressive impulsivity?
Well, the general effects of caffeine
are to increase autonomic arousal.
The activity of the
so-called sympathetic arm
of the autonomic nervous system,
which is to put it very
much in plain language
it's the alertness arm
of your nervous system.
That is, it creates a sense of readiness
in your brain and body and
it does so by activating
the so-called sympathetic chain ganglia.
Again, as I always remind people,
simpa and sympathetic
does not mean sympathy.
Simpa means together, we're all at ones.
And caffeine tends to
bias our brain and body
to activate the sympathetic chain ganglia,
which run from about the base of your neck
until the top of your pelvis
and deploy a bunch of chemicals
that jut out into the rest of your body,
activate adrenaline release.
There's a parallel increase in
of adrenaline in your brain,
creating the state of
alertness and readiness.
That state of alertness
and readiness can be
for all sorts of things,
not just aggression.
However when we are in
a state of increased
sympathetic tone, meaning more alert,
such as after drinking caffeine,
we will bias all those brain
and body systems, the hormones,
the chemicals, et cetera that exist,
toward action as opposed to inaction.
So put simply, caffeine
can increase impulsivity,
no surprise there.
On the opposite end of things,
alcohol tends to decrease
activity in the sympathetic
arm of the autonomic
nervous system, tends to
make us feel less alert.
Now, initially it can
create a state of alertness
because of its effects in
inhibiting the forebrain,
our forebrain prefrontal
cortex in particular
has what's called top-down inhibition.
It exerts a inhibitory
or a quieting effect
on some of the circuits
of the hypothalamus,
such as the ventromedial hypothalamus.
The way to conceptualize
this is that your forebrain
is able to rationalize and think clearly
and to suppress behavior and
to engage the no-go pathways
telling you, "Don't say that mean thing."
"Don't do that violent thing," et cetera.
Alcohol initially tends
to increase our level
of overall activity by
reducing inhibition,
not just in that forebrain
circuit, but in other circuits.
Tends to make us more active.
We tend to talk more
than we normally would,
move more than we normally would,
but very shortly thereafter
starts acting as a sedative
by way of reducing
activity in the forebrain,
releasing some of the
deeper brain circuits
that are involved in impulsivity,
but also causing a
somewhat sedative effect.
And then of course, as alcohol
levels increase even further,
people eventually will pass
out, blackout, et cetera.
So what we've got with
alcohol and caffeine
is we've got two opposite
ends of the spectrum,
caffeine increasing arousal and readiness,
and the tendency for impulsivity
and alcohol also increasing
impulsivity, but through
a different mechanism.
A really interesting study,
and I should just mention
that the title of the study is,
"Caffeinated and
non-caffeinated alcohol use
and indirect aggression at the
impact of self-regulation."
So the title is almost self-explanatory.
This was a paper published
in the Journal of Addictive
Behavior in 2016, examining
how ingestion of alcohol
that's either caffeinated
or non-decaffeinated
alcohol drinks impacted what
they call indirect aggression.
And just to remind you what
indirect aggression is,
these are not physical acts of aggression.
These are verbal acts of aggression,
so embarrassing others or otherwise,
somehow trying to reduce
the wellbeing of others
by saying certain things
in particular in groups,
this study examined
both males and females.
This was done on by way
of a college campus study,
subjects were 18 to 47 years old.
I guess there's some older
students on that campus,
or maybe they use some
non-students, but you know,
these days you've also got some students
that are in their thirties and forties.
So they have a fairly broad
swath of subjects included,
fairly broad racial
background as well, included,
not at equal numbers, but
at least they included
a pretty broad spectrum of people
with different backgrounds.
They looked in particular
people that ingested
non-caffeinated alcohol
drinks at a frequency
of 9.18 drinks per week, okay.
Again, there's a college campus,
not that I encourage that.
I'm one of these people that I don't,
I've never really liked drugs or alcohol
and sort fortunate in that
way I can drink or not drink
and tend to not drink.
But so to me, 9.18, drinks
per week sounds like a lot,
but I know for some people
that might actually be typical.
And then others who are drinking at least
one caffeinated alcoholic
beverage per week.
And those individuals end as high,
I should say as 7.87 caffeinated
alcohol beverages per week.
So this would be energy drinks combined,
typically with hard alcohol,
that's fairly commonly
available in bars and so forth.
And some individuals
drank as much as goodness,
20.36 alcoholic drinks per week, total,
some that were caffeinated,
some that were not caffeinated.
The basic outcome of this study was that
the more alcohol someone
tended to consume,
the more likely it was
that they would engage
in these indirect
aggressive type behaviors.
And in terms of the caffeinated
alcoholic beverages,
there, the effect was
especially interesting.
Here I'm just going to
paraphrase or I'll actually
read from the study, quote,
"With regard to caffeinated
alcoholic beverage use,
our findings indicated
that heavier caffeinated
alcohol beverage use
was associated positively
with indirect aggression,
even after considering
one's typical alcohol use
and dispositional aggression."
What this means is that
even though alcohol
can bias certain individuals
to be more aggressive,
and even though certain
individuals already have
a disposition toward
being more aggressive,
there was an effect that was independent,
meaning above and beyond both
alcohol and a predisposition,
meaning if someone was consuming
caffeinated alcoholic beverages, they had
a particularly high likelihood of engaging
in indirect aggressive behavior.
Now this makes perfect
sense in light of the model
they propose, which is
this self-regulation model,
that basically self-regulation
involves several things.
It involves engaging in certain behaviors
and suppressing other behaviors.
So as described before,
because alcohol tends to have
a sedative suppressive
effect on the autonomic
nervous system, at least
after the initial period,
it's going to tend to
reduce the likelihood
that people will engage
in any type of behavior.
Whereas caffeine will
increase autonomic arousal
and increase the likelihood
that someone will engage
in a particular type of behavior,
aggressive or otherwise.
So the combination of caffeine
and alcohol is really acting
as a two prong system
to bias people towards
more impulsivity that
is less self-regulation.
So it's really yanking
your volitional control,
your ability to engage in
prefrontal top down inhibition
over your hypothalamus from two distinct
and specific circuits.
By now, you should be
getting the impression
that self-regulation is a key feature
of whether or not
somebody, maybe even you,
is going to engage in aggressive speech
or aggressive behavior.
And we've talked about a number
of tools that one can use
to reduce the probability
that that will happen.
I suppose, if the
context were appropriate,
you could even take those
tool recommendations
and just invert them and
increase the likelihood
that aggressiveness would happen.
But regardless, self-regulation is key.
And in light of that, I want
to share with you a study
that's focused on kids, but
that has important ramifications
for adults as well.
As you probably are already
aware there are many kids
out there that suffer from so-called
attention deficit
hyperactivity, disorder, ADHD.
There are also many adults we are finding
that are suffering from ADHD.
And there's also an epidemic
I would say of people
that are concerned about
whether or not they have ADHD.
Now whether or not they have true,
clinical ADHD or not, is not clear.
We did an episode all about
ADHD and tools for ADHD.
I would encourage you to
check out that episode
and some of the diagnostic criteria.
If you have the opportunity you
can find at hubermanlab.com,
as this study I'm about to
share with you aptly points out,
there is no objective
diagnostic marker of ADHD.
There's no biomarker or blood
draw or blood test for ADHD,
whether or not one has ADHD
depends on their performance
on a number of different cognitive tests
and behavioral tests and self report.
In any event, the study
I'm about to share with you
explored how a particular
pattern of supplementation
in kids with ADHD was able
to reduce aggressive episodes
and impulsivity and
increased self-regulation.
And the title of the study is,
"Efficacy of carnitine in
the treatment of children
with attention deficit,
hyperactivity disorder."
Even though they put
carnitine in the title,
that what they focused
on was whether or not
acetyl-L-carnitine
supplementation could somehow
adjust the behavioral tendency
of these kids with ADHD
and to make a long story
short, indeed it did.
There was a very significant
effect of acetyl L-carnitine
supplementation on improving
some of the symptomology,
excuse me, of ADHD.
A few details about this study
that might be relevant to you.
This was a randomized double
blind placebo controlled double
crossover study, this was
done as an outpatient study.
So the kids weren't in a hospital,
they were living out in the world.
This again was done on younger kids.
So this was six to six to 13 year old kids
that were diagnosed with ADHD.
They received either acetyl
L-carnitine or placebo,
and they did all the good practice stuff
that good researchers do of making sure
that the placebo and
the acetyl L-carnitine
had similar look and taste.
It was consumed twice daily after meals.
I should just mentioned
that acetyl L-carnitine
typically is taken in
capsule form or occasionally
an injectable form.
Here, they they were
using this as a drink,
which essentially the
same as capsule form,
but the powders just
going directly into liquid
and the carnitine dosage was
100 milligrams per kilogram.
So they're doing this
according to the body weight
of these kids with a maximum
dosage of four grams per day,
the quantity of the
medication was supplied here.
I'm reading for a period of
eight weeks and every eight
weeks a new quantity of
medication was supplied.
So basically this is a
fairly long term study,
exploring behavioral outcomes
and psychological outcomes
in week eight, 16 and 24.
They also looked at blood
things that you could only get
through a blood draw, so things
like hemoglobin, hematocrit,
red blood cell count, white
blood cell count, et cetera,
they, these are kids and
even if it were adults,
they were quite appropriately examining
a lot of the physiological measures
that one would want to
carry out to make sure,
first of all, that blood levels
of carnitine are increasing.
And indeed they confirmed
that, but also that
no negative effects are
showing up in the physiology
as well as the psychology of these kids.
So, first I'll just tell you
the basic outcome of the study,
which was, here I'm paraphrasing,
"Here, given twice
daily, carnitine appeared
to be effective and well tolerated
treatment for a group
of children with ADHD."
"They showed significant,
the abnormal behavior
compared to these other boys."
And now I'm moving to
the table of results.
They showed significant reductions
in their so-called "Total Problem Score."
The total problem score is
a well-established measure
of behavioral problems in kids with ADHD.
And I should say adults with ADHD,
has to do with challenges
in social and learning
environments and how well or poorly
an individual tends to perform.
Reductions in intentional
problems, overall reductions
in delinquency, and most important
for sake of today's discussion,
significant reductions
in aggressive behavior.
Now what's especially nice
about this study, I think,
is that even though it's
a relatively small number
of subjects and certainly
needs to be repeated
in other studies and other laboratories,
that they were able to confirm
the shifts in L-carnitine
within the bloodstream of these kids,
that is they were able to
correlate the physiology
with the psychological
changes, in studies like this.
And frankly in all studies
of human pharmacology,
you have to worry about
effects that show up,
not just because of placebo effects,
but because of so-called
off target effects
or related things, totally
independent of the drug
or the particular
supplement that you happen
to be looking at,
to put in the words of
a great neuroscientist.
Unfortunately, he passed
away some years ago,
but he was a member of
the national academy,
extremely accomplished
neuroscientist once turned to me
and said, "Never forget
a drug is a substance
that when injected into
an animal or a human being
creates a paper," meaning you
can see effects of pretty much
any drug or any supplement
in most all conditions.
However, it is in cases
such as this study,
where you can quite convincingly
see that the particular
feature of physiology that
you expected to change,
actually changed.
And you see a psychological outcome
that you can gain much greater
confidence that the changes
in delinquency, in this
case reduced delinquency,
improved attention, reduced
aggressiveness and so forth
was at least somehow related to the shift
in blood physiology and
levels of L-carnitine
or acetyl L-carnitine and
carnitine in the bloodstream
of these children, as
opposed to something else
like L-carnitine going and
affecting some downstream target
that you have no knowledge of.
Now, of course that's
still entirely possible,
but I think studies such as
these increase our confidence
that things like L-carnitine can be used
perhaps in concert with things
like omega 3 supplementation,
diets that are biased towards
increasing more tryptophan
and therefore more serotonin,
obviously avoiding things like alcohol
and as it appears from the
study I just described,
reducing one's intake or not consuming
any caffeinated alcoholic
beverages seems like
it would be a good idea if your goal is
to reduce aggressiveness, to
think about the hormone context
and whether or not you tend
to have higher testosterone,
an estrogen or lower
testosterone, an estrogen,
maybe even think about
the work environment,
whether or not you are
existing in a particularly
competitive work environment
and even day life,
time of year and whether or not
you're getting sufficient
sunlight, whether or not
you're avoiding light in
the evening and so on.
So studies such as this I think are useful
because they point to the fact
that very seldom, if ever,
will there be one supplement
or one nutritional change
or even one behavioral change,
that's going to completely
shift in individual
from being aggressive and impulsive,
but rather that by combining
different behavioral regimens,
by paying attention to
things like time of year
and work conditions and school conditions
and overall levels of
stress and likely therefore
levels of cortisol, et cetera,
that you can use behaviors,
diet, and supplementation
as a way to shift that overall
internal milieu from one
of providing a lot of
internal hydraulic pressure
as it's been called throughout the episode
toward aggressive impulsivity and relax
some of that hydraulic pressure
and reduce aggressive tendencies.
So once again, and frankly, as always,
we've done a deep dive
into the neurobiology
and the psychology of what I believe to be
an important feature of our
lives, in this case aggression.
I want to point out that in a episode
in the not too distant future,
I'm going to be hosting
Dr. Professor David Anderson
from Caltech University,
who is the world expert on the
neurobiology of aggression.
In fact, he is the senior
author on many of the studies
related to the ventromedial hypothalamus
that I discussed today.
Our discussion will touch
on aggression, of course.
So hearing today's episode will help you
digest that information, but
we are also going to talk
about other emotional states.
He is an expert, not just in aggression,
but in motivated states related
to sex and mating behavior,
social relationships of all
kinds and how those relate,
not just to biology and psychology,
but also certain forms of pathology,
things like PTSD and the
relationship for instance,
between anger, fear,
anxiety, and depression,
and many other important
topics that I know many of you,
if not all of you will be interested in.
In the meantime, I want to point you
to his recently released
and wonderful book entitled,
"The Nature of the Beast,
How Emotions Guide Us."
And again, the author is
David Anderson from Caltech.
This is a wonderful book.
It serves as a tremendous introduction
to the history of the
study of these areas,
the current science and
discoveries being made
in these areas, all made
accessible to the scientist
and non-scientist alike.
It's a very engaging read and so much so
that even though he was
gracious in sending me a copy,
I also purchased myself a
copy to give to somebody
who is a therapist, and
I've purchased another copy
to give to a high school kid that I mentor
because he's very interested
in the neuroscience of emotions.
And I think we are all
interested in emotions,
not just fear and some
of these negative states,
not just aggression, but
also the positive emotions
of our lives.
And so, "The Nature of the
Beast, How Emotions Guide Us,"
by David Anderson is a wonderful read.
I can't recommend it highly enough.
If you're learning from and
or enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel.
That's a terrific zero
cost way to support us.
In addition, please
subscribe to our podcast
on Apple and Spotify.
And on Apple, you have the
opportunity to leave us
up to a five star review.
Also, if there are any
episodes of the podcast
that you particularly like,
please share them with others.
And if you have suggestions
about particular guests
or topics that you'd like
us to cover on the podcast,
please put that in the
comment section on YouTube,
we do read all those comments.
Please also check out
the sponsors mentioned
at the beginning of today's episode,
that is the best way to
support this podcast.
We also have a Patreon it's
patreon.com/andrewhuberman
and there you can support the podcast
at any level that you like.
During today's episode and
on many previous episodes
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we discussed supplements.
While supplements aren't
necessary for everybody,
many people derive
tremendous benefit from them,
for things like improving
the transition time
and the quality of your sleep
and improving alertness and focus.
And so on.
Anytime you're considering
taking supplements,
there are several key considerations.
First of all, those supplements should be
of the very highest quality.
And you want to make sure that
what's listed on the bottle
is actually what's in the bottle,
which is a problem for any
supplement companies out there.
The Huberman Lab Podcast
is pleased to announce
that we are now partnered
with Momentous supplements
because we believe
Momentous supplements to be
of the very highest quality
of any supplements out there.
And we've been working
very closely with them
in order to direct them,
to create supplements
that are individual ingredient supplements
of the particular quality and sources
that we would like to see,
and that relate to the
science and studies covered
on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
If you'd like to see some
of those supplements,
you can go to livemomentous.com/huberman,
and there you'll see
some of the supplements
that we've talked about
on this podcast before
such as magnesium threonate
for augmenting sleep,
things like L-tyrosine
for augmenting dopamine
and things like L-carnitine,
which we've discussed
on today's podcast.
Right now, the list of
supplements and the products
that are there is only partial to what
will soon be included in the future.
So that's an ever expanding
catalog of, again,
what we believe to be
the very highest quality
supplements available to you.
For those of you that are
interested in behavioral,
nutritional and supplementation
based tools for neuroscience
and other aspects of
your biology, the impact,
your health and performance,
we have a newsletter.
It is a zero cost newsletter.
It's called "The Neural
Network Newsletter."
You can go to hubermanlab.com
and there in the menu,
you'll find "The Neural
Network Newsletter" sign-up.
You can just put your email.
We do not share your
email with anybody else.
You will also find
examples of the newsletter
that you can download right
away without having to sign up
and decide if signing up is right for you.
And if you're not already following us
on Twitter an Instagram,
we are Huberman Lab on
both Instagram and Twitter.
And at both places,
I describe science and
science based tools,
some of which overlaps with the content
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
but much of which is
distinct from the content
of the Huberman Lab Podcast.
Once again, thank you for
joining me for our discussion
about the biology, psychology
and actionable tools
around aggression, and as always,
thank you for your interest in science.
[inspirational music]