- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science based tools
for everyday life.
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today we are discussing nicotine.
Nicotine is one of the most
commonly consumed substances
on the entire planet.
There are literally billions of people
that ingest nicotine on a daily basis.
Most of those people consume
nicotine via smoking,
and in particular smoking tobacco.
Tobacco contains nicotine and it
contains a bunch of other things as well,
which we will talk about.
And the burning of tobacco
liberates nicotine and makes it
accessible to the various
cells and tissues of the body.
But of course, there are other
sources of nicotine as well.
Some people consume nicotine through dip,
that is placing tobacco on the inside
of the lip or in the cheek.
Some people consume nicotine via snuff,
which is literally the
shoving of tobacco leaves
up the nostrils and allowing the tobacco
to access the nervous
system and other areas
of the body by permeating into the
mucosal membranes, that is the lining,
the soft lining of the nasal passages.
And of course there are
nicotine patches, nicotine gum,
there's nicotine in pill form,
there are toothpicks dipped
in nicotine, et cetera.
Today we are going to separate
our discussion of nicotine
from a discussion of smoking and vaping
and the other forms of
delivery for nicotine.
We will be talking
about smoking and vaping
and other routes of
nicotine administration,
both for sake of highlighting
their detriments to health
and, believe it or not, in certain cases,
keep in mind very specific certain cases,
the possible health benefits
of delivering nicotine
through specific modalities.
Turns out those modalities do not
include smoking cigarettes or vaping.
And we are going to pay particular
attention to vaping today
because vaping use is on the rise,
in particular in young
people, and vaping use,
and the fact that most
tobacco that's consumed
through vaping includes
quite amount of nicotine
has created a scenario where nicotine
because of its ability to change
certain chemicals in the
brain can actually lead to
addiction for a number of other
substances related to vaping
and vaping associated behaviors.
If all of that seems like
a lot to get your arms
and your mind around right here
at the outset, don't worry,
I'll walk you through this,
regardless of whether or
not you have a background
in biology or not.
I promise that you'll come
through at the end of this
episode with a deep understanding
of how nicotine works
in the brain and body,
some of its benefits,
some of its potential drawbacks,
and you'll have clear optics
as to why smoking and vaping
and other forms of nicotine
delivery have the effects
that they do on your
biology and psychology.
I'm pleased to announce that
the Huberman Lab Podcast
is now partnered with
Momentous supplements.
We partnered with Momentous
for several important reasons.
First of all,
they ship internationally
because we know that many of you
are located outside of the United States.
Second of all, and perhaps most important,
the quality of their
supplements is second to none,
both in terms of purity and precision
of the amounts of the ingredients.
Third, we've really emphasized supplements
that are single ingredient supplements,
and that are supplied in
dosages that allow you
to build a supplementation protocol
that's optimized for cost,
that's optimized for effectiveness,
and that you can add things
and remove things from your
protocol in a way that's really
systematic and scientific.
If you'd like to see the supplements
that we've partnered with Momentous on,
you can go to livemomentous.com/huberman.
There you'll see those supplements.
And just keep in mind that
we are constantly expanding
the library of supplements
available through Momentous
on a regular basis.
Again, that's livemomentous.com/huberman.
Before we go any further,
I just want to highlight a key takeaway
from a previous episode,
which is our episode on focus.
And in fact was a toolkit for focus.
So during the toolkit for focus episode,
we talked about a large number
of behavioral, pharmacologic,
and another interventions
that you can use to increase
your level of concentration
and focus for whatever purpose,
cognitive endeavors, learning languages,
focusing in school, on work, et cetera,
or physical pursuits.
Now one of the key takeaways is that
there are really two key
protocols that I believe
everyone should understand
and know about and why they work
because they are so effective,
and also because they dovetail
nicely with some of the
information that we're
going to talk about today,
which will explain why nicotine
is so effective in increasing focus.
And these two protocols are as follows.
Data based on studies
done in Wendy Suzuki's lab
at New York University.
And of course, Wendy was
a guest on this podcast.
So you can check out
that episode if you like,
but studies done in her laboratory point
to the fact that a daily,
very brief, in fact,
only 13 minute meditation
can vastly increase
focus and focus ability,
not just immediately after
the meditation practice,
but at all other times as well.
So again,
this is a meditation practice done daily
for just 13 minutes.
It's a very simple meditation practice
where one sits or lies down,
closes your eyes and
directs your attention
to a place just between your
two eyes and right above it.
So on your forehead.
But just inside of that,
and please understand that your brain
does not have sensory receptors.
So unlike focusing on your fingertips
and the sensations there,
if you focus on your brain,
you can't actually sense anything
in your brain except your thoughts.
So the idea then is that you
continually bring your focus
back to that location just about an inch
behind your forehead over and over again.
And it's the refocusing of your attention
to that location after it drifts
that succeeds in increasing
your focus ability, again,
not just during the
meditation and afterward,
but at other times as well.
So this 13 minute a day
meditation is exceedingly simple
and exceedingly effective.
It should be performed every day,
but if you miss a day,
just go back to doing it.
Don't despair too much.
And you will see these
positive effects, say the data.
Also increase effects on mood and other
positive aspects of mental
health and performance.
So that's the first tool in protocol.
The second tool in protocol
relates to the general
what I called arrow model of focus.
This was a model that I created
in order to simplify the
vast amounts of data on
focus and concentration
and how they are created
by the various chemical
systems within your brain.
We're going to hear a lot about
these chemical systems again
today in the context of nicotine
and they are as follows.
You can think about focus
on any goal or any endeavor as an arrow.
So just imagine an arrow
which has an arrow head
and a shaft, and we'll
add a third component
to it in a moment.
The head of the arrow,
meaning the direction of your focus,
is largely set by acetylcholine,
which is a chemical in the brain.
The shaft of the arrow
is set by a chemical
called adrenaline, also
called epinephrine.
Those are the same thing.
In the brain typically it's
referred to as epinephrine,
and in the body,
it's more commonly
referred to as adrenaline,
but those are the same neurochemical.
Epinephrine slash adrenaline
represents the shaft
of the arrow and it's providing the energy
for which to focus.
And then we can put behind that arrow
a little propeller or
a motor, if you like,
and the propeller or motor in the context
of this neurochemistry model is dopamine,
which provides ongoing motivation.
It pushes that arrow forward continually
as you strive to focus
on a particular thing.
This particular arrow model,
that is your ability
to increase your focus,
can be enhanced therefore
by increasing acetylcholine,
epinephrine, and dopamine simultaneously.
And there are a lot of
different ways to do that.
But one of the more effective ways to do
that via supplement protocols
is so-called Alpha GPC.
Alpha GPC taken in 300
milligram form 10 to 30 minutes
before a about of cognitive
work or a about of physical work
will increase your focus by way
of increasing acetylcholine,
and to some extent, increasing
epinephrine as well.
The dopamine increase will
have to be achieved either
through cognitive processing,
that is telling yourself
you're doing a good job
and moving forward because thoughts really
do impact your levels of dopamine,
or some other sort of
pro dopamine or dopamine
increasing protocol also
discussed in the toolkit for focus
and our episode on dopamine
for motivation and drive.
So the key thing here to
understand is that the 13 minute
a day meditation is a very effective way
to increase focus capacity.
And then in the short term,
if you want to provide a
boost now and again to focus,
300 milligrams of Alpha
GPC can be very effective.
There are various sources for that
that we'll link to one of them
in the show note captions.
By no means am I saying that
you need to take alpha GPC.
A number of people will
certainly opt not to.
And a number of people
might be saying, well,
I've heard that Alpha GPC
can increase focus by way of
increasing acetylcholine and
norepinephrine or epinephrine,
but it can also increase TMAO,
which is a kind of a negative
marker of cardiac health
and cardiovascular health.
For that reason, I and many
others will take 600 milligrams
of a garlic capsule, which
can offset that TMAO increase.
It remains uncertain as to how much
Alpha GPC one needs to
take before increasing TMAO
levels to a point where it's of concern
that you would even need
to take the garlic capsule.
But I just mention it in any case,
because it's a pretty simple fix.
Garlic has other health
benefits too, of course,
and for most people,
300 milligrams of Alpha GPC
taken every once in a while.
I certainly don't encourage people
to take Alpha GPC every
time they want to focus.
I always emphasize behavioral tools first,
then focusing on nutritional
tools and on occasion using
supplement based tools to encourage
increased levels of focus.
And then of course there are a various
number of different prescription compounds
that if you're working with
a board certified physician,
they could prescribe you
if you need additional tools
for focus, things like Ritalin,
Adderall, Modafinil,
Armodafinil, Vyvanse, et cetera,
for many people are going to
be important and maybe even
necessary for people with ADHD, et cetera,
but that's a category into itself.
And as I always say,
I'm not a physician, so I
don't prescribe anything.
I'm a professor, so I profess many things.
And today I just wanted to
pass along or redirect your
attention to that episode on focus
and highlight those two tools,
the 13 minute a day meditation,
and 300 milligram Alpha GPC
for increasing focus capacity
and for acutely,
that is temporarily
giving an additional boost
for a about of focus.
And of course, if you choose
not to use those protocols,
that's perfectly fine too,
there's certainly no obligation.
They are simply available to you
should you choose to try them.
And if nothing else you now have in mind
the neurochemistry of acetylcholine,
epinephrine slash
adrenaline, and dopamine,
and that will really set the
stage for understanding just
how effective and why nicotine
is so effective at
increasing focus, motivation,
and even as you'll soon hear,
working memory and cognitive capacity.
Before we begin,
I'd like to emphasize that
this podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however part of my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer information
about science and science related tools
to the general public, and
keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Thesis.
Thesis makes custom nootropics,
and to be quite direct,
I do not like the word
nootropics because it translates
to smart drugs, and to be direct again,
there is no such thing as a smart drug.
That is there's no such thing as a drug
that can make you smarter
because there is no circuit
in the brain for being smart.
There are circuits in the brain for focus.
There are circuits in the
brain for task switching.
brain related to creativity
and so on and so forth.
So the idea that there
would be a single smart drug
or nootropic is simply foolish.
And fortunately Thesis
understands this and therefore has
created custom notropics that
are designed to get you into
the states of mind and body
that are optimal for your goals.
I've been taking Thesis
nootropics for quite a while now,
and I've been extremely
pleased with the results.
I take a clarity formula
that's specifically designed
for me prior to long
bouts of cognitive work.
And I take an energy formula
prior to particularly
challenging physical workouts.
To get your own personalized
nootropic starter kit,
you can go online to
takethesis.com/huberman.
Take a three minute quiz and
Thesis will send you four
different formulas to
try in your first month.
Again, that's takethesis.com/huberman
and use the code Huberman at checkout
to get 10% off your first box.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a personalized
nutrition platform that
analyzes data from your blood
and DNA to help you better
reach your health goals.
I've long been a believer in
getting regular blood work done
for the simple reason
that many of the factors
that impact your immediate
and long-term health
can only be analyzed with
a quality blood test.
One of the major issues
with blood tests or DNA tests, however,
is that typically you'll
get your data back
and you won't know what
to do with those data.
InsideTracker has solved
this problem by creating a
personalized platform where
when you get numbers back
about your hormones,
metabolic factors, et cetera,
it will direct you to specific protocols
in the realms of nutrition,
exercise, supplementation.
And that includes things
to do, things to consider,
and things not to do in
order to bring those numbers
into the ranges that are
optimal for your immediate
and long-term goals.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can visit insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off any of
InsideTracker's plans.
Again, that's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by ROKA.
ROKA makes eyeglasses and sunglasses
that are the absolute highest quality.
The company was founded by
two all American swimmers
from Stanford, and everything about ROKA
eyeglasses and sunglasses were designed
with performance in mind.
I've spent a lifetime
working on the biology
of the visual system.
And I can tell you that your
visual system has to contend
with a number of important
challenges in order for you
to be able to see clearly.
Now ROKA understands this and everything
about their eyeglasses were
designed in order for you
to see with optimal clarity
regardless of activities.
ROKA eyeglasses and sunglasses are superb
for wearing while you run or cycle.
In fact, they were originally
designed for that purpose.
They're extremely lightweight.
In fact, most of the time,
I can't even remember
that they're on my face,
and they won't fall off if you get sweaty.
In addition, ROKA
eyeglasses and sunglasses
have a terrific aesthetic.
So while a lot of so-called
performance eyeglasses out there
will make you look like
a cyborg if you want to,
and they do have those varieties,
they also have varieties of
aesthetic choices that you would
be very comfortable wearing
to work or to school
or just out and about.
And that's one of the reasons I like them.
I don't really have to think about having
too many pairs of
sunglasses or eyeglasses.
I can just have one or two of
each pair and I'm good to go
no matter where I go.
If you'd like to try ROKA
eyeglasses and sunglasses,
you can go to ROKA, that's roka.com,
and enter the code
Huberman to save 20% off
on your first order.
Again, that's roka.com and
enter the code Huberman
at checkout.
Let's talk about nicotine
and how nicotine impacts
our brains, our bodies,
our mental performance,
our mental health, our
physical performance,
and our physical health.
Now once again,
I want to remind everybody that
we really need to separate out
a discussion about nicotine
from the discussion
about the delivery device for nicotine.
In other words, when we're
talking about nicotine,
we are not necessarily
talking about smoking.
Although we might be.
There are things associated
with smoking and with vaping and
other means of getting
nicotine into our system
that have their own
effects, both negative,
and in some cases positive.
Indeed later,
we will talk about how you
can actually use nicotine
to get over smoking addiction.
This won't come as a
surprise to many people,
but what perhaps will come as
a surprise is the fact that
many people actually use
nicotine-like substances or
nicotine itself in order to
relieve nicotine addiction.
So we'll talk about that
and what that looks like
and offer various protocols
for you later in the episode.
I also want to mention here
at the outset that I have
a long standing interest in nicotine.
In fact, early in my scientific career,
I did research on nicotine
and its role in brain development.
And I've had a long standing
interest in neuroplasticity,
the brain's ability to change
in response to experience.
And so experiments that have
been done by close colleagues
and friends of mine have really emphasized
the fact that acetylcholine,
and in particular,
when acetylcholine activates so-called
nicotinic receptors,
something you'll learn
more about in a little bit,
that can actually serve
as a gateway or a trigger
for directed rewiring of the brain.
So this is fascinating.
We think of nicotine as
something that we take,
but actually we have
receptors that is locations
in the brain to which nicotine binds
and can exert its effects.
And those receptors did not
come about because of the
existence of tobacco or the
existence of vaping pens,
or because of the existence of anything
in the outside world.
The fact that there are
nicotinic receptors in our brain
and body tells you that acetylcholine
and nicotine themselves
have very important roles
in normal brain and body function,
so much so that I often
like to point to an anecdote
of a very well known Nobel
prize winning neuroscientist.
I won't reveal who they are.
They're not a faculty member at Stanford,
but many neuroscientists
know of this person
and many people in the outside
world know of this person.
And they are also well known
for their love of nicotine.
I once sat in this
person's office, and he,
I will reveal it as a he,
consumed no fewer than
three pieces of nicotine gum
during that relatively short conversation
of about 45 minutes.
And that was surprising to me.
And I asked him why he was
taking so much nicotine
through nicotine gum.
And he replied that for years,
he had been a chronic smoker,
which on the one hand had greatly impaired
his cardiovascular health and his fitness,
no surprise there.
And we'll talk a little bit more about
what the underlying reasons
are, but most everyone,
if not everyone knows
that smoking cigarettes
or smoking in general
really impairs lung health.
There's just simply no question about it.
There are some more or less
unhealthy ways to smoke,
but the quite honest
message is that smoking
of any kind is going to disrupt
lung endothelial function,
lung function, blood
vessels, and so forth.
It's going to make it harder
to breathe with vigor,
take deep breaths, deliver
oxygen to tissues, et cetera.
That said,
he also pointed out that
the data on nicotine
specifically are pointing
to the fact that nicotine
can be, can be protective
against certain forms
of cognitive impairment.
And that is why he continued
to chew nicotine containing gum.
And he swore by the focus
enhancing and motivation enhancing
effects of nicotine containing gum.
Now that is not a call to
arms for you to run out
and start chewing or consuming
nicotine containing products.
We will talk about those
products later in the episode,
some of their potential advantages,
some of their potential disadvantages.
Now I share this anecdote
because it nicely separates
nicotine from the delivery device
through which nicotine arrives.
Now I haven't talked to this individual
in a few years to see whether
not the nicotine is working
to stave off any kind of
Alzheimer's or neurodegenerative
or cognitive impairment
that would come with age.
This gentleman is getting up in the years
and seems quite sharp nonetheless,
but then again was
always exceedingly sharp.
The point is nicotine is a
substance that can both promote
cognitive function, and
under some conditions,
if taken to inappropriate,
or I should say to extreme dosages,
can also impair cognitive function.
So today we really need to
have a nuanced conversation
about nicotine, one that
includes some of the benefits,
some of the drawbacks, in
particular for children,
certainly for people that are pregnant,
for people that have addictive tendencies,
and for people that have depression
and any other kind of mood disorders.
What I will tell you soon
is that nicotine can be very
powerful as a mood modulator
and many people who have tried
to quit nicotine mainly
through the form of smoking
will find that their mood
can drop substantially.
So nicotine does a lot of
things in the brain and body.
And so I'd like to begin by
talking about what exactly
nicotine is and how it
impacts your brain and body.
So what is nicotine and where is it found?
Now obviously nicotine is
found in the tobacco plant,
but nicotine is also found in nightshades.
That is tomatoes, eggplant,
and sweet peppers.
Although the concentrations
of nicotine in tomatoes,
eggplants, and sweet
peppers is vastly lower
than it is in the tobacco plant.
You actually can also
find nicotine in potatoes.
Now why is nicotine present
in potatoes and tomatoes
and in the tobacco plant at all?
Well, nicotine is a plant alkaloid.
We'll get into alkaloids
a little bit later,
but it is thought that these
alkaloids evolved in plants
as a way to prevent
insects from eating them.
And without going into
a lot of insect biology,
the reason or the rationale
behind this explanation is that
nicotine is not only a substance
in tobacco that people use
or in the various
medications that people use,
but it's also used as a
pesticide because it can
dramatically disrupt the
nervous system of insects.
It can render them infertile,
which is not to say that it
renders humans infertile.
We want to say, again,
it is not the case that nicotine
renders humans infertile,
but it can make certain insects infertile.
It can actually disrupt
their motor function
and their brain function,
and the reasons that it
has such different effects
on insects, in other words,
it can kill them or prevent
them from reproducing,
and therefore explains why
plants probably evolved to have
this plant alkaloid, nicotine.
In humans,
because of the differences
in receptors for nicotine,
where they're located, and
the types of receptors,
the effects of nicotine on
humans is quite a bit different.
And again, it does not
cause infertility in humans.
Although I will talk a
little bit later about some
double blind peer-reviewed
studies conducted in humans
that indicate that for instance,
nicotine can reduce penile girth,
that is the girth of the penis,
and can lead to certain
forms of sexual dysfunction.
And those changes are
largely downstream of changes
in blood flow and
endothelial cell function.
Endothelial cells are the cells
that make up blood vessels
and other vascular type tissues
within the brain and body.
So nicotine is found in these plants.
And what we can know for sure is
that at some point in human evolution,
somebody or some group of people,
either, and here, I'm completely guessing,
it's a just so story,
but someone or some group must
have inhaled the smoke from
the tobacco plant or put the dried leaves
of the tobacco plant
against some mucosal tissue,
and you know the different
mucosal linings of their body
by which substances can
pass through, that's right.
Any of the mucosal soft
lining tissues of the body
will allow certain substances,
not all certain substances to pass in.
That's why people can put
tobacco in their mouth
and a certain amount of nicotine makes it
into the bloodstream,
put tobacco up their nose,
certain amount of nicotine
gets into the bloodstream.
I haven't heard of people
putting tobacco in other orifices
of their body containing mucosal tissue.
And I'm certainly not
suggesting people do that,
but you get the idea
and how nicotine gets from these plants,
these dried leaves into the bloodstream.
Burning tobacco leads
to a heat induced change
in the availability of nicotine.
And this is why smoking tobacco
or vaping tobacco,
simply by heating it up,
allows the nicotine to be
liberated and go into the
bloodstream simply by
inhaling it into the lungs.
We will get back to smoking
of various kinds later.
But right now let's just keep
our attention on how nicotine
is pulled from these plants
and into the human body.
Now whether by inhalation
or whether or not by placing
in contact with the
mucosal tissue of the mouth
or other mucosal containing
orifice of the body,
the nicotine then gets
into the bloodstream.
And once it's in the bloodstream,
it only exerts its
effects because it binds
to certain so-called nicotinic receptors.
So the nicotinic receptors
are of the acetylcholinergic variety.
I know this is a lot to think
about and a lot to hear if you
haven't heard about this, but
it's actually quite simple.
Anyone can understand this.
Acetylcholine is a molecule,
a chemical that is that's
released in the brain and body.
And when it binds to receptors,
that is little parking spots on cells,
it changes the way those cells behave.
Those cells can increase their activity
and release other chemicals.
They can become electrically active,
they can do any number
of different things.
When we ingest nicotine,
it gets into the bloodstream
and eventually some of that
will get into the brain and
some of it gets into the body.
And in both of the brain and body,
there are the so-called nicotinic
acetylcholine receptors.
Now the so-called family,
and indeed they are a family,
this is how we refer
to groups of receptors
of related design and genetic
background just like humans.
You have a family of these
acetylcholine receptors
that are of the nicotinic variety.
So maybe on one street
in your neighborhood,
you know the Joneses and another street,
you know the Chows and another
street, well in your body,
you have the nicotinic
acetylcholine receptors,
and then you have the so-called
muscarinic acetylcholine receptors.
Today it's really simple.
Nicotine only binds to the
nicotinic acetylcholine
receptors and there are
a bunch of different ones
on a bunch of different tissues.
And the differences in those
receptors dictate what sorts of
effects the nicotine will
have on those tissues.
So let's talk about
what those effects are,
and let's do that by dividing
the effects of nicotine
into effects on the brain,
so everything from the
neck up, and on the body,
the so-called central nervous
system and the periphery.
Although I want to point
out that your spinal cord
is part of the central nervous system.
So in fairness to the reality,
your brain and spinal cord are
all central nervous system.
Everything else is
considered the periphery.
Now there are a lot of different nicotinic
acetylcholine receptors,
but for those of you that
want to know, you aficionados,
or if you're ultra curious about this,
the main effects of nicotine
in the brain are mediated
by nicotine binding to the so-called
alpha four beta two receptor.
Alpha four beta two receptor.
Even if you don't care
about receptor subtypes,
that's going to come up
later when we discuss
why nicotine suppresses appetite.
In fact, one of the major
reasons why people don't want
to quit smoking, or they quit smoking
or another form of ingesting nicotine,
and then they relapse,
they go back to smoking or
ingesting nicotine in some other
way is because indeed nicotine
will increase metabolism
and reduce hunger in large part
by binding to this alpha
four beta two receptor
in a particular area of the brain.
We're going to return
to that in a little bit,
but if you've ever heard that
nicotine kills the appetite,
indeed it does.
It's not the behavior of smoking itself.
It's not because you
always have a cigarette
in your mouth that you're
not eating more food.
Although I suppose that
might be a minor effect.
There are direct effects of
nicotine on both appetite,
that is, it reduces
appetite and direct effects
on metabolism, that is,
it increases metabolism
through its effects
on some other areas of the brain and body
we'll talk about in a moment.
Now within the brain,
nicotine binds to this
alpha four beta two receptor
in various locations in the brain.
And there are three and maybe
a fourth that we'll talk about
neurochemical effects of
nicotine after you ingest it.
First things first,
when you ingest nicotine
by smoking nicotine containing tobacco,
or if you place tobacco in
contact with the mucosal lining
of the nasal passages of the mouth,
takes about two to 15
minutes for that nicotine
to enter the bloodstream.
Smoking hits the bloodstream
faster, vaping even faster,
I should mention for a
variety of reasons and placing
tobacco directly in contact
with the mucosal lining
is going to be the slowest.
Now as I mentioned before,
nicotine gets into the bloodstream
and then because nicotine
can pass through the so-called
blood brain barrier, the BBB,
which is basically a
fence around the brain,
because it can pass through
the blood brain barrier,
it's going to have very
rapid effects on the brain
in these four major categories
of neurochemicals and neural circuits.
The first of those categories,
this is a very important one,
this is one that was brought
up in the episode on dopamine,
motivation, and drive.
And I think not just all scientists,
but all human beings should
know that within their brain,
they have what is called the
mesolimbic reward pathway.
The mesolimbic reward pathway
if you just want to call it,
the dopamine reward pathway
is, as the name suggests,
a set of connections between a brain area
called the ventral tegmental area.
You don't have to remember
the names of these things,
of course, but if you
want to, that's fine too.
The ventral tegmental area
or VTA connects to another area called
the nucleus accumbens.
Now here's what's very important.
Nicotine triggers the release of dopamine
from the nucleus accumbens.
This is what gives nicotine
its rewarding properties.
It increases motivation.
It tends to give a not so subtle,
but very transient increase in feelings
of wellbeing and alertness and motivation.
And that's because of
the increase in dopamine
caused by nicotine directly
within the nucleus accumbens.
Nicotine also triggers the
release of certain neurochemicals
from the ventral tegmental area itself.
And those impinge on nucleus accumbens
and increase dopamine levels further.
This is what makes the rewarding
properties or sometimes
referred to as the reinforcing
properties of nicotine
so powerful.
This is why so many billions
of people ingest nicotine
in one form or another.
It's also why nicotine is so hard to quit
because there's a potent
increase in dopamine
from multiple neural circuit pathways
within this mesolimbic reward circuitry.
Now within the mesolimbic
reward circuitry,
there's an interesting feature.
There are accelerators
that essentially push out
more dopamine, get more dopamine released,
and there are breaks of the
so-called GABAergic variety.
GABA's an inhibitory neurotransmitter.
You don't need to know too much
about it to just understand
that nicotine both increases dopamine,
but also decreases the activity of GABA.
And so this is like
pushing on the accelerator
for dopamine, but also removing the brake.
So there's a two pronged
effect of nicotine
on reinforcement reward
dopamine related pathways,
the feel good motivation pathways.
And that is an increase in
dopamine and a decrease in GABA.
And again,
that's all mediated through
this mesolimbic reward pathway,
involving the ventral tegmental area
and the nucleus accumbens.
So if you can conceptualize
even just 5% of what I just told you,
or even if you can just remember
nicotine increases dopamine
and that's why it feels so good,
it makes you want more of it,
you will have everything you
need to know in mind in order
to understand both why
nicotine is so highly used,
and indeed abused, why
it's so hard to quit,
and that will point to avenues
as to how to quit or reduce intake.
And it also points to
how nicotine can actually
be used in an antidepressant
way should you choose.
And we will talk about
what the various criteria
are for choosing that,
but just to understand
nicotine increases motivation,
it decreases negative feelings of mood,
it increases positive feelings
of mood and motivation.
Before we continue with
today's discussion,
I'd like to just briefly
acknowledge our sponsor
Athletic Greens, now called AG1.
Athletic Greens, AKA AG1,
is an all in one vitamin
mineral probiotic drink
that also has adaptogens
and digestive enzymes.
I've been taking Athletic
Greens since way back in 2012.
So I'm delighted that they're
sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I started taking
Athletic Greens and the reason I
still drink Athletic Greens
twice a day is that it supplies
total foundational coverage of
my vitamin and mineral needs.
And it supplies important
nutrients that I need to support
my gut microbiome, the gut
microbiome, as many of you know,
supports the immune system.
It also supports the
so-called gut brain access,
which is vital for
mood, for energy levels,
for regulating focus,
and many other features
of our mental health
and physical health that
impact our daily performance
and high performance
in any endeavors we might be involved in.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and claim a special offer.
They're giving away five
free travel packs plus
a year's supply of vitamin
D3K2 with every order.
And of course,
vitamin D3K2 are vital for
all sorts of things like
hormone health and metabolic health and K2
for cardiovascular health
and calcium regulation.
Again, you can go to
athleticgreens.com/huberman
to claim that special offer.
The second major effect that
nicotine has in the brain
is that it increases acetylcholine.
Acetylcholine is a
neuromodulator that exists in you
and me, it is released from
multiple sites in the brain.
And the two major sites
are the nucleus basalis,
so these are a collection
of neurons in the front
and base of your brain, and
from some brain stem areas.
And there are a bunch of different ones
back there in your brain stem,
which is indeed in the back
that release acetylcholine
that include the locus coeruleus
as kind of a minor site,
the pedunculopontine nucleus.
There are a bunch of
these different areas,
that parabigeminal nucleus.
There are a bunch of
these things back there.
We don't have to go into all the names,
but just understand that they're
little pockets of neurons,
nerve cells located in
the front and the back
and some extent in the
middle of your brain,
but really in the front
and the back of your brain,
that can serve two major
role, here they are.
Acetylcholine released from
nucleus basalis leads to
a sort of spotlighting or highlighting
of particular neural
circuits in the brain.
What do I mean by this?
Well let's say you're working on a puzzle.
Let's say it's a cognitive puzzle.
Maybe you're doing a word puzzle,
or nowadays I've heard
of this Wordle thing.
I'm on Twitter and
people are always posting
their Wordle thing and I
have no idea what it is,
but I'm guessing it's some sort of puzzle.
I'm guessing it's like a crossword puzzle,
and here, if I'm wrong,
I don't know, educate me.
Tell me what Wordle is.
Somebody put it in the comments
and tell me if I should play it or not.
Here's the deal.
When acetylcholine is
released from nucleus basalis,
the neurons are there in
the base of the brain,
but they extend axons,
which are like little wires
elsewhere in the brain.
And when acetylcholine is released,
it tends to be released at
particular locations in the brain
that are associated with whatever activity
we happen to be doing.
So if I'm doing Wordle,
here I'm talking about it
as if I've ever done it,
doing a crossword puzzle or Wordle,
well the neurons that were
involved in trying to figure out
the solution to that Wordle or
crossword puzzle are active,
and then acetylcholine is
released from the little wires,
the little endings of these
cells in nucleus basalis.
And all of a sudden those
neural circuits get a boost.
They become more active,
and believe it or not,
our ability to perform
that crossword puzzle
or at least focus on that Wordle
or crossword puzzle gets enhanced.
It literally increases
our attention for that
and not anything else is enhanced.
So it's literally like a neurochemical
attentional spotlight.
Nicotine increases
acetylcholine and thereby focus
and concentration and mental performance,
not by changing the neural circuits
that are activated per se,
but rather by making more acetylcholine
available at those release sites.
So it's as if the
spotlight got more intense,
the highlighter is more intense
than it would be otherwise.
And I should also mention because
of the so-called pharmacokinetics,
the time course in which
nicotine has its effects,
which are pretty short lived,
we'll talk about those in a moment,
this enhancement in cognitive performance
and attention, it's going
to be very transient,
probably on the order of
about 30, maybe 45 minutes,
the half life of nicotine,
depending on how it's ingested and whether
or not you have food in the gut
and what else is in the
bloodstream, et cetera,
it's going to be anywhere
from one to two hours,
but typically the effects
of nicotine will come on
in about two to 15 minutes
as I mentioned before,
and then will last anywhere
from about 30 to 45 minutes.
This is why in the old days,
and still to some extent in
certain areas of the world,
but less so in the United States
and certainly in Europe as well,
we don't see quite as many
people smoking cigarettes,
for reasons we can discuss later.
But you would see these chain smokers
who are trying to maintain constant levels
of nicotine in their
brain and bloodstream.
Now perhaps they didn't know that nicotine
has this one to two hour half life,
but they could sense
no doubt the cognitive
and the physical effects of nicotine,
including this cognitive
enhancement effect
and highlighting of
neural circuits effect.
And they would notice they
would smoke a cigarette
and then for the next five
to 45 minutes have heightened
focus and then they
would start to drop off.
So they smoke another cigarette.
So in other words,
they're trying to maintain
a constant level of nicotine
for whatever activities
they needed to perform.
Obviously chain smoking
because of the terrible
effects of smoking,
I'll talk about those terrible effects,
but I'm sure you've heard
of them before, cancer,
depletion of just about
every organ and body tissue
to the point that it
can actually be measured
how many years of your
life you're peeling off
in terms of lifespan and
health span by smoking.
Well the terrible effects
of smoking are indisputable,
but the positive effects of
nicotine on this circuitry,
part of the reason why
people would chain smoke
in the first place rather
than get one big peak
of concentration and focus
and then just let it disappear
after 45 minutes.
So what we have is a
scenario where dopamine
is going up in the mesolimbic pathway.
That's why smoking or ingesting
nicotine in any other way
feels good and makes us feel motivated.
And then the increase in acetylcholine,
especially from nucleus basalis
in the front of the brain,
is the reason why it
can increase our ability
to focus on particular types of endeavors,
particular mental work that we're doing,
or maybe even particular physical work.
Although I should mention
anytime I'm pairing the words
nicotine and physical work,
it's obvious that because of the ways
that smoking impairs lung function,
those two things really
run counter to one another.
In other words,
if you are thinking about
ingesting nicotine through smoking
or vaping in order to
improve physical performance,
that's a terrible idea.
The logic isn't there
and the health detriments
are certainly there.
The third neurochemical pathway
that's strongly activated
when nicotine is brought into
the central nervous system
into the brain is epinephrine,
or in particular norepinephrine,
which is related to epinephrine.
Now, earlier I said epinephrine
is the same as adrenaline.
That's still true.
Norepinephrine is closely
related to epinephrine,
and for today's discussion,
we're going to use them interchangeably.
Although I realize as I say that
that the medical students
and some biology students are
probably going to have a minor seizure
when I lump norepinephrine
and epinephrine.
I don't do that to be
too much of a lumper,
in science, we talk about
lumpers and splitters.
Lumpers are people that like
to oversimplify a little bit,
splitters are people that
really like to detail.
You'll see a lot of
splitters on social media
from time to time, they'll say, wait,
you didn't mention the alpha
two beta six receptor yet.
Okay look, I get it.
And I am all for having
splitters in the room,
but for sake of today's discussion
and for ease of digestibility
of some of this,
just want to point out
that norepinephrine,
epinephrine, and adrenaline,
I'm going to treat as a common
pool of similar, in fact,
very similar molecules that
all have the same net effect,
at least in the context of this discussion
and that's to increase levels
of alertness, energy, and arousal.
And the way that nicotine
accomplishes those increases in
alertness and arousal and
energy within the brain is by
triggering the release of
no epinephrine from a little
cluster of neurons in
the back of the brain
called locus coeruleus,
tiny cluster of neurons that
offers up, or I should say has,
because they're always there from birth
has these little wires,
these axons that extend many,
many places in the brain, not every place,
but virtually every place
and can sprinkler the
brain with norepinephrine,
essentially serve as a wake up signal,
elevating levels of energy.
And when that combines
with the acetylcholine
from nucleus basalis, which
causes attentional spotlighting,
increases in concentration and focus,
and with the feel good
properties of dopamine
and the motivating properties
of dopamine released
from the mesolimbic reward pathway.
Now you can start to get
a picture of why nicotine
is such a powerful molecule.
It's making people feel
motivated and good.
It's making people feel focused
and it makes people feel
alert when they would otherwise
feel a little bit sleepy.
So this is a really
powerful compound, in fact,
going back to our earlier
discussion about focus
and some tools for focus,
and I encourage you if you're interested
to please check out the episode on focus,
there are a number of different tools
and protocols there to increase focus.
But here we are talking
about one molecule, nicotine,
found in plants like tomatoes and potatoes
and the tobacco plant.
And it can be synthesized
in a laboratory and ingested
through a patch or a gum or even a pill
or a toothpick dipped in nicotine.
One molecule that can trigger
activation of all the circuits
for focus and motivation
in one fell swoop.
That is remarkable. That
is absolutely remarkable.
And here we haven't even touched on
some of the psychological
components of focus, right?
Whether or not we're
interested in something,
whether or not we're
excited about it or not.
This is a very, very powerful system.
So powerful in fact,
that I think we can really place nicotine
right up there at the top,
right next to caffeine as the molecule
that has fundamentally
changed human evolution,
human consciousness, and human experience.
Even if you're somebody who's
never ingested nicotine,
this absolutely has to be true
because you have these
nicotinic receptors,
which is to say that acetylcholine
that's naturally released
without any external trigger
within your brain and body,
or I should say
without any trigger from
nicotine in particular
is binding these nicotinic
acetylcholine receptors
and is creating these effects
in your brain and body,
just absolutely staggering.
Now earlier I mentioned the
appetite suppressing and indeed
metabolism increasing effects of nicotine.
And while that's a fairly niche component
of what nicotine does, I
mean, it's an important one,
but it's not the major reason
why most people consume nicotine.
I'd like to take a moment
and talk about that now,
because we are in the
brain and we're talking
about the effects of
nicotine in the brain.
And so it seems to me the appropriate time
to talk about this.
Now we can have this
conversation about nicotine
and appetite and
metabolism in a very simple
and straightforward way.
If you'd like to learn more
about the biology of metabolism
and appetite and how those things
are mediated by neural components,
so not just stuff like
your liver, et cetera,
we have episodes on that,
but really the neural components
of hunger and appetite.
I encourage you to check out our episode
on hunger and appetite.
But in that episode, we had a discussion.
And it's one that I'll just
briefly summarize now that you
have a collection of neurons
that sits right above the roof
of your mouth or so
called the hypothalamus.
Hypo means below and
thalamus is right above it,
hypothalamus.
So the small collection of
neurons in the hypothalamus
to a number of different
things related to sex behavior,
aggression, mediating the
temperature of your body,
et cetera, but also appetite
and suppressing appetite.
And within the hypothalamus,
there's a compact collection
of these little neurons,
which we referred to as
the POMC, P-O-M-C neurons.
And the name comes from the fact
that they express certain peptides.
And we won't get into that now,
but the POMC neurons have
a very profound impact on
whether or not you feel hungry
or whether or not you do not feel hungry,
whether or not your
appetite is suppressed.
It turns out that when nicotine
gets into the bloodstream
and then into the brain,
some of that nicotine binds to nicotinic
alpha four beta two containing
nicotinic receptors.
Again, these sub units of receptors,
but basically the nicotine binds some
of those parking spots, parks there.
And as a consequence,
these POMC neurons increase
their electrical activity
and appetite is suppressed.
And that's because the POMC
neurons have outputs to various
areas of the brain and
body controlling everything
from how full we feel to whether or not
our blood sugar goes up or down,
which can impact our hunger,
and believe it or not,
whether or not we have a
tendency to want to move the jaw
of our mouth in order to chew food.
Yes, believe it or not,
the neural circuitry
associated with appetite and
suppression of appetite actually dictates
whether or not you prefer to,
or I should say are more
biased or less biased
to moving your mouth, that is chewing.
Which makes perfect
sense when you hear it.
One way to suppress appetite
is to sew the jaw shut neurally,
or at least make it less likely
to open your mouth and put food in it.
Actually that reminded me of a story.
I'll just interrupt myself
to tell a brief story that
there's a famous Nobel Laureate
who won the Nobel Prize
for something totally
distant from appetite.
But once turned to a friend
of mine at a meeting and said,
I discovered the biological
mechanism for losing weight.
And my friend said, well of course,
ingest fewer calories than you burn.
Calories in, calories out,
fundamental rule of thermodynamics.
And basically the fundamental
rule of weight loss,
weight gain, or weight maintenance.
And he said, no,
it's actually the gene
that controls whether or
not you open your mouth.
Now he was making a very nerdy joke.
So if you didn't register that as a joke,
that's about as funny as
neuroscience or biology jokes get.
There are a couple funnier ones,
but that one's kind of
considered on the funnier side.
So this is why we're not
considered comedians.
But the point of the matter is
that whether or not you crave
or desire or impulsively
want to put things
in your mouth and chew it,
will actually dictate how
many calories that you eat.
And so I find it remarkable
and indeed important to know
that these POMC neurons
are actually inhibiting
the opening and the movement
of the mouth for chewing.
So when we smoke or
when we ingest nicotine
in any other way,
you activate these POMC
neurons, you suppress appetite,
but in part you do that
by actually limiting
the impulse to chew.
Incredible, at least to me.
Now in addition to limiting appetite
by changing one's desire
to ingest food and chew it
and actual craving of food by regulation
of blood sugar, et cetera,
there do seem to be some quite
direct effects of nicotine
on metabolism,
and the effects on
metabolism aren't enormous.
These are increases in metabolism
that are about 2% up to about 5%,
but I want to emphasize that those
are transient increases in metabolism.
Nonetheless, people that
quit smoking often find
that their appetite goes up,
they sometimes gain weight.
They sometimes do not depending
on whether or not they
offset that increase in
appetite with increased physical
exercise or with decrease
food intake in other ways.
But there does seem to
be this direct effect
of ingesting nicotine on metabolism,
which I find is interesting
because if you look in the literature,
one of the reasons why
people are reluctant
to quit ingesting
nicotine, if for instance,
they want to quit using the
delivery device to nicotine
that's causing such problems
for their health like smoking
or vaping or whether or
not they find themselves
quote unquote addicted to,
or have the habit of ingesting nicotine.
In part, that's likely due
to be the dopamine effects,
because dopamine is highly
reinforcing and rewarding.
It feels good, so people
want to do more of it.
But it's also that for many
people and here the data really
point to the fact that a lot
of the younger female smokers
or younger female vapers,
or when I say that,
of course I mean younger
females that vape,
are doing that because they like
the appetite suppressing effects,
which of course opens up
an entire conversation
about the sociology of
body imagery, et cetera,
a topic for a future podcast.
So nicotine has certain effects
on the brain by virtue of
the fact that nicotine binds
these nicotinic acetylcholine receptors.
And those receptors are found on some,
but not all neural
circuits within the brain.
And we talked about some of
them already, mesolimbic,
the POMC neurons, et cetera.
Now when we ingest nicotine,
it goes from the bloodstream
to all the tissues
and organs of the body.
How does it do that? I mean, amazing.
It can pass to everything,
the brain, the body,
it does that because
nicotine is fat soluble.
And now when anytime
people hear the word fat,
they tend to think about
body fat, subcutaneous fat,
or maybe they think about dietary fat.
What I mean by fat soluble in
the context of nicotine being
fat soluble is that the cells of your body
have an outer layer,
so-called outer membrane.
And it's made up of lipid, of fat,
very particular types of lipids in fact.
Nicotine has this remarkable
ability to move through
that fatty tissue.
Not all molecules have that
ability, but nicotine does.
So it can move relatively
freely through the brain
and body and relatively
freely from outside of cells,
extracellular space to
intracellular space.
So it can get into cells, it
can do that within the brain.
We talked about those effects
and it can do that within the body.
Now anytime we're talking about the body,
we can be talking about
any number of things,
but today I'm going to
refer to the periphery
and the body in more or less the same way,
but keep in mind in the back
of your head, pun intended,
you have your brain, your
eyes, and the spinal cord.
And those three things make up
your central nervous system.
The peripheral nervous
system and the periphery,
which is the rest of your body,
the contain your organs
and so forth outside
of the nervous system,
things like your liver and
your stomach, et cetera,
that's what we're going to
talk about now because nicotine
has profound effects on
the organs of the body
that are separate from,
but that occur in
parallel at the same time
as the effects of nicotine on the brain.
So let's talk about what
some of those effects are.
When nicotine makes it into
the bloodstream, again,
within two to 15 minutes of ingesting it,
depending on the delivery device,
your heart rate will increase,
blood pressure will increase,
and the contractibility
of the heart tissue
will actually increase.
So what that essentially
speaks to is an increase
in so-called sympathetic tone.
And when I say that,
I don't mean an increase in sympathy
for others of the emotional sort.
What I mean is an increase
in the sympathetic activity
of the sympathetic arm of
the autonomic nervous system,
which is real mouthful
and mindful of ideas.
But all you need to know is
that it's a generalized system
that increases levels of
alertness and physical readiness.
So it makes you ready for action,
makes you ready for thought.
It's balanced by a whole
other system called
the parasympathetic nervous system,
which is basically the so-called
rest and digest system,
which is a system of neurons
and organs, et cetera,
that put your body and your
brain into a state of not being
able to think clearly, to
digest, and to fall asleep.
So nicotine increases heart rate,
blood pressure, and
contractibility of the heart.
So it's going to cause
more blood flow in theory,
although it also tends to
constrict blood vessels
in many locations in the body.
This explains the decrease
in penile girth effect
of nicotine, in particular
nicotine ingested by smoking or vaping.
That's right, smoking and
vaping reduces penis size
and also will have damaging effects
on the blood lining endothelial tissue.
So over time it actually is
impairing blood's ability to get
to the penis chronically
as well as to other organs of the body.
But when people ingest nicotine acutely,
and let's say they do
that by Nicorette patch
or by toothpick dipped in nicotine,
it will have some of these same effects,
but when not smoking tobacco,
when bringing nicotine
into the bloodstream
through other mechanisms,
many, if not all of the
disruption of the endothelial cell
function can be bypassed, but
the effects on penile girth,
the effects on reducing
blood flow to various tissues
is still present during
the effects of nicotine,
which as I mentioned last
about one to two hours.
The half life is about one to two hours,
depending on a number of factors,
not interesting for today's discussion.
So when nicotine gets
into the bloodstream,
it's making us more alert,
it's preparing our body for readiness.
The heart is pumping harder.
Epinephrine, that is adrenaline,
is released from the adrenal glands,
which right atop our kidneys.
So everything is pointed
toward creating more readiness
to move, more readiness to think.
And again,
this is happening in parallel
with all the effects of
neurochemistry that are
happening with the brain
that we talked about a few minutes ago.
Now what's interesting about
nicotine is that while it
causes this global increase in readiness
and alertness and attention
and mood, et cetera,
it also has the effect of
somewhat relaxing skeletal muscle.
Now that might seem
counterintuitive to those of you out
there that already know what I'm about
to tell the rest of you who
didn't know it previously,
that your muscles are able to
contract because of the effects
of acetylcholine released
from neurons in your spinal
cord that spit out acetylcholine
onto the muscle and bind to what?
Nicotinic acetylcholine receptors.
Put into plain English,
nicotinic receptors are also the ways
in which your muscles can get activated.
So therefore,
why would it be that increasing nicotine
would cause relaxation of the muscles?
And that has to do with some
of the neural circuits that are
upstream of the muscles and
has to do with a little bit
of how the autonomic
nervous system is a range
in terms of which receptors go where,
a topic and kind of rabbit
hole of a conversation
far too deep for right now,
at least in the context of
this already somewhat detailed
discussion of the effects of nicotine.
But if we were to zoom out and just think
about the effects of nicotine,
we now have a very clear picture.
Reward pathways are turned on.
Attention is turned on.
Alertness is turned on.
You feel better than you
felt a few minutes ago.
Your blood pressure is
up. Your heart rate is up.
Your preparedness for
thinking is elevated as well.
And yet your body is somewhat relaxed.
That's a very interesting
state of mind and body.
Interesting because it's somewhat
ideal for cognitive work.
Like if you were going to sit
down and work on a book or you're
going to sit down and try and
figure out a hard math problem,
or you're going to write a
letter that's been really
challenging for you to write,
or maybe that you're
really excited to write,
but that you've been
slow to get out the door
for whatever reason.
I'm talking about my own
habits of procrastination.
Well that state of being very alert,
but your body being relaxed is almost,
if not the optimal state for
getting mental work done,
because if you're feeling
agitated in your body
and you want to physically move your body,
it's very hard to do cognitive work.
At least the sorts of cognitive
work that involve typing
or writing or these sorts of things.
It's also the exact opposite
of the optimal state
for physical performance,
which is one of yes, also alertness,
yes, also motivation and elevated mood.
That's all wonderful
stuff to have in mind,
literally when you are
exercising or competing
in sport or something of that sort.
But under those conditions,
you really also want to
have a fast reaction time,
a low latency for muscle
activation so that you can make
coordinated muscle movements
in the ways that you need to,
which is of course what's
required of physical endeavors.
That tells us a few things, first of all,
it tells us that nicotine is
going to be generally a bad
idea for a pre-workout tool
or for enhancing physical performance,
however, it's apt to be,
and in fact is an excellent tool
for enhancing cognitive ability.
And of course,
that triggers my mind to
return to the anecdote about
my Nobel prize winning
colleague who ingests nicotine
by way of nicotine containing gum in order
to increase levels of cognitive focus.
Certainly not for going
out and playing sport.
In fact, despite the fact
that he is very, very tall,
he often points to himself
in an appropriately funny way that
despite being on the basketball
team of his high school,
he is probably the worst
player that ever existed.
And they only positioned him
there because of his height.
And I guess his head was
designed to prevent balls
from entering the basket.
In any event,
nicotine does seem to be very good
at enhancing cognitive function,
at least in the short term,
which is not to say that it
isn't without its side effects,
which we will talk about.
And again,
those are side effects that
are independent of smoking
or vaping or other forms
of ingesting nicotine.
For instance,
dipping or chewing tobacco
is known to cause a 50 fold,
yes, 50 fold increase in mouth cancers,
things like leukoplakia and just generally
is terrible for your health.
I'm sorry to break it to you,
but if you're dipping
or you're using snuff
or things of that sort,
certainly I'm not going
to tell people what to do.
That's not my role in life,
but you are dramatically
increasing the probability of an
oral cancer or of a mucosal
lining cancer of some sort.
So it's not just that smoking
and vaping are bad for your health.
These other forms of delivery for nicotine
can be bad for your health as well.
Now whether or not ingesting
nicotine by way of nicotine
containing gum or patch or
toothpick or other method
is dangerous,
for other reasons is a discussion
that's important, right now,
it appears that provided the
dosages are kept reasonable.
We'll talk about what
reasonable means a little later,
and the frequency is kept relatively low.
So not relying on these things constantly.
There may in fact
be some benefit to ingesting
nicotine from time to time,
provided that you are not
still developing your brain.
Now in reality,
neuroplasticity goes on
throughout the lifetime.
Your life is actually one
long developmental arc.
It's not like development
occurs and then stops,
but certainly for people
before puberty, during puberty,
and probably for the next 15
to 20 years after puberty,
avoiding nicotine is probably a good idea.
Now of course, development
is your entire life.
It's not like development
starts and then ends,
but certainly for people that
are 25 years old or younger,
ingesting nicotine as a way
to enhance cognitive function
is probably not the best idea.
And certainly, please,
for those of you that are
15 years old or younger,
ingesting nicotine in any form,
unless it's prescribed by your doctor
for a very specific clinical reason,
to me seems just like a terrible idea
based on all the data that I've read.
And the reason for that is
it's going to create a scenario
of nicotine dependence in order
to achieve heightened levels
of mood and alertness, et
cetera, and that's bad.
And what we're effectively talking about
is an addiction for nicotine directly,
not necessarily the delivery device method
like smoking or vaping,
although it could pull
that in as an addictive
or habit forming behavior as well,
but you want to let your
neural circuits develop
to the point where again,
unless there's a clinical
need for a prescribed drug
from a licensed physician
or psychiatrist, et cetera,
that you're not relying
on chemical enhancement
of these circuits.
For people who are 25
years or older, and again,
that's not a strict cutoff,
but roughly 25 years or older,
but for those of you that are
thinking about using nicotine
to enhance cognitive function as adults
and your brain development
is slowing down, right.
Never ceases,
but is slowing down or has
slowed down to the point
where we would say developmental
plasticity is largely over
and you're now operating
in the context of adult neuroplasticity.
Well, in that case,
there may be instances in which increasing
acetylcholine, dopamine, et cetera,
by way of nicotine ingestion
might be a good idea,
but certainly not by smoking, vaping,
or by direct contact of tobacco
to the mucosal lining tissue
of the mouth or nose, so
called dipping or snuffing.
For the last 20 minutes or so,
we've been talking about
the biology of nicotine
specifically, how it impacts the brain,
how it impacts the body,
why it feels so good,
why it can enhance focus.
And we've largely set
aside smoking, vaping,
dipping tobacco, and snuffing,
and the negative effects
that those all have
on mental and physical health.
Working down from the top of the head
to the bottom of the feet, we
can say that smoking, vaping,
dipping, and snuffing negatively
impact every organ and
tissue system and cell of the
body by virtue of the fact
that they all damage
the endothelial cells.
Again, the endothelial cells are the cells
that make up the vasculature,
which delivers blood and other nutrients
to all the cells and organs
and tissues of the body.
And those endothelial cells
are strongly and negatively
impacted by all of the
practices that I just described.
Now the way that that happens
varies a little bit from each
one to the next, for instance,
it has been estimated
that cigarettes contain
anywhere from 4,000 to 7,000 toxins.
Now the word toxins is a
real buzzword these days,
you hear about detoxes and
toxins, but more specifically,
we know that it contains carcinogens.
These are cancer promoting compounds.
For instance,
we know that the tar in cigarettes,
even low tar cigarettes,
as well as the ammonia within cigarettes,
as well as the formaldehyde
contained within cigarettes,
as well as the carbon
dioxide that's generated
from smoking those cigarettes
are all carcinogens.
Carbon dioxide also has the
negative effect of depleting
the amount of oxygen that's
delivered to any and all
of our tissues by way of the impact of
carbon dioxide binding hemoglobin
and preventing hemoglobin
from delivering oxygen to
the tissues of the body.
So while there may be 4,000
or 4,500 or 7,000 toxins,
depending on which cigarette,
which papers they happen to be rolled in,
whether or not they're
filtered or non-filtered,
the type of tobacco, et cetera, et cetera,
there are a tremendous number of toxins.
And there are some very potent carcinogens
within that long list of toxins.
Again, ammonia, tar, formaldehyde,
and carbon dioxide being the most potent
of those carcinogens.
Now the fact that there are
carcinogens in cigarettes
sometimes lead cigarette
smokers and particularly the
cigarette smokers that have
the hardest time quitting or
that enjoy their cigarettes
the most from saying, well,
listen, everything is a carcinogen
or everything kills you.
Well certainly that's
not a true statement.
And while there are other
carcinogens in the environment,
so it environmental hazards like solvents.
And even if you work in a
laboratory, for instance,
we use in the laboratory,
DNA intercalating dyes,
these are literally dyes
that allow us to see the DNA
structure of cells and see the proteins
they make and see the RNAs they make.
And it's very important to wear gloves
when you work with those things,
because as the name
suggests, they intercalate,
they actually get in
between the strands of DNA
and separate them.
They are mutagens, they mutate DNA.
They are often carcinogens as well.
So we have them in our laboratory,
but we take certain precautions
to not have them negatively
impact our health, safety
protocols and so on.
We hear that there are
carcinogens in car exhaust
and bus exhaust and in all sorts of things
like pesticides and that's all true.
So in the argument of probabilities,
one would say, well,
if there are all these other
carcinogens in the environment,
why would you compound
their carcinogenic effect
by smoking or vaping
or dipping or snuffing?
But that usually doesn't get
people to quit smoking or doing
those things because of
the powerful reinforcing
effects of nicotine itself.
So again,
nicotine is the reinforcing element by way
of triggering that dopamine
reinforcement pathway,
the mesolimbic reward pathway.
And of course there are all
the other additional effects
of increased focus,
such as increased ability to pay attention
to work or to others that
lead to other rewards.
And so then it becomes a
situation of compounding rewards.
So it's not really about the cigarette,
it's about the nicotine,
and it's not really about the nicotine,
it's about the dopamine
that the nicotine evokes.
And then it's not really
about the dopamine
that the nicotine evokes directly per se,
but also about all the
positive effects that
that increased dopamine results in.
So we can easily circle back
to the negative effects of
smoking, vaping, dipping, and snuffing,
and say the endothelial
cells are disrupted.
The endothelial cells are
involved in delivery of blood
and other nutrients to every tissue
of the body and smoking
vaping, dipping, and snuffing
contain carcinogens, which
are cancer promoting.
And because the epidemiological
studies are out there,
we can actually arrive at some
very clear numbers as to how
much life one will lose
from ingesting nicotine
by way of those four delivery devices,
or I should say any one of
those four delivery devices.
Although I should also mention
that many people who are
vaping are also smoking cigarettes
is becoming increasingly common.
A lot of people are using
vaping in one context
and cigarettes in another,
dipping in one context, vaping in another.
But even for those that
only smoke or only vape
or only dip or only snuff,
the negative effects are
dramatic and calculable.
So it is thought that for every pack
of cigarettes consumed per day,
so you could average that
out if you're a two a day
cigarette smoker or a pack
a day cigarette smoker,
two pack a day.
For every pack of
cigarettes smoked per day,
we can reliably estimate a 14
year reduction in lifespan.
So cigarettes are literally
peeling years off your life.
Now because of the way that the
brain works and the way that
human beings anticipate the
future and can be grounded both
in the present and the future
or the present and the past,
that's just how the mind works, right?
That's why we can think about the future,
but also realize where we
are in time and space today.
Because of that, many
people will say, well,
I enjoy cigarettes or I enjoy vaping.
And so at least while I'm
here, I'm enjoying it.
And that's because the dopamine system
is not very good at
understanding opportunity costs.
That is what we would be
doing in those 14 years
and what we would be
enjoying and the enrichment
that we would get if we were
to live into those 14 years.
So at some level the smoker or vaper
is being rational when they
say, yeah, but I enjoy this.
And so the years lost,
I can't really register that
because it's hard to register
what you don't have and
what you've never had.
On the other hand,
we can also point to the
statistic that there is
this 50 fold increase in
mouth cancers from dipping.
And there are nasal cancers as well
that are greatly increased
by snuffing and from smoking,
and now we know based on
data from vaping that the
endothelial cell damage
and the direct effects
of damage to the lungs from tars,
and even if people are vaping,
which tends to have lower
tars than do cigarettes,
even for people that are vaping,
greatly increased probability of stroke,
of peripheral vascular disease.
So this is peripheral
pain because remember,
blood is delivering, not just blood,
but other nutrients and
it's clearing things
out from tissues.
So there's an accumulation of
literally toxins and debris
that cells generate all
the time, which is healthy,
but then the normally is cleared away
by the endothelial cells
and by other cell types
of the immune system,
that's all increased in people that engage
in these nicotine
delivery device behaviors.
Rates of heart attack, rates of stroke,
rates of cognitive
decline are all increased.
Now you might say cognitive decline,
I thought that nicotine increases
the likelihood that we can
maintain healthy neural
function and cognitive capacity.
It might even increase cognitive capacity
in a potent way in the short
term, and indeed it does.
However,
cigarette smoking and vaping are now known
to dramatically decrease
cognitive function
because one of the key
things about the brain
is that it is the most
metabolically demanding organ,
which means it consumes a lot of glucose.
Or even if you're
ketogenic, you need ketones,
you need nutrients getting
to the neurons in other cell
types of the brain and nervous system
in order for it to function properly.
And when you disrupt a vasculature
through this endothelial
cell dysfunction, you get
things like interstitial,
which just means in the
spaces between dysfunction.
So it's not just beating up
the endothelial cells themselves,
but the spaces between the
cells is being disrupted.
There's a lot of debris
that accumulates there.
And as a consequence,
the brain just simply
will not function as well.
So you start getting
short term memory lapses,
you start getting working memory lapses,
working memory is the sort of memory
if someone tells you their
seven digit phone number,
typically nowadays people
just share their info,
but seven digit phone number or a sequence
of numbers or an address
and your inability to remember that.
So you're walking back to the
kitchen sink and you can't
remember what you were trying to remember
just a short moment ago,
that's working memory.
Working memory suffers, long term memory,
projective or intergrade
memories into the future.
How can you remember things in the future
that haven't occurred yet?
Well this is more of a memory
for future plans or ideas
and planning for things that are to come.
So what we can very reliably
say is that currently
more than 1 billion, billion,
more than 1 billion people consume tobacco
in order to get their nicotine
because that's really
the reinforcing element
within tobacco,
more than 1 billion people
consume tobacco in the form
of cigarettes every day.
A growing number of people,
more than half a billion people
now are starting to vape.
The estimates range from
200 million to 500 million.
And there's a lot of
debate about this because
a lot of people are
hybrid smokers and vapers,
meaning they do one or both
depending on time of day and location,
as I mentioned before,
but now you start to see how
you can get to the number
that billions of people
are consuming tobacco.
Because of course you
also have your people
that are dipping and your
people that are snuffing.
And as I mentioned before,
you have people that
are engaging in multiple
of these behaviors.
So billions of people on planet Earth,
anywhere from one eighth to
a quarter of human beings,
incredible right?
Anywhere from one eighth to a quarter of
human beings are consuming
tobacco in one form or another
in order to get their
nicotine one way or another.
And as a consequence,
are peeling years off their life,
dramatically increasing
the probability of cancer,
stroke, heart attack,
peripheral neuropathies,
brain dysfunction,
meaning cognitive dysfunction,
memory impairment,
sexual dysfunction.
There are a number of studies
that have looked at increases in cortisol.
And while minor, those increases do exist.
Decreases in growth
hormone, and while minor,
those decreases exist,
but even setting aside the
negative impact on endocrine,
on hormone factors,
it's very, very clear
that smoking, vaping,
dipping, and snuffing are
among the worst things
that we can do for our health.
They are among the leading
causes of preventable death
and debilitating life conditions,
which may lead you to the question as
to why in the world would people do this?
Well it turns out most
of them don't want to.
In the best surveys that one can find of
if you could quit smoking,
if you could quit vaping, would you,
what you find is that at
least for cigarette smokers,
70% want to quit.
They would love to quit.
And yet they find that to
be exceedingly difficult.
And the reason they find it
to be exceedingly difficult is
because of all the brain neurochemistry
that we talked about before.
The reason I spent close
to 20 minutes talking about
dopamine and the mesolimbic pathway,
acetylcholine and nucleus
basalis, and epinephrine,
and the relaxation of muscles
in the periphery and the
increase in readiness
in the body and brain is
that all of those combine
to make nicotine one
of the most powerful and
potent cognitive enhancers
and to some extent physical enhancer,
although, as I mentioned before,
the total number of physical
exercise or physical
sport promoting effects of
nicotine is very, very small,
if not zero.
There are certain conditions
under which one might imagine
using nicotine specifically
for cognitive enhancement where
performance of complex motor
skills would sort of outweigh
the negative effects on
the neuromuscular system,
our ability to generate
coordinated movements.
There was actually an excellent
study looking at the effects
of nicotine, not by smoking delivery,
but by different delivery
mechanism in which they looked at
performance of hitters in baseball.
The experiment was kind
of an interesting one,
even though these were fairly
skilled baseball players,
what they had them do
was hit a ball off a tee,
as I recall growing up and I admittedly
I didn't play much baseball,
but you start off on tee-ball and then
you would go, I think it
was to pitching machine.
Then they would use actual
pitchers who throw the ball.
But in this case it was a couple
of different baseball related tasks.
They'd have people hit the ball off a tee,
but they had to direct that hit
toward a ball atop another tee.
So it's fairly precise targeting that's
required in order to knock
that ball off the other tee.
So this is an activity that
involves not just motor output,
but coordinated motor output,
and not just coordinated motor output,
but directed, coordinated output
that requires some, as we
would say, top down processing.
This isn't the kind of thing
that can be done reflexively.
This is the kind of thing
where the forebrain,
the prefrontal cortex in
particular has to be heavily
involved in order to
suppress certain actions
and then create other actions.
So the basic takeaway of
the study is that nicotine
delivered by way of nicotine gum,
not by smoking, dipping,
or snuffing was able
to increase cognitive
performance and motor output.
So a rare circumstance where
a specific set of demands that
involved both cognitive
engagement and physical engagement
showed a slight but
significant improvement.
But again, in most cases,
nicotine is just simply not
going to improve physical output
if it's delivered through
a smoked cigarette,
through vaping, through
dipping, or through snuffing.
So if all these behaviors
are terrible for essentially
every aspect of our
health, frankly, I mean,
when you look at the literature,
it's terrible for pregnant
women, it's terrible for kids,
it's terrible for older people,
it's terrible for younger people.
You really cannot find a scenario
in which smoking, vaping,
dipping, or snuffing are good for us.
And yet people like the effects
on the brain and they feel
quite addicted to them, even
if they say they're not,
most of those people would
be unwilling to give up their
practice of nicotine delivery
for more than a few hours.
In fact,
if you look at the effects of
withdrawal and we are going
to talk about what withdrawal
of nicotine looks like,
what you find is that
as soon as four hours
after the last ingestion of nicotine
by way of cigarette or vaping
or dipping or snuffing,
what people start to experience
is some agitation, craving
for nicotine, of course.
And while craving is
kind of a vague concept,
it's actually a very specific
biological mechanism.
It's the drop in dopamine
that's starting to occur
so much so that there's a drop
in dopamine below baseline.
That is the increase in
dopamine that would normally
be experienced from
smoking, vaping, dipping,
or snuffing is now not happening.
And in fact, the levels of
dopamine are dropping below
where they would've been even
without performing that behavior.
So that's what craving is.
And withdrawal is an increased
sense of that craving as well
as a lot of negative stuff
like stomach aches or nausea
or irritability, and often
collections of all of those.
So because these nicotine
delivery approaches
are so terrible for our health,
and also because as many as 70% of people
who smoke would like to quit,
but either feel they can't
because they've tried
and failed repeatedly often,
or because it's just too scary,
meaning the reinforcing
properties are too strong and
therefore they can't
imagine living without them
or the withdrawal effects are too strong
and they can't imagine living with those.
Well then is there hope
for quitting smoking,
vaping, snuffing, or dipping?
And the short answer, fortunately is yes,
there are excellent ways to do that.
And some of them are
single event treatments.
And we're going to talk
about those shortly,
but before we do that,
I want to highlight one very brief point,
which is that nicotine is
not the cause of cancer.
Nicotine is not the carcinogen,
it's the other things
in tobacco or associated
with the nicotine delivery
device that are causing cancer.
And I should mention the
other negative impacts
on our health in particular
by way of disrupted endothelial
blood vessel function.
Now that leads us to this issue of vaping,
because as many of you know,
and probably are thinking
as I've been delivering
this information, people
don't vape tobacco.
The way that vaping pens
are designed is that
it includes some liquid, it involves heat,
and it does not involve
the burning off of tobacco.
In fact, there's a constant
updating of the engineering
of these vape pens so that
they can be very low heat.
In some cases they use even
non heating approaches to
vaporize the nicotine and allow it
to enter the bloodstream very quickly.
I must say in a lot of ways,
vaping resembles crack cocaine.
The reason why vaping and
crack cocaine are so similar
is the speed of entry of
nicotine into the bloodstream.
This isn't an episode about cocaine,
but I just want to very briefly
touch on some of the delivery
routes for cocaine because they parallel
a lot of the delivery routes for nicotine.
And we can learn a lot about
drug pharmacokinetics and dopamine
if we look at the parallels
between cocaine and nicotine.
I'll preface this by saying
cocaine is a terrible drug.
It is actually a schedule two
drug in the United States,
which means that it has a very,
very limited yet still
present medical application,
mainly as an anesthetic
in certain laboratory
and hospital conditions.
But aside from that,
it's very clear that cocaine
is one of the most debilitating
drugs that humans can
use because of the way
that it impacts the dopamine system.
And it basically creates a
loop whereby the only thing
that can really trigger
dopamine release is cocaine.
And as I've said before,
the way that I define
addiction is it's a progressive
narrowing of the things
that bring people pleasure.
Cocaine certainly falls into the category
of addictive drugs,
strongly addictive drugs.
And in fact,
it has the additionally pernicious feature
that after using cocaine
for some period of time,
the amount of dopamine that's
released becomes progressively
lower and lower and lower so
that people can never get back
to a state in which dopamine
release is ever as great
as it was the first time they did cocaine
or prior to doing cocaine.
Now with a long period of
no cocaine use whatsoever
and protecting the dopamine system
in a number of different ways,
people can often, not always but often
recover their dopamine system,
if not completely then near completely.
So by all means, if you have
a problem with cocaine, quit,
find a way to quit, get treatment,
get over that one way or another.
We have an episode with an expert guest,
Dr. Anna Lembke,
who's a physician and the chief
of the Stanford School of Medicine
dual diagnosis addiction clinic,
a world expert in dopamine
and addictive substances
and addictions of all kinds.
You can find that episode
at hubermanlab.com.
It's filled with information
about how to get over different
types of addictions,
including cocaine addiction.
Also check out her absolutely phenomenal
and indeed important
book "Dopamine Nation",
which touches on some of this as well.
And in the show note
captions for the episode
where Dr. Lembke was my guest,
you can also find some additional
resources related to that.
So cocaine is terrible. That
needs to be acknowledged.
It should be avoided and you
should find a way to quit it
if you are currently using.
With that said,
the delivery mechanism for
cocaine strongly parallels
the delivery mechanisms for nicotine.
That is people will snort cocaine,
which is a lot like snuffing or dipping.
That is when people snort cocaine,
they're bringing cocaine into
proximity or into contact,
really with the mucosal
lining of the nasal passages,
which then allows the
psychoactive substances
to permeate into the bloodstream.
Very seldom do people eat it,
although that does
happen from time to time,
people will inject it,
as so-called mainlining,
which is a very rapid entry
into the bloodstream because
it's direct application to the bloodstream
by way of injection.
And then there's crack cocaine,
which is essentially like
a vaporizing of the cocaine
from a so-called cocaine rock,
that somewhat resembles
vaping of nicotine.
So while the vape pen
involves a liquid that's sold,
a cartridge that contains nicotine
and often other flavors as
well, flavorings I should say,
both crack cocaine and
vaping cause very rapid
increases in the relative substances
that are psychoactive,
in the case of cocaine,
that would be cocaine and
the increase in dopamine
in the brain and body I should mention.
And in the case of vaping,
there's a very rapid increase
in blood concentrations of nicotine,
much faster than occur
with cigarette smoking
or other modes of nicotine delivery.
So that speed of onset turns
out to be a critical parameter
because the speed of onset
of nicotine is going to also
determine the speed of release of dopamine
in the nucleus accumbens
and ventral tegmental area,
that mesolimbic reward pathway.
And with the mesolimbic reward pathway,
it's not just about the peak,
meaning the maximal amount
of dopamine that's released,
but it's the time course,
how steep the curve is,
how quickly that dopamine increases
that's going to determine how reinforcing,
how habit forming and indeed how addictive
a particular substance is.
One of the major important
differences between vaping and
cigarette smoking is that the onset
of dopamine release from vaping is faster.
And even a subtle increase
in the rate at which dopamine
increases in the mesolimbic
reward pathway can make a given
amount of nicotine much more
habit forming and addictive.
Now this probably explains
the fact that many,
many more people, in particular,
young people age 25 and younger
are vaping at phenomenal rates.
People are starting to vape
in just about everywhere.
You see this in restaurants,
you see it on the street,
indeed you even see it in the classroom.
This has actually become
sort of sport of sorts.
Certainly not something I encourage.
In fact, when I learned about this from
a new college student is telling me
that many college students are
actually bringing vape pens
into the classroom.
I think this is also
happening in high schools
and even junior high schools.
This is a really concerning practice.
And here I'm not trying to come across as
the anti vaping crusader,
but I must say given the negative effects
on one's health in the long term,
but also given these exceedingly
powerful reward properties
of nicotine entering
the bloodstream quickly,
and dopamine being released very quickly
from the mesolimbic reward pathway,
what we're seeing out
there makes total sense.
Young people's brains are
essentially getting wired
to the expectation that dopamine
is going to be increased
dramatically and quickly
under their control,
except it's under their control
only in a very narrow
set of circumstances.
Recall the definition of addiction,
a progressive narrowing of the things
that bring you pleasure.
We can change that statement
to also say a progressive
narrowing and specific kinetics,
that is specific time course of the things
that bring you pleasure.
Now that's a bit of a
nerdier statement than
a progressive narrowing of the things
that bring you pleasure.
But what we are going to
see in the next few years,
I believe is an entire
generation of young people
for which a very large percentage
of them are going to be
seeking out a pattern or feeling
because to the person taking it,
they're not looking at
their dopamine levels
rising in their blood.
They're experiencing this
as an increase in focus,
an increase in alertness,
an increase in mood and
wellbeing that is very rapid,
very dramatic,
and that simply cannot be
recreated by any other substance.
And that's a very concerning scenario,
concerning because that
mesolimbic reward pathway
is the only pathway,
the only pathway by which
you can achieve the rewarding
properties of any kind of endeavor,
not just vaping of course.
It is the way in which people
achieve satisfaction from
reaching a relationship
goal or an athletic goal
or an educational goal,
any kind of goal or sense of satisfaction.
And so it comes as no surprise
that vaping is strongly
associated with increased
levels of depression,
especially when vaping use drops off.
Why would that be?
If people are getting
so much more dopamine
so much more quickly from vaping,
shouldn't they be feeling better?
That brings us back to the
critical, and I should say,
defining feature of the
dopamine reward pathway
for motivation and wellbeing,
which is that initially a
given substance will cause,
let's say an eight out of
10, again, arbitrary units,
but eight out of 10 increase in dopamine.
But with repeated use,
what ends up happening
is that even at similar
or higher levels of ingestion,
so not just one inhalation a minute,
but maybe two inhalations a minute
or an inhalation every 30 seconds.
Now it's level four out of 10 activation
of dopamine and then three and then two.
And eventually it drops below baseline.
Now the whole system can be recovered
by abstinence from nicotine consumption,
but the dopamine system
is applied to everything,
all sense of wellbeing,
all sense of motivation.
So during the period in
which one is abstaining
from nicotine and vaping in particular,
people do not feel good.
They feel miserable. That's
why it's called withdrawal.
It's associated with a
bunch of psychological and
physiological symptoms that all lead back
to trying to get to the same
levels of dopamine release
in the same patterns that were experienced
when one initially started vaping.
So I'm not trying to paint a
dark picture here, but frankly,
the picture is very dark.
I'm very concerned about a
practice of ingesting something
that powerfully modulates the
dopamine system with the sorts
of kinetics that one sees from
ingestion of crack cocaine
in young people that has all
these other negative health
effects that in the short term
is very powerfully rewarding,
increased focus, wellbeing, et cetera,
but that over a very brief
period of time leads to a state
in which the entire dopamine
reward system is impaired and
can become permanently impaired
unless one intervenes in
a very deliberate way.
So people are directly
controlling the rate of dopamine
and the frequency of dopamine
release by the duration
and frequency of inhalations
off the vape pen.
And that's an incredible thing
because what it does is it
sets up the mesolimbic reward
pathway for an expectation
that dopamine will be
delivered on that schedule.
So that's one of the things
that makes vaping in
particular so hard to quit.
Vaping is actually harder to quit
than cigarette smoking for most people.
Now does that mean that cigarette smoking
is fairly easy to quit for most people?
No.
70% of people who smoke cigarettes report
that they would like to quit
if they thought they could.
The success rate of quitting smoking
when people try to go just cold turkey,
just quit with no assistance whatsoever.
They might tell their family and friends,
hey, I'm quitting, that's it,
is exceedingly low, it's 5%.
So 5% of the people that say, that's it,
I'm not smoking again.
Despite cancer diagnosis,
Despite the fear of the
negative health effects,
I'm not going to ever smoke again.
Despite the financial
cost, the health cost.
I could list off a huge
number of things that it does
that are negative,
but you already know these
or you've heard them,
it makes your skin worse, as
I mentioned it lowers libido,
it disrupts hormones,
it disrupts vascular
function, brain function.
It does all these terrible things.
And yet most people who
try and quit simply can't.
And of the 5% that succeed in quitting,
a full 65% of them relapse within a year.
So that's a very depressing picture,
but it's not to say
that people cannot quit.
And in fact, they can.
There are a couple of methods
that have been shown to help people quit.
Some are behavioral and
some are pharmacologic.
I just want to touch on the
behavioral ones first because it
turns out that there's
a quite powerful method
for quitting nicotine ingestion
by way of cigarette smoking,
which also carries over to vaping.
This is beautiful work that's
been done by my colleague,
in fact, close collaborator,
although I was not
involved in the research
that I'm about to describe at Stanford.
And his name is Dr. David Spiegel.
He is our associate chair of psychiatry.
He's been a guest on the
Huberman Lab Podcast,
and he is a world expert,
if not the world expert
in the clinical applications of hypnosis.
Now when I say hypnosis,
a lot of people think stage hypnosis,
which is the hypnotist
trying to get people to do certain things
and say certain things,
not necessarily against their will
because they actually have to agree.
But the hypnotist is dictating
what the person thinks, says, and does.
Clinical hypnosis is
vastly different from that.
Clinical hypnosis is where the person,
the patient actually directs
their own brain changes toward
a specific emotional or behavioral goal.
Work from Dr. David Spiegel's
laboratory done in 1993,
but that now has been repeated many,
many times that has carried
over into some more modern
studies and I will provide
links to those studies
in the show note captions
so that you can access them.
Those studies have shown that
using a specific form of hypnosis,
people can achieve complete
and total cessation of cigarette smoking.
And there's no reason to
believe this doesn't also carry
over to vaping through one
single hypnosis session.
And the success rates are
incredibly high when one considers
that normally it would be
only a 5% success rate.
The success rate with this
particular hypnosis developed
at Stanford School of Medicine
by Dr. David Spiegel is 23%
of people who do this hypnosis one time
succeed in quitting smoking.
Now in the old days,
which actually wasn't that long ago,
before the advent of smartphones
and before the internet took off
to the extent that it has now,
this was done by having
someone come into the clinic
and Dr. Spiegel himself
or one of his colleagues
would take somebody
through the hypnosis.
Nowadays, you can access this hypnosis.
There's a wonderful app that was developed
by Dr. David Spiegel and others.
It's called Reveri, R-E-V-E-R-I.
I've talked about this app a few times
on the podcast before,
because there are hypnosis
scripts within the app for
enhancing sleep, for improving
ability of fall asleep
if you wake up in the middle
of the night, for focus,
and a number of other behavioral
and emotional changes.
There's also a function in the Reveri app
for smoking cessation,
which exactly parallels
the sort of in laboratory
and in clinic approaches
that Dr. Spiegel would use
were you to show up at his
clinic or his laboratory.
And since that's not possible
for the large number of people out there,
if you or somebody else
is trying to quit smoking
or vaping or dipping or
snuffing for that matter,
I strongly encourage you to
check out the Reveri app.
You can find it easily
by going to reveri.com.
It's available in various formats.
Some of it is available free,
some of it is behind a paywall,
but given the tremendously negative impact
of smoking, vaping, dipping, and snuffing,
the hypnosis for smoking
cessation that Reveri has seems
at least to me as a very
powerful and worthwhile resource.
So please check that out
if you're somebody who's trying
to quit ingesting nicotine
by any of the four methods
that I just described.
Now of course,
there are other methods
that people have used to
successfully quit smoking or vaping
or other forms of nicotine delivery.
And there's actually an
excellent review on this topic.
So before diving into a few
of the specifics about some of
the pharmacology of using nicotine itself
to quit smoking or nicotine
itself to quit vaping,
or the use of various things, even SSRIs,
antidepressants to quit smoking or vaping.
I just want to point you to a
review article that if you'd
like to get a complete
survey of all the options
that are available, there's
an excellent review on this.
It was published just a
couple of years ago in 2020.
And the title of the article is
"Pharmacologic Approach
to Smoking Cessation:
An Updated Review for
Daily Clinical Practice".
And even though this is mainly
focused on smoking cessation,
it carries over quite nicely to vaping.
And it details a number of statistics,
the fact that every year,
700,000 or more people die
because of smoking related diseases.
So there again you have
the negative health effects
that younger people are smoking,
that women are smoking more nowadays.
And that even though you see less smoking,
typically in the US and Canada,
and even in Northern Europe,
some places, there are still
many many people are smoking
who would like to quit,
but that 75% of people,
at least according to this
review earlier, I said 70%,
but estimates are as high as
75% of people who try to quit
smoking relapse within the first week.
The first week, they
just go right back to it.
That's how powerfully
reinforcing the nicotine is.
Remember, it's the nicotine
in the cigarette that's
powerfully reinforcing, but
it's also the oral habit,
the motor habit.
There is this thing about density
of sensory receptors in the lips.
People like bringing things to their lips,
food, cigarettes, other lips
in some cases, et cetera,
there is a reinforcement
pathway related to that
for sort of obvious adaptive reasons.
And as a consequence,
there is a reinforcement,
both from the behavior
and from the dopamine
released from the nicotine itself.
And as I mentioned earlier,
from the positive reinforcement
that comes from increased focus.
So the money that you make through work
or your attentional ability
or the fact that you're alert
and people feel you present,
all of that funnels back
into positive reinforcement,
behavioral reinforcement,
and then what we would call addiction.
So this review covers all of
that and then steps beautifully
through nicotine replacement
therapy and various compounds,
several of which I'm
going to talk about now,
which have been shown to increase
that number that we talked
about earlier of only 5%
of people who try to quit
with no other support
pharmacologic or hypnosis
or otherwise just say that's it,
I'm not going to smoke again,
or I'm not going to vape again,
only 5% of people succeed in doing that.
And even among those, many
end up relapsing later,
there are a couple
pharmacologic approaches.
One of the main ones that's
received a lot of attention in
recent years is Bupropion,
sometimes referred to by its
commercial name Wellbutrin.
Now Bupropion is a compound
that increases the release of
dopamine and to a lesser
extent epinephrine
and some other neurochemicals as well.
It's used for the treatment of depression
and for smoking cessation.
Now I want to point out
again, I'm not a psychiatrist,
so I'm not telling you to take
Bupropion, AKA Wellbutrin,
but I'm going to give you a little
bit of the contour of what's
typically done in terms of
Bupropion administration
to help people get relief
from some of the withdrawal
symptoms of trying to
quit smoking or vaping
or other forms of nicotine ingestion.
Typically Bupropion is taken
in 300 milligram per day
doses divided into two dosages
of 150 milligrams each,
or sometimes there's a
slow release formula.
The dosages will vary
from person to person.
I want to really emphasize that there
is an increased seizure
risk with Bupropion.
It only occurs in a small
fraction of the population,
but nonetheless is a real concern
for those members of the population.
So for those of you with seizure risk,
whether you know it or not,
that's going to be a valid concern
in terms of potential side effects.
The other thing about Bupropion
is that it has to be used
with caution in patients that
have liver disease or renal
disease that can impact the amount
that anyone can take meaning
sometimes people have to take
a much lower dose if
they have renal disease
or liver disease.
And sometimes they can't take it at all.
Sometimes if people are taking
benzodiazepines for whatever
reason or other sedatives,
there are contraindications
there, so Bupropion isn't a
kind of one size fits all or magic bullet
for quitting smoking, nonetheless,
for people that can take it safely,
and again, this is a prescription drug,
a board certified psychiatrist
or other physician is going
to have to prescribe it for you
if it's appropriate for you.
And it moves that number of
5% success rate to about what
one sees with the clinical
hypnosis to about 20% of people
will successfully overcome their nicotine,
or I should say their
smoking or vaping addiction.
Now it's important to ask
why this would work, right?
It's not as if Bupropion is
increasing nicotine per se.
What it's doing is it's tapping
on that mesolimbic reward
pathway, increasing dopamine,
or at least allowing dopamine
levels to say substantially
elevated enough that people
don't experience some of the
drop in dopamine that leads
to the withdrawal symptoms,
the lessening of mood, et cetera.
And it's no coincidence that Bupropion
is also an antidepressant.
It's a common antidepressant
for people that experience
negative side effects
with the so-called SSRIs,
the selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors that prevent
them from taking those
things like lessen libido
or appetite,
or in some cases increased
appetite or any number
of other side effects
that some people, not all,
but some people experience with SSRIs.
They'll be prescribed Wellbutrin,
Bupropion is the generic name.
So Wellbutrin being the
commercial name again,
Bupropion is what they'll be
prescribed instead with the
caveats of seizure risk, renal disease,
liver disease, et cetera.
The outcomes with Wellbutrin
for smoking cessation
are pretty good if you
think about an increase
from 5% to 20%, that's pretty dramatic.
And yet I also want to refer
back to the incredible success
of the clinical hypnosis approach.
Again, you can find that at reveri.com,
the clinical hypnosis approach
has a success rate of 23%.
So it's very closely aligned with,
if not exceeding the
success rate with Bupropion.
Of course there are other
pharmacologic approaches
to quitting smoking or vaping.
All of them generally circle
back to increasing dopamine
and/or norepinephrine in order to offset
some of the withdrawal
symptoms of smoking cessation
or vaping cessation.
A very common approach for
people to try and quit smoking or
vaping is to use nicotine
itself to try and prevent people
from seeking nicotine through
a cigarette or a vape pen.
What I mean by that is people
using a nicotine patch or
nicotine gum or other
nicotine delivery device
that is not cigarettes and not vaping
in order to maintain levels of nicotine
in their bloodstream,
which of course means maintain
levels of nicotine in their
brain and body to the same extent
that they would if they
were smoking or vaping,
maybe even gradually taking
down the total amount of
nicotine in their brain
and body by reducing
the number or size of nicotine gum pieces
that they ingest each day,
or keeping the patch on for
a shorter amount of time
or getting a lower dose patch
that releases less nicotine
total or over time.
All of those approaches have been shown
to be reasonably successful,
I'll get to the numbers in a few minutes,
but reasonably successful
in allowing people
to quit smoking or vaping.
Again, most of the data
is on cigarette smoking
because vaping is a
relatively new phenomenon.
Although quite troublingly,
it's a very rapidly increasing behavior,
especially in the young population.
So that's why I'm kind of
lumping these two things together
because I think very soon we
are going to need an all out
campaign for how to
counter vaping addiction.
So what do we know about smoking cessation
using nicotine itself?
Is the patch best? Is nicotine gum best?
Turns out that a combination of approaches
is best, so somewhat surprising,
but it was very clear from the
literature that I was able to
find that using nicotine
patches for some period of time
and then switching to a gum
and then perhaps switching
to a nasal spray,
that's going to be the most effective.
Then the question is how long
to continue each of those
and whether or not to overlap them.
It seems as if doing one for
about a week and then switching
to another for about a week and
then switching to another is
one rationable and reasonable approach
that many people have used successfully.
Why would that be?
It all has to do with the
different rates of absorption
of nicotine into the bloodstream,
and then the downstream consequences
of that on the dopamine,
acetylcholine, epinephrine,
and other systems of the brain and body.
And while there hasn't been
an extremely detailed study
of the exact kinetics of
how the nasal sprays versus
the transdermal patches
versus the gums, et cetera, work,
there's a logical structure to it
that will immediately make sense to you.
First of all,
the transdermal patches
provide a fairly steady state
dopamine release across the day.
And oftentimes people are
wearing them at night as well.
This is relevant because if
people are ingesting nicotine
by way of smoking and vaping,
hopefully they're not waking
up in the middle of the night
just to smoke or vape.
Believe or not, some people do that,
but of course, while people are asleep,
they are not smoking or vaping.
They always tell you don't fall asleep
with a cigarette in your mouth,
you'll burn the whole house down,
but exceedingly rare to have people
are smoking in their sleep.
So people wake up in the morning
and because the half life
of nicotine from smoking
or vaping is very short,
anywhere from one to two hours,
they're essentially in a state
of withdrawal at the point
where they wake up in the morning.
How can I say that?
Remember, withdrawal sets in
about four hours after the last
ingestion of nicotine by cigarette
or by inhalation from the vape pen.
So people are waking up in
nicotine withdrawal and then
immediately going into the
behavior of ingesting nicotine,
or very soon after waking for most people.
So nicotine patch is going to be
very effective for a week or so, again,
talk to your physician about
the best approach for this,
but then switching to a nasal spray
or switching to nicotine
gum for about a week,
which is going to change the
kinetics of that nicotine
absorption into the bloodstream
and change the release
of dopamine and other
neurochemicals within the brain.
That's going to keep the system
intentionally off balance
so that it never comes to
expect one single pattern
or amplitude of dopamine release.
And that is a very powerful way for a,
let's just call it a
quitting method to work.
Because as I've always said,
the most powerful schedule of dopamine
is going to be this random
intermittent reward.
This is what's used in the casinos
in order to take your money.
And generally they do, on average,
they take your money more
than you take theirs,
and they take more of it.
Not just more often because
they use this random
intermittent schedule.
The random intermittent schedule
is one in which you don't
really know when the peaks in
dopamine are going to arrive.
And so there isn't this
expectation and craving.
And then all of a sudden
when dopamine is released,
it's extremely high.
That's how they get you
to continue playing,
even though basically you're losing money
and your dopamine is dropping,
they elevate it every once in a while.
Nicotine replacement can
be used in a similar way,
but in a benevolent way,
in order to help you get
over smoking or vaping
by keeping the total
amounts of dopamine variable
around the clock
and by changing the amount
of dopamine that's released,
it seems to help people
behaviorally and psychologically
because they don't come to
expect having a particular amount
of dopamine in their brain
and blood at any given time.
And this is an important point
because it brings us to
this notion of homeostasis.
Homeostasis is this tendency
for biological systems
to try and reach equilibrium.
What goes up, goes down, et cetera.
And to some extent to the same degree.
So I'll talk about this right now
in the context of nicotine use withdrawal,
and then the period in which people
no longer crave nicotine.
So you can imagine that
if we were to measure your heart rate,
your blood pressure, and your
overall levels of alertness
and wellbeing and mood, let's
just give that some value.
Let's say it runs from zero
to 10, again, arbitrary units.
Let's just take all those
physiological measures
and the subjected measure of your mood.
And let's measure it
four times an hour across the
day, across the waking hours.
What we would find is a
line that would kind of
squiggle a bit,
maybe a nice text comes
in that you really like,
maybe you get not so good
news and your kind of
autonomic arousal is all over the place,
but on average is kind of a squiggly line
where it increases in the morning
because that's typically
when body temperature
and autonomic arousal increase.
And then towards the afternoon,
it's going to come sloping down.
And then right before sleep,
there'll be an increase again,
if you've ever felt that you
kind of run around a lot before
sleep and then it goes down,
that's kind of the typical contour
of autonomic arousal, mood,
et cetera, across the day,
removing of course life events
and things like psychiatric
illness and depression and et cetera.
That's the typical arc of that.
Now let's superimpose on whatever
that contour is for you, nicotine.
So you get a little bolus as we say,
a little bit of nicotine
from smoking a cigarette
or from taking an
inhalation on a vape pen,
what ends up happening is there's
an increase in blood pressure,
increase in heart rate,
increase in mood, increase in alertness,
all the things we talked about earlier.
Over time,
the body starts to adjust so
that the baseline upon which
that nicotine induced increase
in arousal would occur
is actually reduced, right?
Why would that be?
Well, the body and the brain,
your physiology seeks homeostasis.
So if there's a big
increase in all those things
like blood pressure and mood, et cetera,
typically your baseline
will drop a little bit
to compensate for that over time,
after a couple days or even
weeks of ingesting nicotine.
So let's say you wake up,
you're typically take an
inhalation off your vape,
or you have a cigarette around
nine or 10:00 AM and you do that daily.
You get used to a certain
level of mood and alertness
and wellbeing for that time of day.
And then if you smoke
again in the afternoon,
let's say you also get accustomed
to a certain level of mood
and alertness and wellbeing
for that time of day.
Again, it'll vary
depending on life events,
but your system sort of gets
used to it and your baseline
will drop to compensate for those peaks
so that the peaks aren't
quite as high as they were
when you first started using nicotine.
Now you decide to quit.
So now what we're talking
about is transitioning from the
consumption to what we're going
to call the withdrawal phase.
So now what happens is you say,
that's it, I'm going cold turkey.
I know there's only a 5% success rate,
but I'm going to just go cold
turkey or somebody will say,
no, I'm going to use the Reveri app.
Or somebody says, no,
I'm going to use Bupropion or
another method or nicotine patch
or something of that sort.
Setting aside the nicotine patch
or the nicotine delivery device
and only focusing on
approaches for getting through
withdrawal that have no
direct effects on nicotine.
So not using the nicotine patch,
but say the hypnosis or Bupropion,
which can increase dopamine,
but it doesn't increase nicotine directly.
What happens?
The day that you quit,
that homeostatic mechanism
in your brain and body
that sets your level of
mood and arousal, et cetera,
does not know and hasn't
adjusted to the fact
that you're not bringing in nicotine.
You're not having that cigarette.
You're not having that
inhalation on the vape pen.
So what ends up happening
is that baseline,
which has been adjusted
down to offset the increases
in mood and alertness, et cetera,
when you smoke or vape is lower
than it normally would be.
So that 9:00 AM cigarette
time or vape inhalation time
no longer feels above baseline,
it actually feels below baseline
because what you're seeing
is the lower amplitude
of arousal that was there
to offset the increase you were getting
from vaping or smoking.
And then in the afternoon,
if normally you have a kind
of phase of your afternoon
you really enjoy, you go outside,
you have a vape or a cigarette,
you normally are feeling
relaxed or you go out at night
and you like to vape and you say, nope,
I'm not going to do that anymore,
you're going to feel much,
much worse than you would've
had you never started
smoking or vaping.
Now that's not much help to anyone
who's already started smoking or vaping.
But I say this because it's
very important to understand
that the reason why relapse rates
are so high within the first week,
75% of people relapse within
one week and overall failure
rates are 95% is because
people don't expect
to feel even worse than they did prior
to ever smoking or vaping.
So that first week is absolutely critical.
And the beauty of understanding this
is that if you can get
through that first week,
either by sheer grit or
by finding other methods
to increase dopamine,
healthy methods I would hope,
and certainly cold showers,
ice baths have been shown
to do that by the way.
And this was described in
Dr. Anna Lembke's book,
"Dopamine Nation", cold
showers can increase dopamine,
exercise, positive social interactions.
It's very likely that
people will need to use
other healthy methods to offset
that reduction in dopamine
if ever they stand to get
through that first week.
And again, if you can get
through that first week,
chances are quite a bit
higher that you'll be able to
maintain the cessation
of smoking or vaping.
And of course, hypnosis,
things like Bupropion,
can also assist in that,
Bupropion by way of increasing
dopamine pharmacologically,
hypnosis through changes
in neural circuitry
that aren't completely understood,
but seem to involve a remapping
of some of the so-called
default networks and some of
the networks that are involved
in kind of understanding
of your own internal state.
This stuff gets a little bit
complicated and we're going to
return to this in a upcoming episode
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
but there are indeed legitimate
changes in neural circuitry
caused by clinical hypnosis
that can at least partially
explain why it is so
effective in helping treat
or allow people to stop
smoking and vaping.
So for those of you out there
that, either here or
are saying yourselves,
I just can't seem to
quit smoking or vaping
or dipping or snuffing,
hopefully an understanding of
how that homeostasis process
works and the time course of nicotine,
depending on the delivery device,
hopefully understanding that
will allow you to develop a protocol.
Maybe it involves hypnosis.
Maybe it involves just
understanding that the typical times
in which you ingested nicotine
through any of the different
approaches of bringing it into your system
are going to be particularly hard.
But I don't just mean particularly hard.
I mean, particularly hard,
and you're going to need to do
something specific to offset
that decrease in overall autonomic arousal
and dopamine, et cetera.
Hopefully an understanding
of that will allow you
to get through that first week.
And if you can make it
past that first week,
you stand a very good
chance of never going back.
However, I did consult
with Dr. David Spiegel
in anticipation of this episode,
regardless of the method
that you used to quit smoking
or vaping, snuffing, or dipping,
there's good evidence that
a routine maybe once a month
or even once a week hypnosis
type approach to replenish
or even enhance the neural
circuits that are allowing you to
stay away from nicotine is
going to be a very good idea.
And given that it's a purely
behavioral intervention,
I can see no reason as to
why people wouldn't want
to do that, go in and reinforce, you know,
tighten the bolts on that
circuitry that are allowing you to
not feel the impulse to smoke,
not feel the impulse to vape.
And just a very brief mention,
there is a vast literature on
the fact that when people have
quit smoking or vaping or other
form of consuming nicotine,
that when they consume alcohol,
there's a much higher
probability of relapse.
There are interactions
between alcohol and nicotine
that we'll cover in future episodes.
But for those of you that want to quit,
I want to assure you,
despite the fact that 95% of people fail,
with the appropriate tools,
and I like to think within an
additional understanding of
the underlying biology and
psychology and what you can
expect and when to really
dig your heels and when to
reinforce your system with more dopamine
through any of the number
of the different protocols
and tools that we've offered here
and that you can find elsewhere
in other episodes of the
Huberman Lab Podcast,
I have a high degree of confidence
that you can quit smoking
or vaping, dipping or snuffing.
So today, typical of frankly
all episodes of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we've covered a lot about the biology
of a particular system.
We talked about the biology
of nicotine in particular,
we talked about vaping and
smoking, dipping and snuffing
and the negative health
consequences associated with those.
I want to reemphasize that nicotine
is not what causes cancer.
It is the delivery
device that causes cancer
and the other negative health effects.
That is not to say that people
should be ingesting nicotine
through any different methods
simply to get a cognitive boost.
There are certain
circumstances where that might
be appropriate for the
occasional work about,
certainly not for physical exercise,
given what we talked about earlier,
but of course there are
more and more approaches
to increasing, not just nicotine,
but acetylcholine generally
in order to achieve
cognitive enhancement
or physical enhancement,
or I should say physical
performance enhancement.
Some of those we talked about earlier,
such as Alpha GPC.
In any event, nicotine,
it should now be clear, is an
immensely powerful substance.
One of the most commonly
ingested substances
on the face of the earth and
has been for a very long time.
And now that you understand
the underlying biology and the
way in which this changes your
psychology and physiology,
that should come as no surprise.
If you're learning from and
are enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel.
That's a terrific zero
cost way to support us.
In addition,
please subscribe to the
podcast on Apple and Spotify,
and on both Apple and Spotify,
you can leave us up to a five star review.
If you have questions or
comments or suggestions of topics
you'd like us to cover or guests
you'd like us to invite onto
the Huberman Lab Podcast,
please put those in the
comment section on YouTube.
We do read all the comments.
Please also check out the sponsors
mentioned at the beginning
of today's episode.
That is the best way to
support this podcast.
During today's episode and
on various previous episodes
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we talk about supplements,
while supplements aren't
necessary for everybody,
many people derive
tremendous benefit from them
for things like enhancing
sleep, hormone function,
focus, and so on.
The Huberman Lab Podcast is partnered
with Momentous Supplements,
spelled momentous, O-U-S.
You can find those supplements
at livemomentus.com/huberman.
If you haven't already subscribed
to the Huberman Lab Podcast
Neural Network Newsletter,
it's a monthly newsletter.
We provide summaries of
different podcasts and we provide
summaries of specific
tools that you can use
to enhance sleep for
instance, or enhance dopamine.
We talk about deliberate cold exposure,
deliberate heat exposure.
It's very easy to sign up for,
and it's completely zero cost.
You go to hubermanlab.com,
go to the menu, click on
newsletter, provide us your email.
We do not share it with anybody else.
And you'll receive that
monthly newsletter, and there,
you can also find PDFs of
previous newsletters that you can
immediate download without
even having to sign up.
If you're not already
following us on social media,
we are hubermanlab on Twitter,
hubermanlab on Instagram,
and hubermanlab on Facebook.
And at all of those locations,
I describe science and
science related tools.
Some of which overlap with the content
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
much of which is distinct
from the content covered on
the Huberman Lab Podcast.
So once again,
I'd like to thank you for
joining me today for a discussion
about the biology and
psychological effects of nicotine,
this incredibly powerful substance.
And as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]