- Welcome to The Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
[upbeat guitar music]
I'm Andrew Huberman
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today, we are talking about
obsessive-compulsive disorder
or OCD.
We are also going to talk
about obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder which,
as you will soon learn, is distinct
from obsessive-compulsive disorder.
In fact, many people that
refer to themselves or others
as obsessive or compulsive
or quote-unquote,
having OCD or OCD about
this or OCD about that
do not have clinically diagnosable OCD,
rather, many people have
obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
However, there are many
people in the world
that have actual OCD,
and for those people,
there's a tremendous amount of suffering.
In fact, OCD turns out to be number seven
on the list of most
debilitating illnesses,
not just psychiatric
illnesses, but of all illnesses
which is remarkable and
somewhat frightening.
The good news is thanks to
the fields of psychiatry,
psychology, and science in general,
there are now excellent
treatments for OCD.
We're going to talk about
those treatments today.
Those treatments range
from behavioral therapies,
to drug therapies, and brain stimulation,
and even some of the more
holistic or natural therapies.
As you'll soon learn, for certain people,
they may want to focus more
on the behavioral therapies,
whereas for others, more
on the drug-based therapies
and so on and so forth.
One extremely interesting
and important thing
I learned from this episode
is that the particular
sequence that behavioral
and/or drug and/or holistic
therapies are applied
is extremely important.
In fact, the outcomes of studies
often depend on whether not people start
on drug treatment and then follow
with cognitive behavioral
treatment or vice versa.
We're going to go into all those details
and how they relate to
different types of OCD,
because it turns out there are indeed
different types of
obsessions and compulsions,
and the age of onset for
OCD, and so on and so forth.
What I can assure you is
by the end of this episode,
you'll have a much greater understanding
of what OCD is and what it isn't
and what obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder is
and what it is not.
And you'll have a rich array
of different therapy options
to explore in yourself or in others
that are suffering from OCD.
And if neither you or others that you know
suffer from OCD or obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder,
the information covered
in today's episode will
also provide insight
into how the brain and nervous system
translate thought into action generally.
And also, you're going to learn a lot
about goal-directed behavior generally.
My hope is that by the end of the episode
you'll both understand a
lot about this disease state
that we call OCD, you will
have access to information
that will allow you to
direct treatments to yourself
or others in better ways,
and that you will gain greater insight
into how you function and
how human beings function
in general.
The Huberman Lab Podcast
is proud to announce
that we've partnered with
Momentous Supplements.
We've done that for several reasons.
First of all, the quality
of their supplements
is exceedingly high.
Second of all, we wanted
to have a location
where you could find all of
the supplements discussed
on The Huberman Lab Podcast
in one easy-defined place.
You can now find that place
at livemomentous.com/huberman.
In addition, Momentous
Supplements ship internationally,
something that a lot of
other supplement companies
simply do not do.
So that's terrific whether
or not you live in the US
or you live abroad.
Right now, not all of the supplements
that we'd discuss on The
Huberman Lab Podcast are listed,
but that catalog of supplements
is being expanded very rapidly
and a good number of them
that we've talked about,
some of the more prominent
ones for sleep and focus
and other aspects of
mental and physical health
are already there.
Again, you can find them at
livemomentous.com/huberman.
Before we begin, I'd like to emphasize
that this podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the sponsors
of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an
all-in-one vitamin-mineral
probiotic drink that also has adaptogens
and digestive enzymes.
I started taking Athletic
Greens way back in 2012
and I've taken it every day since
so I'm delighted that they're
sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I started
taking Athletic Greens
and the reason I still
take Athletic Greens
once or twice a day is that it covers
all of my foundational nutritional needs.
In fact, when people ask me,
"what's the one supplement I should take?"
I always say Athletic Greens
because by taking Athletic Greens,
you give support to your immune system,
to your endocrine system,
to your nervous system
and to the so-called gut-brain axis
and the gut microbiome.
As many of you've probably heard,
our gut, meaning everywhere from our mouth
down all the way through our intestine,
is populated by trillions
of little microbacteria
that support the different
systems of our body.
Athletic Greens has the
probiotics that support
the microbiome, and in
turn, support things
like mood, endocrine function,
immune system, and so on.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and claim their special offer.
They'll give you five free travel packs
plus a year supply of vitamin D3 K2.
Many people are deficient in vitamin D3
and in general, vitamin D3 and K2
support a huge number of factors
in your brain and body
that support your immediate
and long-term health.
Again, that's athleticgreens.com/huberman
to claim their special offer.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Thesis.
Thesis makes custom nootropics,
and frankly, I'm not a big fan
of the word nootropics.
I've said that on various podcasts
and on social media posts
and the reason I'm not a
fan of the word nootropics
is it means smart drugs.
But as a neuroscientist,
I know that we don't have
circuits in the brain
or chemicals in the brain for being smart,
we have circuits in the brain for focus
and for task switching and for creativity,
and oftentimes those circuits
differ from one another
although they collaborate to create things
that we think of as intelligence
or focus or creativity, et cetera.
Thesis understands this
and for that reason,
has developed custom nootropics
that match your particular goals
and to your particular biology.
They give you the opportunity to try
several different blends
over the course of a month
and discover which ones work best for you
and which ones don't.
In addition to that personalization,
they take it a step further
by offering free consultations
with a coach to help you
optimize your experience
and dial in your perfect formulas.
I've been using Thesis
for about eight months now
and I can confidently
say that their nootropics
are the best that I've ever used.
My go-to formula is the Clarity Formula
or the Motivation Formula
when I'm going to work or work out,
meaning when I'm going to
do focus cognitive work,
or I'm going to exercise.
I also like their Energy
Formula prior to exercise.
To get your own personalized
nootropics starter kit,
go online to takethesis.com/huberman.
You can take a three minute
quiz that will help match you
to the best custom
nootropics to start with.
And Thesis will send you
four different formulas
to try in that first month.
Again, that's takethesis.com/huberman
and use the code Huberman
at checkout to get 10% off
your first order.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Eight Sleep.
Eight Sleep makes smart mattress covers
that have cooling, heating,
and sleep tracking capacity.
I've talked many times on this podcast
and another podcast and on social media
about the critical relationship
between temperature and sleep.
Generally speaking, your
body temperature has to drop
by about one to three
degrees in order to get
into and to stay in deep sleep.
And waking up has a lot to do
with an increase in body temperature
of about one to three degrees.
So for many people like
myself who run warm
during the night, I find myself waking up
in the middle of the night.
However, recently I started using
an Eight Sleep mattress cover
and by programming in
the specific temperatures
that work for me across the night,
I'm staying asleep through the whole night
and as a consequence, I'm feeling
far better during the day,
much more focus, alertness, et cetera,
all the great things that come
from getting excellent sleep consistently.
The Pro Pod Cover by Eight Sleep
is their most advanced
solution on the market
for thermal regulation during sleep,
that's the one I use.
It pairs dynamic cooling and heating
with biometric tracking.
It also has this really nice feature where
your mattress basically
vibrates a little bit
right upon waking, I like that as well.
You can cover any mattress with it.
You can start sleeping as
cool as 55 degrees Fahrenheit,
or as warm as 110 degrees Fahrenheit,
And that range is available to you
simply because Eight Sleep understands
that people have a tremendous range
in natural body temperatures
and sleeping environments.
If you want to try Eight Sleep,
you can go to eightsleep.com/huberman
and check out their Pro Pod Cover
and save $150 at checkout.
Eight Sleep currently ships
within the USA, Canada,
and in the United Kingdom.
Again, that's eightsleep.com/huberman
to save $150 at checkout.
Let's talk about OCD or
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
First of all, as the name suggests,
OCD includes thoughts or obsessions
and compulsions which are actions.
The obsessions and the
compulsions are often linked.
In fact, most of the time,
the obsessions and the
compulsions are linked
such that the compulsion, the behavior,
is designed to relieve the obsession.
However, one of the hallmark themes
of obsessive-compulsive disorder
is that the obsessions are intrusive.
People don't want to have them.
They don't enjoy having them.
They just seem to pop into people's minds
and they seem to pop into
their mind recurrently.
And the compulsions, unlike
other sorts of behaviors,
provide brief relief to the obsession,
but then very quickly reinforce
or strengthen the obsession.
This is a very key theme to realize
about obsessive-compulsive disorder
so I'm just going to repeat it again.
These two features, first,
the fact that the obsessions
are intrusive and recurrent,
as well as the fact that the
compulsions, the behaviors,
provide, if anything, only
brief relief for the obsessions,
but in most cases simply serve to make
the obsessions stronger
are the hallmark features
of obsessive-compulsive disorder.
And it turns out to be very important
to keep these in mind as we go forward,
not just because they define
obsessive-compulsive disorder,
but they also define
the sorts of treatments
that will and will not work
for obsessive-compulsive disorder.
And then once you understand a little bit
about the neural circuitry underlying
obsessive-compulsive disorder,
which we'll talk about in a few moments,
then you will clearly understand
why being a quote-unquote,
obsessive person
or having obsessive-compulsive personality
is not the same as OCD.
In fact, we can leap ahead a little bit
and compare and contrast OCD
with obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder
along one very particular set of features.
Again, I'll go into this
in more detail later,
but it's fair to say
that OCD is characterized
by these recurrent and
intrusive obsessions.
And as I mentioned before,
the fact that those obsessions
get stronger as a function of people
performing certain behaviors.
So unlike an itch that you feel,
and then you scratch
it and it feels better,
OCD is more like an itch that
you feel, you scratch it,
and the itch intensifies.
That contour or that pattern of behaviors
and thoughts interacting is very different
than obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder,
which mainly involves a sense
of delayed gratification
that people want and somewhat enjoy
because it allows them to function better
or more in line with how they would like
to show up in the world.
So again, OCD has mainly
to do with obsessions
that are intrusive and recurrent,
whereas obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder
does not have that
intrusive feature to it.
People do not mind, or in fact,
often invite or like the
particular patterns of thought
that lead them to be compulsive
along certain dimensions.
So leaving aside obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder for the moment,
let's focus a bit more on OCD and define
how it tends to show up in the world.
First of all, OCD is extremely common.
In fact, current estimates
are that anywhere
from 2.5% to as high as 3
or even 4% of people suffer from true OCD,
that is an astonishingly high number.
Now, the reason the range is so big,
2.5% all the way up to
3, or maybe even 4%,
is that a lot of the features of OCD
go unnoticed both in
the clinician's office
and simply because people don't report it
and don't talk about it.
In fact, it is possible to have recurrent
and intrusive obsessions and not engage
in the sorts of behaviors
that would ever allow
people to notice that somebody has OCD.
That can be because some
of the intrusive thoughts
don't actually lead to overt behaviors
like hand washing or checking
that other people would notice.
It can also be because people learn
to disguise or hide their obsessions
and their compulsions out of shame
or fear of looking strange
or whatever it might be
such that they have these obsessive
and intrusive thoughts, and
they do little micro-behaviors
like they might tap their
fingers on their thigh
as a way to avoid, at
least in their own mind,
something catastrophic happening.
That might seem crazy to you,
it might seem bizarre, but
this is the sort of thing
that operates in a lot of people.
And I really want to emphasize this
because the clinical
literature that are out there
really point to the fact
that many people have OCD,
full blown OCD, and never report it
because of the kind of shame and hiding
associated with it.
Another thing to point out is that OCD
is extremely debilitating.
I mentioned this a few minutes ago,
but OCD is currently
listed as number seven
in terms of the most
debilitating illnesses,
not just mental illnesses or disorders,
but all types of illnesses
including things like asthma
and cancer, et cetera.
So you can imagine with that
standing at number seven,
that it is both extremely common
and extremely debilitating.
And as a consequence, it's now realized
that many hours, days,
weeks, months, or even years
of work performance or showing up at work
of relational interactions really suffer
as a consequence of people having OCD.
So this is a vital problem
that the scientific
and psychiatric and psychological
communities understand.
And it's one of the reasons
that I'm doing this podcast.
And of course, I received
a ton of interest in OCD
because of this incredibly
high incidence of OCD
and how debilitating it is.
We could go really deep into
why it's so debilitating.
I don't want to spend
too much time on that
because I think most of
that is pretty obvious,
but some of it is not.
For instance, one of the
things that makes OCD
so debilitating is, of course,
the shame that we talked about before.
But it's also the fact that
when people are focusing
on their obsessions and their compulsions,
they're not able to focus on other things.
That's simply the way
that the brain works.
We're not able to focus on
too many things at once.
The other thing is that
OCD takes a lot of time
out of people's lives.
With recurrent intrusive
thoughts happening
at very high frequency, or
even at moderate frequency,
people are spending a lot of
time thinking about this stuff
and they're thinking about the behaviors
they need to engage in, and
then engaging in the behaviors,
which as I mentioned before,
just serve to strengthen the compulsions
and so they're not actually
doing the other things
that make us functional human beings
like commuting to work or doing homework
or doing work or listening
when people are talking
or interacting or sports or working out,
all the things that make
for a rich quality life
are taken over by OCD in many cases.
So while that might be obvious to some,
I'm not sure that it's
obvious to everybody
just how much time OCD can occupy.
Another thing you'll
soon learn is that sadly,
a lot of the obsessions
and compulsions in OCD
often relate to taboo topics.
And that's because the
general categories of OCD
fall into three different bins,
checking obsessions and compulsions,
repetition obsessions and compulsions,
and order obsessions and compulsions.
The checking ones are somewhat obvious,
checking the stove or checking the locks,
which I think we all tend to do.
I'm somebody typically
I'll head off to the car
to commute to work and I'll think,
did I lock the front door,
and I'll go back once,
but I won't go back twice or 50 times.
People with OCD will often
go back 20 or 30 times
before they'll actually allow
themselves to drive off.
And then it's a real challenge for them
to continue to drive off
and discard with the idea
that they didn't check the stove
or they didn't check the locks
or they didn't check
something else critical.
Repetition obsessions and compulsions,
obviously can dovetail
with the the checking ones,
but those tend to be
things like counting off
of a certain number of numbers,
like one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven,
seven, six, five, four, three, two, one.
People perform that repeatedly,
repeatedly, repeatedly,
or feel that they have to.
I remember years ago
watching a documentary about
the band, The Ramones, right?
Most people heard of The Ramones, right?
Jeans, T-shirts, aviator glasses,
everyone had to change
their last name to Ramone.
They weren't actually all related
to one another, by the way.
You had to change your
last name to Ramone.
The Ramones had one band member
who was admittedly and known
to others as having OCD.
And during that documentary,
which I forget the name,
I think it was called,
can't remember, anyway,
can't remember, hippocampal lapse there,
but in this documentary,
the band members describe Joey Ramone
as leaving hotels, walking down the stairs
to the parking lot, but then having
to walk up and down them
seven or eight times,
and sometimes getting out of the van again
and walking up and down
them seven or eight times
and it always had to be a
certain number of times,
given a certain number of stairs.
This appears, quote-unquote, crazy,
but of course, we don't want
to think of this as crazy.
This is somebody who very
likely had full blown OCD.
Now that particular
example, believe it or not,
is not all that uncommon.
It just so happens that that example
entailed certain compulsions and behaviors
that were overt and that
other people could see.
And you can imagine how
that would prevent somebody
from moving about their daily life easily.
A lot of people, as I mentioned before,
have obsessions and
compulsions that they hide
and they do these little micro behaviors,
or they'll just count off in their head
as opposed to generating
some sort of walking up
and downstairs or tapping
or things of that sort.
So we have checking, we have repetition,
and then there's order.
Order oftentimes is thought of
as putting cleanliness
or making sure everything is aligned
and perfect and orderly.
And oftentimes that is the case,
but there are other forms of order
that people with OCD can focus on
in a obsessive and compulsive way.
Things like incompleteness, the idea that
one can't walk away from something
or stop doing something
because something's not right
or complete in that picture.
It could be the way the table is set.
It could be the way that
something's written on a page.
It could be an email.
Again, now we're still talking
about OCD, the disorder.
We're not talking about
obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
I'm aware of, well, I'll just be direct,
several colleagues of mine
and it's just remarkable,
the order in their emails.
Every email is perfect,
punctuated, perfect,
grammar, perfect,
everything's spaced perfect.
Do they have OCD?
Well, they might, they might not.
How would I know unless
they disclose that to me.
But they might have obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder, or
they just might be able
to generate a lot of order
and they have a lot of discipline
around the way they write,
and the way they present
any communication with anybody at all.
So if somebody has a OCD
that's in the domain of order,
it could be incompleteness
and the constant feeling
of something not being completed
and a need to complete it.
It can also be in terms of symmetry,
that everything be aligned
in symmetric in some way.
This could be seen perhaps in young kids.
This is one example that
I read in the literature
of children that need to
arrange their stuffed animals
in exact same order every day
and in a particular order to the point
where if you were to move
the little stuffed frog
over next to the stuffed rabbit,
that the child would have
an anxiety reaction to that
and feel literally
compelled, driven to fix that
maybe even multiple times
over and over again.
We'll talk about OCD in children
versus adults in a little bit.
And then the other aspect of order,
which is a little bit less than intuitive,
is this notion of disgust,
this idea that something is contaminated.
So we often think about OCD
and hand washing behavior
in response to people feeling
that something is contaminated,
a space, a towel, et cetera,
or even simply somebody else's hand
and so they're unwilling
to shake somebody's hand.
You can imagine how these
different bins of obsessions
and compulsions, checking
repetition and order
be extremely debilitating
depending on how severe
they are and how many
different domains of life
they show up in.
Because oftentimes in movies
and even the way I'm describing it now
it sounds as if, okay, well
somebody has to check the locks
but they don't have to
also check the stove,
or somebody has the need to
count to seven back and forth
up to seven and down to seven seven times
seven times a day or
something of that sort
where they need symmetry in
very specific domains of life.
But it turns out that this recurrent
and intrusive aspect of obsessions
leads people with OCD
to have checking repetition
and/or order compulsions everywhere.
So whether or not somebody
is at work or in school
or trying to engage in sport
or trying to engage in relationship
or just something simple
like walking down the street,
the obsessions are so
intrusive that they show up
and they compel people to
do things in that domain
independent of whether or not
they happen to be in
one location or another.
In other words, the thought patterns
and the behaviors take
over the environment
as opposed to the environment
driving the thought
patterns and behaviors.
So it therefore becomes impossible
to ever find a room that's clean enough,
to find a bed that's made well enough,
to find anything that's done well enough
to remove the obsession.
And I know I've said
it multiple times now,
but I'm going to say it many
times throughout this episode
in a somewhat obsessive,
but I believe justified way
that every time that one
engages in the compulsion
related to the obsession,
the obsession simply becomes stronger.
So you can imagine what a powerful
and debilitating loop that really is.
So let's drill a little bit deeper
into how the obsessions and compulsions
relate to one another.
If we were to draw a line
between the obsessions
and the compulsions, that
line could be described
as anxiety.
Now, we need to define what anxiety is
and to be quite honest,
most of psychology and science can't agree
on exactly what anxiety is.
Typically the way we think about fear
is that it's a heightened
state of autonomic arousal,
so increased heart rate,
increased breathing,
sweating, et cetera, in
response to an immediate
and present threat or perceived threat.
Whereas anxiety, generally speaking
in the scientific literature,
relates to the same
sorts of thought patterns
and somatic bodily responses, heart rate,
breathing, et cetera,
but without a clear and present danger
being in the environment or right there.
So that's the way that we're
going to talk about anxiety now.
And anxiety is really
what binds the obsessions
and compulsions such
that someone will have
an intrusive thought.
So for instance, someone
will have the thought that
if they turn left on any street,
that something bad will happen.
Okay, that's an obsession.
It's actually not all that uncommon.
Now, how bad and what the specificity
of that bad thing really is will vary.
Some people will think, if I turn left,
something generally bad will happen,
it just makes me feel anxious,
So they always insist on going right.
Whereas other people will
think if I turn left,
so and so will die, or I will die,
or something terrible will happen,
I'll get a disease or someone
else will get a disease
or I'll be cursing myself or somebody else
in some very specific way.
This is unfortunately quite
common in people with OCD.
So they have this feeling
and the feeling can be generally
or specifically related
to a particular outcome.
But beneath that is a feeling of anxiety,
a quickening of the heartbeat,
a quickening of breathing,
a narrowing of one's visual focus.
I've talked about this
before in another podcast,
the Master Stress, another podcast
but if you haven't heard those,
let me just briefly describe
that when we are in a state of increased
so-called autonomic arousal, alertness,
stress, et cetera,
our visual field literally narrows,
the aperture of our
visual field gets smaller
and that's because of the relationship
between the autonomic nervous system
and your visual system, so
you start seeing the world
through sort of soda straw view
or through binocular-like view,
as opposed to seeing the big picture.
Why is that important?
Well, it literally sharpens
and narrows your focus
toward the very thing that the obsessions
and the compulsions are focused on.
So the person walking
down the street who sees
the opportunity to go left or right
will only see the bad decision,
their visual field narrows very tightly
along that possibility
of taking a left turn.
And I know as I describe this
seems totally irrational,
but I want to emphasize
that the person with OCD
knows it's irrational.
They might feel crazy because
they're having these thoughts,
but they know it makes no sense whatsoever
that left somehow would
be different than right
in terms of outcomes in
this particular case,
and yet it feels as if it would.
In fact, in some cases it
feels as if they went left,
they would have a full blown panic attack.
So the idea here is that the
obsessions and compulsions
are bound by anxiety, but then by taking
a right-hand turn, again, in
this one particular example,
by taking a right-hand
turn, there's a very brief,
I should mention, very
brief relief of that anxiety
at the time of the decision
to go right, not left
and there's an additional drop in anxiety
while one takes the right-hand turn
as opposed to the left-hand turn.
And then as I alluded to before,
there's a reinforcement of the compulsion.
In other words, by going right,
it doesn't create a situation in the brain
and psychology of the person
that, oh, you know what,
I'm not anxious anymore, left
would've probably been okay.
It reinforces the idea that
right made me feel better,
or turning right made me feel better,
and going left would've
been that much worse.
Again, it reinforces the
obsession even further.
And again, we could swap out
right turns and left turns
with something like hand washing,
the feeling that something is contaminated
and the need to wash one's hands
even though one already washed their hands
20, 30, 50 times prior.
And we're actually going
to go back to that example
a little bit later when we talk about
one particular category of therapies
that are very effective
in many people for OCD
which are the cognitive
behavioral and exposure therapies.
I think some of you have heard
of cognitive behavioral
and exposure therapies,
but the way they're used to treat OCD
is very much different
than the way they're used
to treat other sorts of anxiety disorders
and other sorts of disorders generally.
So it's fair to say that up
to 70% of people with OCD
have some sort of anxiety
or elevated anxiety,
either directly related to the OCD
or indirectly related to the OCD
and it's really hard to tease those apart
because OCD can create its own anxiety,
as I mentioned before, it can
even increase its own anxiety.
And there's also an issue of depression.
Having OCD can be very depressing,
especially if some of these
OCD thoughts and behaviors
start to really impede people's ability
to function in life.
At work, and school, and relationship,
they can start feeling
less optimistic about life.
And in fact, some people can
become suicidally depressed.
That's how bad OCD can be for us.
So we have to be careful when saying
that 70% of people with
OCD also have anxiety
or X number of people with
OCD are also depressed
because we don't know whether or not
the depression led the OCD
or the other way around
or whether or not they're operating,
as we say in science, in parallel.
Some of the drug treatments
for OCD and depression
and anxiety can tease some of that apart
and we'll talk about that,
but I think it's fair to say that
what binds the obsessions
and compulsions is anxiety,
that there's a feeling of,
or I should say an
urgent feeling of a need
to get rid of the obsession.
And the person feels as if the only way
they can do that is to engage
in a particular compulsive behavior.
Some people are probably wondering
if there's a genetic component to OCD
and indeed there is,
although the nature of
it isn't exactly clear.
And oftentimes when
people hear that something
has a genetic component,
they think it's always directly
inherited from a parent,
and that's not always the case.
There can be genes that
surface in siblings
or genes that surface in children
that are not readily apparent
in terms of what we call a phenotype.
So you have a genotype, the gene,
and then you have a
phenotype, the way it shows up
as a body form or like eye color
or how it shows up in terms of a behavior
or behavioral pattern.
Based on twin studies where researchers
have examined identical
twins, fraternal twins,
even identical twins that
share the same sack in utero,
the what we call monochorionic,
so sitting in the same
little bag during pregnancy
or in different little bags,
you can see different levels
of what's called genetic concordance.
But if we were to just
sort of cut a broad swath
through all of the genetic data,
it's fair to say that about
40 to 50% of OCD cases
have some genetic component,
some mutation or some
inherited aspect that's genetic
and that one could point to
if they got their genome mapped.
Now, while that's interesting,
I don't think it's terribly
useful for most people.
First of all, you can't
really control your genes,
at least at this point in history,
even though there are things
like epigenetic control
and people are very
excited about technologies
like CRISPR for modifying the genome
in humans at some point,
most people can't control
their genetics, right?
You can't pick who your
parents were as they say.
So just know that there
is a genetic component
in about half of people
with OCD, but not always.
Now as is typical for this podcast,
I want to focus on some
of the neural mechanisms
and chemical systems in the brain and body
that generate
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
In fact, if you've watched
this podcast before,
listen to this podcast before,
this is always how I structure things.
First, we introduce a topic
and we explore that topic in detail
and really define what
it is and what it isn't.
And then it's very
important that we focus on
what is known and what is not known
about the biological
mechanisms that generate
whatever that thing happens
to be, in this case,
OCD and obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
Now I want to emphasize
that even if you don't have
a background in biology,
I will make this information
accessible to you.
And I also want to emphasize
that for those of you
that are interested in treatments
and are anxiously awaiting
the description of things
that can help with OCD, I encourage you,
if you will, to please try and digest
some of the material about
the underlying mechanisms
because understanding
even just a little bit
of those biological
mechanisms can really help
shed light on why particular drug
and behavioral treatments
and other sorts of treatments
work and don't work.
This is especially
important in the case of OCD
where it turns out that the order
and type of treatment can really vary
according to individual,
and that's something really
special and important about OCD
that we really can't say
for a number of the other
sorts of disorders that we've described
on previous podcasts.
So let's take a step back
and look at the neural circuitry.
What's going on in the brain
and body of people with OCD?
Why the intrusive recurrent thoughts?
Why the compulsions?
Why is that whole system bound by anxiety?
And in some ways in thinking about that,
I want you to keep in mind
that the brain has two main functions.
The brain's main functions are
to take care of all
the housekeeping stuff,
make sure digestion works,
make sure the heart beats,
make sure you keep
breathing no matter what,
make sure that you can see, you can hear,
you can smell, et cetera,
the basic stuff, and then
there's an enormous amount
of brain real estate that's designed
to allow you to predict
what's going to happen next,
either in the immediate future
or in the long-term future.
And largely that's done based
on your knowledge of the past.
So you also have memory systems.
And of course you have
systems in the brain and body
that are designed to bind what's happening
at the housekeeping level,
like your heart rate,
to your anticipation of
what's going to happen next.
So if you're thinking about
something very fearful,
your body will have one type of reaction.
If you're thinking about
something very pleasant
and relaxing, your body will
have another type of reaction.
So whenever I hear about
the brain-body distinction,
I have to just remind everybody
that there really is no distinction
between brain and body
when you think about it
through the nervous system.
The nervous system is the brain,
the eyes, the spinal cord,
but of course all their connections
with all the organs of the body
and the connections of
all the organs of the body
with the brain, the
spinal cord, et cetera.
So as I describe these neural circuits,
I don't want you to think of them
as just things happening in the head,
they are certainly happening in the head,
in fact, the circuits all
described most in detail
do exist within the confines
of your cranial vault,
that's nerd speak for skull,
but those circuits are
driving particular predictions
and therefore particular biases
towards particular actions in your body.
They're creating a state of readiness
or a state of desire to
check or desire to count
or desire to avoid et cetera, et cetera.
So what are these circuits?
Well, there's been a lot
of wonderful research
exploring the neural circuit's underlying
obsessive-compulsive disorder
and that's mainly been accomplished
through a couple of methods.
Most of those methods
when applied in humans
involve getting some look
into which brain areas
are active when people
are having obsessions
and when people are
engaging in compulsions.
Now that might seem simple to do,
but of course your brain is
housed inside the cranial vault.
And in order to look inside it,
you have to use things like
magnetic resonance imaging,
which is just fancy technology
for looking at blood flow,
which relates to activation
of neurons, nerve cells,
or things lik PET, P-E-T, imaging,
which has nothing to do with the verb pet
and has nothing to do with your house pet,
has everything to do with
positron emission tomography,
which is just another way of seeing
which brain areas are active
and then you can also
use PET to figure out
what sorts of neurochemicals are active,
like dopamine, et cetera.
Many studies, we can fairly say dozens
if not hundreds of studies,
have now identified a particular circuit
or loop of brain areas
that are interconnected
and very active in
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
That loop includes the cortex,
which is kind of the outer
shell of the human brain.
The lumpy stuff, as
it's sometimes appears,
if the skull is removed.
And it involves an area
called the striatum
which is involved in action selection
and holding back action.
The striatum is involved
in what's commonly called
go and no-go types of behaviors.
So every type of behavior
like picking up a pen
or a mug of coffee involves
a go type function.
It involves generating an action.
But every time I resist an action,
my nervous system is also doing that
using this brain structure, the striatum,
which includes, among other
things, the basal ganglia.
We've talked about that before.
I'm not trying to overload
you with terminology here,
but I know some people are
interested in terminology.
So you have go behaviors
and you have no-go,
resisting of behaviors,
not going toward behavior.
The cortex and the striatum
are in this intricate
back and forth talk.
It's really loops of connections.
The cortex doesn't tell
the striatum what to do,
the striatum doesn't tell
the cortex what to do.
They're in a crosstalk.
Like any good relationship, there's a lot
of back and forth communication.
There's a third element in
this cortico-striatal loop
as it's called, and that's the thalamus.
Now, the thalamus is not a structure
I've talked a lot about
before on this podcast,
but it's one of my favorite
structures to think about
and teach about in neuroanatomy,
which I teach back at Stanford
and I've taught for many years elsewhere
because the thalamus is this incredible
egg-like structure in
the center of your brain
that has different channels through it.
Channels for relaying visual information
or auditory information
or touch information
from your environment up into your cortex,
and as a consequence,
making certain things
that are happening to you and around you
apparent to you, making you aware of them,
making you perceive them
and suppressing others.
So for instance, right now,
if you're hearing me say this,
your thalamus has what are
called auditory nuclei,
there's collections of neurons
that respond to sound waves
that are of course coming
in through your ears,
and your thalamus is active in a way
that those particular
regions of your thalamus
are allowed, literally permitted
to pass the information
coming from your ears
through some other steps
but then to your thalamus,
your auditory thalamus,
then up to your cortex and you can hear
what I'm saying right now.
At the same time, your
thalamus is surrounded
by a kind of a shell,
something called the
thalamic reticular nucleus.
Again, you don't have
to remember the names,
but this thalamic reticular nucleus,
also sometimes called the
reticular thalamic nucleus,
this is, believe it or not, a
subject of debate in science.
There are people that
literally hated each other,
probably still hate each other,
even though one of them
is dead for decades,
because they would argue it
was thalamic reticular nucleus,
the other was reticular thalamic nucleus.
Anyway, these are scientists,
they're people, they tend to debate.
but the thalamic reticular nucleus,
as I'm going to call it,
serves as a sort of gate
as to which information
is allowed to pass through
up to your conscious
experience, and which is not.
And that gating mechanism
is strongly regulated
by the chemical GABA.
GABA is a neurotransmitter
that is inhibitory, as we say,
it serves to shut down
or suppress the activity
of other neurons.
So the thalamic reticular
nucleus is really saying,
no, touch information
cannot come in right now.
You should not be
thinking about the contact
of the back of your legs with the chair
that you're sitting on, Andrew,
you should be thinking about
what you're trying to say
and what you're hearing
and how your voice sounds
and what you see in
front of you, et cetera.
Whereas if I'm about to get
an injection from a doctor
or I'm in pain, or I'm in pleasure,
I'm going to think about
my somatic sensation
at the level of touch
and I'm probably going to think less
about smells in the room,
although I might also think
about smells in the room
or what I'm seeing and what I'm hearing.
We can combine all these
different sensory modalities,
but the thalamic reticular nucleus
really allows us to funnel,
to direct particular categories
of sensory experience
into our conscious awareness
and suppress other categories
of sensory experience.
In addition, the thalamic
reticular nucleus
plays a critical role in which thoughts
are allowed to pass up to
our conscious perception
and which ones are not,
so much so that some neuroscientists
and indeed some neurophilosophers,
if you want call them that,
have theorized or philosophized that
the thalamic reticular nucleus
is actually involved in our consciousness.
Now, consciousness isn't a topic
that I really want to
talk about this episode
and it's a very kind of mushy-murky,
as we say in science, it's a shmooey term
because it doesn't really
have clear definitions
so arguments about it often get lost
in the fact that people are
arguing about different things.
But when I say consciousness,
what I mean is conscious awareness.
So let's zoom out and
take a look at the circuit
that we've got and that we now know
based on neuroimaging studies is
intimately involved in
generating obsessions
and compulsions in OCD.
We have a cortex or neocortex,
which is involved in
perception and understanding
of what's happening.
We have the striatum and basal ganglia,
which are involved in
generating behaviors, go,
and suppressing behaviors, no-go.
And we have the thalamus which collects
all of our sensory experience in parallel,
hearing, touch, smell, et cetera,
not so much smell through the
thalamus, I should mention,
but the other senses that is.
And then that thalamus is encased
by the thalamic reticular
nucleus, which serves
as a kind of a guard
saying you can pass through
and you can pass through,
but you, you, you
can't pass through up to conscious
understanding and perception.
So that loop, this
cortico-striatal-thalamic loop,
cortico-striatal-thalamic
loop is the circuit
thought to underlie OCD,
and dysfunction in that circuit
is what's thought to underlie OCD.
Now, again, this circuit
exists in all of us
and it can operate in healthy ways,
or it can operate in ways
that make us feel unhealthy
or even suffer from full blown OCD.
How do we know that this
circuit is involved in OCD?
Well there, we can look to
some really interesting studies
that involve bringing human
subjects into the laboratory
and generating their
obsessions and compulsions
and then imaging their brain using
any variety of techniques
that we talked about before.
What would such an experiment look like?
Well, in order to do
that sort of experiment,
first of all, you need people who have OCD
and of course you need
control subjects that don't,
and you need to be able to reliably evoke
the obsessions and the compulsions.
Now, it turns out this is
most easily, or I should say
most simply done, 'cause it can't be easy
for the people with OCD,
but this is most straightforward,
that's the word I was looking for,
most straightforward when
looking at the category
of obsessions and compulsions that relate
to order and cleanliness.
So what they do typically
is bring subjects
into the laboratory who have a obsession
about germs and contamination
and a compulsion to hand wash,
and they give these
people, believe it or not,
a sweaty towel that contains the sweat
and the odor and the
liquid, basically, from
somebody else's hands.
In fact, they'll sometimes have someone
wipe their own sweat off
the back of their neck
and put it on the towel
and then they'll put it
in front of the person,
which as you can imagine
for someone with OCD is
incredibly anxiety-provoking
and almost always evokes
these obsessions about,
ugh, this is really, this is really bad.
This is really bad, I need to clean,
I need to clean. I need to clean.
Now they're doing all this while someone
is in a brain scanner or
while they're being imaged
for positron emission tomography.
And then they can also look at
the patterns of activation in the brain
while the person is doing hand washing.
Although sometimes the apparati
associated with these imaging studies
make it hard to do a lot of movement,
they can do these sorts of studies.
They have done these sorts of studies
in many subjects using
different variations
of what I just described.
And low and behold what lights up?
And when I say lights up,
what sorts of brain regions
are more metabolically
active, more blood flow,
more neural activity?
Well, it's this particular
cortico-striatal-thalamic loop.
In addition to that,
some of the drug treatments
that are effective in some,
and I want to emphasize some individuals,
at suppressing obsessions
and or compulsions
such as the selective
serotonin reuptake inhibitors
or SSRIs, which we'll talk
about in a little bit,
when people take those drugs,
they see not just a suppression of
the obsession and compulsion,
but also a suppression of these
particular neural circuits.
They become less active.
Now I want to emphasize
and telegraph a little bit
of what's coming later,
these drugs like SSRIs do not
work for everybody with OCD.
And as many of you know,
they carry other certain
problems and side effects
for many but not all individuals.
But nonetheless, what we have now
is an observation that this circuit,
the cortico-striatal-thalamic loop,
is active in OCD.
We have a manipulation that
when people take a drug
that at least in those individuals
is effective in suppressing or eliminating
the obsessions and compulsions,
there's less activity in this loop.
And thanks to some very
good animal model studies,
that at least at this point in time,
you really couldn't do in humans,
although soon that may change,
we now know in a causal way
that the equivalent circuitry
exists in other animals,
such as mice, such as
cats, such as monkeys,
and that activation of those particular
cortico-striatal-thalamic circuits
in animal models can indeed evoke OCD
in an individual that prior to that
did not have OCD.
So I'm just going to
briefly describe one study.
This is a now classic study published
in the journal Science,
one of the three apex journals in 2013.
The first author on this paper
is Susanne Ahmari, A-H-M-A-R-I.
I will provide a link to
this in the show notes.
It's a truly landmark paper done
in Rene Hen's lab at Columbia University.
And the title of the paper
is repeated cortico-striatal
stimulation generates,
that's the key word here,
generates persistent OCD-like behavior.
What they did is they took mice,
mice do mouse things.
They move around, they play with toys,
they eat, they pee, they mate,
they do various things in their cage,
but they also groom.
Humans groom, animals with fur groom,
Well, you hope most people groom,
some people over-groom,
some people under-groom,
but most people groom.
They'll comb their hair,
they'll clean, et cetera.
Those are normal behaviors
that humans engage in.
I'm not aware that mice comb their hair,
but mice adjust their hair.
So they'll kind of pet their hair
and they'll do this.
They'll sometimes even
do it to each other.
We used to have mice in the lab,
now we only do human studies,
but the mice will groom themselves,
and typical, what we call wild type mice,
not because they're wild,
but because they're typical,
will groom themselves at
a particular frequency,
but not to the point where
their hair is falling out.
Not constantly, they are
grooming some of the time
and they're doing other mouse
things other mouse times.
So in this particular study,
what they did is they
used some technology,
which it actually was discussed
on a previous episode of
The Huberman Lab Podcast,
this is technology that was
developed by a psychiatrist
and bioengineer by the
name of Karl Deisseroth,
one of my colleagues at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This is technology that allows researchers
to use the presentation of light
to control neural activity
in particular brain areas
in a very high fidelity way.
You control the activity in
the cortex of the striatum
or the thalamus when you
want and how you want.
It's really a beautiful technology.
In any event, what they
did in this study is,
or I should say what Susan Ahmari
and colleagues did in this study
was to stimulate the
cortico-striatal circuitry
in animals that did not
have any OCD-like behavior.
And when they did that,
those animals started grooming incessantly
to the point where their hair
was falling out or they even,
they didn't take the experiments
this far, fortunately,
but the animals would have a tendency
to almost rub themselves raw
in the same way that
somebody who has a compulsion
to hand wash would, sadly,
people will hand wash
to the point where their hands
are actually bleeding and raw.
It's really that bad.
I know that's tough imagery to imagine,
and you can't even imagine
why someone would self harm
in that way, but again,
that's that incredible anxiety
relationship between the
compulsion, excuse me,
the obsession and the compulsion,
and the fact that
engaging in the compulsion
simply strengthens the obsession
and therefore the anxiety.
So that collection of studies, of data,
FMRI, PET scanning in humans,
the treatment with SSRIs,
and these experiments where
researchers have actively triggered
these particular circuits in animal models
that previously did not have
too much activity in these circuits
and then they observe OCD emerging
really points squarely to the fact
that the cortico-striatal-thalamic loop
is likely to be the basis of OCD.
Now, of course, other circuits
could also be involved,
but the cortico-striatal-thalamic circuit
seems to be the main circuit
generating OCD-like behavior.
That's a lot of mechanism.
Hopefully it was described in a way
that you can digest and understand.
And some of you might be
thinking, well, so what?
Why does that help me?
I mean, I can't reach into my brain
and turn off my cortex.
I can't reach into my brain
and turn off my thalamus.
And indeed, on the one hand, that's true.
But as you'll next learn
when thinking about the
various behavioral treatments
and drug treatments
and holistic treatments for OCD,
what you'll notice is that each one taps
into a different component
of this cortico-striatal-thalamic loop.
And by understanding
that, you can start to see
why certain treatments
might work at one stage
of the illness versus others.
You will also start to understand why
obsessive-compulsive personality disorder
does not have the same
sorts of engagements
of these neural loops,
and yet relies on other
aspects of brain and body
and therefore responds best
to other sorts of treatments.
Or in some cases, people
with obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder are
not even seeking treatment
as I alluded to before.
The point here is that by understanding
the underlying mechanism
why certain drugs and
behavioral treatments work
and don't work will become
immediately apparent
and in thinking about
that, in knowing that,
you'll be able to make excellent choices,
I believe, in terms of what
sorts of treatments you pursue,
what sorts of treatments you abandon,
and most importantly, the order,
the sequence that you pursue
and apply those treatments.
Before we go any further,
I'd like to give people
a little bit of a window into
what a diagnosis for OCD would look like.
Give you a sense of the sorts of questions
that a clinician would ask to determine
whether or not somebody has OCD or not.
Now, I want to be clear,
I'm not going to do this
in an exhaustive way.
I wouldn't want anyone to self-diagnose.
Although I'm hoping that
by sharing some of this,
that some of you might get insight
into whether or not you do have obsessions
and compulsions that
might qualify for OCD,
and perhaps even to seek out help.
The most commonly used test of OCD,
or for OCD, I should say,
is called the Yale-Brown
Obsessive Compulsive Scale.
And this is, scientists love acronyms
as do the military, and it's the Y-BOCS,
the Y-B-O-C-S, the Y-BOCS.
So typically someone
will go into the clinic
either because a family
member encouraged them to
or because they feel
that they're suffering
from obsessions and compulsions,
and before the clinician would proceed
with any kind of direct questions,
they would very clearly define
what obsessions and compulsions are.
And here I'm actually
reading from the Y-BOCS.
So quote, "obsessions are
unwelcome and distressing ideas,
thoughts, images or impulses
that repeatedly enter your mind.
They may seem to occur against your will.
They may be repugnant to you,
you may recognize them as senseless
and they may not fit your personality."
Then there are compulsions.
Quote, "Compulsions, on the other hand,
are behaviors or acts that
you feel driven to perform
although you may recognize
them as senseless or excessive.
At times, you may try to resist doing them
but this may prove difficult.
You may experience anxiety
that does not diminish
until the behavior is completed."
And as I mentioned before in many cases,
immediately after the
behavior has completed,
the anxiety doesn't just return,
it indeed can strengthen.
Now, there are a tremendous
number of questions
on the Y-BOCS.
So I'm just going to highlight
a few of the general categories.
Typically, the person
will fill out a checklist,
so they will designate whether or not
currently or in the past they have,
for instance, aggressive obsessions,
fear that one might harm themselves,
fear that one might harm others,
fear that they'll steal things,
fear that they will act
on unwanted impulses,
currently or in the past or both,
that's one category.
The other one are
contamination obsessions.
So concern with dirt or germs,
bothered by sticky substances or residues,
et cetera, et cetera.
So there are a bunch
of different categories
that include, for instance,
sexual obsessions,
what are called saving obsessions,
even moral obsessions,
excess concern with right
or wrong or morality,
concerned with sacrilege and blasphemy,
obsession with need for
symmetry and exactness.
Again, all of these
questions being answered
as either present in the past
or not present in the past,
present currently or
not present currently.
And then the test generally
transitions over to questions
about target symptoms.
They really try and get people to identify
if they have obsessions, what
are their exact obsessions?
Now, this turns out to be really important
because as we talk about some
of the therapies that really work,
I'll just give away a little bit
of why they work best in certain cases
and why they don't work
as well in other cases,
it turns out that it
becomes very important
for the clinician and the patient
to not just identify the obsessions
and the compulsions generally
in a kind of a generic or top contour way,
but to really encourage
or even force the patient
to define very precisely what the biggest,
most catastrophic fear is,
what the obsession really relates to.
That turns out to be very important
in disrupting this
cortico-striatal-thalamic loop
and getting relief from symptoms
one way or the other.
So the Yale-Brown Obsessive
Compulsive Scale, this Y-BOCS,
again, is very extensive,
it goes on for dozens of pages actually,
and has all these different categories,
not so much designed to just pinpoint
what people obsess about
or what they feel compelled to do,
but to also try and identify
what is the fear that's driving all this.
In the way that we've
set this up thus far,
we've been talking about
obsessions and compulsions
is kind of existing in a vacuum.
You're obsessed about germs
and you're compelled to wash your hands,
obsessed about germs,
compelled to wash your hands.
Or obsessed about symmetry,
compelled to put right
angles on everything.
Or obsessed about counting
and therefore counting, et cetera.
But beneath that
is a cognitive component
that is not at all apparent
from someone describing their obsession
and from someone describing or
displaying their compulsion.
The deeper layer to all
that is what is the fear,
exactly, if one were to
not perform the compulsion,
meaning what is the fear
that's driving the obsession?
So that brings us to a
very powerful category
of treatments that I
should say does not work
in everybody with OCD
but works in many people with OCD
and really speaks to the
underlying neural circuitry
that generates OCD and
how to interrupt it.
And that is the treatment
of cognitive behavioral therapy
and in particular,
exposure-based cognitive
behavioral therapy.
So we're going to talk about
cognitive behavioral therapy
and exposure therapy now,
but right at the outset,
I want to distinguish the kinds
of cognitive behavioral therapy
and exposure therapies that are done
for obsessive-compulsive disorder,
for the sorts of cognitive
behavioral therapies
that are done for other types
of mental challenges and disorders
because cognitive
behavioral therapy for OCD
really has everything to do
with identifying the utmost fear.
In some sense, we can think of fears
as kind of along a hierarchy.
An the example earlier of somebody
being afraid to turn left and therefore
feeling compelled to turn right,
you would want to take that person
and really understand
what do they fear most
about turning left?
Now they might not be aware of it.
They might not be conscious
to what that really is,
but if you were to probe
them in a clinical setting,
you would eventually get to an answer.
That answer could be at first,
I don't know, just, it's just bad.
I don't know why it's
bad, it makes no sense,
but it's just bad.
I do not want to go left.
I don't know why, I don't know why.
But if you were to push
that person a little bit
in a respectful and kind and caring way
aimed at their treatment,
if you were to push 'em and say,
well, what do you mean by bad?
If you turn left, you
think the world would end?
They might say, no, the
world's not going to end,
but you know, someone is
going to die suddenly.
I know that sounds crazy, but
somebody's going to die suddenly.
This almost sounds like superstition,
we'll talk about superstitions later,
but indeed it is somewhat superstitious.
So for instance, you would
say, who's going to die?
And they'd say, I don't know.
And you'd say, no, really
who's going to die?
If you think about this,
are you going to die?
Is so and so going to die?
And very often,
very often what you find is that
people will start to
reveal the underlying obsession
at a level of detail that
both to the clinician
and to them can be somewhat astonishing
even though they've been
living with that detail
in their mind for a very long time.
Now, how could somebody
start to reveal detail
about something that's
existed in their mind
for a very long time, but
not known about it, right?
Not been aware of it.
Now, some of you might think,
oh, it's repressed or something.
That's not at all what's happening.
If you think about the
architecture of OCD,
typically, people will have an obsession
and then they'll engage in the compulsion
as quickly as they can to
relieve that obsession.
So in many ways, the disease itself
prevents people from ever
getting to the bottom
of that trough, ever getting to the point
where they really clearly
articulate to themselves
exactly what it is that they fear.
But it becomes so essential to articulate
exactly what it is that they fear
for a somewhat counterintuitive reason.
You might think, oh,
the moment they realize
exactly what they fear, everything lifts,
the circuit turns off
and they just feel better
because they realized it.
I wish I could tell you that's the case,
but it turns out it's the opposite.
What the clinician is
actually trying to do
is get people to feel
more anxiety, not less.
What they're trying to get them to do
is to short circuit, no pun intended,
to intervene in their own neural circuit,
I should say, with that relief of anxiety,
however brief, brought on by engaging
in the compulsion
related to the obsession.
So, whereas typically someone would feel
the obsession with, ugh,
I don't want to turn left
'cause something bad's going to happen,
someone's going to die,
and then they turn right,
they never get the
option or the opportunity
to really explore what would happen
were they to turn left or to
not be able to turn right.
By forcing them down the path of inquiry,
that leads them to the place
where they very clearly
identify the fear, the anxiety,
it raises the anxiety in them,
and that's actually what
the clinician is after.
Cognitive behavioral
therapy and exposure therapy
in the context of OCD, most often involves
trying to get people to tolerate,
not relieve their anxiety.
This is extremely important.
And I realize there's variation to this
depending on the style of
cognitive behavioral therapy,
the style of exposure therapy,
but almost across the board,
The goal, again, is to get
people to feel the anxiety
that normally they are able
to at least partially relieve,
however briefly, by
engaging in the compulsion.
So if we think back to that circuit
of cortico-striatal-thalamic,
what's going on here?
Where is CBT intervening?
What part of the circuit
is getting interrupted?
Well, as you recall,
the cortex is involved
in conscious perception.
The thalamus and that
thalamic reticular nucleus
are involved in the
passage of certain types
of experience up to our
conscious perception, not others.
And the striatum is involved
in this go, no-go type behavior.
When OCD is really expressing
itself in its fullness,
people feel an anxiety
around a particular thought
and they either have a go,
for instance, wash hands,
or a no-go, do not turn
left type reaction.
By having people progressively,
in a kind of hierarchical way,
reveal their precise source of anxiety,
their utmost fear in this context,
what happens is they feel enormous amounts
of autonomic arousal.
Now in the context of anxiety treatment
or other types of treatments,
the goal would be to
teach people to dampen,
to lessen their anxiety
through breathing techniques
or through visualization techniques
or through self-talk or
through social support,
any of the number of
things that are well-known
to help people self
regulate their own anxiety.
Here, it's the opposite.
What they're trying to
get the patient to do
is to really feel the
anxiety at its maximum,
but then do the exact opposite
of whatever the normal compulsion is.
So if normally the compulsion
is to wash one's hands,
then the idea is to suppress hand washing
while being in the experience
of the utmost anxiety.
Or in the case of not turning left,
the person is expected to
or would hopefully be able
to actually turn left,
and as you can imagine, that
would evoke tremendous anxiety
and yet to tolerate that anxiety.
Now I want to be very clear,
this is not the sort of thing
you want to do on your own.
This is not the sort of thing
you want to do for a friend.
This is done by trained
licensed psychologists
and psychiatrists.
But nonetheless, it
really points to the fact
that as a anxiety-related disorder,
OCD is distinct from
other types of anxiety
and anxiety-related disorders,
things like PTSD and
panic disorder, et cetera,
because the goal again
is to bring the person
right up close to the thing
that they fear the most
and then to interrupt the circuit.
And now you should be able to know,
just intuitively, 'cause you
understand the mechanisms,
that the circuit you're trying to disrupt
is the pattern of information flow
from the thinking part of the brain,
the perception part of the brain,
which is the cortex, to the striatum.
The striatum has these
neurons which are active
that essentially are, I
know it sounds a little bit
like a discussion about free will,
but they're trying to get some,
the person to generate a certain behavior,
suppress a certain behavior.
And as anxiety ramps up,
it's sort of a hydraulic
pressure to do that very thing
that they've done for so long
and they suffer from so much.
We talked about hydraulic
pressure in the context
of aggression in the aggression episode,
this is very similar.
There's a kind of a,
now when I say hydraulic pressure,
it's not actual hydraulic pressure,
it's the confluence of a
lot of different systems.
It's neurochemicals, we'll soon learn,
it's hormonal, it's electrical,
it's a lot of different
things operating in parallel
so we can't point to one
chemical or transmitter.
What's happening is the
person is feeling compelled
to act, act, act to relieve the anxiety
and through a progressive
type of exposure,
you don't throw people in the deep end
in this kind of therapy right off the bat,
you gradually ratchet them toward
or move them toward the discussion
of exactly what they fear the most
and then eventually move them toward
the interruption of the compulsion
as they're feeling this
extremely elevated anxiety,
of course, within the context
of a supportive clinical setting.
But in doing that, what
you are teaching people
is that the anxiety can
exist without the need
to engage in the compulsion.
Now some of this might
sound to people like, oh,
this is a lot of kind of fancy
psychological neuroscience speak
around something that's kind of intuitive.
But I think for most people,
this is not intuitive.
And for people with OCD,
there's no really other way to put it,
the impulse, the
compulsion to avoid anxiety
is such a powerful driving force
that it should now make sense to you
as to why being able to tolerate anxiety
and really sit with it
and do the exact opposite
of what you're normally compelled to do
is going to be the path to treatment.
And indeed CBT has been shown
to be enormously effective,
again for a large number
of people with OCD,
but not all of them.
And oftentimes it requires that it also be
used in concert with
certain drug treatments,
which we're going to
talk about in a moment.
Next, let's talk about some
of the really unique features
of cognitive behavioral
therapy and exposure therapy
in the context of OCD
that you often don't see
in the use of CBT, that is
cognitive behavioral therapy,
for other types of psychiatric
challenges and disorders.
The first element is one of stair casing.
And I already mentioned this before,
but this gradual and progressive increase
in the anxiety that you're
trying to evoke from the patient,
from the person suffering from OCD.
That's done in the context of
the office or the laboratory,
again, by a trained
and licensed clinician.
But then the person leaves, right?
They leave the office,
they leave the laboratory.
And a very vital component
of CBT and exposure
therapy for people with OCD
is that they have and perform
what's called homework,
is literally what they call.
This might be seen in
other sorts of treatments
but for OCD, homework
is extremely important,
because within the context
of a laboratory experiment or the clinic,
patients often feel so much support
that they can tolerate
those heightened levels
of anxiety and interrupt
their compulsions.
Whereas when they get home,
oftentimes the familiarity
of the environment
brings 'em to a place
where all of a sudden
those obsessions and compulsions start
interacting the same way
and they have a very hard time
suppressing the behaviors.
Why would that be?
Well in neuroscience, we have a phrase,
it's called conditioned place preference
and conditioned place avoidance.
There's some other phrases too
but basically it all has to do
with a simple thing which is,
when you feel something
repeatedly in a given environment,
or sometimes even once
within a given environment,
you tend to feel that same thing again
when you return to that
or similar environments.
Okay, So conditioned place blank,
or conditioned place that
is simply fancy nerd speak
for the fact that when you're in a place
and something good happens,
you tend to feel good if
you return to that place
or a place like it, or
if something bad happens
in a given place, you tend to feel bad
when you return to that
place or a place like it.
I think that most salient
example that leaps to mind
is in, unfortunately, the category of bad,
but I had some friends years
ago visit San Francisco.
There's been a ongoing,
it seems like it's been happening forever,
but this is really in the last decade
of daytime break-ins and
nighttime break-ins into cars
to steal anything from computers
to what seems to be like a box of tissues.
And there are numerous reasons for this,
I don't want to get into,
it's not the topic of today's podcast,
but I will use this as
an opportunity to say
if you're visiting
anywhere in the Bay Area,
do not leave anything in your car
because the window will get broken into,
sometimes in broad daylight.
Some good friends of mine
were visiting the Bay Area
and I texted them and said,
hey, by the way, when you're
headed to dinner, guys,
make sure you bring in all
your luggage and computers
however inconvenient that might be.
They wrote back, too late,
everything got stolen.
So some years ago now, I
think five, six years ago
this happened, sadly,
everything got stolen.
Most of it could be replaced,
but some of it was very
sentimental to them.
Every time we talk, every time we consider
having a meeting in a particular city,
this comes up as I don't want to be there,
I don't like that city anymore, et cetera.
And of course, San
Francisco has some wonderful
redeeming features, but it
only takes one bad incident
in one location to kind of color
the whole picture dark, so to speak.
The brain works that way.
The brain generalizes, it's
not a very specific organ,
again, it's a prediction machine
in addition to other things.
So in the case of CBT therapy,
the reason there's homework
is that when people go home,
oftentimes that's when they relapse,
if you want to call it that,
back into their obsessions
and compulsions.
And that location, that conditioned place
is where it becomes most
important to challenge
the anxiety and to deal with the anxiety,
to not try and suppress the anxiety
through compulsions or other means.
And when I say other means, I
want to highlight something,
it will come up again a little
bit later in the podcast,
that substance abuse is very
common in people with OCD
because of the anxiety component
and also because of people's feelings
that they just can't
escape from the thoughts
or behavioral patterns that
are so characteristic of OCD.
So alcohol abuse or cannabis abuse,
or other forms of narcotics abuse
are very common in OCD.
Later, we'll talk about
whether or not cannabis
can or cannot help with OCD.
But needless to say,
suppressing anxiety is
exactly the wrong direction
that one should take if
the goal is to ultimately
relieve or eliminate the OCD.
So we now have two characteristics
of CBT exposure therapy
that are extremely important for OCD
and somewhat unique to
the treatment of OCD
and that's the staircasing up
towards the really bad fear,
the really severe and
specific articulation
and understanding and
feeling of how bad things
really would be if someone engaged
in a particular behavior or
avoided a particular behavior.
Then there's the component of homework
given by the clinician for
the person to be able to
create a broader set of context
in which they can deal with the anxiety,
not engage in the compulsions.
And then a very unique
feature of treatment of OCD
that you don't see in many
other psychiatric disorders
are home visits.
And I find this fascinating.
I think that the field of
psychiatry and psychology
traditionally doesn't allow
for or invite home visits,
but this component of
context, location and context
being so vital to the
treatment and relief of OCD
has inspired many
psychiatrists and psychologists
to get permission to do home visits
where they actually go
visit their patients
in their native setting,
in their home cages, right?
They're not mice, but in
their home-home cages,
I'm being facetious here, but people,
mice live in cages, at
least in the laboratory,
and humans generally live
in houses or elsewhere,
so they visit them in their home
in order to see how they're interacting
and the particular locations that evoke
the most anxiety and the least anxiety.
Some of the, I don't want
to call them crutches,
but some of the tools
that people are using
to confront and deal with the
obsessions and compulsions
and in particular to try and identify
some of the tools and tricks
that people are using to try and avoid
that heightened anxiety,
because, once again,
and I know I'm repeating myself,
but I think this is just
so vital and so unique
about OCD and the treatment of OCD,
the critical need for the
patient to be able to tolerate
extremely elevated levels
of anxiety is so crucial.
So if people are avoiding
certain rooms in the house,
or if people are avoiding certain foods
or certain locations in the kitchen,
the clinician can start to identify that
by mere observation.
And I should mention here that patients
are not always aware of
how they're interacting
with their home environment.
Some of these patterns are
so deeply ingrained in people
that they don't even realize that they're
constantly turning to the left,
or they don't even realize that
they're only washing their
hands on one side of the sink.
And so the clinician,
by visiting the home,
can start to interrogate
a bit in a polite way,
in a friendly, in a supportive way
as to, do you ever think
about why you always
flip the faucet to the left
or flip the faucet to
the right, et cetera.
Now, we all do a lot of
things that are habitual.
We all do things that are
somewhat regular from day to day.
In fact, I would invite
you to ask yourself,
do you always put your
toothbrush in the same location?
Do you always cap the toothbrush
before or after you use it?
What sorts of things do you-
You wipe the little threading
on the toothpaste or not?
I'm somebody, I confess that I have,
well, I have about 3,500 pet peeves,
but one of my pet peeves
is toothpaste kind of on the
thread of the toothpaste.
It really bothers me, I don't know why,
almost as much as trying
to wipe it off bothers me,
which creates a certain challenge.
And if I talk about this any further,
then I think I would qualify
for obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
But I have to say, I don't experience
a ton of anxiety about it.
It doesn't govern my life.
In fact, I realize that right now
there are tubes of toothpaste
that have toothpaste along the thread
everywhere in the world
and it doesn't really bother me.
I can still sit here and
provide some information
about OCD to you.
It's not intrusive, at
least not to my awareness.
So by the home visit,
the therapist can really start to explore
through direct questioning
and can allow the patient
to explore through direct
questioning of themselves
the things that they might be conscious of
and the things that they
might not be conscious of
that would qualify for OCD.
So I'd like to just briefly
summarize the key elements
of cognitive behavioral
therapy and exposure therapy
and how they can be combined
with drug treatments
that are very effective.
Much of what I'm going to talk about next
relates to the data
and indeed the practice
of an incredible research
scientist and clinician.
So this is Helen Blair Simpson,
or I should say Dr. Helen Blair Simpson,
because she is indeed an MD medical doctor
and a PhD research scientist
at Columbia University School of Medicine.
And one of the world's foremost experts,
if not the expert, I would
put her in a category
of maybe just one to three people who
is most knowledgeable about
the mechanisms of OCD,
is actively researching OCD in humans,
trying to find new treatments,
trying to unveil new mechanisms
and expand on our current
understanding and who also treats
OCD quite actively in her own clinic.
Dr. Simpson gave a beautiful presentation
which she summarized
some of the core elements
of CBT and exposure therapy
for the treatment of
obsessive-compulsive disorders.
She describes that the key
procedures are exposures,
of course, done in person
and with the actual thing that evokes
the obsessions and compulsions.
So this could be the sweaty
towel as described earlier,
or could be any number of
different triggers done
with the patient in real time,
so in vivo, as we say.
And it could also be
things that are imaginal,
sitting somebody down in a chair,
in an office and saying,
okay, I want you to imagine the thing
that triggers the intrusive thought,
or let's just focus on the
intrusive thought as it arises,
and then to explore and expose the patient
to their obsessions and
compulsions that way.
So it can be real, or it can be imaginal.
And the goal, of course, then
is to gradually and progressively
increase the level of anxiety,
but then to intervene in
so-called ritual prevention
to prevent the person from
engaging in the compulsion.
The goals, again I'm paraphrasing here,
are to, as she states, disconfirm fears
and challenge the beliefs
about the obsessions
and compulsions, to
intervene in the thoughts
and the behaviors, and to break the habit
of ritualizing and avoiding.
Now, how is this typically done?
What are the nuts and
bolts of this procedure?
Typically, this is done
through two planning sessions
with the patient.
So describing to the
patient what will happen
and when it will happen
and how long it will happen
so that they're not just thrown into this
out of the blue.
And then 15 exposure sessions
done twice a week or more.
So the one thing to really understand
about cognitive behavioral therapy
is that it can take some period of time,
several or more weeks, as
many as 10 or 12 weeks.
However, as you'll soon learn,
many of the drug treatments
that are effective
in treating OCD either
alone or in combination
with behavioral therapies
also can take 8, 10, 12 weeks
or longer, and many of
those never work at all.
So even though 10 to 12 weeks
seems like a long period of time,
it's actually a pretty standard.
If you'd like to see
more complete description
of the protocols for
cognitive behavioral therapy
and exposure therapy for OCD,
I'll provide links to two papers,
Kozak and Foa, F-O-A,
which is published in 1997,
which might seem like a long time ago,
but nonetheless, that the
protocols are still very useful.
And then the second paper
is by that last author,
FOA et al in 2012
and we'll provide links to both of those.
In addition, Dr. Blair Simpson and others
have explored what are the best treatments
for patients with OCD by comparing
cognitive behavioral
therapy alone, placebo,
so essentially no intervention
or something that takes an
equivalent amount of time
but is not thought to be
effective in treatment.
As well as selective
serotonin reuptake inhibitors.
So what is an SSRI?
An SSRI is a drug that
prevents the re-uptake
of serotonin at the synapse.
What are synapses?
They're the little spaces between neurons
where neurons communicate with one another
by vomiting little bits of
chemical into the space,
the synapse, and then those
chemicals either evoke
or suppress the electrical activity
of the next neuron across the synapse.
And in this case, the neurotransmitter,
the chemical that we're
referring to is serotonin.
SSRI, selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors
prevent the reuptake of
the chemical that's left,
in this case, the serotonin
that's left in the synapse.
After that, I call it
vomiting to be dramatic,
but it's not actually vomiting,
the extrusion of the
chemical into the synapse.
And as a consequence,
there's more serotonin around
to have more of an effect over time,
the net effect being more
serotonergic transmission,
more serotonin overall.
So not more serotonin being made,
more serotonin being available for use,
that's what an SSRI does.
So they compared cognitive
behavioral therapy, SSRIs,
they also had the placebo group
and they had cognitive behavioral therapy
plus the selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitor.
This was a 12-week study
done as described before,
two times a week over
the course of 12 weeks.
First of all, the most
important thing, of course,
placebo did nothing.
It did not relieve the OCD
to any significant degree.
How did they know that?
They gave them the Y-BOCS test
that we talked about
before, the Yale-Brown test
with all those questions
of which I read a few.
So the OCD severity that one has to have
on the Y-BOCS is measured
in terms of an index
that goes from here from
8 all the way up to 28,
that shouldn't mean anything.
So that number eight is
kind of meaningless here.
It's in terms of an index
that's only meaningful
for the Y-BOCS, but if
somebody has a threshold
of 16 or higher, it means
that they're still having
somewhat debilitating symptoms
or very debilitating symptoms.
Placebo did not reduce the
obsessions or compulsions
to any significant degree.
However, and I think quite excitingly,
cognitive behavioral
therapy had a dramatic
effect in reducing the
obsessions and compulsions
such that by four weeks, that
score that, in this case,
ranged from 8 to 28,
dropped all the way from
25 down to about 11.
So it's a huge drop in the
severity of the symptoms.
Now, what's really interesting
is that when you look
at the effects of SSRIs
in the treatment of OCD symptoms,
they had a significant effect
in reducing the symptoms
of OCD that showed up first at four weeks,
and then continued to eight weeks.
In fact, there was a progressive
and further reduction
in OCD symptoms from the
four to eight week period.
Again, these are the people
just taking the SSRI,
and then it sort of
flattened out a little bit,
such that by 12 weeks,
there was still a significant
reduction in OCD symptoms
for people taking SSRIs
as compared to placebo.
But the severity of their symptoms
was still much greater than those
receiving cognitive
behavioral therapy alone.
So at least in this study,
and I should tell you which study it is,
this is Foa, Liebowitz et al 2005
in the American Journal of Psychiatry,
we'll also provide a link to this
so you can peruse the data if you like.
But at least in this study,
cognitive behavioral therapy
was the most effective,
selective serotonin reuptake
inhibitors, less effective.
So what happens when you combine them?
Well, they explored that as well,
and the combination of
cognitive behavioral therapy
and the SSRIs together
did not lead to any further
decrease in OCD symptoms.
This points to the idea that
cognitive behavioral therapy
is the most effective treatment.
And again, when I say
cognitive behavioral therapy,
now I'm still referring
to cognitive behavioral,
slash, exposure therapy done in the way
that I detailed before,
twice a week for 12 weeks or more.
So all of the data, at
least in this study,
point to the fact that
cognitive behavioral therapy
is really effective
and the most effective.
Does it alleviate OCD
symptoms for everybody?
No.
Is it very time consuming? Yes.
Twice a week for two sessions
or more of 15 minutes,
sometimes in the office,
plus there's homework,
plus, in an ideal case,
there's also home visits
from the psychiatrist or psychologist,
that's a lot of investment,
a lot of time investment,
to say nothing of the
potential financial investment.
Now, Dr. Blair Simpson has
given some beautiful talks
where she describes these data
and also emphasizes the fact that
despite the demonstrated power
of cognitive behavioral therapy
for the treatment of OCD,
most people are given drug treatments
simply because of the availability
of those drug treatments.
Now, when I say most people,
I want to emphasize that I'm referring
to most people who
actually go seek treatment
because a really
important thing to realize
is that most people with OCD
do not actually go seek
evidence-based treatment.
I want to repeat that,
most people with OCD
do not seek evidence-based treatment,
which is a tragic thing.
One of the motivations for
doing this podcast episode
is to try and encourage people
who think they may have
persistent obsessions
and compulsions to seek treatment,
but most people don't
for a variety of reasons
we spelled out earlier, shame, et cetera.
Of those that do, the first line of attack
is typically a prescription,
most often an SSRI,
although not always just SSRIs
because soon we'll talk
about the somewhat common use
of also prescribing a
low dose of a neuroleptic
or an antipsychotic, not always but often.
So the important thing to understand here
is that excellent
researchers like Dr. Simpson
understand that while there are treatments
that we could say are best or are ideal
based on the data, that
doesn't necessarily mean
that's what's being deployed
most often in the general public.
As a consequence, Dr. Simpson and others
have explored in a very practical way
whether or not it matters if somebody
is getting SSRI treatment
and is experiencing that
reduction in OCD symptoms
that as you may recall, is more than
what they would experience
with placebo alone,
but not as dramatic a
reduction in OCD symptoms
as they would get with
cognitive behavioral therapy.
And as I mentioned before,
there was this exploration
of combining drug treatment
with cognitive behavioral
therapy from the outset,
but they also quite impressively explored
what happens when people
who are already taking SSRIs
initiate cognitive behavioral therapy.
This is a really wonderful thing
that they've done this
because in doing that,
first of all, they're acknowledging that
there are many people out
there who have sought treatment
and are getting some
relief from those SSRIs,
but it perhaps is not as much
relief as they could get.
And they are actively
acknowledging that many people
are getting these drug treatments first.
In fact, most often people are getting
these drug treatments first.
So what happens when you add in
cognitive behavioral therapy?
Well, the good news is when you add
cognitive behavioral therapy
to someone who's already taking SSRIs,
that further improves their symptoms.
Now that's different than the results
that I described before
from the same laboratory in fact,
that if you combine
cognitive behavioral therapy
with SSRIs from the outset,
there's no additional benefit of SSRI.
However, as I just described,
if someone is already taking an SSRI
and they're experiencing a
reduction in their OCD symptoms,
by adding in cognitive behavioral therapy,
there is a further reduction
in the symptoms of OCD.
This is very important.
So for those of you that
have sought treatment
and you're taking a SSRI,
or if you're thinking about treatment
and you're prescribed an SSRI,
the ideal scenario really would be
to combine the drug treatment
with cognitive behavioral therapy,
or in some cases, maybe cognitive
behavioral therapy alone,
although that's a decision
that you really have to make
with the close
advice and oversight of
a licensed physician,
because, of course, these
are prescription drugs.
And anytime you're going to add or remove
a prescription drug or change dosage,
you really want to do that
in close discussion with
and on the advice of your physician.
I don't just say that to protect me,
I say that to protect you
'cause it's just the right thing to do.
So again, cognitive behavioral therapy
is extremely powerful.
Drug treatments seem less powerful though.
If you're already on a drug treatment,
adding cognitive behavioral
therapy can really help.
So I've been talking about SSRIs
and described a little
bit about how they work
at a kind of superficial level of
keeping more serotonin in the synapse
so that more serotonin can be in action
as opposed to gobbled
back up by those neurons.
I should just mention what some
of the selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors are.
So things like clomipramine,
which is not entirely selective,
I should say that that one generally falls
into a category of less selective.
So it can impair
or can enhance some of
the other neurotransmitter
or neuromodulator systems
like epinephrine, et cetera.
The selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors are,
at least the classic ones
are, fluoxetine, Prozac,
fluvoxamine, Luvox,
paroxetine, sertraline,
citalopram, et cetera, et cetera.
There are about six or classic SSRIs,
some of them like citalopram
are used in children and are available
in pediatric doses.
Some like Prozac may or may
not be used in children.
The details of which SSRIs, et cetera,
is a very extensive
literature and discussion.
And I think it's safe to say that
which drugs to use and which dosage
and whether or not to continue, excuse me,
the same dosage over time depends a lot
on the individual variation
that people express
and the responses that they have.
All of these drugs, in
fact, I think we can say
all drugs have side effects.
The question is how detrimental
those side effects are
to daily life.
The SSRIs are well known to
have effects on appetite.
In some cases, they abolish appetite.
In some cases, they just
reduce it a little bit.
In some cases, they increase appetite.
Really is highly individual.
They can have effects on libido.
For instance, they can reduce sex drive,
sometimes in a dose dependent way,
sometimes in a way that's
more like a step function
where people are fine at
say 5 or 10 milligrams,
but then they get to 15 milligrams
and there's a cliff for their libido.
That can happen, it really depends.
Please don't take those
dosages as exact values
'cause this is going to depend on
what they're being used for,
depression or anxiety or OCD,
and it's also going to depend
on the drug, et cetera.
I just threw out those numbers as a way
to illustrate what a
kind of a step function
would look like.
It's not gradual, it's
immediate at a given dose
is what that means.
The other thing is that
some of these drugs
will have transient effects.
So side effects that show
up and then disappear
or sadly people will
sometimes take these drugs
for a while and then side
effects will surface later
that weren't there previously
depending on life factors,
nutrition factors.
So it's a very complicated
landscape overall.
And that's why it's really
important to explore
any kind of drug treatment,
SSRI or otherwise,
really in close communication
with a psychiatrist
who really understands
the pharmacokinetics
and has a lot of patient history
and experience with them.
So what I'm about to tell you next
is most certainly going
to come as a big surprise,
which is that despite the fact
that the selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors
can be effective in reducing
the symptoms of OCD,
at least somewhat,
and certainly more than placebo,
there is very little, if any evidence,
that the serotonin system
is disrupted in OCD.
And I have to point out that this is
a somewhat consistent theme
in the field of psychiatry,
that is a given drug can be very effective
or even partially effective
in reducing symptoms
or in changing the overall landscape
of a psychiatric disorder or illness,
and yet there is very little,
if any evidence, that
that particular system
is what's causal for OCD, or anxiety,
or depression, et cetera.
This is just the landscape
that we're living in
in terms of our understanding of the brain
and psychiatry and the ways
of treating brain disorders.
So as a consequence,
there are a huge number
of academic reviews that
clinicians and research scientists
have generated and read and share.
One of the more, I think, thorough ones
in recent years was published in 2021.
I'll provide a link to this.
This is by an excellent,
truly excellent researcher
from Yale university School of Medicine,
I should say not just a researcher
but a clinician scientist,
again, an MD-PhD.
This is Christopher Pittenger
And the title of the review
is Pharmacotherapeutic Strategies
and New Targets in OCD.
And again, we'll provide a link to it.
This is a just gorgeous review describing,
as I just told you, that
the serotonin system
isn't really disrupted in OCD
and yet SSRIs can be very effective.
The review goes on to explore
even what sorts of receptors
for serotonin might be involved.
If it's in fact the case that serotonin
is a culprit in the
creation of OCD symptoms.
Talk about the serotonin 2A receptor
and the serotonin 1A receptor.
Why am I mentioning all that detail?
If in fact it's not clear,
serotonin is involved because
I'll just tell you right now,
there is currently a lot of interest
in whether or not some
of the psychedelics,
in particular psilocybin, can be effective
in the treatment of OCD.
Psilocybin has been shown
in various clinical trials
in particular the clinical trials done
at Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
by Matthew Johnson and others.
Matthew was on The Huberman Lab Podcast.
He's been on the Tim Ferris podcast.
He's been on the Lex Fridman podcast.
He's a world class researcher
on the use of psychedelics for depression
and other psychiatric challenges.
And their psilocybin treatment
has been seen, at least in those trials,
to be very effective in the treatment
of certain kinds of major depression.
Currently the exploration of psilocybin
for the treatment of OCD
has not yielded similar results,
although the studies are ongoing.
Again, has not yielded
similar effectiveness,
but the studies are ongoing
And the serotonin 2A receptor
and the serotonin 1A receptors
are primary targets for
the drug psilocybin.
So I figured there were
going to be some questions
about whether or not
psychedelics help with OCD,
thus far it's inconclusive.
If any of you have been
part of clinical trials
or have knowledge or intuition
about this relationship
or potential relationship, I should say,
between psilocybin and other psychedelics
in OCD, please put them
in the comment section.
We'd love to love to hear from you.
One thing I should point out
is that even though serotonin
has not been directly implicated in OCD,
serotonin and the general
systems of serotonin,
the circuits in the brain
that carry serotonin
and depend on it have been shown
to impact cognitive
flexibility and inflexibility,
which are kind of hallmark themes of OCD.
So in animals that have
their serotonin depleted
or in humans that have very
low levels of serotonin,
you can see evidence of
cognitive inflexibility,
challenges in tasks, switching challenges
and switching the rules by
which one performs a game,
challenges in any kind of
cognitive domain switching.
And so that does indirectly implicate
serotonin in some of the aspects of OCD.
Again, when one starts to explore
the different transmitter systems
that have been explored in
animal models and in humans,
it's a vast, vast landscape,
but serotonergic drugs do seem to be
the most effective drugs in treating OCD
despite the fact, again, despite the fact
that there's no direct evidence
that serotonin systems
are the problem in OCD.
If you recall the
cortico-striatal-thalamic loop
that is so central to the etiology,
the presence and the
patterns of symptoms in OCD,
of course, serotonin is
impacting that system.
Serotonin is impacting just
about every system in the brain,
but there's no evidence that
tinkering with serotonin levels,
specifically in that network,
is what's leading to
the improvements in OCD.
However, if people go into a FMRI scanner
and those people have OCD
and they evoke the
obsessions and compulsions,
you see activity in that
cortico-striatal-thalamic loop.
Treatments like SSRIs that
reduce the symptoms of OCD
equate to a situation where
there is less activity
in that loop.
And I should point out
cognitive behavioral therapy,
which we have no reason to believe
only taps into the serotonin system,
I think it would be extreme stretch,
it would be false actually to say
that that cognitive
behavioral therapy taps
only into the serotonin system,
clearly it's going to affect
a huge number of circuits
in neurochemical systems.
Well, people who do
cognitive behavioral therapy
and find some relief for OCD,
they also show reductions
in those cortico-striatal-thalamic loops.
So basically we have a situation
where we have a behavioral
therapy that works,
in many people, not all,
and we have a pretty good understanding
of about why it works.
It increases anxiety tolerance,
and interference with pattern execution,
getting people to not engage
in the same sorts of behaviors
that are detrimental to them.
And we have drug treatments that work
at least to some degree,
but we don't know how they work
or where they work in the brain.
One of the things that really unifies
the behavioral treatments
and the drug treatments
is that they take some period of time.
Some relief from symptoms seems to show up
around four weeks and
certainly by eight weeks
for both cognitive behavioral
therapy and the SSRIs,
but it's really at the 10 to 12 week stage
when someone's been
doing these twice a week,
cognitive behavioral sessions,
where they've been taking
a SSRI for 10 to 12 weeks,
that the really significant reduction
in OCD symptoms starts to really show up.
Now, up until now, I've
been talking about the fact
that people are getting
relief from these treatments,
but sadly,
in the case of OCD,
there is a significant population
that simply does not respond to CBT
or to SSRIs, or to their combination,
which is why psychiatrists
also explore the combination
of SSRIs and neuroleptics
or drugs that tap into the
so-called dopamine system
or the glutamate system.
These are other neurotransmitters
and neuromodulators
that impact different
circuits in the brain.
And just to really remind you
what neurotransmitters
and neuromodulators do,
because this is important
to contextualize all this,
neurotransmitters are
typically involved in the
rapid communication between neurons.
And the two most common
neurotransmitters for that
are the neurotransmitter glutamate,
which we say is excitatory,
meaning when it's
released into the synapse,
it causes the next neuron to
be more active, or active,
and GABA which is a neurotransmitter
that is inhibitory,
meaning when it's released
into the synapse, typically, not always,
but typically, that GABA
is going to encourage
the next neuron to be
less electrically active
or even silence its activity.
The neuromodulators, by contrast,
So not neurotransmitters,
but neuromodulators
like dopamine, serotonin, epinephrine,
and acetylcholine and others
operate a little bit differently.
They tend to act a
little bit more broadly.
They can act within the synapse,
but they can also change
the general patterns
of activity in the brain,
making certain circuits more likely
to be active and other circuits
less likely to be active.
So when we say dopamine does X
or dopamine does Y, or serotonin does X
or serotonin does Y,
they don't really do one thing,
they change the sort of overall tonality.
They make it more likely or less likely
that certain circuits will be active.
You can think of them as
kind of activating playlists
or genres of activity in the brain,
rather than being involved
in the specific communication
or specific songs, if you will,
in this analogy, or discussions
between particular neurons.
So when we hear that
SSRIs increase serotonin
and reduce the symptoms of OCD,
or a neuroleptic reduces
the amount of dopamine
and makes people feel calmer for instance,
or can remove some stereotype,
repetitive motor behavior,
which they can either generate
or reduce motor behavior it turns out.
So when I say that, what I'm referring to
is the fact that these neuromodulators
are kind of turning up the
volume on certain circuits
and turning down the
volume on other circuits.
I say that because if
you are going to explore
drug treatments again
with a licensed physician,
if you're going to explore
drug treatments for OCD,
and in particular, if you
are not getting results
from SSRIs, or you're not getting results
from cognitive behavioral therapy
or the side effect profiles of the drugs
that you're taking for OCD
are causing problems that
you don't want to take them,
well, then it's important to understand
that anytime you take one of these drugs,
they're not acting specifically
on the cortico-striatal-thalamic circuit.
That would be wonderful.
That's the future of psychiatry,
but as now, when you take a drug,
it acts systemically.
So it's impacting serotonin in your gut.
It's also impacting serotonin
in other areas of the brain,
hence the effects on things
like digestion or libido or
any number of different things
that serotonin is involved in.
Likewise, if you take a
neuroleptic like haloperidol
or something that reduces
dopamine transmission,
well, then it's going to
have some motor effects
'cause dopamine is
involved in the generation
of motor sequences and
smooth limb movement.
That's why people with Parkinson's
who don't have much dopamine
will get a resting tremor,
have a hard time
generating smooth movement.
And so the side effects
start to make sense,
given the huge number of
different neural circuits
that these different
neuromodulators are involved in.
I don't say that to be discouraging,
I say that to encourage patients
and careful systematic exploration
of different drug treatments for OCD
always again with the careful and close
guidance and oversight of a psychiatrist
because psychiatrists really understand
which side effect profiles make it likely
that you can or cannot or will never,
or maybe someday will be
able to take a given drug
at a given dose.
They're the ones that
really have that knowledge.
This is not the sort
of thing that you want
to cowboy and go try
and figure out yourself.
Now, I also want to acknowledge
that there are other
forms of drug treatments.
We touched on psilocybin briefly,
but there are other
forms of drug treatments
that have been explored for OCD.
Earlier, we talked a
little bit about cannabis.
Why would cannabis be a
place of exploration at all?
Well, first of all,
a number of people try
and self medicate for OCD.
There is some clinical evidence,
I'm not talking about recreational use,
I'm talking about clinical evidence
that cannabis can reduce anxiety.
Now earlier we were talking about
not reducing anxiety, but
learning anxiety tolerance
in order to deal with and treat OCD
in the context of cognitive
behavioral therapies.
That doesn't necessarily rule out cannabis
as a candidate for the treatment of OCD.
And in fact, this has been explored.
A study from Dr. Blair Simpson
herself looked at this.
This was a fairly small scale study.
So first of all, I'll give you the title.
And again, we'll provide a link.
This is entitled, Acute
effects of cannabinoids
on symptoms of
obsessive-compulsive disorder:
A human laboratory study.
very briefly, this was 14 adults with OCD.
They had prior experience with cannabis.
This was randomized, placebo-controlled.
The cannabis was smoked,
they had different varietals,
as they're called.
They had a placebo.
So this is basically a condition
in which certain subjects
consumed a cigarette that had 0% THC,
others had 7% THC,
other groups that is, or
some had 0.4% CBD and THC.
So they looked at CBD.
I know a lot of people out
there are interested in CBD.
This is one of the few
studies I could find
where they explored different percentages
of THC and CBD in these
cannabis or marijuana
cigarettes basically.
The total amount that they consumed,
I believe, was 800 milligrams.
These, again, are not suggestions.
These are just simply
reporting what's in this study.
You can, again, I'll provide a link.
They looked at OCD symptoms, ratings.
They looked at cardiovascular effects.
They had a large number
of different things
that they explored.
And I should say this
study was done in 2020,
and it was the first
placebo-controlled investigation
of cannabis in adults with
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
Pretty interesting.
And I'm just reading from
their conclusions here.
The data suggests that smoked cannabis,
whether containing primarily THC or CBD,
remember they looked at
different concentrations
of those, has little acute impact,
meaning immediate impact on OCD symptoms
and yield smaller reductions in anxiety
compared to placebo.
So they did not see a, when
I say a positive effect,
I mean a ameliorative effect,
an effect in reducing symptoms of OCD
from cannabis or CBD,
which, it's unfortunate.
I think it's unfortunate anytime
a treatment doesn't work.
But nonetheless, those are the data,
I'm sure there are going
to be other studies.
I'm sure there are also going to be people
in the YouTube comments section saying
that cannabis and CBD
helps their OCD symptoms,
at least I anticipate there probably will.
Almost everything I say here,
somebody will contradict it with something
from their experience, which
I encourage, by the way.
I want to hear about your
experience with certain things
even if it's not from randomized
placebo-controlled studies,
I still find it very interesting
to know what people are doing
and what they're experiencing.
I think that's one of the
better uses of social media
comment sections, is to be
able to share some of that,
not in an advice-giving
way or prescriptive way,
but simply as a way to share and encourage
different types of exploration.
There are other sorts of drug treatments
that are gaining popularity for OCD,
at least in the research realm.
One treatment that is a legal, L-E-G-A-L.
Sometimes when I say legal,
sometimes people think I say
illegal, but that is legal,
at least by prescription in
the United States, is ketamine.
The actions of ketamine
are somewhat complex
although we know, for instance,
that ketamine acts on
the glutamate system,
it tends to disrupt the transmission
or the relationship, I should say,
between glutamate, not glutamine,
not the amino acid, but
glutamate, the neurotransmitter,
and the so-called NMDA, the
N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor,
which is a receptor that's very special
in the nervous system
because when glutamate binds
to the NMDA receptor, it tends to
offer the opportunity for
that particular synapse
to get stronger, so-called neuroplasticity
and ketamine is a,
essentially, an antagonist,
although it works through
a complicated mechanism,
it tends to block that
binding of glutamate to the NMDA receptor
or the effectiveness of that.
Ketamine therapy is now
being used quite extensively
for the treatment of
trauma and for depression.
It leads to a dissociative state.
It's a so-called dissociative analgesic
in the variety of ways
in which that happens.
We did an episode on depression.
We're going to do another entire
episode all about ketamine
describing the networks that
ketamine impacts, et cetera.
Ketamine therapies are
being explored for OCD.
As of now, the data
look somewhat promising,
but there's still a lot more
work that needs to be done.
My read of the data are that
the more extensive clinical trials
have not happened yet.
The smaller studies that have happened
revealed that some
patients do get some relief
from ketamine therapy for OCD,
but there was nothing
overwhelmingly pointing to the fact
that ketamine is a magic
bullet for OCD treatment.
So cannabis, CBD, at least now,
even though it's one smaller study,
there's no real evidence that it can
alleviate OCD symptoms.
If there are new studies published soon,
I'll be sure to update you.
And if you see those studies,
please send them to me.
Ketamine therapy, the jury is still out,
psilocybin, The jury is still out.
These are early days.
Another treatment that's
becoming somewhat common,
or at least people are
commonly excited about
is transcranial magnetic stimulation.
So this is the use of a magnetic coil.
This is completely noninvasive,
placed on one portion of the skull,
and one can direct magnetic
energy toward particular
areas of the brain
to either suppress, or nowadays,
you can also activate
particular brain regions.
There are some interesting data
showing that if TMS is applied
to areas of the brain involved
in the generation of motor action,
so the so-called motor areas,
or supplementary motor
areas as they're called,
while people think about
or have intrusive thoughts,
we know that the TMS coil can interrupt
the motor behaviors, the
compulsive behaviors,
and at least in a small cohort of studies
and a small number of
patients within those studies,
this has been shown to be effective,
not just while the coil
is on the head, of course,
but after the study has been performed
or the treatment's been performed
in reducing OCD symptoms
by disrupting the tendency
for the compulsive behavior
to be so automatic.
One of the key features of
obsessive-compulsive disorder
is that, especially if it's
been around for a while,
the person's been dealing
with it for a while,
there isn't a pattern in
which the person thinks,
oh, I have this contamination fear,
or I need symmetry, or
I'm kind of obsessed
to count to the number seven.
And then they pause and they go,
ooh, and then they do it.
No, typically there's a very close
pairing of the obsession
and the compulsion in time
so that somebody's
walking down the street,
thinking one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven,
one, two, three, four,
five, six seven, seven...
and then they're doing this
in such rapid succession
because the obsessions
are coming up so quickly.
Thoughts can be generated very quickly.
And then they're
generating the compulsions
as a way to beat down
or to try and suppress that anxiety
and then it comes right back up again
at even stronger as I described earlier.
So transcranial magnetic stimulation
seems to intervene in these
various fast processes.
Right now, I don't think it's fair to say
that TMS is a magic bullet either.
I think there's a lot
of excitement about TMS
and in particular,
I really want to nail this point home,
in particular, there's excitement about
the combination of TMS
with drug treatments,
or the combination of TMS with
cognitive behavioral therapy.
And this is a really important point,
not just for sake of discussion
about obsessive-compulsive disorder,
but also depression, ADHD, schizophrenia,
any number of different
psychiatric challenges
and disorders in most cases
are going to respond best
to a combination of behavioral treatment
that's ongoing that
occurs in the laboratory
and clinical setting,
but also in the home setting
where there's homework,
maybe even home visits.
Drug treatments, often, not always,
are a terrific augment to
those cognitive behavioral therapies
or other behavioral therapies.
And then now we are living in the age
of brain-machine interface.
You have companies like Neuralink
that I think it's fair
to say are going to enter
the brain machine-interface world first
through the treatment
of certain syndromes,
movement syndromes or
psychiatric syndromes
probably before they
start putting electrodes
into the brain to
stimulate enhanced memory
or enhanced cognition, who knows,
I don't know exactly what they're doing
behind the walls of Neuralink.
But I have to imagine, in fact,
I would wager maybe not both arms,
but I'll wager my left arm
that the first set of
FDA approved technologies
to come out of companies like Neuralink
are going to be those for
the treatment of things
like Parkinson's and movement disorders
and cognitive disorders, rather than,
shall we say, kind of recreational
cognitive enhancement
or things of that sort.
So transcranial magnetic
stimulation is noninvasive.
It doesn't involve going
down below the skull,
can have some effect,
but most laboratories
that I'm aware of at
Stanford and elsewhere
that are exploring TMS for things like OCD
and other types of psychiatric
challenges are using TMS in combination
with drug therapies, are using,
in some cases, for instance,
a laboratory at Stanford, hope
to get 'em on the podcast,
a psychiatrist, Nolan Williams,
is exploring TMS in combination with
psychedelic therapies, not
necessarily at the same time,
but nonetheless combining them
or exploring how they
impact brain circuitry.
So if you have OCD, should
you run out and get TMS,
or should you try ketamine therapy,
of course, with a licensed physician?
I think it's too early to say yes.
I think the answer is
we need to wait and see.
I think cognitive behavioral
therapy, the SSRIs,
and some other drug
treatments like neuroleptics
combined with SSRIs and
cognitive behavioral therapy
are where the real bulk of the data are.
I want to make one additional
point about cannabis CBD
as it relates to
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
To me, it's not at all surprising
that cannabis CBD did not
improve symptoms of OCD.
Because in my discussion
with Dr. Paul Conti
a few weeks ago,
and I should mention, Dr. Conti
is indeed a medical
doctor, a psychiatrist,
we were talking about
cannabis and its various uses,
because it does have some
clinical applications.
And he mentioned that
one of the main effects
of cannabis is to tighten focus
and to enhance concentration on
and thoughts about one particular thing.
And in some cases that can
be clinically beneficial,
and in other cases that can
be clinically detrimental.
If you accept the idea that
cannabis increases focus,
and you think about OCD
and the networks involved,
and you think about the
anxiety and the relationship
between the obsession and compulsion,
well, then it shouldn't
come as any surprise
that cannabis did not
improve the symptoms of OCD
because if anything,
it would increase focus
on the obsessions and the compulsions.
Now that's not what they observed.
They did not see an exacerbation
or a worsening of the
symptoms of OCD with cannabis,
at least that's not my read of the data,
but they did not see an improvement
in OCD symptoms with cannabis or CBD.
And to me, that's not surprising
given that cannabis CBD
seems to increase focus.
Next, I'd like to talk
about some of the research
on and the roles of hormones in OCD,
because it turns out to be
a very interesting relationship there.
But before I do, I want
to point out something
that I realize I probably
should have said earlier,
which is one of the key
things for someone with OCD
to come to understand if
they're going to experience
any relief of their symptoms,
whether or not they're
doing drug treatments
or behavioral treatments or otherwise,
is that thoughts are
not as bad as actions.
Thoughts are not as bad as actions.
One of the kind of rules
that people with OCD
seem to adopt for themselves
is that thoughts are really,
truly the equivalent of actions.
So they'll have an intrusive thought and,
we haven't spent too
much time on this today,
but earlier I touched on the fact
that some of the intrusive
thoughts that people have
in OCD are really disturbing.
They can be really gross,
or at least gross to that person.
They can evoke imagery that
is toxic or infectious,
or is highly sexualized in a way
that is disturbing to
them, it can be very taboo.
This is not uncommon
when you start talking to people with OCD
and you start pulling on the thread.
Again, this would be a psychiatrist
who was trained to ask the right questions
and gain the comfort
and trust of a patient.
And they start to reveal that
these thoughts are really
intrusive and kind of disturbing,
which is why they feel so compelled
to try and suppress them with behaviors.
One of the powerful elements
of treatment for OCD
is to really support the patient
and make them realize that
thoughts are just thoughts
and that everyone has disturbing thoughts.
And that oftentimes
those disturbing thoughts
arise at the most
inconvenient, and sometimes,
what seems like the most
inappropriate circumstances.
And this relates to a
whole larger discussion
that we could have about what are thoughts
and why do they surface,
and how come when you stand
at the edge of a bridge,
even if you do not want to jump off,
you think about jumping off.
And this has to do with the fact
that your nervous system,
as a prediction machine,
is oftentimes testing possibilities.
And sometimes that testing
goes way off into the
Netherlands of the thought patterns
and emotional patterns that
we all have inside of us.
The big difference between
a thought and an action
is that, of course, the nervous system is,
in one case, not translating
those patterns of thinking
into motor sequences.
That nerdy way of saying
thoughts aren't actions,
believe it or not,
can be helpful for people if they really
think about that and
use it as an opportunity
to realize that, first of
all, they're not crazy.
They're not thinking
and feeling this stuff
because they're bad or evil.
And of course, sometimes
this can cross over
with other elements of life
where we place moral judgment on people
for certain behaviors.
I think that's part of a
healthy society, of course,
that's why we have laws and punishments
and rewards for that matter
for certain types of behaviors.
But this idea that thoughts
are not as bad as actions
and that thoughts can be tolerated
and the anxiety around thoughts
can be tolerated and
over time can diminish,
that's a very powerful hallmark theme
of the treatment of OCD
so I'd be remiss if I didn't mention it.
Thoughts are not actions.
Actions can harm us, they
can harm other people,
they can soak up enormous amounts of time.
Thoughts can soak up
enormous amounts of time.
They can be very troubling.
They can be very detrimental.
We of course want to be sensitive to that,
but when it really comes down to it,
the first step in treatment
for OCD is this realization
where the approach to the realization
that thoughts are not as bad as actions.
So what about hormones in OCD?
Well, this has been explored,
albeit not as extensively
as I would've liked to find,
but when I went into the literature,
I found one particularly
interesting study,
entitled, Neurosteroid Levels in Patients
with Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder.
First author, Erbay
And as always, we'll
provide a link to the study.
The objective of this
study was to explore serum
within blood, neurosteroid
levels in people with OCD.
Why?
Well, because of the relationship
between OCD and anxiety
and the fact that in
stress-related disorders
such as anxiety and depression,
the hormones have been
extensively explored,
but not so much in OCD,
at least until this study.
So they compared serum levels of a number
of different hormones,
progesterone, pregnenolone,
DHEA, cortisol, and testosterone.
This was done in 30 patients with OCD
and 30 healthy controls.
So it's not a huge study,
but it's enough to draw
some pretty nice conclusions.
These subjects were 18 to 49 years old,
and the controls were age and sex matched
healthy volunteers.
Again, no OCD.
What was the basic
takeaway from the study?
The basic takeaway from the
study was that in females
with OCD, there was evidence
for significantly elevated
cortisol and DHEA.
Now that's interesting because cortisol
is well known to be associated
with the stress system.
Although every day, should mention,
we all, male or female,
everybody experiences
an increase in cortisol
shortly after awakening.
That's a healthy increase in cortisol.
Late shift, I mean, late in
the day peaks in cortisol
where a shift in that cortisol peak
to later in the day is a known correlate
of depression and anxiety disorders.
So the fact that cortisol is elevated
and DHEA are elevated in female patients
with OCD suggests that
cortisol is either reflective of or causal
for the increase in anxiety.
We don't know the
direction of that effect.
Now in male patients with OCD,
there was evidence for increased cortisol.
Again, not surprising given the
role of anxiety in cortisol,
or I should say, given the
role of cortisol in anxiety
and the increasing anxiety seen in OCD,
but there are also significant
reductions in testosterone,
which should also not surprise us
because cortisol and
testosterone more or less compete
in some fashion for their own production,
both are derived from
the molecule cholesterol.
And there are certain biochemical pathways
that can either direct
that cholesterol molecule
toward cortisol synthesis
or testosterone synthesis,
but not both.
So they compete.
So when cortisol goes up in general,
not always, but in general,
testosterone goes down and vice versa.
If you want to learn more
about the relationship
between cortisol and testosterone,
and there are even some tools
to try and optimize those
ratios in both males and females,
you can find that in our episode
on optimizing testosterone and estrogen,
that's at hubermanlab.com.
Now, I would say the
most interesting aspect
of this study is not
that DHEA and cortisol
are elevated in females with OCD
or that cortisol and testosterone
have this opposite effect,
cortisol up and testosterone
down in males with OCD,
but rather the relationship
between all of those,
DHEA, cortisol, and testosterone.
In terms of GABA, GABA again
being this inhibitory neurotransmitter
that tends to quiet
certain neuronal pathways,
it does different things
at different synapses,
but in general, the more
GABA that's present,
the more inhibition that's present,
and therefore the more
suppression of neural activity.
And DHEA is known to
be a potent antagonist
of the GABA system.
So here we have elevated DHEA in females.
And I should also
mention that testosterone
is also known to tap into the GABA system.
Typically, when testosterone is elevated,
GABA transmission, at
least is slightly elevated.
So here we have a situation
in which the pattern
of hormones in females and males with OCD
are different from those
in people without OCD
such that GABA transmission is altered
and the net effect would be
an overall reduction in GABA.
Now GABA, as an inhibitory
neurotransmitter,
and broadly speaking is associated
with lower levels of anxiety,
and it tends to create balance
within various neural circuits.
Now, that's a very broad statement,
but we know for instance, in epilepsy,
that GABA levels are reduced
and therefore you get runaway excitation
of certain circuits in the brain,
and therefore seizures, either petite mal,
mini seizures, or grand
mal, massive seizures,
or even drop seizures where
people completely collapse
to the floor in seizure.
You may have seen this before.
I certainly have, it's very dramatic
and it actually is quite
debilitating for people
because obviously they don't
know when these seizures
are coming on most often, and then
they can fall into a stove
or while driving, et cetera.
So the situation with OCD is one in which,
for whatever reason, we don't
know the direction of effect.
Certain hormones are elevated in females
and certain hormones are elevated in males
and those hormones differ
between males and females,
and yet they both funnel into a system
where GABAergic or GABA
transmission in the brain
is reduced because of this ability
for those particular hormones
to be antagonists to GABA,
and as a consequence, there's
likely to be overall levels
of increased excitation in
certain networks in the brain
and that brings us back to this
cortico-striatal-thalamic loop,
this repetitive loop
that seems to reinforce,
we can say reinforces
obsession, leads to anxiety,
leads to compulsion, leads to
transient relief of anxiety,
but then increase in anxiety,
increased obsession, anxiety,
compulsion, anxiety,
compulsion, anxiety, compulsion,
and so on and so forth.
So I have not found
studies that have explored
adjusting testosterone levels
through exogenous administration,
cream or injection or otherwise,
or that have focused on
reducing DHEA in females.
If anyone is aware of such studies,
please put them in the
comment section on YouTube
or send them to us.
We have a contact site on the
website at hubermanlab.com,
but the comment section
on YouTube would be best.
But because we know that
hormones impact neuromodulators
and neurotransmitters,
as I just described,
and that those neuromodulators
and neurotransmitters
play an intimate role in the generation
and the treatment of things like OCD,
it stands to reason that manipulations
of those hormone systems, however subtle
or dramatic might, I want to highlight,
might prove useful in
adjusting the symptoms of OCD
and I hope that this is
an area that researchers
are going to pursue in
the very near future
because many of the
treatments for reducing DHEA
or increasing testosterone
or reducing cortisol
have already made it through FDA approval.
They're out there, they're
readily prescribed.
Many of them are already in generic form
which means that the
patents have already lapsed
on the first versions of those drugs.
So when they're available as
generic drugs, very often,
they're available at
significantly lower cost.
There's a whole discussion we had there
about patent laws and prescription drugs.
But because these drugs
are largely available
in prescription yet generic form,
I think there's a great opportunity
to explore how hormones,
not just cortisol,
testosterone, and DHA,
but the huge category of hormones
might impact the symptoms of OCD,
especially since many
of the symptoms of OCD
show up right around the time of puberty.
We haven't talked a lot
about childhood OCD,
'cause we're going to do an entire series
on childhood psychiatric
disorders and challenges but
many children develop OCD early as young
as three or four, believe it or not,
or even 6 or 7 and 10
and in adolescence, and
certainly around puberty.
and in young adulthood.
It is rare, although it does happen,
that people will develop
OCD very late in life
around 40 or older, just
kind of spontaneously.
Most often when you look
at their clinical history,
you find that either they were hiding it
or is being suppressed in some way,
or if it does spontaneously
show up late in life
like mid-thirties or in one's forties,
typically there's a
traumatic brain injury,
could be due to stroke or
physical injury to the head
or something of that sort.
Nonetheless,
there is a interesting correlation
between the onset of puberty
in certain forms of OCD.
There's certain forms of, or I should say,
there's certain aspects of menopause
that can relate to OCD.
You can find all these
things in the literature.
All this to say that hormones
impact neurotransmitters
and neuromodulators, which clearly impact
the kinds of circuits
that are involved in OCD
and it makes sense that,
and I would hope that there
would be an exploration
of how these hormones impact OCD
in the not too distant future.
Now there is an extensive
literature exploring
how testosterone therapy,
both in males and
females, can be effective
in some cases in the treatment
of anxiety-related disorders,
but not, at least to my
knowledge, in OCD in particular.
So this whole area of the use
of testosterone and estrogen therapies,
DHEA, cortisol suppression,
or maybe even enhancement
for the treatment of OCD
is essentially a big black box
that very soon, I believe, will be lit.
I realize that a number of
listeners of this podcast
are probably interested in the non-typical
or holistic treatments for OCD.
Dr. Blair Simpson's lab
has at least one study
exploring the role of
mindfulness meditation
for the treatment of OCD.
There, the data are a
little bit complicated
and I should mention that
good things are happening, at
least in the United States,
probably elsewhere as well,
but good things are happening in terms of
the exploration of things like meditation
and other, let's call them non-traditional
or holistic forms of treatment
for psychiatric disorders
because of the division
of complimentary health
that's now been launched
by the National Institutes of Health.
So, whereas before
people would think about
meditation or yoga nidra,
or even CBD supplementation
for that matter,
as kind of fringe maybe, or kind of woo
or non-traditional at the very least,
the National Institutes of
Health in the United States
has now devoted an entire division,
an entire Institute,
purely for the exploration
of things like breathing
practices, meditation, et cetera.
So there's a cancer institute,
there's a hearing and deafness institute,
there's a vision institute,
and now there's this
complimentary health Institute,
which I think is a wonderful addition
to the more traditional
aspects of medicine.
I think no possible useful treatment
should be overlooked or
unresearched in my opinion,
provided that can be done safely.
And as I mentioned,
Dr. Blair Simpson's lab
has looked at the role
of mindfulness meditation
and the treatment of OCD.
Now we should all keep in mind,
no pun intended, that most of the data
on mindfulness meditation
shows that it increases
the ability to focus.
Now, this brings us back to a
kind of repeating theme today,
which is that increased focus
may not be the best thing
for somebody with OCD
because it might increase
focus on the obsession
and/or compulsion.
Turns out that mindfulness
meditation can be useful
in the treatment of OCD,
but mainly by way of how it impacts
the focus on and the ability
to engage in cognitive
behavioral therapies.
So it's very unlikely, at
least by my read of the data,
to be a direct effect of meditation
on relieving the symptoms,
rather it seems that
meditation is increasing focus
on things like cognitive
behavioral therapy homework
and to not focus on other things
and therefore indirectly
improving the symptoms of OCD.
Now somewhat surprisingly, at least to me,
there have also been a fairly
large number of studies
exploring how nutraceuticals,
as they're sometimes called,
supplements that are
available over the counter
can impact the treatment of
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
Now there's such an extensive
number of different compounds
and supplements that
fall under the category
of nutraceuticals and
that have been explored
in the treatment of OCD
that I'd like to point you
to a review that is entitled,
Nutraceuticals in the treatment
of obsessive-compulsive
disorder: a review,
excuse me, of mechanistic
and clinical evidence.
So it's published in 2011,
so it's over 10-years-old.
And so by now,
I have to imagine that
there are an enormous number
of additional substances
that could be explored,
but there are just one or two
here that I want to focus on.
Here in this review,
they describe effects
of 5-HTP and tryptophan,
so things that are in
the serotonin pathway,
which would make sense
given what we know about the SSRIs
that people would explore
how different supplements
that increase serotonergic transmission
might impact OCD.
What you find is that they
do have significant effects
in improving or reducing
the symptoms of OCD
in somewhat similar way
to some of the SSRIs.
But you of course have to be careful.
Anything that's going to tap into a given
neurochemical system to the same degree
may very likely have the
same sorts of side effects
that a prescription drug would.
One compound that I like to focus on
in a little more depth, however,
because it's exciting
and interesting to me
is inositol.
Inositol is a compound that
we are going to talk about
in several future podcasts, because,
well, first of all,
it seems that it can
have impressive effects
on reducing anxiety.
It also can have pretty impressive effects
in improving fertility
and particular in women
with polycystic ovarian syndrome.
And here I'm referring
specifically to myo-inositol
because it comes in several forms.
And it does appear that
900 milligrams of inositol
can improve sleep and can reduce anxiety
perhaps when taken at that
dosage or higher dosages.
I will just confess, first
of all, I don't have OCD,
although I will also confess
that when I was a child,
I had a transient tick.
I've talked about this on podcast before.
It was a grunting tick.
So when I was about six or seven,
I recall a trip to
Washington DC with my family,
where I was feeling a strong
desire or need even as I recall,
to grunt in order to clear something
in my throat, but I didn't
have anything in my throat.
I didn't have a cold
or any postnasal drip,
it was really just the feeling
that I needed to do that,
to release some sort of tension.
And I remember my dad at the time
telling me don't do that.
Don't do that, it's not good to grunt
or something like that.
I think he saw that it was a
kind of compulsive behavior.
And so I would actually
hide in the back seat
of the rental car and do
it, or I'd hide in my room.
Fortunately for me, it was transient,
I think about six months or
a year later, it disappeared.
Although I did notice, actually
an ex-girlfriend of mine
point out that when I get very tired
and I've been working very long hours,
sometimes that grunting
tick will reappear.
What does that mean?
Do I have Tourette's?
I don't know, maybe.
I was never diagnosed with Tourette's.
Do I have OCD? Maybe.
I certainly could be accused
of having obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder,
which we'll talk about
still in a few minutes.
But the point here is that many children
transiently express ticks
or low level Tourette's
or OCD, and again, transiently
and it disappears over time.
So inositol has been explored
in a bunch of different contexts,
including for ticks in OCD, et cetera.
Going back to inositol
and its current use,
or I should say my current use,
I've been taking 900
milligrams of inositol
as in addition to my
existing toolkit for sleep,
which I've talked about
many times on this podcast
and other podcasts, consists
of magnesium threonate,
apigenin, and theanine.
If you want to know more about that kit,
you can go to our newsletter,
Neural Network Newsletter
at hubermanlab.com.
The toolkit for sleep is there.
You don't even have to
sign up for the newsletter
but it'll give you a flavor
of the sorts of things
that are in the newsletter.
In any case, I've been experimenting a bit
with taking 900 milligrams of myo-inositol
either alone or combination
with that sleep kit.
And I must say the sleep I've been getting
on inositol is extremely deep
and does seem to lead to enhanced levels
of focus and alertness during the day.
And perhaps you're noticing that
'cause I'm talking more quickly
on this podcast than in previous podcast.
No, I'm just kidding.
I don't think the two things relate
in any kind of causal way.
The point here is that inositol is known
to be pretty effective
in reducing anxiety,
but when taken at very high dosages.
Can it do the same at low dosages?
We don't know.
I would consider 900
milligrams a low dose.
Most of this, given the fact
that most of the studies of inositol
have explored very high dosages,
like even 10 or 12 grams per day,
which I must say seems exceedingly high
and they do report that
some of the subjects
in those experiments actually stop taking
the inositol because of gastric discomfort
or gastric distress as it's called.
So I've reported my results with sleep
in a kind of anecdotal way.
They certainly aren't
peer-reviewed studies
that I described about my own experience
in an anecdotal way.
But nonetheless, it's been explored that
things like glycine, which is another,
which is an amino acid,
which also acts as an
inhibitory neurotransmitter
in the brain, taken at very high dosages,
60 grams per day, that is a absolutely
astonishingly high amount of glycine.
I would not recommend
taking that much glycine
unless you're part of a study
where they tell you to
and you know it's safe.
18 grams, excuse me, of an inositol,
these are very, very high
dosages used in these studies.
Nonetheless, there's some interesting data
about inositol leading to
some alleviation of OCD symptoms
or partial alleviation of OCD symptoms
in as little as two weeks after initiating
the supplement protocol.
So I think there's a great
future for these nutraceuticals,
meaning I think more
systematic exploration
in particular of lower dosages
in the context of OCD treatment.
And as we saw before for the SSRIs
and other prescription drug treatments,
I think there really
needs to be an exploration
of these nutraceuticals in combination
with behavioral therapies.
And who knows, maybe with
brain machine interface
like cranial magnetic stimulation as well.
Now way back at the
beginning of the episode,
I alluded to the fact
that OCD is one thing,
obsessive-compulsive disorder,
and it's truly a disorder
and it's truly debilitating
and it's extremely common,
and then there's this other thing
called obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder,
which is distinct from that
does not have the intrusive component
so people don't feel overwhelmed
or overtaken by these thoughts,
rather, they find that the obsessions
can sometimes serve them
or they even welcome them.
And I think many of us
know people like this,
I perhaps even could be
accused or who knows,
maybe have been accused of having
an obsessive-compulsive
personality at times.
Why do I draw this distinction?
Well, first of all, we've come
to a point in human history,
I think in large part
because of social media
but also in large part
because there are a number
of discussions being held
about mental health that have
brought terms like trauma,
depression, OCD, et cetera,
into the common vernacular
so that people will
say, ah, you're so OCD,
or someone will say I
was traumatized by that,
or I was traumatized by this.
We should be very careful, right?
I'm certainly not the word police,
but we should be very careful in the use
of certain types of language,
especially language that
has real psychiatric
and psychological definitions
because it can really draw us off course
in providing relief for
some of these syndromes.
For instance,
the word trauma is thrown
around left and right nowadays.
I was traumatized by this,
or that caused trauma,
you're giving me trauma.
Listen, I realize that many people
are traumatized by certain events
including things that are said to them,
I absolutely acknowledge that,
hence our episodes on
trauma and trauma treatment,
several of them, in fact.
Dr. Conti, Dr. David Spiegel,
and then dedicated solo episodes
with just me blabbing about
trauma and trauma treatment.
But as Dr. Conti so
appropriately pointed out,
trauma is really something that changes
our neural circuitry and
therefore our thoughts
and our behaviors in a very persistent way
that is detrimental to us.
Not every bad event is traumatizing,
not everything that we
dislike or even that we hate
or that feels terrible
to us is traumatizing.
For something to reach
the level of trauma,
it really needs to change
our neural circuitry
and therefore our
thoughts and our behaviors
in a persistent way that
is maladaptive for us.
Similarly, just calling
someone obsessive is one thing,
saying that someone has
OCD or assuming one has OCD
simply because they have a
personality or a phenotype,
as we say, where they need
things in perfect order,
like I find myself correcting these pens
making sure that the caps are facing
in the same direction
for instance right now,
that is not the same as OCD.
If, for instance, I
can tolerate these pens
being at different orientation
or even throw the cap on
the floor or something,
it doesn't create a lot of anxiety for me.
I confess, I agree it's a
little bit in the moment,
but then I can forget
about it and move on.
That's one of the key distinctions
between obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder
and obsessive-compulsive disorder
in its strictest form.
Now, once one hears that OCD
is different than obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder
because of this difference
in how intrusive the thoughts are or not,
then that's useful, but
it really doesn't tell us
anything about what is
happening mechanistically
in one situation or another.
Fortunately, there are
beautiful data again
from Dr. Blair Simpson's lab.
And you can tell based
on the number of studies
that I've referred to from her laboratory,
she's truly one of the
luminaries in this field,
that there really are some
fundamental wiring differences
and behavioral differences
and psychological differences
between people who have
obsessive-compulsive disorder
and those who have obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
So this is a study, first
author, Pinto, P-I-N-T-O
entitled, Capacity to
delay reward differentiates
obsessive-compulsive disorder
and obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
And the methods in this
study were to take 25 people
with OCD and 25 people
with obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder and 25 people
who have both, because it
is possible to have both
and that's important to point out,
and 25 so-called healthy controls,
people that don't have
obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder or
obsessive-compulsive disorder.
They take clinical assessments
and then they took a number of tests
that probed their ability
to defer gratification,
something called, in the laboratory,
we call it delayed discounting.
So their ability to defer gratification
through a task where they
can either accept reward
right away or accept reward later.
Some of you may have heard
of the two marshmallow task.
This is based on a study
that was performed years ago
on young children at
Stanford and elsewhere
where they take young
children into a room,
they offer them a marshmallow,
kids like marshmallows generally,
and you say, you can eat
the marshmallow right now
or you can wait some period of time,
and if you are able to wait
and not eat the marshmallow,
you can have two marshmallows.
And in general, children
want two marshmallows
more than they want one marshmallow.
So really what you're probing is
their ability to access
delayed gratification.
And they're very entertaining,
even truly amusing videos
of this on the internet.
So if you just do two
marshmallow task video
and you go into YouTube,
what you'll find is that
the children will use
all sorts of strategies
to delay gratification.
Some of the kids will
cover the marshmallow.
Others will talk to the
marshmallow and say,
I know you're not that delicious.
You look delicious, but
no, you're not delicious.
They'll engage with the marshmallow
in all sorts of cute ways.
They'll turn around and try
to, you know, avoidance,
which actually speaks to a
whole category of behaviors
that people with OCD also use.
I'm not saying these kids had OCD,
but avoidance behaviors are
very much a component of OCD.
People really trying to avoid the thing
that evokes the obsession.
Well some kids are able
to delay gratification,
some aren't and it's
debatable as to whether or not
the kids that are able
to delay gratification
go on to have more
successful lives or not.
Initially, that was the
conclusion of those studies.
There's still a lot of debate about it,
we'll bring an expert on to
give us the final conclusion
on this 'cause there is one
and it's very interesting
and not intuitive.
Nonetheless, adults are also faced
with decisions every day, all day
as to whether or not they
can delay gratification.
And this study used a, not
a two marshmallow task,
but a game that involved rewards
where people could delay in order
to get greater rewards later.
What is the conclusion?
Well, first of all, obsessive-compulsive
and obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder subjects
both showed impairments in
their psychosocial functioning
and quality of life.
They had compulsive behavior.
So these are people that
are suffering in their life
because their compulsions
are really strong.
So it's not just being really nit-picky
or really orderly in one case
and having full blown OCD in the other,
both sets of subjects
are challenged in life
because they're having relationship issues
or job-related issues, et cetera,
because they are that compulsive.
However, the individuals with
obsessive-compulsive personality disorder,
they discounted the value
of delayed gratification
significantly less than those
with obsessive-compulsive disorder.
What do I mean?
They are both impairing disorders
that are marked by compulsive behaviors,
here I'm paraphrasing,
but they can be
differentiated by the presence
of obsessions in OCD.
So obsessions in OCD.
People with OCD are absolutely fixated
on certain ideas and
those ideas are intrusive.
Again, that's the hallmark theme.
And by an excessive
capacity to delay reward
in obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
That is people who have
obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder are really good
at delaying gratification.
So they are able to
concentrate very intensely
and perform very intensely in ways
that allow them to instill order
such that they can delay reward.
Now you can see why this
contour of symptoms,
meaning that the people with OCD
are experiencing intrusive thoughts,
whereas the people with
obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder
show an enhanced ability
to defer gratification.
You could see how that would lead
to very different outcomes.
People with obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder
can actually leverage
that personality disorder
to perform better in
certain domains of life,
not all domains of life,
because remember, again,
these people are in this study
and they're showing up as
experiencing challenges in life
because of their obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
Nonetheless, people with
obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder, you could imagine,
would be very good at say architecture
or anything that involves
instilling a ton of order.
Maybe sushi chef, for instance,
maybe a chef in general.
I know chefs that just
kind of throw things around
like the chef on the Muppets
and just like throw things
everywhere and still produce amazing food.
And then there's some people
there incredibly exacting,
they're just incredibly precise.
I think that movie, what is it?
Jiro Dreams of Sushi?
That movie is incredible.
Certainly not saying he
has obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder, but
I think it's fair to say
that he is obsessive or
extremely meticulous and orderly
about everything from start to finish.
You can imagine a huge array
of different occupations
and life endeavors where
this would be beneficial,
science being one of them
where data collection
and analysis is exceedingly
important that one be precise,
or mathematics or physics or engineering,
anything where precision has a payoff
and gaining precision takes time and delay
of immediate gratification,
you can imagine that obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder would synergize well
with those sorts of
activities and professions.
Whereas obsessive-compulsive
disorder is really intrusive.
It's preventing functionality in many
different domains of life.
So the key takeaway here is that
when we use the words
obsessive-compulsive,
or we call someone obsessive-compulsive,
or we are trying to
evaluate whether or not
we are obsessive compulsive,
it's very important that we highlight
that obsessive compulsive
disorder is very intrusive.
It involves intrusive thoughts
and it interrupts with
normal functioning in life.
Whereas obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder,
while it can interrupt
normal functioning in life,
it also can be productive.
It can enhance functioning
in life, not just in work,
but perhaps at home as well.
If you are somebody and
you have family members
that really place enormous value on having
a beautiful and highly organized home,
well, then it could lend
itself well to that.
it's going to be a matter
of degrees, of course.
None of these things is an absolute,
it's going to be on a continuum,
but I think it is fair to
say that obsessive-compulsive
disorder, whether or
not in mild, moderate,
or severe form is impairing
normal functioning,
whereas obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder,
there's a range of expressions of that,
some of which can be adaptive,
some of which can be maladaptive,
and again, it's all going
to depend on context.
Before we conclude, I do
want to touch on something
that I think a lot of people experience
and that's superstitions.
Superstitions are fascinating,
and there's some fascinating
research on superstitions.
One particular study that I'm a big fan of
is the work of Bence Olveczky at Harvard.
He studies motor sequences
and motor learning,
and he has beautiful
data on how people learn,
for instance, a tennis swing
and the patterns that
they engage in early on
and then the patterns
of swinging that they,
swinging the racket that is,
that they engage in later
as they acquire more skill.
And basically the takeaway is that
the amount of error or
variation from swing to swing
is dramatically reduced
as they acquire skill.
That's all fine and good,
and there's some
beautiful mechanistic data
that he and others have discovered
to support how that comes to be,
but they also explore animal models,
in particular, rats pressing
sequences of buttons
and levers to obtain a reward.
Believe it or not, rats are pretty smart.
I've seen this with my own eyes.
You can teach a rat to press
a lever for a pellet of food.
Rats can also learn to press levers
in a particular sequence in order to gain
a piece of food.
And they can actually learn to press
an enormous number of levers
in very particular sequences
in order to obtain pellets of food.
You can also give them
little buttons to press
or even a paddle to, or I
should say a pedal, excuse me,
to stomp on with their foot
in order to obtain a pellet of food.
Basically rats can learn
exactly what they need to do
in order to obtain a piece of food,
especially if they're made
a little bit hungry first.
Bence's lab has published beautiful data
showing that as animals and humans
come to learn a particular motor sequence,
very often they will
introduce motor patterns
in that sequence that are
irrelevant to the outcome
and yet that persist.
If you've ever watched a game of baseball,
you've seen this before.
Oftentimes the pitcher
up on the mound will
bring the ball to their chin.
They'll look over their shoulder,
they'll look back over the other shoulder,
and then they will, of course,
reel back and pitch the ball.
But if you watch closely,
oftentimes there are components
in the motor sequence,
which are completely
unrelated to the pitch.
They're not looking necessarily to see
if someone's stealing a base.
They're not necessarily looking
down at home plate where the batter is.
They're also doing things like
touching the back of their ear
before they bring the ball to their chin
or adjusting their hat.
And if you watch individual pictures,
what you'll find is that
they'll do the same sequence
of completely irrelevant motor patterns
before each and every single pitch.
Similarly, rats that have
been trained to, for instance,
hit two levers and step on a pedal
with their left hind foot, and then
tap a button up above
that is the red button,
will do that to gain a piece of food.
But sometimes they'll
also introduce a pattern
into that motor sequence where they will
shake their tail a little bit,
or they'll turn their head a little bit,
or they'll move their ears
a little bit, et cetera.
Motor patterns that have nothing to do
with obtaining the
particular outcome in mind.
In other words, you could eliminate
certain components of the motor sequence
and it would not matter, the
rat would still get the pellet,
the pitcher would still be able to pitch,
and yet that get
introduced because somehow
because they were
performed again and again
prior to successful trials,
the rat or the human baseball pitcher
comes to believe in some way
that it was involved in
generating the outcome,
hence superstition, right?
I confess I have a few superstitions.
I occasionally will knock on wood.
I'll say something that I want to happen,
and I'll say, oh, knock on
wood, and I'll just do it.
And occasionally I'll
challenge myself and think,
ah, I don't want to knock,
don't knock on wood,
Andrew, don't do that.
I don't think anyone
wants to be superstitious,
I certainly don't.
And so every once in a while,
I'll just challenge it, and I
won't actually knock on wood.
I'm admitting this to you to kind of
I guess normalize some of this.
Some people have superstitions
that border on or even become compulsions.
They really come to believe
that if they don't knock on wood,
that something terrible
is going to happen,
maybe something in particular.
Or in the case of the baseball pitcher,
they come to believe
that if they don't touch
their right ear before they
reel back on the pitch,
that the pitch won't be any good
or that they're going to lose the game.
Well, I don't know what
their thought process is.
Now, I also don't know
what the rat is thinking,
but the rat is clearly doing something
or thinking something is
related to the final outcome.
I don't know of any studies
where they've intervened
with the particular
superstition-like behaviors
of the rat to see whether or not the rat
somehow doesn't continue
to do the motor sequence
to get the pellet.
We don't know the rats, they're rats.
I don't speak rat, most people don't,
or if you speak to a rat,
if it speaks back, it's not in English.
Anyway, the point is that
superstitions are beliefs
that we, on an individual
scale, come to believe
are linked to the
probability of an outcome
when in fact we know, we actually know
in our rational minds, they
have no real relationship
to the outcome.
Superstitions can become full-blown
compulsions and obsessions
when we repeat them often enough
that they become automatic.
And I think this is what
we observe most of the time
when we see a pitcher touching their ear,
or for instance, in
tennis, you see this a lot,
you'll see someone
they'll slap their shoes.
Often, I see this, they'll like slap
the undersides of their soles.
They may tell themselves
that this is, I don't know,
maybe moving out some
of the dust or something
in the bottoms of their soles,
that gives them more
traction and they want that
to be ready for the serve
or something like that.
And maybe there's some truth to that,
but here, what we're referring to
are behaviors that really
have no rational relationship
to the outcome, and yet we
perform in a compulsive way.
People with OCD, yes, tend
to have more superstitions.
People with more superstitions, yes,
tend to have a tendency towards OCD
and I should mention, obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
If you think way back to the
first part of this episode,
when I was just describing
what the brain does, right?
What does your brain do?
Housekeeping functions to keep you alive
and it's a prediction machine.
Your neural circuits, you,
have an enormous amount
of biological investment
of real estate, literally,
cells and chemicals
that are there to try and
make your world predictable
and to try and give you control,
or at least the sense of
control over that world
and that's a normal process.
Low-level superstitions,
moderate superstitions
represent a kind of a
healthy range, I would say,
of behaviors that are aimed
at generating predictability
that don't disrupt normal function.
Obsessive-compulsive personality disorder,
provided is not too severe,
would I think represent the next level
along that continuum.
And then obsessive-compulsive disorder,
as I pointed out earlier,
is really a case of highly debilitating,
highly intrusive, really
overtake of neural circuitry
over our thoughts and behaviors
that requires very
dedicated, very persistent,
and very effective
treatments in order to stop
those obsessions and compulsions
and the anxiety that links them
somewhat counterintuitively
by teaching people
to tolerate that level
of increased anxiety
and interrupt those patterns.
And fortunately, as we described earlier,
such treatments exist,
cognitive behavioral therapy,
drug treatments like
SSRIs, also drug treatments
that tap into the glutamate system
and into perhaps also the dopamine system,
the so-called neuroleptics.
And then, as we described,
there's now an extensive
exploration of things
like ketamine, psilocybin, cannabis,
the initial studies don't
seem to hold much promise
for cannabis and CBD and
the treatment of OCD,
but who knows, maybe more
studies will come along
that will change that story.
And then of course,
brain machine interface
like transcranial magnetic stimulation.
And then just to remind you
what I already told you before
combinations of behavioral
and drug treatments
and brain machine interface, I think,
is really where the future lies.
Fortunately, good treatments exist.
We cannot say that any
one individual treatment
works for everybody.
There are fairly large
percentages of people
that won't respond to one
set of treatments or another,
and therefore one has
to try different ones.
And then there are the
so-called supplementation-based
or more holistic therapies.
Today, I've tried to cover each and all
of these in a fairly
substantial amount of detail.
I realize this is a fairly long episode,
that is intentional.
Much like our episode on ADHD,
on attention deficit
hyperactivity disorder,
I received an enormous number of requests
to talk about OCD, and
my decision to make this
a very long and detailed episode about OCD
really doesn't stem from any desire
to subject you to too much information
or to avoid the opportunity
to just list things off,
but what I've tried to
provide is an opportunity
to really drill deep
into the neural circuitry
and an understanding of
where OCD comes from,
how OCD is different from things like
the personality disorders
that I described.
And also to give you a
sense of how the individual
behavioral and drug treatments work
and perhaps don't work
so that you can really make
the best informed choices,
again, highlighting the fact that OCD
is an extremely common, extremely common,
and yet extremely debilitating condition
and one that I hope
that if any of you have,
or that you know people that have it
that you'll both gain
sympathy and understanding
for what they're dealing with,
perhaps as a consequence of some
of the information presented today,
and maybe help them
direct their treatment,
find better treatment, and of course,
apply those treatments for some relief.
If you're learning from and
or enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel.
That's a terrific zero
cost way to support us.
In addition, please
subscribe to the podcast
on Spotify and Apple.
And on both Spotify and Apple,
you can also leave us
up to a five star review
and give us feedback.
The best place to give us
written feedback, however,
is on the YouTube channel
within the comment section.
There you can leave us feedback
or suggestions about topics
you'd like us to cover
or guests you'd like us to interview here
on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
In addition, please check out the sponsors
mentioned at the beginning
of today's podcast,
that's the best way to support us.
During today's podcast and
on many previous episodes
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we talk about supplements.
While supplements aren't
necessary for everybody,
many people derive
tremendous benefit from them
for things like sleep and
focus and anxiety and so on.
The Huberman Lab Podcast is now partnered
with Momentous Supplements
because Momentous Supplements
are of the very highest quality,
they ship everywhere in the
world, not just in the US,
and we wanted to have one location
where people could go in order
to access the supplements
that we described and
detail the various roles of
here on The Huberman Lab Podcast.
If you go to livemomentous.com/huberman,
you can find those supplements.
the catalog of supplements available there
is going to be expanding quite a bit
in the weeks and months to come.
But right now, already, there are a number
of different supplements
for enhancing focus,
enhancing sleep, and so
on that are available.
Again, that's livemomentous.com/huberman.
If you're not already
following Huberman Lab
on Instagram and Twitter, please do so.
There I cover science and
science-related tools,
some of which overlap with the content
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
and some of which is
distinct from the content
on The Huberman Lab Podcast.
So again, that's hubermanlab on Instagram
and hubermanlab also on Twitter.
If you haven't already subscribed
to our Neural Network Newsletter,
this is a monthly newsletter.
It's completely zero cost.
You go to hubermanlab.com.
You go into the menu,
you click on newsletter,
you can see some example newsletters,
for instance, a toolkit for sleep.
You can download that right away.
You don't even have to
sign up for the newsletter.
You can get the toolkit
for neuroplasticity,
for the use of cold,
for the use of heat in
health and et cetera.
All of that's there.
And if you sign up for the newsletter,
you'll get the monthly
newsletter sent to you.
We don't share your email
information with every anybody,
and we have a very clear
privacy policy there.
So again, it's the
Neural Network Newsletter
available within the newsletter tab
under the menu at hubermanlab.com.
In closing, I'd like to thank you
for this in-depth discussion
about the mechanisms
and various treatments
for obsessive-compulsive disorder
and some of the related disorders.
And as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat guitar music]