- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
I'm Andrew Huberman
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate from my teaching
and research roles at Stanford.
It is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring zero-cost-to-consumer information
about science and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is ExpressVPN.
ExpressVPN is a virtual private network
that keeps your data
secure by routing your data
and online activities
through their servers
and keeping your data safe and secure
but also not selling your
data to third parties.
I started using ExpressVPN
because unfortunately I had
my bank accounts hacked.
I was traveling a lot
and I typically go on hotel or airline
or other public Wi-Fi from time to time
and I don't know how it happened,
but somehow my information got out there,
and as I learned more from my friends
and people that work
in the tech community,
it turns out that many
networks are not secure,
so with ExpressVPN,
it keeps all your information secure.
It keeps information about
your passwords secure.
the websites that you visit secure,
and as I mentioned earlier,
they never give away or sell your data.
The nice thing is you can use ExpressVPN,
it runs in the background
and you don't even really
realize that it's on.
It works on your phone,
it works on your laptop,
it even works on your smart TV.
If you'd like to try ExpressVPN,
you can go to expressvpn.com/huberman
to get three months free
on their one-year program.
I love ExpressVPN.
I use it even when I'm at home,
and so if you want to try it,
you can go to expressvpn.com/huberman
and you'll get three months
free on their one-year program.
The second sponsor of today's
podcast is Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is a vitamin
mineral probiotic drink.
I started taking Athletic Greens in 2012
because I wanted to cover my
vitamin and mineral bases.
I didn't know which things to take.
I found it really dizzying to know
which vitamins and minerals to purchase
and Athletic Greens allowed
me to get all the things
I needed to cover my bases in
one easy to consume formula
that also happens to taste really good.
I mix mine with water and a
little bit of lemon juice.
The probiotics in Athletic Greens
are also really important to me
because now there's an
abundance of data showing
that the gut microbiome, which
is supported by probiotics,
is important for gut-brain axis, mood,
metabolic function, hormone function,
just a huge number of biological functions
and health parameters.
If you want to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman,
and if you do that,
they'll give you a year's
supply of vitamin D3 K2.
Vitamin D3 also has lot of support
from the scientific literature
showing that it's important
for immune function,
so if you go to
athleticgreens.com/huberman,
you'll get Athletic Greens
plus the year's supply of vitamin D3 K2
and they'll give you
five free travel packets.
Mixing up powders is a
little bit messy sometimes
when you're on the road,
if you're in the car,
you're on the plane or you're on the move.
These travel packets make
everything really clean
and really easy.
Once again, that's
athleticgreens.com/huberman
for Athletic Greens, the
five free travel packets,
and the year's supply of vitamin D3 K2.
Many of you have graciously asked
how you can help support
the Huberman Lab Podcast.
There are several ways
that you can do that.
One is to check out our sponsors,
the other is we've set
up a Patreon account.
You can go to patreon.com/andrewhuberman
and that allows you to
donate to the podcast
at a variety of different levels.
In addition,
if you could subscribe to
the podcast on YouTube,
that's terrific.
If you haven't done that
already, please do so,
and please leave a comment.
If you want to make suggestions
about future episodes,
please also put that
in the comment section.
If you subscribe on Apple or
Spotify or both, that helps us,
and as well, Apple gives
you the opportunity
to leave a review and
give us a five star rating
if you feel we deserve a five star rating,
and of course,
please recommend the
podcast to your friends,
to your family members,
anyone that you think would
benefit from the information.
Really, the answer to your question of
how you can support the podcast is
you don't have to buy products,
although checking out
the sponsors does help.
You don't have to donate to Patreon.
We, of course, can't
require you to subscribe
and fill out reviews
and things of that sort,
but we like to think that by providing
a number of different ways
to support the podcast,
some of which are zero cost,
some of which, if you like,
gives you the opportunity
to contribute financially,
that's terrific as well.
Thank you so much.
We really appreciate your interest
in helping us keep this coming your way.
Thank you.
Let's continue our discussion
about neuroplasticity.
This incredible feature
of our nervous system
that allows it to change itself
in response to experience,
and even in ways that we consciously
and deliberately decide to change it.
That's an incredible feature.
No other organ in our
body has that capability.
Our nervous system,
which governs everything about who we are,
how we feel and what we do,
does have that capability.
The issue is most people don't know
how to access neuroplasticity.
Children readily access neuroplasticity
and they don't even realize
that they're doing it.
Adults want neuroplasticity
and so that's what this entire month
of the Huberman Lab
Podcast has been about.
We've explored neuroplasticity
from a variety of different perspectives.
We talked about
representational plasticity.
We talked about the importance
of focus and reward.
We talked about this amazing
and somewhat surprising aspect
of the vestibular system,
how altering our relationship to gravity,
and in addition to that,
making errors as we try and learn,
can open up windows to plasticity,
but we have not really
talked so much about
directing the plasticity
toward particular outcomes,
and thus far,
we really haven't talked yet
about how to undo things
that we don't want.
I've talked about learning and I say
learn a language, learn free throws,
learn a particular motor skill, et cetera,
but what about what we
would call unlearning
or about removing some aspect
of our experience that we don't want?
And so today,
we are going to explore that
aspect of neuroplasticity
and we are going to do that in the context
of a very important and
somewhat sensitive topic
which is pain regeneration,
and in some cases, injury
to the nervous system.
For those of you that are fortunate enough
to not have or had a concussion
or not have or know someone
who is experiencing chronic or acute pain,
I encourage you to stay in here with us
because a lot of the information
that we are going to cover
has direct relevance to
neuroplasticity for other purposes.
We, as always here on this podcast,
are going to discuss some of the science,
we get into mechanism,
but we also really get at principles.
Principles are far more
important than any one experiment
or one description of mechanism
and certainly far more
important than any one protocol
because principles allow you
to think about your nervous system
and work with it in ways
that best serve you.
They are very flexible
batches of information.
We are going to talk about the
principles of neuroplasticity
for removing pain and
wound healing and injury.
We're going to talk about
acupuncture, of all things.
We are going to talk about
modern medicine's attempt
to try and restore youth to the aging
or injured or demented brain,
and we are going to
definitely talk about tools.
Got a lot of tools.
I consulted a number of
fantastic colleagues at Stanford,
at Harvard Medical School,
and in the greater community
of tissue rehabilitation,
injury and pain management in
preparation for this podcast.
I do want to be very
clear and just remind you
that I'm not a medical doctor.
I'm a professor, so I
don't prescribe anything.
I profess things.
I have my beliefs,
but the podcast is for
information purposes.
I do hope that the tools that we discuss
will be of benefit to you, but as always,
you should talk to your
doctor or healthcare provider
about any tools that you plan to add
or are looking to explore,
as well as anything that
you might look to remove
from your daily protocols.
In other words, don't change anything
without consulting an expert first.
You are responsible for
your health, not me,
and I say this not just to protect me
but also to protect you.
Please keep that in
mind as we move forward
and I'm very excited to share
with you this information
because I do feel that it
can be of great benefit
to a number of people.
Let's start our discussion
about pain and sensation
and regeneration and wound
healing with a discussion about
a very important system
in the nervous system,
which is the somatosensory system.
The somatosensory system
is, as the name implies,
involved in understanding touch,
physical feeling on our body,
and the simplest way to think
about the somatosensory system
is that we have little sensors
and those sensors come in the
form of neurons, nerve cells,
that reside in our skin
and in the deeper layers below the skin,
and indeed, we do.
We have some that correspond to,
and we should say respond
to, mechanical touch,
so pressure on the top
of my hand or a pinpoint,
or other sensors, for instance,
respond to heat, to cold.
Some respond to vibration.
We have a huge number of
different receptors in our skin
and they take that information
and send it down these
wires that we call axons
in the form of electrical
signals to our spinal cord
and then up to the brain,
and within the spinal cord and brain,
we have centers that
interpret that information,
that actually make sense of
those electrical signals,
and this is amazing because
none of those sensors
has a different unique form
of information that it uses.
It just sends electrical
potentials into the nervous system.
The nervous system,
you somehow decode what a
given stimulus on your skin is.
Maybe it's the wind blowing gently
and deflecting some of
the hairs on your arm
or maybe it's a sharp
pinprick or a hot stove
or the warmth of a glowing fire.
That all arrives in your nervous system
in the form of these electrical things
we call action potentials,
which is just amazing,
and then the brain computes
them and make sense of them.
We have peripheral sensors
and we've got stations up in our brain
and within our spinal cord
that make sense of all
the stuff coming in.
Pain and the sensation of
pain is, believe it or not,
a controversial word in
the neuroscience field.
People prefer to use the word nociception.
Nociceptors are the sensors in the skin
that detect particular types of stimuli.
It actually comes from
the Latin word nocere
which means to harm,
and why would neuroscientists
not want to talk about pain?
Well, it's very subjective.
It has a mental component
and a physical component.
We cannot say that pain
is simply an attempt
to avoid physical harm to the body,
and here's why.
They actually can be
dissociated from one another.
A good example would be if, God forbid,
you were exposed to high
levels of radiation,
such as working with some sort of material
that was radioactive
or you were near a
former radioactive plant
or some some radiation,
excessive X-rays, et cetera,
you wouldn't feel any
pain during the X-rays.
In fact, you don't.
If you've ever had X-rays, as I have,
you don't feel anything.
They put you under that lead blanket,
they run behind a wall
and then they, in my case,
then they take these
pictures of your teeth
and it's really scary because you go,
"Something really terrible
must be happening here,"
but you don't feel anything,
but there can be a lot of tissue damage.
There can be mutations
introduced to cells, et cetera.
I've had X-rays,
I'm not saying people
shouldn't have X-rays,
but excessive X-rays
certainly are not good
for human beings,
likewise with excessive
exposure to any radiation.
There can be tissue damage
without the physical perception
or mental perception of pain at all.
As well, there can be the belief of pain
or the feeling of pain without
there being tissue damage,
and there's a famous
case that was published
in the "British Journal of Medicine"
where a construction worker,
I think he fell is how the story went,
and a 14-inch nail
went through his boot
and up through the boot
and he was in excruciating pain
just beyond anything he'd experienced.
He reported that he couldn't
even move in any dimension,
even a tiny bit, without
feeling excruciating pain.
They brought him into the
clinic, into the hospital,
they were able to cut away the boot
and they realized that the
nail had gone between two toes
and it had actually not
impaled the skin at all.
His visual image of the
nail going through his boot
gave him the feeling,
the legitimate feeling,
that he was experiencing the pain
of a nail going through his foot,
which is incredible
because it speaks to the power of the mind
in this pain scenario
and it also speaks to the
power of the specificity.
It's not like he thought
that his foot was on fire.
He thought, because he saw a
nail going through his foot,
well, it was going through his boot,
but he thought it was
going through his foot,
that it was sharp pain of the sort
that a nail would produce,
and there are thousands
of these kinds of case reports out there.
That is not to say that
all pain that we experience
is in our head,
but it really speaks to
the incredible capacity
that these top-down,
these higher-level
cognitive functions have
in interpreting what we're experiencing
out in the periphery,
even just on the basis of what we see,
and the example of
radiation speaks to the fact
that pain and tissue damage
are dissociable from one another.
Why are we talking about pain
during a month on neuroplasticity?
Well, it turns out that
the pain system offers us
a number of different principles
that we can leverage to,
A, ensure that if we are ever injured,
we are able to understand the difference
between injury and pain
because there is a difference,
that if we're ever in pain,
that we can understand
the difference between
injury and pain,
that we will be able
to interpret our pain,
and during the course of today's podcast,
I'm going to cover protocols
that help eliminate pain
from both ends of the spectrum,
from the periphery, at
the level of the injury,
and through these top-down
mental mechanisms.
A lot of times on this
podcast, in fact mostly,
I tend to center on the physiology,
on the really objective things
that you can describe and talk about,
diaphragmatic movement
or sunlight of a particular
number of photons, et cetera,
but today's a really exciting opportunity
for us to discuss some of
the more subjective things.
Believe it or not, we're
going to talk about love.
A colleague of mine at Stanford,
who runs a major pain clinic,
is working on and has published
quality peer-reviewed data
on the role of love in
modulating the pain response,
only there's a twist to it
and I'm not going to reveal it just yet,
but it turns out that the
specific type of connection
one has to a romantic partner
actually dictates whether
or not their love for them
will alleviate physical pain
and the effects are really robust.
It's an amazing literature,
and so what we're talking about today
is plasticity of perception,
which has direct bearing on emotional pain
and has direct bearing on trauma
and other things that we discussed
in previous episodes a little bit
but that we're going to explore even more
in an entire month about those topics.
Let's get started in thinking
about what happens with pain,
and I will describe some examples
of some kind of extreme cases.
For instance, I will tell you just now
that there is a mutation,
a genetic mutation in a
particular sodium channel.
A sodium channel is one of
these little holes in neurons
that allows them to
fire action potentials.
It's important to the
function of the neuron.
It's also important for the
development of certain neurons,
and there's a particular mutation,
there are kids that are born
without this sodium channel 1.7,
if you want to look it up.
Those kids experience no
pain, no pain whatsoever,
and it is a terrible situation.
They burn themselves.
They tend to rest on their limbs too long.
They don't make the microadjustments.
You might see me swiveling
around in my chair,
moving around a lot.
Those microadjustments are actually
normal, healthy microadjustments
that prevent us from going into pain.
They don't make those adjustments.
They don't get the feedback
that they're in a particular position
and so they never make those adjustments
and their joints get
destroyed, essentially.
They don't tend to live
very long due to accidents.
It's a really terrible and
unfortunate circumstance.
Some people have a mutation
in the same channel
where they make too much of this channel
so they feel too much pain.
In fact, it's reasonable to speculate
that one of the reasons, not all,
but one of the reasons
why people might differ
in their sensitivity to pain
is by way of genetic variation
in how many of these sorts of
receptors that they express.
People who make too much of this receptor
experience extreme pain
from even subtle stimuli.
The good news is there
are good drug treatments
that can block specifically
this sodium channel 1.7
and so those people get a lot of relief
from taking such drugs.
Pain and how much pain we are sensitive to
or insensitive to probably
has some genetic basis,
and then of course, there
are things that we can do
to make sure that we experience less pain,
although pain has this adaptive role.
Let's talk about some of the features of
how we're built physically
and how that relates to pain
and how we can recover from injury.
First of all,
we have maps of our body
surface in our brain.
It's called a homunculus.
In a rat, believe it or
not, I'm not making this up,
it's called a ratunculus.
In Costello, my dog, who
is snoring behind me,
it's a dogunculus.
I could get into the nomenclature
and why it's called this,
but it's basically a
representation of the body surface.
That representation is scaled
in a way that matches sensitivity,
so the areas of your body
that are most sensitive
have a lot more brain real
estate devoted to them.
Your back is an enormous piece of tissue
compared to your fingertip,
but your back has fewer
receptors devoted to it
and the representation of
your back in your brain
is actually pretty small,
whereas the representation
of your finger is enormous.
How big a brain area is
devoted to a given body part
is directly related
to the density of receptors
in that body part,
not the size of the body part,
and that's why if we were
to draw your homunculus
or Costello's dogunculus,
what we would find is that certain areas,
like the lips, like the fingertips,
like the genitalia,
like the eyes and the
area around the face,
would have a huge representation,
whereas the back, the torso,
and areas of the body
that are less sensitive
are going to have smaller representations.
It'd be a very distorted map.
You can actually know
how sensitive a given body part is
and how much brain area is devoted to it
through what's called
two-point discrimination.
You can do this experiment if you want.
I think I've described
this once or twice before,
but basically if you have someone put,
maybe take two pens
and put them maybe six
inches apart on your back
and touch while you're facing away
and they'll ask you how many
points they're touching you
and you say two,
but if they move those closer
together, say three inches,
you're likely to experience
it as one point of contact,
whereas on your finger,
you could play that game all day
and as long as there's a
millimeter or so spacing,
you will know that it's two
points as opposed to one
and that's because there's more pixels,
more density of receptors.
This has direct bearing to pain
because it says that areas of the body
that have denser receptors
are going to be more sensitive
to pain than to others,
and where we have more receptors,
we tend to have more
blood vessels and glia,
which are the support cells,
and other cells that lend
to the inflammation response
and that's really important.
Just as a rule of thumb,
areas of your body that are injured
that are large areas that have
low sensitivity before injury
likely are going to experience less pain
and the literature shows
will heal more slowly
because they don't have
as many cells around
to produce inflammation,
and you might say, "Wait, I
thought inflammation is bad."
Well, one of the things I
really want to get across today
is that inflammation is not bad.
Inflammation out of control is bad,
but inflammation is wonderful.
Inflammation is the tissue repair response
and we are going to talk about
subjective and objective ways
to modulate inflammation
after tissue injury,
even after just exercise
that's been too intense.
You have this map of your body surface.
It's sensitive in different
ways. Now you know why.
You've got your neurobiology
of somatosensation 101
under your belt now.
We didn't cover everything,
but we'll touch on some
of the other details
as we go forward.
I thought it might be a nice
time to just think about
the relationship between the
periphery and the central maps
in a way that many of you have
probably heard about before,
which will frame the
discussion a little bit better,
which is phantom limb pain.
Some of you are probably
familiar with this,
but for people that have an arm or a leg
or a finger or some other
portion of their body amputated,
it's not uncommon for those people
to feel as if they still
have that limb or appendage
or piece of their body intact,
and typically, unfortunately,
the sensation of that limb
is not one of the limb
being nice and relaxed and just there.
The sensation is that the
limb is experiencing pain
or is contorted in the
specific orientation
that it was around the time of the injury.
If someone has a blunt force to the hand
and they end up having
their hand amputated,
typically they will continue to feel pain
in their phantom hand,
which is pretty wild,
and that's because the
representation of that hand
is still intact in the
cortex, in the brain,
and it's trying to balance
its levels of activity.
Normally it's getting what's
called proprioceptive feedback.
Proprioception is just our knowledge
of where our limbs are in space.
It's an extremely important aspect
of our somatosensory system,
and there's no proprioceptive feedback
and so a lot of the
circuits start to ramp up
their levels of activity
and they become very
conscious of the phantom limb.
Before my lab was at Stanford,
I was at UC San Diego and one
of my colleagues was a guy,
everyone just calls him by
his last name, Ramachandran,
who is famous for understanding
this phantom limb phenomenon
and developing a very simple
but very powerful solution to it
that speaks to the incredible capacity
of top-down modulation,
and top-down modulation,
the ability to use one's
brain cognition and senses
to control pain in the body,
is something that everyone,
not just people missing
limbs or in chronic pain,
can learn to benefit from
because it is a way to tap into
our ability to use our mind
to control perceptions of
what's happening in our body,
and this is not a mystical statement.
This is not about mind, I
guess, as much as it is brain
to control our perceptions of our body.
What did Ramachandran do?
Ramachandran had people
who were missing a limb
put their intact limb into a box
that had mirrors in it
such that when they looked in the box
and they moved their intact limb,
the opposite limb,
which was a reflection of the intact limb
'cause they're missing the opposite limb,
they would see it as if it was intact,
and as they would move their intact limb,
they would visualize with their eyes
the limb that's in the
place of the absent limb,
so this is all by mirrors,
moving around and they
would feel immediate relief
from the phantom pain,
and he would tell them and
they would direct their hand
toward a orientation that
felt comfortable to them.
Then they would exit the mirror box,
they would take their hand out,
and they would feel as if
the hand was now in its
relaxed normal position.
You could get real time, in moments,
remapping of the
representation of the hand.
Now, that's amazing.
This is the kind of thing that all of us
would like to be able
to do if we are in pain.
If you stub your toe,
if you break your ankle,
if you take a hard fall on your bike
or if you're in chronic pain.
Wouldn't it be amazing to be able to use
a mind trick,
but it's not a trick because
it's real, visual imagery,
to remap your representation
of your body surface
and where your body is.
That is something that
we could all benefit from
because if you do anything for
long enough, including live,
you're going to experience
pain of some sort,
and this, again I just want to remind you,
isn't just about physical
injuries and pain,
this has direct relevance
to emotional pain as well,
which, of course, we'll talk about.
The Ramachandran studies
were really profound
because they said a couple things.
One, plasticity can be very fast,
that it can be driven by
the experience of something,
just the visual experience.
He had people do this mirror box thing
but not look into the mirror box
and they didn't get the remapping,
so it required visual imagery coming in.
We also know, for instance,
that in cases like where
people are congenitally deaf,
the cochlear implant,
which is simply a way of
putting, it's not simple,
but it's a way of putting in a device
that replaces the cochlea,
the device that we're
normally born with in the ear
that has these little
what are called hair cells
that deflect according to sound
waves and allow us to hear.
By replacing the normal hearing apparatus
that's deficient in deaf people
with this cochlear implant,
the brain can make sense of
this artificial ear, basically,
it's not the outside ear, not
the pinna, but the inner ear,
and they can start to hear sounds.
Some people really like
the artificial cochlea.
They really benefit from it.
It restores their ability
to hear and they like it.
Other people don't.
Some deaf people would
prefer not to hear anything,
can be very disruptive to them,
and some of that might
have to do with the need
for further better engineering
of these artificial cochleas,
but all this really speaks to the fact
that the brain is an adaptive device.
It will respond to what you give it.
It is not a device that is fixed.
In fact, the essence of the brain,
especially the human brain,
is to take sensory inputs
and to make sense of those,
meaning cognitive sense,
and then to interpret those signals,
and so this may come as
a shock to some of you
and by no means am I
trying to be insensitive,
but pain is a perceptual thing
as much as it's a physical thing.
It's a belief system about
what you're experiencing in your body
and that has important relevance
for healing different types of injury
and the pain associated with that injury.
In people's pursuit for neuroplasticity,
a question that comes
up every once in a while
is people will say,
"If I just brush my teeth
with the opposite hand
for a couple nights in a row,
will I get neuroplasticity?"
And the answer is probably
yes. It's a deliberate action.
You're focusing on it.
There's an end goal.
You're very likely to make errors,
like jamming up into your
lips and gums at first
and then getting better at it,
and as you heard in last episode,
making errors is really important
'cause those errors are the signal
that plasticity needs to happen,
and then when you get the actions correct,
then those correct
actions are programmed in.
I'm not sure that brushing one's teeth
with the opposite hand is the most
effective use of this
incredible thing that we have,
which is plasticity.
It's not going to open up
plasticity for many other things.
If that were really important
to you, for whatever reason,
maybe you have a crowded bathroom
and it's easier to do on one
side or the other, then fine,
but it's kind of hard to
imagine why this would be
a highly adaptive behavior,
unless, of course, you
have an injured limb
or you're missing a limb,
and that gets me to some really exciting
and important studies that were performed
mostly in the '90s as
well as in the 2000s,
and that, for now, there is
really a solid base of data.
There's really a center of mass around
a particular set of experiments
that point to particular protocols
for how to overcome motor injury,
and this may resonate with some of you
who've ever been injured to the point
where you couldn't walk well,
temporarily, I hope, or even longer.
Think about a sprained ankle scenario
or a broken arm scenario.
We're all familiar with
the stories of people
having a cast on and
then getting the cast off
and the particular limb
that wasn't being used
that was casted is much
smaller and atrophied.
Most of that atrophy, you
might be surprised to learn,
is not because the
muscles aren't being used.
It's because the nerves sending
signals to those muscles
are not active and therefore
the muscles aren't contracting.
Work done by a guy named Timothy Schallert
and his graduate students and postdocs,
Theresa Jones and others,
in the '90s and 2000s showed
something really wonderful
that I think we can all benefit from
should we have an injury
and even if we simply want
to balance out imbalances
in our motor activity,
and I think all of us tend to be stronger
on one side or the other side.
Usually a right-handed person
will be stronger in their
left arm, not always,
for compensatory reasons.
Some other time we can
talk about handwriting.
The lefties likely will be
stronger in their right arm,
although it depends on whether or not
people are hook righties,
that's when you hook around
and write from the top,
or hook lefties.
There are all sorts of theories about this
that we can talk about,
right brain, left brain,
math proficiency, et cetera.
In any event,
what Schallert and colleagues showed
was that if we have damage to our brain
in the sensory motor pathways,
any number of different
sensory motor pathways,
or we have damage to a limb,
could be a leg, could be
an arm, could be a hand,
there's great benefit
to restricting the use
of the opposite,
better-performing, uninjured limb
or hand or other part of the body.
They had about a dozen papers showing
that if there was damage
centrally in the brain
or there was damage to a limb,
so unilateral damage, as we say, one side,
the thing to do is not to
cast up the damaged side,
although you need to do
that to protect the limb,
of course, from further damage.
If it's a broken arm,
you need to cast the arm
or you need to brace the arm,
but that the key thing
was to restrict movement
of the intact, uninjured, opposite limb,
and when they did that,
it forced some movement
in the injured limb
and remarkably,
through connections from
the two sides of the brain,
through the corpus callosum,
this huge fiber pathway
that links the two sides of the brain,
they saw plasticity on
both sides of the brain.
This makes sense when you hear it.
Let's say I injure my left ankle
and I'm limping along
or I'm using crutches.
You would think, well, the
last thing you want to do
is injure your opposite limb
or not use your opposite limb.
My right ankle is perfectly fine,
but if I lean too hard on my right limb
and I take all the work
out of the left limb,
the left ankle,
that's actually setting up a situation
where there's going to
be runaway asymmetry
in the central pathways
and the nerve-to-muscle
pathways on my left side,
and so what they suggested
and what they showed in
a variety of experiments
was that by encouraging
activity of the injured limb,
provided it could be done without pain,
and importantly,
not just exercising that
limb or part of the body
but restricting the opposite
healthy part of the body,
that the speed of recovery
was significantly faster.
Now, I want to repeat,
you don't want to go
injuring something further.
That's probably the
worst thing you could do,
but in some cases where people
have damage in their brain,
the limbs are perfectly fine,
but the motor signals aren't
getting down to the limbs,
and in that case, the limb is fine,
so you actually are free to use
either limb as much as you
want, and in that case,
you don't want to rely on the
uninjured pathway too much.
In fact, you want to restrict
the uninjured pathway.
I find these studies remarkable
and they've been followed up
on at the molecular level,
at the cellar level many times,
and I think the physiotherapists out there
and the rest of you who are
involved in sports medicine
and some of the physicians will say,
"Well, of course that
makes perfect sense,"
but oftentimes this is not what happens.
Oftentimes what happens
is it's all about resting
and limiting inflammation, et cetera,
of the injured limb
or the limbs corresponding to
the injured part of the brain,
and these experiments and
the collection of them
point to the fact that the balance between
the right and left side of
our body is always dynamic.
It's always being updated at
the level of neural circuitry,
the Ramachandran studies
with the mirror box
support that too,
and that even slight imbalances
in the two sides of the body
can get amplified,
and so when you're in a situation
where one side is injured
or the brain is injured
representing one side of the body,
the key thing to do is to really overwork
the side that needs the work
and to restrict the activity of the side
that doesn't need the
work because it's healthy,
and this has great semblance
to ocular dominance plasticity,
which I talked about
a couple episodes ago.
I won't go into it in detail,
but where the Nobel Prize
winning neurobiologists
Torsten Wiesel and David Hubel showed
that if one eye is closed
early in development,
that the representation of
the opposite eye in the brain
is completely overtaken by the intact eye.
This is important.
It means that all of our
senses and our movements
are competing for space in our brain
and so the way to think
about the principle is
anytime you're injured
and you're hobbling along,
you don't want to injure yourself further,
but you want to try and compensate
in the ways that respect this competition
for neural real estate,
and what that usually
means is not relying on
where you're still strong
because that's just going
to create runaway plasticity
that's going to make it very hard
for you to recover the motor function,
and in some cases, the sensory function,
of the damaged limb.
Some of you may be wondering
how long and how often one
should restrict the activity
of the intact or healthy limb,
or limbs in some cases,
and the answer is
you don't have to do
that all day, every day.
These experiments centered on
doing one or two hours of dedicated work,
sensory motor work or,
so for instance, if you had
a sprained ankle on the left,
you might spend part of the
day where your left leg,
provided it's not too
painful, can be exercised,
again, in a way that's not
damaging to the injury,
and the right limb can't
contribute to that exercise.
This might be peddling unilaterally
on a stationary bike if you can do that.
For a different type of limb
injury, like an arm injury,
this might be reaching,
provided the shoulder is
mobile, doing reaching.
It might be even writing
with the damaged side
and then intentionally not writing
with the preferred or undamaged side.
This has been shown to
accelerate the central plasticity
and the recovery of function,
which I think is what most people want
when people are injured.
They want to get back to doing
what they were doing previously
and they want to be able
to do that without pain.
This brings up another topic,
which is definitely related
to neuroplasticity and injury
but is a more general one
that I hear about a lot,
which is traumatic brain injury.
Many injuries are not just about the limb
and the lack of use of the limb
but concussion and head injury,
and I want to emphasize
I'm not a neurologist.
I have many colleagues that are.
At some point, we will
do a whole month on TBI
because it's such a serious issue
and it's such a huge discussion,
but I want to talk a little bit about
what is known about
recovery from concussion,
and this is very important
because it has implications
for just normal aging as well
and offsetting some of
the cognitive decline
and physical decline that
occurs with normal aging.
We shouldn't think of TBI as
just for the football players
or just for the kids that had an injury
or just for the person that
was in the car accident.
We want to learn about TBI
and understand TBI for those folks,
but we're also going to talk about TBI
as it relates to general
degradation of brain function
because there's a
certain resemblance there
of TBI to general brain aging.
Typically after TBI,
there are a number of
different things that happen
and there are a huge range of
things that can create TBI.
Neurologists and the
emergency room physicians
are going to want to know
was the skull itself injured
or did the brain rattle
around in the skull?
Was there actually a
breach through the skull?
Is there a physical object in there?
How many concussions has the person had?
Everyone's situation with
TBI is incredibly different,
but there's a constellation of symptoms
that many people, if
not all people with TBI,
report which is headache,
photophobia, that lights become aversive,
sleep disruption, trouble concentrating,
sometimes mood issues.
There's a huge range
and of course the severity
will vary, et cetera.
In a previous episode, I
mentioned the Kennard Principle.
The Kennard Principle,
named after the famous neurologist,
named by and after the famous
neurologist Margaret Kennard,
said that if you're going
to get a brain injury,
better to get it early in
life than later in life
and that's because the
brain has a much greater
or heightened capacity
for repairing itself
early in life than later,
but of course, none of us want TBI
and you can't pick when you get your TBI.
You can avoid certain activities
that would give you TBI,
but really, when it comes to TBI,
there are a couple of things that are
agreed upon across the board.
The first one is,
as much as possible you want to avoid
a second traumatic brain
injury or concussion.
That's going to be a tough
one for some of the athletes
and even recreational athletes to swallow
because they want to
continue in their sport,
and I'm not here to tell you
that you should or you shouldn't,
but that's simply the way that it is.
For folks that are in military
or that are in certain professions,
construction is a place
where we see a lot of TBI.
It's not always just football.
A lot of construction workers
are dealing with heavy objects
swinging around in space.
They wear those hardhat helmets,
which unfortunately don't protect much
against a lot of those blunt forces
and certainly not against
falls and things of that sort.
Many people, in order to
survive and feed their families,
have to go back to work.
It's very clear that
regardless of whether or not
there was a skull break
and regardless of when the TBI happened
and how many times it's happened,
that the system that repairs
the brain, the adult brain,
is mainly centered around
this lymphatic system
that we call, for the brain,
the glymphatic system.
The brain wasn't thought
to have a lymphatic system.
It wasn't thought to have
circulating immune cells,
but about 10 years ago it
was sort of rediscovered
because if you look in the literature
you realize this stuff was around longer,
that there's a glymphatic system.
It's sort of like a sewer
system that clears out
the debris that surrounds neurons,
especially injured neurons,
and the glymphatic system
is very active during sleep.
It's been imaged in functional
magnetic resonance imaging
and the glymphatic system is something
that you want very active
because it's going to
clear away the debris
that sits between the neurons,
and the cells that surround
the connections between the
neurons, called the glia,
those cells are actively involved
in repairing the connections
between neurons when damaged.
The glymphatic system is so important
that many people, if not
all people who get TBI,
are told, "Get adequate
rest, you need to sleep,"
and that's kind of twofold advice.
On the one hand, it's
telling you to get sleep
because all these good
things happen in sleep.
It's also about getting those people
to not continue to engage
in their activity full time
or really try and hammer through it.
You might say, "Well, if
you have trouble sleeping,
how are you supposed to get deep sleep?"
Most of the activity of
the glymphatic system,
this wash out of the debris,
is occurring during slow-wave sleep.
Slow-wave sleep, as I mentioned
in a previous episode,
is something that happens typically
in the early part of the evening.
Even for those of you that are falling,
or early part of the night, rather,
if you're falling asleep
and then waking up
three, four hours later,
it's important that you
continue to get sleep
but know that the slow-wave sleep
is mainly packed toward the
early part of the night,
so that hopefully will
alleviate some of the anxiety
of the 3:00 and 4:00 am wake up,
although you really should follow
some of the protocols that I've suggested
and your physician's protocols
in order to try and get
regular, longer sleep
of seven, eight hours.
Later, we're going to talk
about the eight-hour mark
as a prerequisite for repair.
The glymphatic system has been shown
to be activated further in two ways.
One is that sleeping on one side,
not on back or stomach,
seems to increase the amount of wash out,
or wash through, I should say,
of the glymphatic system.
There aren't a ton of data on this,
but the data that exist are pretty solid.
Again, sleeping on one side
or with feet slightly elevated, as well,
has been shown to increase
the rate of clearance
of some of the debris
and that's because the way that
the glymphatic system works
is it has a physical
pressure fluid dynamic to it
that allow it to work more efficiently
when one is sleeping on their side
or with feet slightly elevated.
This means not falling asleep
in a chair while watching TV.
This means, if possible,
not falling asleep on one's
back or on one's stomach,
sleeping on one's side,
and if you can't do that,
I don't really like to sleep on my side.
I sleep with my feet slightly elevated.
I put a thin pillow under my ankles.
I don't have TBI, but I have
had a few concussions before,
but right now I feel fine,
but I find that putting
the pillow under my ankles
helps me sleep much more deeply
and I wake up feeling much more refreshed.
The other thing that has been shown
to improve the function
of the glymphatic system,
and this is, again, is for sake of TBI
as well as for everyone,
even without brain injury,
is a certain form of exercise,
and I want to be very, very clear here.
I will never and I am not suggesting
that people exercise in any way
that aggravates their injury
or that goes against
their physician's advice.
Take your physician's advice
as to whether or not you
should be exercising at all
and how much and then to what intensity.
However, there's some interesting data,
and we can provide a link
to the review on this.
It shows that exercise of
what I guess people would
nowadays call it Zone 2 cardio,
which is low-level
cardio that one could do
while talking to somebody else.
You could maintain a conversation,
although you don't have
to talk to somebody else.
It just gives you a sense of
the intensity of the exercise.
That Zone 2 cardio
for 30 to 45 minutes 3 times a week
seems to improve the rates of clearance
of some of the debris after injury,
and in general, injury or no,
to accelerate and
improve the rates of flow
for the glymphatic system.
I find this really interesting
because I think nowadays
there's such an obsession
with high-intensity interval training
and people trying to pack
in as much as they can
into a short workout,
which is great if it
brings people to the table
who haven't been exercising before,
but I think it's really
important that we know
that the data on exercise
and its relationship to brain health
speak to doing 30 to 45 minutes
of this what we call low-level cardio.
It could be fast walking.
It could be jogging
if you can do that with
your injury safely.
It could be cycling.
This is not the kind of workout
that's designed to get your
heart rate up to the point
where you're improving your fitness levels
at some sort of massive rate
or taking huge jumps in your
VO2 max or anything like that.
This is exercise,
I do this and I know a
number of other people,
especially people in communities
where there is a lot of TBI,
are now starting to adopt this,
that the 30 to 45 minutes
3 times a week or so,
could be more,
of this Zone 2 type cardio
can be very beneficial
for washout of debris from the brain,
and this is really
interesting outside of TBI
because what we know from aging
is that aging is a nonlinear process.
It's not like with every year of life
your brain gets a little older.
Sometimes it follows what's
more like a step function
where you get these big
jumps in markers of aging.
I guess that we could
think of them as jumps down
because it's a negative
thing for most everybody.
We'd like to live longer and
be healthier in brain and body,
and so the types of exercise
I'm referring to now
are really more about brain longevity
and about keeping the brain healthy
than they are about physical fitness.
There's no reason why you
couldn't do this and also,
provided, again, it's safe for you
given your brain state and
injury state, et cetera,
there's no reason why you
couldn't also combine it
with weight training and
other forms of cardio.
I think this is really interesting
and if some of you would
like to know the mechanism
or at least the hypothesized mechanism,
there's a molecule called aquaporin-4.
It almost sounds like
the fourth in a sequel of
movies or something like that,
but aquaporin-4 is a molecule
that is related to the glial system.
Glia are the, it means glue in Latin,
are these cells in the brain,
the most numerous cells
in the brain, in fact,
that ensheathe synapses, but
they're very dynamic cells.
They're like little ambulant cells.
The microglia will run in
and will gather up debris and soak it up
and then run out after an injury.
Aquaporin-4 is mainly expressed
by the glial cell called the astrocyte.
Astro, it looks like a little star.
Incredibly interesting cells
and the thing to remember is
that the astrocytes bridge the connection
between the neurons,
the synapse, the connections between them,
and the vasculature, the blood system,
and the glymphatic system.
They sit at the interface
and they kind of,
imagine somebody on an
emergency site, car crash site,
who's directing everybody
around as to what to do.
Get that person on a
stretcher, bandage them up,
call their mother, et cetera, et cetera,
get this out of the road,
put down some flares.
The astrocytes work in that capacity
as well as doing some
things more directly.
This glymphatic system and
the glial astrocyte system
is a system that we
want chronically active
throughout the day as much as possible,
so low-level walking, Zone 2 cardio,
and then at night, during slow-wave sleep,
is then really when this
glymphatic system kicks in.
That should hopefully be
an actionable takeaway,
provided that you can do
that kind of cardio safely,
that I believe everybody should be doing
who cares about brain longevity,
not just people who are
trying to get over TBI.
Now I'd like to return a little bit
to some of the subjective
aspects of pain modulation
because I think it's so
interesting and so actionable
that everyone should know about this,
and in this case,
we can also say that
regardless of whether or not
you're experiencing
pain, acute or chronic,
what I'm about to tell you
is as close as anything is to proof,
in science, we rarely talk about proof,
we talk about evidence in
favor or against a hypothesis,
but as close as possible to proof
that our interpretation,
our subjective interpretation
of a sensory event
is immensely powerful
for dictating our experience of the event.
Here are a couple examples.
First of all,
anyone who's ever done
combat sports or martial arts
knows that it's incredible
how little a punch hurts during a fight
and it's incredible how
much it hurts after a fight.
The molecule adrenaline,
when it's liberated into our body,
truly blunts our experience of pain.
We all know the stories of people
walking miles on stumped legs,
people doing all sorts of things
that were incredible feats
that allowed them to move through
what would otherwise be pain,
and afterward they do
experience extreme pain,
but during the event oftentimes
they are not experiencing
pain and that's because of
the pain-blunting effects of adrenaline.
I'll tell you exactly how
this works in a few minutes
when we talk about acupuncture,
but norepinephrine binding
to particular receptors,
adrenaline binding to particular receptors
actually shuts down pain pathways.
People who anticipate
an injection of morphine
immediately report the
feeling of loss of pain.
Their pain starts to diminish
because they know they're
going to get pain relief
and it's a powerful effect.
All of you are probably
saying placebo effect.
Placebo effects are very real.
Placebo effects and belief
effects, as they're called,
have a profound effect on our experience
of noxious stimuli like pain
and they can also have a profound
effect on positive stimuli
and things that we're looking forward to.
One study that I think is
particularly interesting here,
it's from my colleague
at Stanford, Sean Mackey.
They did a neuroimaging study.
They subjected people to pain.
In this case, it was a heat pain.
People have very specific
thresholds to heat
at which they cannot
tolerate any more heat,
but they explored the extent to which
looking at an image of somebody,
in this case, a romantic
partner that the person loved,
would allow them to adjust
their pain response,
and it turns out it does.
If people are looking at an image
or thinking about a person that they love,
or even a thing that they
love, a pet that they love,
studies previous to the one
that Mackey and colleagues did
showed that their experience
of pain was reduced.
Their threshold for pain was higher.
They could tolerate more pain
and they reported it as not as painful,
but there's a twist there
which is it turns out
that the extent to which
love will modulate pain
has everything to do with how infatuated
and obsessed somebody is with
the object of their love.
People that report thinking
about somebody, or a pet,
for many hours of the day,
kind of having an obsessive nature,
almost like what people might call
quote, unquote, codependency.
For those of you that are listening,
I'm just providing air quotes
'cause codependency is kind
of a clinical thing now
although it's thrown
around a lot all the time.
It's sort of like gaslighting.
People talk about
gaslighting all the time now.
Gaslighting is a real thing
but then people talked about gaslighting
for many things outside
the clinical description.
If people are very obsessed with somebody,
they have a kind of obsessive
love of somebody's face,
even if the other person
doesn't know them,
which is a little weird,
that response, that
feeling of love internally
can blunt the pain experience
to a significant degree.
These are not small effects.
It's not just that love
can protect us from pain.
It's that infatuation and obsession
can protect us from pain,
and not surprisingly,
how early a relationship is,
how new a relationship is
directly correlates with
people's ability, they showed,
to use this love, this internal
representation of love,
to blunt the pain response.
For those of you that have
been with your partners
for many years and you love them very much
and you're obsessed with them, terrific.
You have a pre-installed,
well, I suppose it's not pre-installed.
You had to do the work because
relationships are work,
but you've got a installed
mechanism for blunting pain,
and again, these are not minor effects.
These are major effects
and it's all going to be
through that top-down modulation
that we talked about,
not unlike the mirror box
experiments with phantom limb
that relieve phantom pain
or some other top-down modulation,
and the opposite example was
the nail through the boot,
which is a visual image
that made the person think
it was painful when in fact
it was painful even though
there was no tissue damage.
It was all perceptual.
The pain system is really subject
to these perceptual influences,
which is remarkable because, really,
when we think about the
somatosensory system,
it has this cognitive component,
it's got this peripheral component,
but there's another component
which is the way in which our sensation,
our somatosensory system is woven in
with our autonomic nervous system,
and we're going to get to that next,
but I want to just raise the idea
that the reason that
this kind of infatuation
and obsessive love can
blunt the pain response
and increase one's threshold for pain
may have to do,
I would say almost certainly has to do,
but it hasn't been measured yet,
with dopamine release
because dopamine is
absolutely the molecule
that's liberated in our brain and body
when there's a new kind of
obsession or infatuation.
It's very distinct from
the kind of love chemicals,
if you will,
I don't even like calling
them love chemicals.
That just feels weird.
If this were text, I
would delete that line,
but from the chemicals associated
with warmth and connection,
such as serotonin and oxytocin,
which tend to be for more stable,
long-lasting relationships.
Dopamine is what dilates the pupils,
which gets people really excited.
They can't stop thinking about somebody.
The text messages are even exciting.
They write to them and they can't wait
for the text message to come back,
the dot dot dot on the screen.
The text message is excruciating.
They don't respond for two minutes
and people are getting flipped out.
I'm not here to support
that kind of whatever,
what I'm saying is that
that obsessive type of love,
which without question
is going to be associated
with the dopamine pathway,
does seem to have a
utility in the context of
reducing the unpleasantness
of physical pain,
and probably has a lot to do
with reducing the
unpleasantness of a lot of life,
like sitting in traffic, et cetera,
because when we talk about pain,
emotional pain and physical pain
start to become one in the same.
They are so closely intertwined
that the lines between them
neurally become very blurry.
What do I mean by that?
Well, if love and infatuation
can reduce pain,
presumably through the
release of dopamine,
well, then does dopamine
release itself blunt pain?
Should we be chasing dopamine release
as a way to treat chronic and acute pain?
And that's exactly what we're
going to talk about now.
Independent of love,
we're going to talk about
something quite different
which is putting needles and electricity
in different parts of the
body, so-called acupuncture.
Something that, for many people,
it's been viewed as a kind
of alternative medicine,
but now there are excellent
laboratories exploring
what's called electroacupuncture
and acupuncture.
These are big university centers.
In fact, my source for everything
I'm about to tell you next
is Professor Qiufu Ma at
Harvard Medical School
and his papers.
I stand behind the information
that I'm going to provide today,
but it's extracted largely
from the Ma lab's papers
which use very rigorous
variable-isolating experiments
to address just how does
something like acupuncture work,
and I think what you'll be interested in
and surprised to learn
is that it does work,
but sometimes it can exacerbate pain
and sometimes it can relieve pain
and it all does that through
very discrete pathways
for which we can really say,
"This neuron connects to that neuron
connects to the adrenals,"
and we can tie this all back to dopamine
because in the end it's the
chemicals and neural circuits
that are giving rise to these perceptions,
or these experiences, rather,
of things that we call
pain, love, et cetera.
In a previous podcast episode,
I mentioned my experience
of visiting an acupuncturist
and getting acupuncture.
The acupuncture itself
didn't really do that much for me,
but I wasn't there for
any specific reason.
It was gifted to me by somebody
and I wanted to try it.
I'm not passing judgment on acupuncture.
In fact, I know a number of people
that really derive tremendous
benefit from acupuncture
for pain and for gastrointestinal issues.
There are actually a lot of
really good peer-reviewed studies
supporting the use of
acupuncture for, in particular,
GI tract issues.
In recent years, there's
been an emphasis on
trying to understand the mechanism
of things like acupuncture
and acupuncture itself,
not to support acupuncture
or to try to get everybody
to do acupuncture
but as a way to try and understand
how these sorts of practices
might actually benefit people
who are experiencing pain
or for changing the nervous system
or brain-body relationship in general,
and actually,
the National Institutes of
Health in the United States
now has a entire subdivision,
an institute within the
National Institutes of Health,
which is complementary health,
and that institute is interested
in things like acupuncture
and a variety of other
practices that, I think,
10, 15 years ago people probably thought
were really alternative and
maybe even counterculture,
at least in the States, and it's exciting.
I think people are starting
to really take a look at
what's going on under the hood
for certain types of
treatments that are very useful
and I think it's very likely to lead
to an expanded number of treatments
for a number of different conditions.
What I want to talk about
in terms of acupuncture
is the incredible way in
which acupuncture illuminates
the crosstalk between
the somatosensory system,
our ability to feel stuff
externally, exteroception,
internally, interoception,
and how that somatosensory system
is wired in with and communicating
with our autonomic nervous system
that regulates our levels
of alertness or calmness.
After that, I'm going to talk about
how the acupuncture that's
being done right now
also points to relief for
what's called referred pain.
This takes us all back to the
homunculus. Let's start there.
We have this representation
of our body surface
in our brain.
That representation is
what we call somatotopic,
and what somatotopy is
is it just means that areas of your body
that are near one another,
so your thumb and your
forefinger, for instance,
are represented by neurons
that are nearby each other
in the brain.
You might say, "Well, duh,"
but actually, it didn't
have to be that way.
The neurons that represent
the tip of my forefinger
and the neurons that represent
my thumb on the same hand
could have been distantly located
and therefore the map of my
body surface, the homunculus,
would be really disordered,
but it's not that way.
It's very ordered. It's very smooth.
As, let's say you were to image my brain,
if you were to stimulate
my finger, my forefinger,
and then march that
stimulation across my finger,
across the palm and to the nearby thumb,
you would see that neurons in the brain
would also make a sort of J shape
in their pattern of activation.
That means there's so-called somatotopy,
but the connections
from those brain neurons
are sent into the body
and they are synchronized with,
meaning they cross-wire with
and form synapses with some of the input
from the viscera, from our guts,
from our diaphragm, from our stomach,
from our spleen, from our heart.
Our internal organs
are sending information
up to this map in our
brain of the body surface,
but it's about internal information,
what we call interoception,
our ability to look
inside or imagine inside
and feel what we're feeling inside.
The way to think about this accurately
is that our representation of ourself
is a representation of
our internal workings,
our viscera, our guts,
everything inside our skin,
and the surface of our skin,
and the external world, what we're seeing.
Those three things are
always being combined
in a very interesting,
complex but very seamless way.
Acupuncture involves taking needles,
and sometimes electricity
and or heat as well,
and stimulating particular
locations on the body
and through these maps of stimulation
that have been developed
over thousands of years,
mostly in Asia,
but now this is a
practice that's being done
many places throughout the world,
they have these maps that speak to,
oh, well, if you stimulate
this part of the body,
you get this response,
and if somebody has a
gastrointestinal issue,
like their guts are moving
too quick, they have diarrhea,
you stimulate this area
and it'll slow their gut motility down,
or if their gut motility is
too slow, they're constipated,
you stimulate someplace
else and it accelerates it,
and hearing about this
stuff, it sounds kind of,
to a Westerner who's not thinking about
the underlying neural circuitry,
it could sound kind of wacky.
It really sounds like alternative
or even really out there stuff,
but when you look at the neural
circuitry, the neuroanatomy,
it really starts to make sense,
and Qiufu Ma's lab at
Harvard Medical School
is an excellent laboratory,
has been exploring how
stimulation of different types,
intense or weak, with
heat or without heat,
on different parts of the body
can modulate pain and inflammation,
and what they've shown in a
particularly exciting study
is that stimulation of the abdomen,
anywhere on the midsection,
weakly does nothing.
"Well, that's not very
interesting," you might say.
Intense stimulation of
the abdomen, however,
with this electroacupuncture
has a very strong effect
of increasing inflammation in the body,
and this is important to understand
because it's not just that
stimulating the gut does this
because you're activating the gut area.
It activates a particular nerve pathway.
For the aficionados,
it's the splenic spinal sympathetic axis
if you really want to know,
and it's pro-inflammatory
under most conditions.
However, there are other
conditions where if, for instance,
the person is dealing with a
particular bacterial infection,
that can be beneficial,
and this goes back to a
much earlier discussion
that we had on a previous podcast
that we'll revisit again and again,
which is that the stress response
was designed to combat infection.
It turns out that there
are certain patterns
of stimulation on the abdomen
that can actually liberate immune cells
from our immune organs, like our spleen,
and counter infection
through the release of
things like adrenaline.
Qiufu's lab also showed
that stimulation of the feet and hands
can reduce inflammation,
and again, this was done mechanistically.
This was done by blocking certain pathways
with the appropriate control experiments.
This was done not in any
kind of subjective way.
This was also done by
measuring particular molecules,
IL-6 and cytokines
and things that are related
to the inflammation response,
and what they showed is
that the stimulation of the,
in particular, the hind
limbs at low intensity
led to increases in the
activity of this vagal pathway.
The vagus nerve being
this 10th cranial nerve
that serves the rest and
digest and parasympathetic,
in other words, calming response.
What this means is that we
are now at the front edge
of this research field that's,
it's early days still,
but it's discovering that
depending on whether or not
the stimulation is intense or mild
and depending on where the
stimulation is done on the body
you can get very different effects.
This points to the idea that
you can't say acupuncture good
or acupuncture bad.
There has to be a
systematic understanding of
what exactly the effect is
that you're trying to achieve
and the underlying basis
for this is really relevant
to the thing about adrenaline
that I said before,
that in a fight,
it's rare that you ever
feel pain when you get hit,
I've experienced that,
but later it hurts a lot.
It turns out that when you
stimulate these pathways
that activate, in
particular, the adrenals,
the adrenal gland liberates
norepinephrine and epinephrine
and the brain does as well,
it binds to what are called
the beta noradrenergic receptors.
This is really getting
down into the weeds,
but the beta noradrenergic
receptors activate the spleen
which liberates cells
that combat infection
and it's anti-inflammatory.
That's the short-term quick response.
The more intense stimulation
of the abdomen and other areas
can be pro-inflammatory
because of the ways that
they trigger certain loops
that go back to the brain and
trigger the anxiety pathways
and that place people
into a state of anxiety
that exacerbates pain.
One pathway stimulates
norepinephrine and blunts pain,
the other one doesn't.
What does all this mean?
How are we supposed to
put all of this together?
Well, there's a paper that was published
in "Nature Medicine" in 2014,
this is an excellent journal,
that describes how dopamine
can activate the vagus
peripherally in the,
not dopamine in the brain, peripherally,
and norepinephrine can
activate the vagus peripherally
and reduce inflammation,
and I'm not trying to throw
a ton of facts at you.
You'll say, "Well, what
am I supposed to do
with all this information?"
What this means is that
there are real maps of our body surface
that when stimulated
communicate with our
autonomic nervous system,
the system that controls
alertness or calmness,
and thereby releases either molecules
like norepinephrine and dopamine,
which make us more alert,
as we would be in a fight,
and blunt our response to pain
and they reduce inflammation,
but there are yet other
pathways that when stimulated
are pro-inflammatory,
and that brings us to the question of
what is all this inflammation stuff
that people are talking about?
One of the things that
bothers me so much these days,
and I'm not easily irritated,
but what really bothers me is when people
are talking about inflammation
like inflammation is bad.
Inflammation is terrific.
Inflammation is the reason
why cells are called
to the site of injury to clear it out.
Inflammation is what's going to allow you
to heal from any injury.
Chronic inflammation is bad,
but acute inflammation
is absolutely essential.
Remember those kids that
we talked about earlier
that have mutations in these
receptors for sensing pain?
They never get inflammation
and that's why their joints
literally disintegrate.
It's really horrible
because they don't actually
have the inflammation response
because it was never triggered
by the pain response.
Inflammation can be very beneficial.
There's a lot of interest nowadays
in taking things and doing
things to limit inflammation.
One of the ones that comes
up a lot is turmeric.
I'm sure the moment anyone
starts talking about
inflammation the question
is, "What about turmeric?"
I have talked before
about turmeric elsewhere.
I am very skeptical of turmeric
and I might lose a few friends,
although that'd be weird if my friend,
that would say something
about my friendships
if I lost friends over a
discussion about turmeric,
but in any case,
turmeric does have
anti-inflammatory properties,
there's no question about that,
but as we've just described,
inflammation can be a very good thing,
at least in the short term.
The other thing about turmeric is
there was a study
published out of Stanford
in collection with some
work from other universities
showing that a lot of turmeric
is heavily contaminated with lead.
The lead is used to get
that really rich, dense,
orange coloring to it
that everyone wants to see,
so you have to check
your sources of turmeric.
The other thing is, for men in particular,
turmeric can be very antagonistic
to dihydrotestosterone.
Dihydrotestosterone is
the more dominant form
of androgen in human males
and it's involved in things
like aggression and libido
and things of that sort.
Many people that I've talked
to who have have taken turmeric
get a severe blunting
of affect and libido.
For some people that might
be a serious negative.
I certainly avoid turmeric.
I don't like turmeric for that reason.
I also think that the
inflammation response
is a healthy response.
You have to keep it in check
and we're going to talk
about specific practices
for wound healing and injury in a moment,
but this idea that just
inflammation is bad
and you want to reduce
inflammation across the board,
nothing could be further from the truth.
We have pathways that exist in our body
specifically to increase inflammation.
It's the inflammation that goes
unchecked, just like stress,
which is problematic for
repair, for brain injury,
and it can exacerbate certain
forms of dementia, et cetera,
but I'd like to create
a little bit more nuance
or a lot more nuance, if possible,
in the conversation around inflammation
because people have just taken
this discussion around
inflammation to be this idea
that just inflammation is bad
and nothing could be
further from the truth.
Before I continue,
I just thought I'd answer
a question that I get a lot
which is what about Wim Hof breathing?
I get asked about this a lot.
Wim Hof, also called aka The Iceman,
has this breathing that's
similar to Tummo breathing,
as it was originally called,
involves basically hyperventilating
and then doing some exhales
and some breath holds.
A couple of things about that.
It should never be done near water.
People who have done it near water
unfortunately have drowned.
It's certainly not for everybody
and I'm not here to either promote it
nor discourage people from doing it,
but I think we should ask ourselves,
"What is the net effect of that?"
Because a number of people
have asked me about it
in relation to pain management.
The effect of doing
that kind of breathing,
it's not a mysterious effect.
It liberates adrenaline from the adrenals.
There is a paper published in
the "Proceedings of the
National Academy of Sciences,"
which is a very fine journal,
showing that that breathing pattern
can counter infection from endotoxin
and that's because when you
have adrenaline in your system
and when the spleen is very active,
that response is used to counter infection
and stress counters infection.
We'll talk about this more going forward,
but the idea that stress lends
itself to infection is false.
Stress counters infection
by liberating killer cells in the body.
You don't want the stress response
to stay on indefinitely, however.
Things like Wim Hof
breathing, like ice baths,
anything that releases adrenaline
will counter the infection,
but you want to regulate the duration
of that adrenaline response.
This should make perfect sense.
We, as a species,
had to evolve under
conditions of famine and cold.
Actually, Texas right now
is an extreme case of
cold and power outage.
I've seen the pictures and
a lot of people out there
are really suffering.
Their systems are releasing
a ton of adrenaline.
They're cold. Some of them
are likely to be hungry.
They're probably stressed.
They're releasing a lot of adrenaline
which is keeping them safe from infection.
After they get their heat
back on and they relax
and they can finally warm up again,
which we would like for them very soon,
hopefully by the time
this podcast comes out,
that will have already happened,
that's typically when people get sick
because the immune response is blunted
as the stress response starts to subside.
Stress, inflammation,
countering infection,
that comes from endotoxin,
that comes from any number of things.
It can be from cold. It can
be from hyperventilation.
It can be from a physical threat.
It can be from the stress of
an exam or an upcoming surgery.
This adrenaline thing
and the inflammation
associated with it is adaptive.
It's highly adaptive.
It is a short-term plasticity
that is designed to make us better
for what we're experiencing
and challenged with, not worse,
and so hopefully that will
add an additional layer
to this whole idea that stress is bad,
inflammation is bad, et cetera.
Again, I'm not suggesting
people do or don't do
something like Wim Hof, Tummo breathing,
I just want to point to the utility.
It's very similar to the
utility from cold showers,
ice baths and other forms of anything
that increase adrenaline.
Every episode, I want to make sure
that every listener comes away
with as much knowledge as possible
but also actionable tools,
and today we've talked
about a variety of tools,
but I want to center in on a
particular sequence of tools
that hopefully you won't need,
but presumably if you're a
human being and you're active,
you will need at some point.
It's about managing injury
and recovering and healing fast
or at least as fast as possible.
It includes removing the pain.
It includes getting mobility back
and getting back to a normal life,
whatever that means for you.
I want to emphasize that what
I'm about to talk about next
was developed in close
consultation with Kelly Starrett,
who many of you probably
have heard of before.
Kelly can be found at The Ready State.
He's a formally trained,
so degreed and educated,
exercise physiologist.
He's a world expert in movement
and tissue rehabilitation, et cetera.
They're not sponsors of the podcast.
Kelly is a friend and a colleague.
He's somebody that I personally trust
and his views on tissue
rehabilitation and injury
I think are really grounded extremely well
in both medicine, physiology,
and the real cutting edge of what's new
and what you might not
get in terms of advice
from the typical person.
All that said, you always,
always, always should consult
with your physician before
adopting any protocols
or removing any protocols.
I asked Kelly, I made it
really simple, I said,
"Okay, let's say I were to sprain my ankle
or break my arm or injure my knee
or ACL tear or something
like that or shoulder injury,
what are the absolute necessary things
to do regardless of situation
and what science is this grounded in?"
And then I made it a point
to go find the studies
that either supported or
refuted what he was telling me
because that's why I'm here.
The first one is a very basic one,
that now you have a lot
of information to act on,
which is in terms of
what we know about tissue rehabilitation,
both brain and body, we know
that sleep is essential,
and so we both agreed
that eight hours minimum
in bed per night is critical.
What was interesting, however,
is that it doesn't have to
be eight hours of sleep.
We acknowledged that some of that time
might be challenging to get to sleep,
especially if one is in
pain or mobility is limited.
We forget how often we roll over in bed
or how the conditions of our sleeping
can impact those injuries too.
Kelly acknowledged, and I agree,
that eight hours of sleep would be ideal,
but if not, at least eight hours immobile
and that speaks to the power of
these non-sleep deep rest protocols too.
If you can't sleep,
doing non-sleep deep rest protocols,
we've provided links to them before,
we're going to continue to
provide links to the previous ones
and new ones are coming soon,
that is extremely beneficial.
That's a non-negotiable
in terms of getting the
foundation for allowing
for glymphatic clearance and
tissue clearance, et cetera.
The other is, if possible,
unless it's absolutely excruciating
or you just can't do it,
a 10-minute walk per day,
of course you don't want
to exacerbate the injury,
at least a 10-minute walk
per day and probably longer.
This is where it gets interesting.
I was taught, I learned that
when you injure yourself,
you're supposed to ice something.
You're supposed to put ice on
it, but I didn't realize this,
but when speaking to
exercise physiologists
and some physicians,
they said that the ice is
really more of a placebo.
It numbs the environment of the injury,
which is not surprising,
and will eliminate the
pain for a short while,
but it has some negative effects
that perhaps offset its use.
One, it sludges,
it creates sludging within the blood
and other lymphatic tissue,
so it actually can create
some clotting and sludging
of the tissue and fluids,
the fascial interface with muscle,
and a number of the stuff
that's supposed to be
flowing through there
can slow up and increase
inflammation in the wrong way,
can actually restrict movement
out of the injury site,
which is bad because
you want the macrophages
and the other cell types
phagocytosing, eating up,
the debris in an injury
and moving it out of there
so that it can repair.
That was surprising to
me which made me ask,
"Well, then what about heat?"
Well, it turns out heat is
actually quite beneficial.
A lot of people talk
about heat shock proteins
and all these genetic
pathways and protein pathways
that can be activated by heat.
Very little data to support the idea
that heat shock proteins
are part of the wound healing process,
at least in terms of the
sorts of conventional heat
that one could use like a hot water bottle
or a hot bath or a hot compress.
The major effects seem to be explained
by heat improving the
viscosity of the tissues
and the clearance and
the perfusion of fluid,
blood, lymph and other fluids,
out of the injury area.
That's really interesting.
I didn't know this.
I thought, well, you're
supposed to ice something.
I said, well, whenever I would see
a kid get injured in soccer,
never me, of course,
no, of course I got injured
in soccer from time to time,
they give you an ice pack
and the ice pack removes some of the pain.
I think the consensus now,
which was surprising to me,
is that the ice pack is actually
more of the top-down modulation.
You think you're doing
something for the pain
and there's some interesting studies
that actually showed the
placebo effect of the ice pack,
so ice packs are placebo, perhaps.
That's interesting.
I'll underline perhaps because who knows?
Maybe there's some people out
there that are going to say
this is totally crazy
and the ice is actually very beneficial,
but it seems like heat, mobility,
sleep, keeping movement,
and it turns out that the movement itself
can act as a bit of an analgesic,
it can actually reduce the pain,
whereas the ice reduces the
pain but sludges the tissue
and keeps the cells
that need to be removed
from leaving the area.
What's also interesting
is in neuroscience we know
that if we want to kill
neurons or silence neurons,
we cool them.
This is a well-known
tool in the laboratory.
Some of the early and most
important studies in neuroscience
that formed the basis for the textbooks
were lowering a cooling probe
into a particular area of the
brain or a peripheral nerve
in order to shut down that nerve,
so the cooling will shut down the nerve,
but another very well-known
fact in neuroscience text books
is that when the activity
of the nerve pathway
or neurons comes back,
there's what's called
homeostatic plasticity,
that it rebounds with greater pain,
with a higher level of intensity,
which in the pain system
would equate to greater pain.
Regardless of where these
neurons are in the body,
if you stimulate a neuron, it's active.
If you cool it, it becomes inactive
and when the neuron heats
back up after being cooled,
it becomes hyperactive,
and so this makes really
good sense as to why heat,
provided it's not damaging levels of heat,
would be more beneficial for wound healing
and for reducing pain in
the short and long run
than would be cold or ice,
which I find very interesting.
In terms of chronic pain,
the manuscripts on this,
my discussion with Kelly and with others,
point to the fact that
chronic pain is basically
plasticity gone wrong.
It's sort of like PTSD
for the emotional system
and the stress system,
and chronic pain is going to involve
a number of different protocols
to rewire both the brain centers
and the peripheral centers
associated with chronic pain.
Certain things like
fibromyalgia, for instance,
which is whole-body pain,
relate to too little inhibition.
In the brain, you have
excitation and inhibition.
They come from different
sources of neurons.
The inhibition is mainly from GABA
and glycine and things like that.
In fibromyalgia, there's
too little central,
within the brain,
modulation of the pain responses
so that people experience whole-body pain.
In that case, the emerging
therapies are really interesting.
I have a friend who works
for the National Institutes of Health
who unfortunately
suffers from fibromyalgia
who asked me about this a lot
and his question and what
he's now actually exploring
is red light therapy.
Something that I've talked about
on various Instagram posts.
Red light therapy
typically is talked about
in terms of mitochondria
and the data on that are not so terrific,
at least not really published
in blue ribbon journals in most cases,
except for one study that I'm aware of
from Glen Jeffery's lab at
University College London
showing that red light
stimulation to the eyes
in people 40 or older
can offset some of the effects
of macular degeneration
by improving the health
of the photo receptors.
People with fibromyalgia,
which is this whole-body pain,
are now starting to use
red light therapies.
When I asked Kelly and others
and some experts in pain,
"What are your thoughts
on this red light therapy
for things like fibromyalgia and pain,
especially red light local therapy?"
Their idea, and I don't
think this is a field
that's progressed far enough now
to really place any firm conclusions on,
but the idea is that red
light therapy locally
may have some effect,
but the systemic red light therapy,
this is like wearing protection
to the eyes, in some cases,
so not for the treatment
of macular degeneration
but wearing protection of the eyes
and getting very bright red light therapy
in many ways may be, and
to use Kelly's words,
"Approximating the effects of nature."
These are like surrogate technologies
for getting outside in the sunshine.
When you're in the sun,
it might not look red,
but there are a lot of red
wavelengths coming toward you.
The red light therapies
may have some utility,
but getting into sunlight
may actually have
as much or more effect.
Of course, if these wounds
are on a part of the body
that you can't expose,
then you could imagine why
the red light therapy might be good.
I don't know, depending on
the neighborhood you live in,
that may or may not be a
weird thing to go outside
and expose your body to sunlight.
Probably a number of factors that dictate
whether or not that'd be weird or not,
but that's up to you, not me,
and it seems that,
so movement, heat, not ice,
light, sleep,
and in some cases, the use,
and I'll talk about this in a moment,
that some cases the use of restricting
above and below the injury to then release
and then increase
perfusion through the site
may actually accelerate the wound healing.
All of this might sound just
like common sense knowledge,
but to me, at least as a 45-year-old,
I always just thought it's ice,
it's non-steroid anti-inflammatory drugs,
it's things that block prostaglandins,
so things like aspirin,
ibuprofen, acetaminophen.
Those things generally
work by blocking things,
they're called the COX
prostaglandin blockers
and things of that sort,
things in that pathway.
Those sorts of treatments
which reduce inflammation
may not be so great at the beginning
when you want inflammation,
they may be important for limiting pain
so people can be functional at all,
but the things that I talked about today
really are anchored in three principles.
One is that the inflammation
response is a good one.
This is what we're learning
from Qiufu Ma's lab's
work on acupuncture.
The immediate acute
inflammation response is good.
It calls to the site of injury
things that are going to clean
up the injury and bad cells.
Then there are going to be things
that are going to improve perfusion,
like the glymphatic
system, getting deep sleep,
feet elevated, sleeping on one side,
low-level Zone 2 cardio
three times a week.
Red light, perhaps, is going to be useful
although sunlight might be just as good
depending on who you talk to,
and we can talk about that
probably more at length
in a future episode.
A number of people will ask
me, I'm sure, about stem cells
and I don't want to take more of your time
by going into an hour-long
discussion about stem cells.
Stem cells exist in all
of us during development.
We were created from stem cells,
which are cells that can
become essentially anything.
Later, cells get what's called
restricted in their lineage,
so a skin cell,
unless you do some fancy
molecular gymnastics to it,
you can't actually turn
that cell into a neuron.
Yamanaka won the Nobel Prize
for finding these Yamanaka factors
which you could give a skin
cell to turn into a neuron,
but that's not an approved
therapy at this time,
but many people ask me
about platelet-rich plasma,
so-called PRP.
They take blood, they
enrich for platelets,
and they re-inject it back into people.
Here's the deal. This
deserves an entire episode.
It has never been shown whether
or not the injection itself
is what's actually creating the effect.
This is something that
the acupuncture literature
suffered from for a long time,
that the sham control, as it's called,
sham, we don't mean it's a sham,
but in science you say a sham control
meaning you do everything
exactly the same way you would.
So for acupuncture,
you would bring the needle
right up to the skin,
but you wouldn't actually poke it
into the skin, for instance.
That would be a sham control.
With a drug treatment,
you would inject a drug into a person
and then the control, the sham control,
would be that you would
bring the injection over,
you might do the injection
or not do the injection
'cause you imagine that
the injection itself
could have an effect.
It's never really been
shown whether or not PRP
has effects that are separate
from injecting a volume
of fluid into a tissue.
The claims that PRP
actually contains stem cells
are very, very feeble,
and when you look at the literature
and you talk to anyone expert
in the stem cell field,
they will tell you that it's,
the number of stem cells in
PRP is infinitesimally small.
In fact, so much so that these places
that inject PRP for injuries
are not allowed to advertise
through the use of the words stem cells.
It's actually illegal at this point,
at least as far as I know.
It was through the end of last year
and I'm guessing it still is now.
Stem cells are an exciting
area of technology.
However, there's a clinic down in Florida
that was shut down a couple of years ago
for injecting stem cells
harvested from patients
into the eye for macular degeneration.
These were people that were
suffering from poor vision
and very shortly after injecting
the stem cells into the eyes,
they went completely blind.
I'm somebody who is very skeptical
of the stem cell treatment
work that's out there.
It's actually very hard to get
in the United States for this reason.
It's not approved. The PRP
treatments are very complicated.
The marketing around them is
shaky at best.
I'm sure a number of people
will say that they had PRP
and benefited from it tremendously
and I don't doubt that.
Whether or not it was placebo,
today we talked a lot
about top-down control,
that's just a variant on the
word placebo, belief effects,
whether or not it was
placebo or not, I don't know.
I wasn't there.
That's for you to decide
and I'm not here to tell you
that you should or shouldn't do something,
but I do think that anything
involving stem cells,
one should be very cautious of.
You should also be very cautious
of anyone that tells you
that PRP is injecting a lot of stem cells.
This is an evolving area that really needs
a lot more work and attention.
The major issue with stem cells
that I think is concerning
is that stem cells are cells
that want to become lots
of different things,
not just the tissue that
you're interested in.
If you damage your knee
and you inject stem cells into your knee,
you need to molecularly
restrict those stem cells
so that they don't become tumor cells.
A tumor is a collection of stem cells.
When you get something horrible
like glioblastoma in the brain,
which is a terrible thing to have,
it's glial cells that returned
to stemness, excessive stemness,
they've started to produce
too many of themselves,
and glioblastoma is
often deadly, not always.
Injecting stem cells, it sounds great,
and it sounds like something
that one would want to do,
but one needs to approach
this with extreme caution,
even if it's your own blood
or stem cells that you're re-injecting.
I think those technologies are
coming. They're on the way.
If any of you are devotees of PRP,
tell me your experiences with them.
I'm curious. I want to see the papers.
I want to know the evidence,
and of course, there are always
folks out there that say,
"I don't care what the scientists
and the physicians and the FDA say.
I just want to do this,"
and if that's your stance,
that's your stance.
I'm not here to govern that,
but I do think that
people should be informed,
and in thinking about
tissue recovery and injury,
that's what I was able to glean.
Again, check out what Kelly
and his coworkers are
doing at The Ready State.
It's phenomenal and they've
worked with all the top people
in just about every
domain of life, it seems.
Very high-integrity folks.
Some of you are probably
saying, "Well, I'm not injured.
I'm not an athlete. I don't
want stem cell injections.
I don't have," again,
I'm saying you shouldn't get
stem cell injections for now.
Please hold off until
the field learns more
about how to do that safely,
but I want to talk about
and end with a really interesting
and somewhat weird technology,
which is baby blood.
I have a colleague at Stanford,
his name is Tony Wyss-Coray,
and in 2014 his laboratory
published a study
showing that the blood of young rodents,
mice and rats,
when transfused into
old, demented rodents,
mice and rats,
made those old, demented rodents
recover much of their
memory and seem much more
vital and energetic,
better recall of different
spatial learning tasks.
Tissue and wound healing,
they've since shown,
can be improved in these older animals.
It's pretty incredible.
They went on to show several years later
that blood from umbilical cords,
I'm not making this up,
blood from umbilical cords can do the same
and this is the basis
of a biotech company.
Actually, one of my former postdocs
is now an employee there.
They've isolated the
molecules from young blood
that seems to vitalize
or revitalize the old brain and body,
and one of those molecules
goes by the name TIMP2.
T-I-M-P-2.
Where's all this going?
Well, I don't know how
long it's going to be
before there are treatments based on
these blood transfusions.
I doubt that blood transfusions themselves
from young people into old people
is going to be used for
the treatment of dementia,
although it might, as weird as it seems.
We know that transfusions
of all sorts of stuff,
for instance, fecal transplants
are being used to treat obesity.
The gut microbiome of
thin people is being,
not transfused, but is being transplanted
into the colons and guts of obese people
and leading to weight loss,
which sounds really wild
and is not a topic I
particularly enjoy talking about,
but nonetheless, it
points to the importance
of the gut microbiome in regulating things
like blood sugar and health
as it relates to obesity and diabetes
and all sorts of things.
It does appear that there are things,
factors in the blood of young members
of a given species that are lost over time
in the older members of that species.
I'm not going to give you a tool
on the basis of these findings today.
I am not going to tell
you to consume any fluid
from any other member of your species,
our species, for any reason,
but I do think that it's
important to mention
that the science is asking questions
such as what are the
factors within the brain
that allow the young brain
to recover so much better
than the older brain from injury,
from all sorts of things,
events, et cetera,
and what are the factors
in the older brain
that are limiting,
and thinking about
identifying which factors
are going to allow people to
restore cognitive function,
physical function, wound
healing and so forth.
It's a really exciting area.
I mention it not to be sensationalist
but because it's happening
and because there's a lot
of excitement about it
and because I think it's clear
that the young brain and body and blood
are very different from the
old brain, body and blood,
and the goal of science is to identify
and isolate those factors
that make that so,
such that people who would
otherwise get dementia
or perhaps even have dementia
will be allowed to recover.
Again, not an actionable
item at this point,
but one to think about,
perhaps not too long,
but one to think about.
I'm going to close there.
I've talked about a lot of tools today.
I've talked a lot about somatosensation,
about plasticity, about
pain, about acupuncture,
some of the nuance of acupuncture,
inflammation and stress.
We even talked a little bit
about high-intensity breathing,
talked about restricting limb movement
to get compensatory regrowth of pathways,
or I should say reactivation of pathways
that have been injured or damaged.
As always,
we take a whirlwind tour
through a given topic,
lay down some tools as we go.
Hopefully the principles that
relate to pain and injury
but also neuroplasticity in general,
today in the context of
the somatosensory system,
will be of use to all of you.
I don't wish injury on any of you,
but I do hope that you'll
take this information to mind
and that you will think about it
if ever you find yourself in a situation
where you have to ask
what's the difference
between my perception
and the actual tissue damage?
Is injury and pain, is it the same?
Well, no.
Do I have some control
over my experience of pain?
Absolutely.
Does all of that involve taking drugs
or doing certain therapeutics?
No, not necessarily.
There's the incredible
subjective component.
There also is a need sometimes
to treat the injury at the
level of the pain receptors
at the site of the wound,
so please take the information,
do with it what you will,
and in the meantime,
thank you so much for
your time and attention.
Before we go, I just want to remind you
to please subscribe to
the YouTube channel,
Apple and or Spotify.
Leave us comments and feedback.
Five star review on Apple if
you think we deserve that.
Please check out our sponsors.
Check out our Patreon,
patreon.com/andrewhuberman,
and as well,
if you're interested in
the supplements that I take
and you want to try any of those,
you can go to Thorne,
thorne.com/u/huberman
and you'll get 20% off any of
the supplements listed there
as well as any others on the Thorne site.
Once again,
thanks so much for your
time and attention today,
and as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[relaxing rock music]