- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
My name is Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring you zero cost
to consumer information
about science and science-related tools.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Headspace.
Headspace is a meditation app
that makes meditation easy.
I've been meditating on and
off now for about 30 years,
although I confess more off than on.
And that's because I think
like, for a lot of people,
sticking to a meditation practice
can be pretty challenging.
I started using Headspace a few years ago
and I found that it's really allowed me to
stick to a meditation
practice on a regular basis.
I meditate anywhere from
five to seven times a week.
The app includes meditations
that are all backed by
scientific peer-reviewed studies.
And it makes it really easy to start
and complete the meditations.
I started using these
meditations while I was flying
a few years back.
On JetBlue flights,
they started offering
Headspace meditations.
That's where I initially started.
And then I moved over to the app,
and I really enjoy it and I
derive great benefit from it.
If you'd like to try Headspace,
you can go to headspace.com/specialoffer.
And if you do that,
you'll get all the meditations
that Headspace offers
for free for one month.
That's headspace.com/specialoffer.
You get all the meditations for free,
which is the best offer that
they has available right now.
So if you're interested
in it, check it out.
The second sponsor of today's
podcast is Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an
all-in-one vitamin mineral
probiotic drink.
I started using Athletic Greens in 2012,
and I've been using it
continuously ever since.
I started using Athletic Greens because
I found it rather dizzying to know
which vitamins and minerals to take.
And Athletic Greens allows me to get
the full base of all the
necessary vitamins and minerals
in one easy to consume drink.
It also turns out that the
drink tastes quite good.
I mix mine with some lemon
juice and some water,
I drink it once or twice a day.
The probiotics in Athletic
Greens are also important to me
because there are a lot
of data now supporting
the fact that the gut microbiome
is important for the gut-brain axis
for various aspects of cognitive function,
immune function, metabolic function.
There's just a huge number of things
that having a healthy gut microbiome
has been shown to be important for.
So by taking Athletic Greens,
I have that base covered as well.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman.
And if you do that,
they'll give you a year supply
of liquid vitamin D3 K2.
There are also a lot of data
now showing that vitamin D3
is very important for
a number of different
biological functions.
In addition, they'll give
you five free travel packs
with your order.
It can be difficult to mix
up powders while on the road,
when in a car, or in a hotel,
or on a plane, et cetera.
The travel packs make everything
really clean and easy.
So you'll get the year
supply of vitamin D3 K2
plus the five free travel packs
if you go to athleticgreens.com/huberman.
The third sponsor of
today's podcast is Madefor.
Madefor is behavioral science company
that makes learning positive
habits and growth mindset easy.
I've been involved with
Madefor since the beginning
as the lead of their scientific advisory.
Other members of the
scientific advisory include,
for instance, the head
of the chronobiology unit
at the National Institutes
of Mental Health,
as well as psychiatrists
from Harvard Medical School
and elsewhere, all of whom
are serious about science
and science-related tools
for developing positive
habits and growth mindset.
The program is a 10 month-program,
during which each month you
engage in a specific activity
designed to encourage and cultivate
positive habits and growth mindset.
As well, we hold a monthly Zoom call,
during which we discuss the
program, people's progress,
and answer any questions
they have directly.
If you'd like to try Madefor,
you can go to getmadefor.com,
and if you put Huberman in at checkout,
you'll get 20% off the program.
That's getmadefor.com,
put Huberman in at checkout,
and get 20% off the program.
Today, we're going to talk about
how to change your nervous
system for the better.
As you recall, your nervous
system includes your brain
and your spinal cord,
but also all the connections
that your brain and spinal cord
make with the organs of your body
and all the connections
that the organs of your body
make with your brain and spinal cord.
This thing that we call the
nervous system is responsible
for everything we know,
all our behavior, all our emotions,
everything we feel about
ourselves and the outside world,
everything we think and believe.
It's really at the center of
our entire experience of life
and who we are.
Fortunately, in humans,
unlike in other species,
we can change our nervous system
by taking some very specific
and deliberate actions.
And, today, we're really
going to focus on the actions,
the motor commands and the
aspects of movement and balance
that allow us to change
our nervous system.
It turns out that movement and balance
actually provide windows or portals
into our ability to
change our nervous system
the way we want,
even if those changes are not about
learning new movements or
learning how to balance.
And soon you'll understand why.
So, today, we're going to talk a lot about
the basic science of neuroplasticity.
I promise to not use
excessive nomenclature.
There'll be a little bit,
but I'll try and make
it as clear as possible.
And we're also going to talk a
lot about protocols and tools
that the scientific literature points to
and support for changing
our nervous system,
again, not just for sake of
learning new motor movements
or how to balance better,
but for how to feel differently
about particular experiences,
both past, present, and future,
and as well as how to learn faster.
We're not going to discuss
hacks, a word I loath,
we're not going to discuss gimmicks,
we're going to discuss
mechanism and scientific data
and the tools that those mechanisms
and scientific data point to
so that you can tailor your
practices around learning
to your specific needs and goals.
So let's begin by just examining
the big picture question which is,
does the brain control behavior?
And my hope is that everyone
is immediately thinking yes.
The brain and nervous
system, we really should say,
'cause the brain is just one component
of the nervous system,
controls our behavior.
How does it do that?
Well, there are a couple different
levels that it does that.
First of all, if we're
talking about movement,
behavior generally means movement,
if we're talking about movement,
we have two categories of neurons
that are very important to think about
in the context of neuroplasticity.
First of all, we have what are
called lower motor neurons.
These are motor neurons that
live in our spinal cord.
For the aficionados out there,
for those of you that might
be headed to medical school
or just want to learn
more about the anatomy,
they live in the ventral
horn of the spinal cord.
But that doesn't matter if
you don't want to know that,
just know that you have
these things called
lower motor neurons.
These are neurons that
are in the spinal cord
but they extend a wire
that we call an axon
out into the peripheral
nervous system, into the body.
And those neurons connect with muscle.
They send electrical potentials out there
that allow our muscles
to twitch into contract.
As a little point of fact, actually,
we don't have muscle memory.
There's no such thing as muscle memory.
Muscles are dumb.
They don't know anything,
they don't have a history,
they don't have a memory,
they don't know anything.
It is the neurons that
control those muscles
and their firing patterns
in which all the information
for motor patterns are stored.
So your ability to walk
is not muscle memory,
it's neural memory.
Now, the lower motor neurons,
while smarter than the muscle so to speak,
are not the most brilliant
of the motor neurons.
They are generally involved
in doing what they are told,
and they are told what
to do from two sources.
We have circuits in our brainstem,
so this would be kind of around
your neck deep in the brain,
that are called central
pattern generators.
These are sometimes called CPGs.
Central pattern generators
are what allow us to generate
repetitive patterns of movement.
So inhaling and exhaling,
inhaling and exhaling
subconsciously is controlled
by a central pattern generator.
That just means a collection of neurons.
If you really want to know,
they're called the pre-Botzinger neurons
discovered by Jack Feldman
and colleagues at UCLA.
These neurons in the brainstem
send information down the phrenic nerve
and control the diaphragm.
And it goes inhale,
exhale, inhale, exhale.
And you don't have to think about that.
You could think about it
and you could change the
durations of inhales and exhales
and change that up,
but the motor neurons that control that
are just responding to what
the brain is telling it to do.
The other central pattern
generators include
things like walking.
The right limb-left limb, right
limb-left limb pattern that
we normally associate with walking
was learned during childhood,
and these central pattern
generators, sometimes called CPGs,
tell our lower motor neurons, "Fire.
Now you fire, now you fire."
So they are literally saying,
"Right, left, right left."
They are the marching
orders from the brainstem
to the lower motor neurons.
So these lower motor neurons
do what they are told.
They are obedient little soldiers
and they do what they are told,
and their job is to make
the muscles contract
at specific times.
Okay.
That's all simple.
But then there are the
upper motor neurons.
The upper motor neurons actually
reside in our motor cortex,
way up on top of the brain.
And they are involved in sending signals
for deliberate action.
So they send signals to
the lower motor neurons
which are the effectors,
the ones that actually
control the muscles,
but the upper motor neurons are the ones
that send very specific signals.
For instance, the signals
that would allow you
to make a cup of coffee in the morning
or to deliberately engage
in any kind of behavior.
Now, you can probably make a
cup of coffee in the morning
without having to think about it too much.
It's almost reflexive for you now,
which means that a lot of the information
about how to perform
that particular movement
has been passed off to
circuitry that's now
more or less in the brainstem
and below the motor cortex.
Now, why am I giving you all this detail?
Well, if you want to
change motor patterns,
you have to know where in the
circuitry changes are possible
and you ought to know where the changes
are most likely to occur.
You also need to know, how
do you signal to the brain
and nervous system that
a change is necessary?
So let's just pause there,
return to the initial
question that we started with,
which is, does the brain control behavior?
And the answer is yes,
and now you know how.
It's upper motor neurons,
lower motor neurons,
you've got these things called
central pattern generators
and some connection with the muscle.
So there you go, you just got,
basically, what was the equivalent of
the introduction to a college lecture
on motor control and the nervous system.
But the point today is
all about plasticity.
How can that be leveraged
in order to open up
this magical thing that we call plasticity
in order to access changes
to our emotional experience,
or to our belief system,
or to our ability to remember
and use specific kinds of information
for say math, or language, et cetera?
Well, what I'm not going
to tell you is that
you need to go running
or you need to go biking,
or that simply going
through motor patterns
is going to open up plasticity because
I hate to tell you this, but
as beneficial as exercise is,
it does not open plasticity
unless you do certain things.
And I will tell you exactly
what those certain things are today.
To be clear, I think exercise
is wonderful and healthy,
can improve cardiovascular function,
maintain strength, bone
density, all that good stuff.
But just working out or doing
your exercise of various kinds
will not change your nervous system.
It will maintain it,
and it can certainly improve
other health metrics,
but it is not going to open
up the window for plasticity.
The question we need to ask
is can behavior change the brain?
We already agree that the
brain can change behavior,
but can behavior change the brain?
And the answer is yes,
provided that behavior is
different enough in specific ways
from the behaviors that you
already know how to perform.
Let me repeat that.
Can behavior change the brain?
And the answer is yes,
provided that behavior is different enough
from the sorts of behaviors
that you already know how to perform.
And I should've added the word well.
Because you can't obviously
perform a behavior
that you don't know how to perform
because you don't know how to do it yet.
But there's a key element
to accessing neuroplasticity
that frankly I don't see out there
in the general discussion
about neuroplasticity.
In the general discussion
about neuroplasticity
and about learning, I hear
all these gimmicks about using
different ways to remember
lots of people's names
and arranging things
into their first letters
and mnemonics and all this kind of stuff,
which, frankly, to me
feels really gimmicky.
I think that if you
look at super learners,
they tend to be people that have a process
of say extreme memory.
But people who have
extreme memory, generally,
the literature shows us, are
pretty poor at other things.
I don't think most of us are
interested in walking around
knowing how to remember everything.
In fact, there are some
interesting studies
looking at humans who over-remember,
and they suffer tremendously
because they remember all sorts of things,
like the number at the top of the receipt
at the bodega that they bought
a Coca-Cola 10 years ago.
This is useless information
for most people.
They don't do well in life, really.
So the goal isn't to remember everything,
the goal is to be selective
about your brain changes.
And when we talk about brain changes,
I want to highlight adaptive changes.
There's a whole category of
things that we're going to discuss
when we talk about traumatic
brain injury and dementia,
a topic for a future episode,
about all the things that happen when you
have damaged your nervous system
or you're missing neurons.
But, today, I really want to talk about
something that I think
is very near and dear
to many of your hearts, which is
what are the behaviors
that you can engage in
to access neuroplasticity
so that then you can apply that plasticity
to the specific things that
you want to learn or unlearn.
This is very important
because I don't want people to
get the impression that
we're really talking about
learning a bunch of motor movements.
You may be an athlete, you
might not be an athlete.
You might want to learn how
to dance, you might not.
You might want to learn how to dance
and get better at remembering
and learning languages, for instance,
or at unlearning some
difficult emotional experience,
meaning you want to
remove the emotional load
from a particular memory of an experience.
What we're talking about today
is using behavior as a gate
to enter states of mind and body
that allow you to access plasticity.
So let's talk about the
different kinds of plasticity
that are available to us.
Because those will point directly
towards the type of protocols
that we should engage in
to change ourselves for the better,
the so-called adaptive plasticity.
There is something called
representational plasticity.
Representational plasticity is just your
internal representation
of the outside world.
So you have a map of auditory
space, believe it or not,
meaning you have neurons that respond
when something over on my right happens,
like I'm [snaps fingers]
snapping my fingers
over to my right.
I can't snap as well on my left,
which is the whole thing unto itself.
[snaps fingers]
Yeah, weak over there on the left side.
But when I do that,
there are different
neurons respond to those.
We have a map of visual space.
Certain neurons are seeing things
in certain portions of
visual space and not others.
We have a map of motor space,
meaning when we move our limbs
in particular directions,
we know where those limbs are
because even if we can't see them,
we have what's called
proprioceptive feedback.
So we have knowledge
about where our limbs are.
In fact, people that lack certain neurons
for proprioceptive feedback,
they are very poor at
controlling their motor behavior.
They get injured a lot.
It's actually a terrible situation.
So we've got all these
representations inside
and we have maps of our motor commands.
We know that, for instance,
if I want to reach out
and grab the pen in front of me,
that I need to generate a
certain amount of force.
So I rarely overshoot,
I rarely miss the pen.
Our maps of the motor world
and our maps of the
sensory world are merged.
The way to create plasticity
is to create mismatches or
errors in how we perform things.
And this I think is an amazing
and important feature of neuroplasticity
that is highly underappreciated.
The way to create plasticity
is to send signals to the
brain that something is wrong,
something is different, and
something isn't being achieved.
I think this will completely reframe
the way that most people
think about plasticity.
Most of us think about plasticity as,
"Okay, we're going to get into this
optimal learning state or flow,
and then suddenly we're going to be able
to do all the things that
we wish that we could do."
Well, I hate to break it to you, but flow
is an expression of what
we already know how to do.
It is not a state for learning.
And I'm willing to go to bat with any of
the flo-wa-nis-tas out there
that want to challenge me on that one.
Flow is an expression of
nervous system capabilities
that are already embedded in us.
Errors and making errors
out of sync with what we would like to do
is how our nervous system is cued
through very distinct
biological mechanisms
that something isn't going right.
And, therefore, certain
neurochemicals are deployed
that signal the neural circuits
that they have to change.
So let's talk about the experiments
that support what I just said.
'Cause I'm about to tell
you that making errors
over and over and over again
is the route to shaping
your nervous system
so that it performs better
and better and better.
And I'm not going to tell you
that the last rep of a set
where you hit failure in the gym
is anything like neuroplasticity.
You hear that too that it's
pushing to that point of a cliff
where you just can't function anymore,
that's the signal.
That's not the signal.
That's a distinct neuromuscular phenomenon
that bears zero resemblance
to what it takes to get neuroplasticity.
So let's talk about
errors and making errors
and why and how that triggers
the release of chemicals
that then allow us to not just
learn the thing that we're
doing in the motor sense,
play the piano, dance, et cetera,
but it also creates an environment,
a milieu within the brain,
that allows us to then go
learn how to couple or uncouple
a particular emotion to an experience,
or better language learning,
or better mathematical learning.
It's a really fundamental
aspect of how we're built.
And when you look at it, it's
actually very straightforward.
It's a series of logical steps
that once you learn how
to open those hatches,
it becomes very straightforward to deploy.
Last episode, we discussed
some of the basic principles
of neuroplasticity.
If you didn't hear that episode,
no problem, I'll just review it quickly,
which is that it's a falsehood
that everything that we do and
experience changes our brain.
The brain changes when
certain neurochemicals,
namely acetylcholine,
epinephrin, and dopamine,
are released in ways and
in the specific times
that allow for neural circuits
to be marked for change.
And then the change
occurs later during sleep.
I'll review that later, but, basically,
you need a certain cocktail of chemicals
released in the brain in order
for a particular behavior
to reshape the way that our brain works.
So the question really is
what allows those
neurochemicals to be released?
And last episode, I
talked all about focus.
If you haven't seen it
or heard that episode,
you might want to check it out,
about some specific tools and practices
that can allow you to build
up your capacity for focus
and release certain
chemicals in that cocktail.
But, today, we're going to talk about
the other chemicals in the
cocktail, in particular dopamine.
And we're really going to
center our discussion around
this issue of making errors
and why making errors
is actually the signal
that tells the brain,
"Okay, it's time to change,"
or, more generally, it's time
to pay attention to things
so that you change.
And I really want to distinguish
this point really clearly,
which is that I'm going
to talk today a lot about
motor and vestibular,
meaning balance programs,
but not just for learning
motor commands and balance,
not just for learning new
motor skills and balance,
but also for setting a stage
or a kind of condition in your brain
where you can go learn
other things as well.
Let's talk about some classic experiments
that really nail down
what's most important in this
discussion about plasticity.
As I mentioned last episode,
and I'll just tell you right now again,
the brain is incredibly plastic
from about birth until about age 25.
Passive experience will shape the brain
just because of the way that the chemicals
that are sloshing around in there
and the way that the neurons are arranged
and all sorts of things.
The brain's job is to customize itself
in response to its experience.
And then somewhere about 25,
it's not like the day
after your 26th birthday,
plasticity closes,
there's a kind of tapering
off of plasticity,
and you need different
mechanisms to engage plasticity
as an adult.
We're mostly going to be talking
about adult plasticity today,
but I got a lot of questions about,
"Well, what about if I'm younger than 25?"
First of all, that's great.
I wish I had a time machine, but I don't.
Because as I've said before,
the stinger is when you're young,
your brain is very plastic,
but you have less control
over your experience.
When you're older, generally,
you have more control of your experience,
but your brain is less plastic.
So if you're already asking the question
as a 20-year-old or a
15-year-old, "What can I do now
that's really going to enhanced my brain?"
I guess the simple
answer would be an aside,
which would be get the broadest
education you can possible.
That means math, chemistry,
physics, literature, music,
learn how to play an instrument.
I'm saying that 'cause
I wish I had, et cetera.
Get a broad training in a number of things
and find the thing that really
captures your passion and excitement,
and then put a ton of
additional effort there.
That's what I recommend,
including emotional development.
Maybe a topic for a future episode.
But if you are an adult,
or if you are a young person,
knowing how to tap into
these plasticity mechanisms
is very powerful.
You need these chemicals
deployed in the nervous system
in order to mark whatever nerve cells
happen to be firing in the
time afterward for change.
And people are obsessed with asking,
"What supplements, what
drugs, what conditions,
what machines will allow for that?"
But there's a natural set of
conditions that allow for that.
When we came into this world,
we learned to take our
different maps of experience,
our motor maps, our auditory
maps, our visual maps.
And to link them, we align those maps.
The simplest example is
the one I gave before.
If I hear something off to my
right, like I click like that,
it could come from my fingers snapping
or it could come from something
generated by somebody else or
something else to my right,
I look to my right.
If I hear it on the
left, I look to my left.
If I hear it right in front of me,
I keep looking right in front of me.
And if I hear it behind me, I turn around.
And that's because our
maps of visual space
and our maps of auditory space
and our maps of motor space
are aligned to one another
in perfect register.
It's an incredible feature
of our nervous system.
It takes place in a structure
called the superior colliculus,
although you don't need to know that name.
Superior colliculus has layers,
literally stacks of
neurons like in a sandwich
where the zero point right in front of me,
or maybe 10 or 15 degrees off to my right
or 10 or 15 degrees off to my left,
are aligned so that the auditory neurons,
the ones that care about sounds,
at 15 degrees to my right,
sit directly below the neurons
that look at 15 degrees to
my right in my visual system.
And when I reach over to this direction,
there's a signal that's sent
down through those layers
that says 15 degrees off to the right
is the direction to look,
it's the direction to listen,
and it's the direction to
move if I need to move.
So there's an alignment.
And this is really powerful.
And this is what allows
us to move through space
and function in our lives
in a really fluid way.
It's set up during development.
But there have been some
important experiments
that have revealed that
these maps are plastic,
meaning they can shift, they're
subject to neuroplasticity.
And there are specific rules
that allow us to shift them.
So here's the key experiment.
The key experiment was
done by a colleague of mine
who's now retired but whose
work is absolutely fundamental
in the field of
neuroplasticity, Eric Knudsen.
The Knudsen Lab,
and many of the Knudsen
Lab scientific offspring,
showed that if one is
to wear prism glasses
that shift the visual field,
that eventually there'll be a shift
in the representation of
the auditory motor maps too.
Now, what they initially did is
they looked at young subjects,
and what they did is they
moved the visual world
by making them wear prism glasses.
So that, for instance, if
my pen is out in front of me
at five degrees off center,
so just a little bit off center,
if you're listening to
this, this would be like
just a little bit to my right,
but in these prism glasses,
I actually see that pen
way over far on my right.
So it's actually here,
but I see it over there
because I'm wearing prisms on my eyes.
What happens is in the first day or so,
you ask people or you ask
animal subjects or whatever
to reach for this object,
and they reach to the wrong place
because they're seeing it where it isn't.
This gets especially complicated
when you start including sounds.
When you have a thing off to
your right making a sound,
but the thing is actually right here.
So you're hearing the
sound at one location
and you're seeing the
object at another location
because you're wearing these prisms.
So your image of the world
is totally distorted.
Or, in experiments done by other groups,
they wear glasses,
subjects wore glasses
that completely invert
the visual world so that
everything is upside down,
which is an extreme example
of these representational maps
being flipped or shifted.
But what you find is that
in young individuals,
within a day or two,
they start adjusting their motor behavior
in exactly the right way
so that they always reach
to the correct location.
So they hear a sound at one location,
they see the object that
ought to make that sound
at a different location,
and they somehow are able to
adjust their motor behavior
to reach to the correct location.
It's incredible.
It's absolutely incredible.
Or, in the case of the people
who would look at the world upside down,
they somehow are able to
navigate this upside down world
even though we're completely used to
our feet being on the floor
and not on the ceiling
and people not walking at us
by hanging off the ceiling like bats.
Amazing.
And what it tells us is that these maps
that are aligned to one another
can move and shift and rotate,
and even flip themselves.
And it happens best in young individuals.
If you do this in older individuals,
in most cases, it takes a very long time
for the maps to shift,
and in some cases they never shift.
So this is a very experimental scenario,
but it's an important one to understand
because it really tamps down the fact
that we have the capacity
to create dramatic shifts
in our representation
of the outside world.
So how can we get plasticity as adults
that mimics the plasticity
that we get when we are juveniles?
Well, the Knudsen Lab and
other labs have looked at this,
and it's really interesting.
First of all, we have to ask,
what is the signal for plasticity?
Is it just having prism glasses on?
No, because they did that
experiment and ruled that out.
Is it just the fact that the visual thing
appears to be far over to my right
when in fact it's right in front of me?
No.
The signal that generates the plasticity
is the making of errors.
It's the reaches and failures
that signal to the nervous system
that this is not working.
And, therefore, the shifts
start to take place.
And this is so fundamentally important
because I think most people think,
"Oh, well, practice is going to be
I have to access beginner's mind,"
which is a great concept, actually,
it's about approaching things
expecting to make errors,
which is great.
I think I am a believer
in beginner's mind.
But people understandably get frustrated,
like they're trying to
learn a piece on the piano
and they can't do it,
or they're trying to
write a piece of code,
or they're trying to access
some sort of motor behavior,
and they can't do it,
and the frustration drives them crazy,
[indistinct] "I can't
do it, I can't do it,"
when they don't realize that
[laughs] the errors themselves
are signaling to the
brain and nervous system,
"Something's not working."
And of course the brain doesn't understand
the words something isn't working.
The brain doesn't even
understand frustration
as an emotional state.
The brain understands the
neurochemicals that are released,
namely epinephrine and acetylcholine,
but also, and we'll get into this,
the molecule dopamine
when we start to approximate
the correct behavior
just a little bit,
and we start getting a little bit right.
So what happens is when we make errors,
the nervous system kind of,
I don't want to say freaks
out because it's a very
mechanistic and controlled situation,
but the nervous system starts
releasing neurotransmitters
and neuromodulators
that say, "We better change
something in the circuitry."
And so errors are the basis [laughs]
for neuroplasticity and for learning.
And I wish that this was
more prominent out there.
I guess this is why I'm saying it.
And humans do not like
this feeling of frustration
and making errors.
The few that do do exceedingly
well in whatever pursuits
they happen to be involved in.
The ones that don't,
generally don't do well.
They generally don't learn much.
And if you think about it,
why would your nervous system ever change?
Why would it ever change?
Unless there was
something to be afraid of,
something that made us feel awful
will signal that the nervous
system needs to change,
or there's an error in our performance.
So it turns out that the
feedback of these errors,
the reaching to the wrong location
starts to release a number of things.
And now you've heard
about them many times,
but this would be epinephrin.
It increases alertness,
acetylcholine, focus.
And this is why frustration
that leads us to just kind of quit
and walk away from the endeavor
is the absolute worst thing.
Because if acetylcholine is released,
it creates an opportunity to
focus on the error margin,
the distance between what
it is that you're doing
and what it is that you would like to do.
And then the nervous system starts to
make changes almost immediately
in order to try and
get the behavior right.
And when you start getting
it even a little bit right,
that third molecule comes
online or is released,
which is dopamine,
which allows for the plastic
changes to occur very fast.
Now, this is what all
happens very naturally
in young brains.
But in old brains, it
tends to be pretty slow,
except for in two conditions.
So let me just pause and just say this,
if you are uncomfortable making errors
and you get frustrated easily,
if you leverage that frustration
toward drilling deeper into the endeavor,
you are setting yourself up for a terrific
set of plasticity mechanisms to engage.
But if you take that frustration
and you walk away from the endeavor,
you are essentially setting up plasticity
to rewire you according to
what happens afterwards,
which is generally
feeling pretty miserable.
So now you can kind of start to appreciate
why it is that continuing
to drill into a process
to the point of frustration
but then staying with that
process for a little bit longer,
and I'll define exactly
what I mean by a little bit,
is the most important
thing for adult learning
as well as childhood learning,
but adult learning in particular.
Now, the Knudsen Lab did two
very important sets of experiments.
The first one was published in "Nature,'
very important study,
which showed that juveniles
can make these massive shifts
in their map representations,
meaning you can shift the visual world
using visual prisms a huge
amount and very quickly.
Young individuals can
shift their representations of the world
so that they learn to reach
to the correct location.
They get a lot of plasticity all at once,
and it happens very fast in a
period of just a couple days.
In adults, it tends to be very slow
and most individuals
never actually accomplish
the full map shift.
They don't get the plasticity.
Here we're talking about map shifts,
but this could be learning a new language,
this could be any number
of different things
that [indistinct] we're attempting.
So what we're saying is
what I already said before,
which is that we learn
very well as youngsters,
but not as adults after 25.
But then what they did
is they started making the
increment of change smaller.
So instead of shifting
the world a huge amount
by putting prisms that
shifted that the visual world
all the way over to the right,
they did this incrementally.
So, first, they put on prisms
that shifted it just a little bit,
just like seven degrees I
believe was the exact number.
And then it was 14 degrees,
and then it was 28 degrees.
And so what they found was
that the adult nervous system
can tolerate smaller and
smaller errors over time,
but that you can stack those errors
so that you can get a lot of plasticity.
Put simply, incremental
learning as an adult
is absolutely essential.
You are not going to get massive shifts
in your representation
to the outside world.
So how do you make small errors
as opposed to big errors?
Well, the key is smaller
bouts of focused learning
for smaller bits of information.
It's a mistake to try and
learn a lot of information
in one learning about as an adult.
What these papers from
the Knudsen Lab show,
and what others have gone on to show,
is that the adult nervous
system is fully capable of
engaging in a huge amount of plasticity,
but you need to do it
in smaller increments
per learning epoch or
per learning episode.
So how would you do this?
Well, say for instance, I'm
terrible at free throws,
so let's say I wanted
to learn free throws.
I'm 45 years old, so I'm well
past the 25 and under mark.
I'm going to make errors.
I'm going to make a lot errors.
If I go into learning free throws
knowing that errors are
the gate to plasticity,
well, then I feel a little bit better,
but I still have to aim for
the rim of the basket or the net.
Basically, showing how little
I know about basketball.
But I think I know the general
themes around basketball,
involves a net, a back
board, and a ball, of course.
So I go to the free throw
line and I'll throw.
How long should I go?
Well, until I'm hitting
the point of frustration.
And at that point, continuing probably for
anywhere from 10 to 100 more trials
should be my limit, right?
That should be my limit if I want to
improve some specific aspect
of the motor behavior.
And so the question then is
what should I be paying attention to?
What should I be focusing on?
Well, obviously trying to
get the ball into the basket.
But the beauty of motor learning
is that the circuits for
auditory and visual and motor
more or less teach themselves.
I don't necessarily have
to be paying attention to
exactly the contact of
my fingers with the ball
or some random feature like
whether or not I'm
bending my knees or not.
The key is to try a number
of different parameters
until I start to approximate
the behavior that I want
to get a little bit better,
and then trying to get
consistent about that.
Now, many of you involved
in sports learning will say,
"Okay, well, that's obvious,
it's just incremental learning."
But the key thing is in those errors.
By isolating the errors and
making a number of errors
in a particular aspect
of the motor movement,
it signals to the brain that it's plastic.
And if I leave that episode of going
and trying to learn how
to shoot free throws,
my brain is still plastic.
Plasticity is a state of the
brain and nervous system.
It's not just geared
toward the specific thing
I'm trying to learn.
So there are two aspects to plasticity
that I think we really need to highlight.
One is that there's
plasticity geared toward
the thing that you are
trying to learn specifically.
And then there are states of mind and body
that allow us to access plasticity.
Now, toward the end of this episode,
I'm going to spell out specific protocols
in a little more detail.
That free throw example
might not correlate with
what you want to learn.
Actually, I don't have a huge
desire to learn free throws.
I've more or less given up on basketball,
and free throws in particular.
But I think that it's
important to understand
that motor movements are
the most straightforward way
to access states of plasticity.
And that can be for sake of
learning the motor movement
or for sake of accessing
plasticity more generally.
One very important aspect to
getting plasticity as an adult
is not just smaller increments,
meaning shorter bouts.
So I gave an example of
another 100 free throws or something,
but going out there and just
getting 10,000 free throws
all at once or packing as
much as I can into one episode
is not going to be as efficient for me
as shorter bouts of intense
learning as an adult.
Because the error signals
are not as well-defined
to my nervous system.
It's not going to know
what needs to change.
And so this is really the key element
of incremental learning,
is that you're trying to
signal to the nervous system
at least one component
that needs to change.
The nervous system needs
to know what the error is.
Now, when I shoot free throws, Lord knows
there are a lot of different
kinds of errors that happen,
probably the way I'm bending my knees,
the arc of the ball, the way
I'm organizing my shoulders,
probably where my eyes
are, lots of things.
So which ones to focus on?
And that's what I said before,
the beauty of the motor system is
I don't have to worry about all of that.
I just need to get the
reps in a number of times,
and the nervous system will figure out
how far off my motor commands are,
at the level of these maps
that I described earlier,
how far those deviate
from the desired behavior,
getting the ball into the basket,
and it will start making adjustments.
But as I make adjustments,
or as my nervous system
makes adjustments for me,
the key thing is to not start adding
a variety of new errors
because then it gets confused.
And so this is why short learning bouts
are absolutely essential.
So let's say it's for learning
an instrument as an adult.
Probably anywhere from 7 minutes
to 30 minutes,
provided that you're fully
attending, you're very focused,
is going to be a pretty
significant stimulus
to inspire plasticity
in the nervous system.
Now, there is one way to
get a lot of plasticity
all at once as an adult.
There is that kind of Holy Grail thing of
getting massive plasticity
as you would when you were a
young person but as an adult.
And the Knudsen Lab revealed this
by setting a very serious
contingency on the learning.
What they did was they
had a situation where
subjects had to find food
that was displaced in their visual world,
again, by putting prisms,
and they had to find the food,
and the food made a noise,
there was a noise set to kind
of the location of the food
through an array of speakers.
Basically, what they found was that
if people have to adjust
their visual world
in order to get food,
the plasticity would eventually occur,
but it was very slow as an adult.
It was very, very slow.
Unless they actually
had to hunt that food.
In order to eat at all,
they needed plasticity.
And then what happened was remarkable.
What they observed is that
the plasticity as an adult
can be as dramatic, as robust
as it is in a young person
or in a young animal subject,
provided that there's a serious incentive
for the plasticity to occur.
And this is absolutely
important to understand,
which is that how badly we
need or want the plasticity
determines how fast that
plasticity will arrive,
which is incredible because
the brain is just neurons
and soup of chemicals.
But this means that the
importance of something,
how important something is to us,
actually gates the rate of plasticity
and the magnitude of plasticity.
And this is why just passively
going through most things,
going through the motions, as we say,
or just getting our
reps in quote, unquote,
is not sufficient to get the
nervous system to change.
This study, a beautiful study,
published in the journal
of neuroscience shows
that if we actually have to
accomplish something in order to eat
or in order to get our ration of income,
we will reshape our nervous
system very, very quickly.
So the nervous system has a capacity
to change at a tremendous rate,
to an enormous degree at any stage of life
provided it's important
enough that that happen.
And I think some of you might be saying,
"Well, duh, that's obvious.
If it's really crucial,
then, of course, it's
going to change faster."
But it didn't have to be that way.
And for most people who
are trying to learn how to
learn faster or learn better,
they probably, in most cases,
they are hitting a limit
because the need to change
is not crucial enough.
And I think there are a number of places
where this has important relevance
in the people who are battling
addiction, for instance.
I will be the first to say that
I sympathize with the fact that addictions
have a biological component.
There's clearly cases where people
struggle tremendously
to change their behavior
and their nervous system, in
some cases, is so disrupted
by whatever substance they've been abusing
or behavior that they've been engaging in,
that it's that much
harder for them to change.
But we've also seen incredible
examples where when people
have to change from an
internal standpoint,
from their own belief
and desire to change,
that massive change is possible.
And so I think that the
studies that Knudsen did
showing the incremental learning
can create a huge degree
of plasticity as an adult
as well as when the
contingency is very high,
meaning we need to eat, or
we need to make an income,
or we need to do
something that's vitally important for us,
that plasticity can happen
in these enormous leaps
just like they can in
adolescence and young adulthood.
That points to the fact that it has to be
a neurochemical system.
There has to be an underlying mechanism.
This wasn't a case of
sticking a wire into the brain
or taking a particular drug.
All the chemicals that
we're about to talk about
are released from drugstores,
if you will, [laughs]
chemical stores that already
reside in all of our brains.
And the key is how to
tap into those stores.
And so we're going to next talk about
what are the specific behaviors
that liberate particular
categories of chemicals
that allow us to make the
most of incremental learning
and that set the stage for
plasticity that is similar enough
or mimics these high contingency states,
like the need to get food,
or really create a sense
of internal urgency,
chemical urgency, if you will.
If you've heard previous
episodes of this podcast,
you may have heard me talk
about ultradian rhythm,
which are these 90-minute rhythms
that break up our 24-hour day.
They help break up our sleep
into different cycles of sleep
like REM sleep and non-REM sleep.
They break up our day in ways that
allow us to learn best within
90-minute cycles, et cetera.
So some of you might be saying,
"Wait, you've been talking
about ultradian cycles,
and a moment ago you were talking about
7-minute or 12-minute or
30-minute learning cycles.
Today, we're really talking
about how to tap into plasticity
through the completion of a task
or working towards something
repetitively and making errors.
And so just to frame this
in the context of the ultradian cycle,
you might sit down,
decide that you're going to
learn conversational French,
which would mean that you probably
don't already speak French.
So you're going to sit down,
you're going to decide
you're going to learn
some nouns and some verbs,
you might do some practice set.
The ultradian cycle
says that for the first
5 to 10 minutes of doing that,
your mind is going to drift
and your focus will probably kick in,
provided that you're
restricting your visual world
to just the material in front of you,
something we talked about last episode,
somewhere around the 10 or 15-minute mark.
And then at best you're probably
going to get about an hour of
a deliberate kind of tunnel
vision learning in there.
Your mind will drift.
And then toward the end of that,
what is now an hour and 10
or hour and 20 minute cycle,
your brain will sort of
start to flicker in and out,
you might start thinking
about what you need to eat
or the fact that you have to
use the bathroom or something.
And then by 90 minutes, it's probably time
to just stop the learning
about and go do something else,
maybe return for a second
learning about later,
maybe take a nap afterwards or something
to enhance the learning.
It's going to happen within
about a 90-minute block.
You're going to go through
that cycle of learning.
But when I refer to the 7 or 12
or 30 minutes of making errors,
what I mean is when
you're really in a mode of
repeating errors, not deliberately,
you're trying your best
to accomplish something,
and you're failing.
You're absolutely failing.
You're trying to remember say
the sign language alphabet.
I was trying to teach
myself this recently,
and then I keep repeating and repeating,
and then get to a certain point
where I kept making errors,
making errors, making errors.
You want to keep making
errors for this period of time
that I'm saying will last anywhere
for about 7 to 30 minutes.
It is exceedingly frustrating,
but that frustration, it
liberates the chemical cues
that signal that
plasticity needs to happen
and they also signal the
particular neurons that are active.
So in the case of sign language,
it might be the ones that
control my hand movements
as well as me thinking about
what the different letters are.
It's signaling different
opponents within the networks
between the brain and body,
and it's trying to figure out,
"Wait, where are these errors coming from?
Where are the errors coming from?
Ah, it's those neurons,
they're making the mistakes.
They're making the mistakes,
they're making the mistakes."
And it essentially highlights
that pathway for change.
And it is the case that when we come back
a day or two later in a
learning about after a nap
or a night or two of deep rest,
then what we find is that we
can remember certain things
and the motor pathways work.
And we don't always get it perfectly,
but we get a lot of it right.
Whereas, we got it wrong before.
So that 7 to 30-minute
intense learning about
is within the ultradian cycle,
and I want to be clear about that.
And some people can tolerate
many of these per day.
Most people can only tolerate
one or two, maybe three.
This is intense work.
If shooting free throws, you
could probably do it all day.
But what I'm talking about
is really trying to accelerate plasticity
by having a period of the 7 to
30 minutes per learning about
that is specifically about making errors.
I want to really underscore that.
And it's not about, as I mentioned before,
coming up with some little hack or trick
or something of that sort.
It's really about trying to
cue the nervous system that
something needs to change
because otherwise it simply won't change.
Now, there's another aspect to learning,
I think it's only fair to mention,
which is that we can all learn very easily
when there's something
very bad happens to us.
I don't wish this on anyone,
but it is the case that if
something really terrible happens
that we will have a lifetime
memory for that event.
There are processes that
allow us to uncouple
the emotional load of that event.
I talked about some of
those a few episodes back,
the episode on dreams,
trauma, and hallucinations.
And we're going to return
to trauma release, PTSD,
and some of those other
themes in a future episode.
But the reason why negative experiences
can be wired into us so quickly is because
our nervous system's main
job is to keep us safe,
but at a deeper level, it's
because negative experiences
cue us to the fact that
whatever's happening
that's really bad is very different
than the other things that
tend to happen before.
Most of our experience doesn't remap us,
but those negative experiences deploy
high levels of norepinephrine,
high levels of acetylcholine,
and really make so that
whatever it is that we
experienced in that bad episode
is essentially queued up,
and so we're on the lookout for it.
And this has a number of negative effects
in terms of psychological
and emotional effects,
but it is really a process
designed to keep us safe.
The other ways in which
we can learn more quickly
besides just making errors
is when something really surprises us.
And if we're positively
surprised by something
or we are just flooded with
this molecule dopamine,
then there's a great
opportunity for plasticity.
Dopamine is a molecule that's
almost always associated
with pleasure
and with the accomplishment
of a particular goal,
but it's really also a
molecule of motivation.
It's a molecule that is
released inside of us
when we think we're on the right path.
And it does have a capacity
to increase neuroplasticity,
motivation, et cetera.
It's released in response to
a number of natural behaviors,
just that help with
the progression of ours
and other species,
things like food, sex,
in some sense social connection,
although that's more serotonin,
and serotonin doesn't have the same
effects on plasticity quite the same.
And we'll talk about a few later.
But dopamine is when we
think we're on the right path
toward an external goal,
a little bit is released
and it tends to give us more
motivation toward that goal.
I think everyone could stand
to enhance the rate of learning
by doing the following.
Learn to attach dopamine,
in a subjective way,
to this process of making errors.
Because that's really combining
two modes of plasticity
in ways that together can
accelerate the plasticity.
So, earlier, I talked about making errors
and having a focus about
of learning that includes
making a lot of errors
inside of that learning about.
That is going to be frustrating,
but the frustration itself is the cue,
and epinephrine will be very
high under those conditions.
But if you can just subjectively
associate that experience
with something good
and that you want to
continue down that path
as opposed to quitting
when you hit the point of frustration,
well then you now start to
create a synergy between
the dopamine that's released
when we subjectively
think something is good,
or tell ourselves something is good,
and that situation of making failures.
In other words, making
failing repetitively,
provided we're engaged in a
very specific set of behaviors
when we do it,
as well as telling ourselves
that those failures
are good for learning and good for us,
creates an outsize effect
on the rate of plasticity.
It accelerates plasticity.
Now, some of you might be
asking, and I get asked a lot,
"Well, how do I get
dopamine to be released?
And can I just tell myself
that something is good
when it's bad?"
Well, actually yes, believe it or not.
The thing about dopamine
is it's highly subjective.
What's funny to one person
is not necessarily funny to the next.
So it has to have some sense
of authenticity for you.
But if you really want to be learning
the thing that you're trying to learn,
that should be reason
enough to tell yourself,
"Well, I'm frustrated,
but the frustration is the
source of accelerated learning."
Dopamine is one of these
incredible molecules
that both can be released
according to things
that are hardwired in us
to release dopamine.
Again, things like food,
sex, warmth when we're cold,
cool environments when we're too warm.
It's that kind of
pleasure molecule overall.
But it's also highly subjective
what releases dopamine in
one person versus the next.
Everyone releases dopamine in
response to those very basic
kind of behaviors and activities,
but dopamine is also released
according to what we subjectively
believe is good for us.
And that's what's so powerful about it.
In fact, a book that I highly recommend,
if you want to read more about dopamine,
is a book that frankly
I wish I had written,
it's such a wonderful book,
it's called "The Molecule of More."
And it really talks about dopamine
not just as a molecule
associated with reward,
but a molecule associated
with motivation and pursuit,
and just how subjectively
controlled dopamine can be.
So make lots of errors,
tell yourself that those
errors are important
and good for your overall learning goals,
so learn to attach dopamine,
meaning release dopamine in your brain
when you start to make errors,
keep the bouts of
learning relatively short
if you're an adult.
Younger people can probably engage
in more bouts of learning.
And it's probably one of the reasons why
they learn so much faster.
They can just pack so
much more information
into the brains and nervous
systems compared to adults.
It's a little bit like,
I'll use the example of
performance-enhancing drugs.
Some of those drugs probably
do enhance performance
at the level of increasing red
blood cell count, et cetera.
But a lot of what those
drugs do is they allow
athletes to recover faster
so they can just train more.
They allow them to do more work.
And so being a child is a little bit like
being in a performance
enhanced brain milieu.
Their brains are kind of on
natural, healthy neurochemicals
that afford them a lot more
learning should they pursue it.
So this goes back to my advice
for young people early on.
If you're young, what should you do?
Learn as much as you can
about as many things as you possibly can.
And I suggest specializing in something.
I guess I'm not in a position
to give anyone direct advice,
but I would say, hopefully,
by about age 30, hopefully younger,
you have some sense of what excites you
and try and get really good at that thing,
provided it serves the world for better.
But that's all I'll say in
terms of parenting advice.
It's not my place.
But maybe sometime I'll have an episode
completely devoted to sort of
youth and learning in youth.
But once you're attaching dopamine
to this process of making errors,
then I start getting lots of questions
that really are the right questions,
which are, how often should I do this?
And when should I be doing
this and at what time?
Well, I've talked a little bit about this
in previous episodes,
but as long as we're now
kind of into the nitty-gritty
of tools and application,
each of us have some natural
times throughout the day
when we are going to be much better
at tolerating these errors
and much more focused on what
it is that we're trying to do.
Last episode was about focus,
but chances are that you
can't focus as well at 4:00 pm
as you can at 10:00 am.
It differs for everybody
depending on when you're sleeping
and your kind of natural
chemistry and rhythms.
But find the time or times of day
when you naturally have
the highest mental acuity,
and that's really when you want to engage
in these learning bouts.
And then get to the point
where you're making errors
and then keep making
errors for 7 to 30 minutes.
Just keep making those
errors and drill through it.
And you're almost seeking frustration.
And if you can find some
pleasure in the frustration,
yes, that is a state that exists,
you have created the
optimal neurochemical milieu
for learning that thing.
But then here's the beauty of it,
you also have created the optimal milieu
for learning other things afterward.
If you leave that about of,
I gave the example of free throws,
or maybe it's playing tennis,
or maybe it's some other skill,
and you sit down to read a book,
your brain is in a heightened state
to learn and retain the information.
Because those chemicals don't get released
and then shut down.
You're creating a whole milieu,
an environment of these chemicals.
And the tale of how long
these chemicals stay
sloshing around in your brain
has too many factors for me
to put a hard number on it.
It's going to depend on
transporters and enzymes
and all sorts of things.
But at least for an
hour or so I would say,
you're going to be in a
state of heightened learning,
and the ability to learn,
not just the motor patterns
but cognitive information,
language information,
maybe you go to therapy right after that
and you work on something
in a very deliberate way that
you're trying to work on,
maybe you don't go to therapy,
maybe you do something else
that's important to you.
Again, there are just a variety
of examples I could give.
There are a number of things that
allow us to powerfully
access these states of error
that are kind of surprising
but also kind of fun.
Again, these aren't gimmicks,
these tap into these basic
mechanisms of plasticity.
And the three that I'd
like to talk about next
are balance,
meaning the vestibular system,
as well as the two sides
of what I call limbic
friction or autonomic arousal.
And if none of that makes sense,
I'm going to put a fine
point on each one of those
and what it is and why it works
for opening up neuroplasticity.
Let's talk about limbic friction.
Now, limbic friction is not a term
you're going to find in the textbooks.
So if any of my colleagues are listening,
I want to repeat limbic friction,
I realize is not something
you're going to find
in any of the textbooks.
But it is an important principle
that captures a lot of
information that is in textbooks,
both neurobiology and psychology,
and it has some really
important implications.
Limbic friction is my attempt
to give a name to something
that is more nuanced and
mechanistic than stress.
Because, typically, when
we hear about stress,
we think of heart rate,
heartbeat going too fast,
breathing too fast, sweating,
and not being in a state that we want,
we're to alert and we
want to be more calm.
And, indeed, that's one condition in which
we have limbic friction,
meaning our limbic system
is taking control of a
number of different aspects
of our autonomic or automatic biology.
And we are struggling to control that
through what we call top-down mechanisms.
We're trying to calm down
in order to reduce that level of arousal.
We're all familiar with this,
it's called the stress response.
However, there's another aspect of stress
that's just as important,
which is when we're
tired and we're fatigued
and we need to engage,
we need to be more alert than we are.
And so what I call
limbic friction is really
designed to describe
the fact that when our
autonomic nervous system
isn't where we want it,
meaning we're trying to be more alert
or we're trying to be less alert,
both of those feel stressful to people.
The other way to put it
is that the word stress
is not a very good word to describe
what most people experience as stressful
because it can either be being
too tired or being too alert.
Now, why am I bringing this up
in a discussion about neuroplasticity?
This is not a discussion about stress.
At some point, we will talk about stress
and tools to deal with stress.
But the reason I'm
bringing this up is that
in order to access neuroplasticity,
you need these components of focus,
you need the component of
attaching subjective reward,
you need to make errors, all this stuff.
And a lot of people find it difficult
to just get into the overall
state to access those things.
So now there's a series of gates
that people are having
a hard time accessing.
They're too tired and they
can't focus, for instance.
Well, here's the beauty of it.
If you are too alert,
meaning you're too anxious,
and you want to calm down
in order to learn better,
there are things that you can do.
The two that I've spoken about previously
on various podcasts,
and I'll just review them really quickly,
are the double inhale exhale.
So inhaling twice through the nose
and exhaling once through the mouth.
This is not some yoga trick or some hack.
This is what's called
a physiological sigh.
It offloads carbon dioxide from the lungs,
it has a number of different effects.
These were described in
textbooks dating back to the 30s
and a number of laboratories have explored
the neurocircuitry underlying these
so-called physiological sighs.
That will calm you down
faster than anything else
that I'm aware of.
The other thing is starting
to remove your tunnel vision.
When you use tunnel vision,
you're very focused,
that epinephrine up is
released by dilating
your field of gaze,
so-called panoramic vision.
Great, so now you can start to
sort of move up and down this
level of autonomic arousal.
The key is you want to
be in a state of arousal
that's ideally matched
to the thing that you're
trying to perform or learn.
So if I'm really anxious
and I can't even pick up the basketball
or I feel like I'm shaking
or my muscles are too tight,
I don't have that kind of looseness,
when I move like that, it
almost makes it look like
I could throw a free throw,
but I miss 95% of the time,
unless the basket is very, very low
and I place it in directly.
I guess that's not a free
throw, is it? [laughs]
In any case, the point being that
you want to be in a state
of alertness but calm.
And so you need to have
ways to calm yourself down
when you're too amped up.
But the other side of limbic
friction is important too.
If you are too tired and you can't focus,
well, then it's going to be
impossible to even get to
the starting line, so to speak,
for engaging in neuroplasticity
through incremental learning, et cetera.
So in that case, there are other methods
that you can do to wake yourself up.
The best thing you should do
is get a good night's sleep,
but that's not always possible,
or use a NSDR, non-sleep
deep rest protocol.
But if you've already done those things
or you're simply exhausted
for whatever other reason,
then there are other things
that I often get asked about,
like sure a cup of coffee or
super oxygenation breathing,
which means inhaling more than exhaling
on average in a breathing about.
Now we're sort of getting
toward the realm of like
how you could trick your
nervous system into waking up.
And if you bring more oxygen in
by making your inhales deeper and longer,
you will become more alert.
You'll start to actually
deploy norepinephrine
if you breathe very fast.
So there are things that you
can do to move up or down
this so-called autonomic arousal arc.
And what you want to
ask before you undergo
any learning about is
how much limbic friction
am I experiencing?
Am I too alert and I want to be calmer,
or am I too calm and too sleepy
and I want to be more alert?
You're going to need
to engage in behaviors
that bring you to the starting
line in order to learn.
There are other things that
you can do in order to then
learn better and faster
besides incremental learning,
and those center on the vestibular system.
And this may come as a
surprise to some people,
but probably not as a surprise
to some of you whose
professions or whose recreation
involves a lot of motor activity
and sort of what we call high
dimensional skill activity,
not just running or cycling
or very linear activities
like weightlifting,
but things that involve inversions
and a lot of lateral movement,
actual sports, jumping, diving, rolling,
these kinds of things,
gymnastics type stuff.
Why the vestibular system
to access neuroplasticity?
Well, we have a hardwired
system for balance,
and here's how it works
in as simple terms as I
can possibly come up with.
As we move through space,
or even if we're stationary,
there are really three
main planes of movement.
Now, I realize some people
are just listening to this,
so I'm going to do this for both the folks
that are just listening
and for those of you that
are watching on video.
So there are three main modes of movement.
And it turns out that your brain
doesn't really know where your body is,
except through that
proprioceptive feedback.
The main way it knows
is through three planes of
movement that we call pitch,
which is like nodding.
So if I nod like this, that's pitch.
Then there's yaw, which is side to side,
which is like shaking my head no.
And then there's roll from side to side
like when a puppy looks
at you, like mm-mmm,
that kind of thing.
So pitch, yaw, and roll.
And the pilots out there
will know exactly what I'm talking about.
The brain knows the orientation
and position of your body
relative to gravity,
depending on whether or
not your brain in your head
actually is engaging more
in pitch, yaw, or roll,
or some combination because
if I lean down like so
or like so, it's a combination
of pitch, yaw, and roll.
You might say like,
"What is going on here?"
Well, we have these little
things in our inner ear
called the semicircular canals.
Just like our eyes have
two main functions,
one is to see objects in space
and the other is to set
our circadian clocks
through subconscious mechanisms,
our ears have two main roles.
One is to hear, to perceive sound waves
or take in sound waves for
perception, so-called hearing,
and the other is balance
or vestibular function.
So sitting in our ears are
these semicircular canals,
and they're these little tubes
where these little stones,
they're actually little bits of calcium,
roll back and forth like little marbles.
When we roll this way, they
roll this way, when we pitch.
When we go from side to side,
there's some that sit flat like this
and they go [makes swishing sound]
like marbles inside of a hula hoop.
And then we have roll,
there's some that are kind of
at 45 degrees to those and
it's kind of pitchy on roll.
Okay, great.
That sends signals to the
rest of our brain and body
that tell us how to compensate
for shifts relative to gravity.
And you say, "Okay,
I thought we were talking
about plasticity."
But this is where it
gets really, really cool.
Errors in vestibular
motor sensory experience,
meaning when we are off-balance
and we have to compensate by
looking at, thinking about,
or responding to the world differently
cause an area of our brain
called the cerebellum,
it actually means mini brain,
it looks like a little mini brain
like tucked below our cortex in the back,
cause the cerebellum to signal
some of these deeper brain centers
that release dopamine,
norepinephrine, and acetylcholine.
And that's because these circuits
in the inner ear, et cetera,
and the cerebellum,
they were designed to
recalibrate our motor movements
when our relationship to gravity changes.
Something fundamental to survival.
We can't afford to be
falling down all the time
or missing things that we grab for,
or running in the wrong direction
when something is pursuing us.
These are hardwired circuits that tap
right into these chemical pathways.
And those chemical pathways
are the gates to plasticity.
So I really want to spell this out clearly
'cause I've given a lot
of information today.
The first thing is,
how are you arriving
to the learning about?
You need to make sure your level
of autonomic arousal is correct.
The ideal state is going to
be clear, calm, and focused,
maybe a little bit more
on the arousal level,
like heightened arousal.
So understand limbic friction,
understand that you can be too tired,
in which case you're going to
need to get yourself more alert,
or you can be too alert
and you're going to need
to get yourself calmer.
That gets you to the starting line.
When you're at the starting line,
then you're going to go
into a learning about,
and that's when you want to
start making these errors.
But what I'm saying is
there's a layer in between
where if you are interested
in using motor patterns
as a way to open up plasticity
for all kinds of learning,
not just motor learning,
disrupting your vestibular
motor relationship,
and I'll tell you how
to do that in a moment,
can deploy or release
neurochemicals in the brain
that place you into a state
that makes you much better at learning
and makes making errors
much more pleasureful,
you're much more willing to do that.
Now, some of you are probably saying,
"Flow state, flow state."
Okay, I have friends
that work on flow states
and who are involved in
flow states and trying to
figure out what they are.
I have great respect for those people.
I want to tip my hat to them.
Very important work.
But, again, flow is an expression
of what you already know how to do.
It's not how you learn,
it's how you express what
you've already learned.
I want to be really clear about that.
It's been kind of presented
as this super state
or highly desirable state
that we can all reach for.
That's the wrong [indistinct] to reach for
until you already know
how to do the things
that I'm describing, in my opinion.
So the vestibular system,
if you can engage the vestibular system
and create some errors
within the vestibular motor
operations that you're carrying out,
you create a neurochemical
state that then makes you
very, very good at learning
very quickly regardless of age.
So what would this look like?
Does this mean just doing inversions?
Does this mean doing yoga?
Maybe.
Does this mean taking corners
faster on your road bike?
Let's say you always swim
freestyle or breaststroke,
does this mean swimming
backstroke or butterfly?
It depends.
It depends, however, on a very,
very easy to understand
parameter, which is
how regularly you perform
a particular motor behavior
and how novel a behavior is.
So the more novel that a behavior is
in terms of your relationship to gravity,
the more it will open up the
opportunity for plasticity.
Have you ever seen somebody who just
jumped out of a plane for the first time
with a parachute? [laughs]
I don't even want to think about what,
if you've just seen somebody
who jumped out of a plane
for the first time without a parachute,
I just hope the plane was on the ground.
But if you seen somebody after that,
they are in this incredible
state because their
body and brain are flooded
with all these neurochemicals
because it's very novel to them.
However, I've got friends
from communities that
have done thousands upon thousands,
maybe tens of thousands of jumps,
and they're always alert and aware,
but it becomes pretty regular for them.
That's the point.
And they're not in this
kind of buzzed out,
excited state afterwards
because it's routine for them.
The key is to bring novelty
to the vestibular motor experience,
the vestibular motor commands
that you're performing.
How do you do that?
Well, it's all about your
orientation relative to gravity.
Now, I wouldn't want anyone
to place themselves at risk.
So if you can't do handstands,
don't try and do them,
freestanding and whatever.
If you're good at handstands,
guess how much plasticity doing
handstands for half an hour
is going to create for you.
Zero.
Your body is fully comfortable
walking on your hands.
I see these people walking on your hands,
being upside down, being inverted.
Your Cirque du Soleil performers,
they're very comfortable there,
and there is zero
learning, zero plasticity
because the failures and errors
and the relationship to gravity
are very typical for that individual.
Now, what this means is
that if we're going to use motor practices
to open up plasticity for learning,
not just those practices, but
maybe some cognitive skills
or other things in the
period that follows,
we need to create a sense of
novelty relative to gravity.
And that means being
either in a new position
or slightly unstable.
Believe it or not,
I don't want anyone injuring themselves,
but the sensation of
falling or close to falling
signals the cerebellum to
signal the deep brain centers
that release these neurochemicals
that something is very different
and we need to correct
this error very, very fast.
Now, earlier, I was talking about
high contingencies for learning,
and you definitely don't want
to make it a kind of like
either survive this or
die kind of experience.
I confess, I occasionally look at these
parkour videos on YouTube.
Believe it or not, a lot
of those people have died,
the ones that do these ridiculous things
of hanging off of buildings and things.
I am not suggesting you do that.
Please don't do that.
What I'm talking about is
finding safe ways to explore
the sensory motor vestibular
space, as we call it,
the relationship between those things.
So that could be through yoga.
If you're terrible at yoga,
there's more opportunity for you to learn
than somebody who's very
skilled at yoga, for instance,
or gymnastics, or handstands,
or on your road bike.
This is, unfortunately, what,
I don't want to name
brands, but stationary bikes
where they give you the visual experience
of moving through space,
but you're not actually
moving through physical space,
there's no vestibular feedback.
It's all visual.
You're stationary on the bike.
So unless you're hanging off
the bike in your living room
like almost to the point
you're tipping the bike,
you're not getting the actual vestibular
motor sensory mismatch.
That mismatch is the signal that deploys
dopamine, epinephrin,
and these other things.
I don't care how excited or
how much fun the ride was
or how much music you're
playing that you love,
it's not the same situation
as being out of your normal relationship
to the gravitational pull.
So the first gate is to arrive at learning
at the appropriate level
of autonomic arousal.
Clear and focused is best,
but don't obsess over being
right there, it's okay.
If you're a little anxious
or a little bit tired,
then you want to make errors.
We talked about that,
and this vestibular motor
sensory relationship
is absolutely key
if you want to get heightened
or accelerated plasticity.
And we talked about another feature,
which is setting a contingency.
If there's a reason,
an important reason for
you to actually learn,
even if you're making failures,
the learning will be accelerated.
So there's really four things
that you really need to do
for plasticity as an adult.
And I would say that these
also apply to young people.
And there's an interesting
kind of a thought
experiment there as well,
which is if you look at children,
they are moving a lot
in different dimensions.
They are sometimes hanging from trees.
My sports were always
things where I tended to get
hurt a lot, fall a lot.
So it's skateboarding for
me when I was younger,
so a lot of falling and rolling
and various things of that sort.
But whatever sport the kids are playing,
or even if they don't play a sport,
they tend to move in a lot of different
relationships to gravity,
more dimensionality to their
movements I should say,
than adults.
And one of the questions that's always
kind of been in the back of my mind is,
as we age we get less good at
engaging in neuroplasticity.
Part of that is because
as the brain ages there
are certain changes to
the way that neurons are structured,
their molecular components, et cetera.
But it's kind of a self-amplifying,
or I should say self-degenerating cycle
where as we get older, we
tend to get more linear
and more regular about
specific kinds of movements.
So we'd get on the treadmill,
or we take the walk,
or we just always go up
the same stairs, et cetera.
And there's less opportunity, typically,
for engaging these relationships
to the gravitational pull
through the vestibular
motor sensory convergence
that we talked about a moment ago.
And so you sort of have
to wonder whether or not
the lack of plasticity
or the reduced plasticity
in older individuals, which includes me,
would reflect the fact that
those chemicals aren't
being deployed because
we're not engaging in certain behaviors
as opposed to we can't
engage in the behaviors
because the chemicals
aren't being deployed.
Now, I have a feeling it's both.
These have a reciprocal relationship.
And I certainly, again, I don't think
it would be wise for
anyone who doesn't have
the muscle stabilizing skills
or the bone density, et cetera,
to start doing inversions
and things of that sort.
That's not what I'm talking about here.
But it's interesting to think about
the sorts of exercise that we engage in.
We all know that getting
the heart rate elevated
three to five times a week
is really good for us for
cardiovascular health.
I think there's a ton of
data to support that now.
Some load-bearing exercise is important
for increasing bone density
and maintaining muscular strength
and proprioceptive feedback.
Because, I'm sure many of you know this,
but resistance exercise actually trains
the nerve to muscle connections
as much as it does the muscles themselves.
Something I talked about at
the beginning of the episode.
But I think most of us
could stand to increase
the degree to which we
engage this vestibular system
in novel ways.
And that can be done quite safely
through a number of different mechanisms.
I'm not a surfer, but people
who do that sort of thing
are very familiar with
orienting their body differently
according to the gravitational pull.
They're lying down, then
they're standing up,
then they're turning,
they're leaning their head.
So, again, it's this
pitch, yaw, roll thing.
And, again, if you're
very skilled at surfing,
you're actually not going to
open up plasticity just by surfing.
It's in the learning of these
new relationships to gravity
that the windows for
plasticity are enhanced.
I want to make sure that
I underscore the fact
that this vestibular thing
that I've been describing
is a way to really accentuate plasticity.
It's tapping into an
inborn biological mechanism
where the cerebellum has outputs
to these deep brain nuclei
associated with dopamine,
acetylcholine, and norepinephrine.
You don't want to endanger
yourself in the course of
pursuing these activities, but
it is a powerful mechanism.
That's kind of an amplifier on plasticity,
as is high contingency.
If you really need to
learn conversational French
to save your relationship,
the chances are you're going to learn it.
There are limits, of course, to the extent
to which one can accentuate
or accelerate plasticity.
The ceiling on this is not infinite,
although we don't know how high it goes.
I think it's reasonable to say that
if someone put a gun to my head and said,
"Learn conversational French
in the next 120 seconds,"
that conversational French will be limited
probably to just one word,
probably the word oui
or something like that.
Because I can't stuff in all
the knowledge all at once.
I think that's the dream
of brain-machine interface,
that one will be able to download a chip
into their hippocampus or cortex,
or some other brain structure
that would allow them
to download conversational French.
And someday we may get to that,
that capability may come about.
Right now, it does not exist,
nor is there a specific pill
or chemical that will allow you
to download more information more quickly.
This is the issue around nootropics
I've talked about before.
There are things that can increase focus,
mainly things that increase acetylcholine
and transmission through
the nicotine system,
things that can increase
dopamine, things like L-tyrosine.
Again, I'm not recommending these.
You need to heed the
warnings on those bottles,
but they will increase
these neurochemicals.
And there are, of course,
things that will increase epinephrin,
things like caffeine,
or some people, because of
prescription, take Adderall.
I'm, again, not suggesting
people take any of these things.
In fact, today I focused
almost exclusively
on behavioral tools and ways
of structuring learning bouts
that will allow you to
access more plasticity
regardless of age.
And they center around things that
I'm sure if you look around you you'll see
evidence for, "Oh, incremental
learning is powerful,"
or, "Oh, the vestibular system
can open up opportunities for plasticity."
I'm sure that the yogis
out there all saying,
"Wait, this sounds exactly like yoga.
We're supposed to push to an edge
and do these inversions and
do all those sorts of things."
Well, I want to be clear,
I never said anyone should do inversions.
I said that the vestibular
system is a valuable portal
into some of these neurochemical states
that favor plasticity.
But not so seldom, I hear
from the yoga community,
and they will say things like,
"Much of what you're saying
about how the brain works
or neuroplasticity has
already been described
or is embedded in yoga practices."
And I just want to be very clear,
I have tremendous respect for
the yoga community and the practices,
I've done yoga from time to time,
I find it challenging and valuable.
I'm not a regular practitioner.
But the problem with yoga
is exactly the same problem with science,
which is that yoga has a lot of practices
for which there are very specific names,
but no description
or lending of understanding
about mechanism.
And science has a lot
of mechanisms [laughs]
and a lot of publications and papers
for which there's very little,
if not no description
of tools and practices.
My goal in not just today
but in many ways throughout
the course of the podcast
is to bridge the gaps between
these various disciplines
in ways that are grounded mainly
to the fields of neuroscience
and some related fields.
So, yes, it's true that I look at things
mainly through the lens of science,
but that's not to say that
it exhaustively explains
everything about anything,
nor is it to say that it's the only lens
through which one could look at
something like neuroplasticity.
So I just want to acknowledge that
I have great respect for all these
different practices and communities.
And I think that, indeed,
there are many cases in which
different communities
and practices have been
aimed at targeting the
same goals or outcomes.
Science and neuroscience,
through an understanding of mechanism,
can allow all of us to gain
kind of common understanding
about what those practices are
and how to access things
like neuroplasticity,
sleep, et cetera.
And I do believe. as I've said
previously on this podcast,
that understanding mechanism
affords us a certain flexibility.
And I don't mean physical flexibility.
I mean a flexibility when we can't engage
in a particular behavior,
maybe we were injured or
maybe we're not in the right
situation to do a particular practice,
but by thinking about mechanism,
we can adapt our circumstances.
I talked about this with sleep.
If you're rigidly attached to one protocol
of always looking at sunlight
at one particular time
in the morning and in the evening,
that is not as valuable as
understanding the mechanisms
of why you might look at
sunlight at one particular
time versus another
because that affords you a flexibility,
allows you to adapt.
And life is very dynamic and
we don't have control over
all the external conditions all the time.
And so understanding mechanism
through the lens of neuroscience,
I do believe, can be very powerful
because, of course,
there are multiple ways
to access dopamine,
to adjust limbic friction.
It's not just through respiration.
Of course, there are many ways to do that.
And so my overall goal
here in this episode
and with this podcast
is to give you some
understanding of the mechanisms
and the insights into
the underlying biology
that allow you to tailor
what these kind of
foundational mechanisms are
to suit your particular learning needs.
So I really thank you for
your time and attention today.
I've covered a lot of material.
I very much encourage questions
in the comments section
if you're looking at this on YouTube.
And if you're not and
you're listening to it,
on Apple or Spotify.
Please feel free to visit us
over on the YouTube channel
and put your questions
in the comments section.
I do read them.
This entire month is all
about neuroplasticity.
There's a lot to cover,
but I'm very excited to
delve deeper into this topic
as it relates to your
particular interests.
Many of you have graciously asked
how you can help support the podcast.
The best way you can do that
is to subscribe to the YouTube channel,
if you haven't done that already,
as well as to place questions
in the comments section below,
or comments if you'd
like to give us feedback.
Also to subscribe on Apple and/or Spotify.
And Apple allows you to
leave a five-star review,
if you believe we deserve
a five-star review,
as well as leave comments
about the podcast.
In addition, if you
can suggest the podcast
to your friends, to your family members,
or anyone that you think
might be able to use
and appreciate the information,
that's a terrific way to support us.
And, of course, check out our sponsors
that we mentioned at the beginning.
That's a terrific way
to support us as well.
Several times throughout today's episode,
as well as on previous
episodes of the podcast,
I've talked about various supplements
that can be useful for enhancing sleep,
enhancing neuroplasticity, et cetera.
And, again, I want to emphasize that
I always think that behavioral practices
are the place to start.
I don't think supplements should ever be
the first line of entry
for people looking to
enhance these aspects
of their nervous system and life.
But for those of you that
are interested in supplements
and the supplements that I take,
I'm pleased to announce that
we partnered with Thorne,
T-H-O-R-N-E.
And Thorne makes supplements
that are, in my opinion,
of the very highest stringency in terms of
what's listed on the bottle
is actually what you'll
find in the bottle,
this is a serious issue for
the supplement industry,
as well as just the overall quality
of the materials they put
into their supplements.
If you'd like to take a look
at the supplements that I take
as well as explore any
of them for yourself,
you can go to thorne.com/u/huberman.
And if you look there, you'll see
a number of the different
supplements that I take.
And if you decide to purchase any of them,
you'll get 20% off your order.
So that's Thorne, thorne.com/u/huberman
to see the supplements that I take
and to explore if any of
them are right for you.
In the next episode of this podcast,
we're going to continue to
explore neuroplasticity.
This, as you may recall, is
the way that we go about things
here the Huberman Lab Podcast,
which is to really drill deeply
into a topic for three or
four, or even five episodes
so that by the end of those episodes,
all of you have a very firm
understanding of how to
apply the principles of neurobiology
to the specific practices
and endeavors that are
most important to you.
So I very much thank you
for your time and attention.
I know it's a lot of information
and it takes a bit of focus and attention,
and certainly will trigger plasticity
to learn all this information.
I want to encourage
you and just remind you
that you don't have to
grasp it all at once,
that it is here archived
and that if you want to
return to the information,
it will still be here.
And that I, most of all,
really appreciate your
interest in science.
Thank you so much.