- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
[upbeat rock music]
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today we are going to be
discussing bipolar disorder,
often called bipolar depression.
Bipolar depression is a condition
in which people undergo massive shifts
in their energy, their
perception, and their mood.
However, it is very important to note
that these shifts in mood,
energy, and perception
are all maladaptive.
They can often cause tremendous damage
to the person suffering
from bipolar disorder
and tremendous damage to
the people in their lives.
Today we are going to parse the biology
that leads to these shifts in
mood, energy, and perception.
And we are going to talk
about the various treatments that exist.
Some of those treatments have been around
for a very long time,
and indeed one of those
treatments, lithium,
has an incredible backstory
about its discovery
and in understanding how lithium works
and some of the ways in
which it does not work well,
it reveals a tremendous amount
about how the brain works
normally in all individuals.
So that's a miraculous
story that I look forward
to sharing with you.
As we go forward in this
discussion about bipolar disorder,
I want everyone to keep in mind
that it is a very severe condition.
In fact, people suffering
from bipolar disorder
are at 20 to 30 times
greater risk of suicide.
So today is a serious discussion
and it's certainly one in which people
who are suffering from
manic bipolar disorder
or who know people that are suffering
from manic bipolar
disorder can benefit from.
However, for those of you
that might know people
or who themselves suffer
from major depression,
we will also be talking about important
treatment developments
for major depression.
Major depression is a very
common thing for many people.
In fact, most people will
suffer from depression
of some sort at some point in their life,
although not necessarily a
major depressive episode,
and yet major depression is very common.
So you'll soon learn up to 20% of people
will suffer from major depression.
So today's discussion will
encompass all of that.
And it will also encompass
basic brain mechanisms
of neuroplasticity, the
brain's ability to change
in response to experience
both for good and for worse.
And you'll learn a lot
about the basic biology
of how the brain regulates
mood, energy, and perception.
I'm pleased to announce that
the Huberman Lab Podcast
is now partnered with
Momentous Supplements.
We often talk about supplements
on the Huberman Lab Podcast
and while supplements aren't
necessary for everybody,
many people derive
tremendous benefit from them
for things like enhancing
the quality and speed
with which you get into sleep,
or for enhancing focus
or for hormone support.
The reason we partnered
with Momentous Supplements
is several fold.
First of all, their supplements
are of the absolute highest quality.
Second of all, they ship internationally
which is important because
many of our podcast listeners
reside outside the US.
Third, many of the supplements
that Momentous makes
and most all of the supplements
that we partnered with them directly on
are single ingredient formulations.
This is important for a number of reasons.
First of all, if you're going to create
a supplement protocol that's
customized for your needs,
you want to be able to figure
out which supplement ingredients
are most essential and only use those
and supplements that
combine lots of ingredients
simply won't allow you to do that.
If you'd like to see the supplements
that we partnered with Momentous on,
you can go to livemomentous.com/huberman,
and there you'll see
many of the supplements
that we've talked repeatedly about
on the Huberman Lab Podcast episodes.
I should mention that the
catalog of supplements
that are available at
livemomentous.com/Huberman
is constantly being expanded
So you can check back there,
livemomentous.com/huberman
to see what's currently available.
And from time to time, you'll notice
new supplements being
added to the inventory.
Before we dive into the discussion
about manic bipolar disorder,
I want to highlight some recent findings
in an area totally
separate from mental health
that I think are really
important for everyone
to know about.
This is a paper published
in the journal Cell,
which is a Cell Press
Journal, an excellent journal.
In fact, one of the three apex journals.
So for those of you that are curious,
papers published in the journal
Nature, Science and Cell
are considered the sort of Super Bowl,
Stanley Cup, and NBA
championships of publishing.
And this paper entitled,
an inter-organ neural circuit
for appetite suppression illustrates
a very important principle
that I think everyone
should know about,
and that's the principle of
so-called parallel pathways.
Parallel pathways, as the name suggests,
are pathways, they
could be neural pathways
or hormonal pathways or otherwise
that operate independently of one another
to accomplish a common goal.
And what this paper really shows
is that there's a set
of peptides in the body
and the peptide that
I'm referring to today
is called GLP-1, Glucagon-like peptide-1,
and some related peptides.
I've talked about these
on the podcast before
for two reasons.
First of all, I'm a big
proponent and consumer
of yerba mate.
Yerba mate is a tea that
can promote the release
of glucagon-like peptide-1.
And there are also new prescription drugs
that are now hitting the market.
And for which there are really
impressive clinical trials
for diabetes and obesity
that are essentially glucagon-like
peptide-1 stimulator,
so they stimulate the release of that,
or they are in fact, a synthetic version
of glucagon-like peptide-1.
what is glucagon-like peptide-1?
It is a peptide, which is
a small little protein,
that can dramatically suppress appetite.
So that's why these
drugs are being explored
and are showing quite impressive results
for things like treatment
of type 2 diabetes
and other forms of diabetes,
as well as obesity.
So they lead to weight loss.
Now in terms of the yerba mate stimulation
of glucagon-like peptide-1,
that's going to be a much lower amount
of glucagon-like peptide-1 that's released
from drinking yerba
mate as opposed to say,
taking a drug that stimulates GLP-1
or taking a drug that is GLP-1.
Nonetheless, should also point out
that yerba mate comes in a
bunch of different forms.
There is some concern about
certain smokey-flavored forms
of yerba mate being carcinogenic,
so that's why I avoid
those forms of yerba mate.
But for me, yerba mate is one
of the preferred sources of caffeine.
For me, I like the way it tastes.
It does provide that sort of caffeine kick
that I like to have early in the day
for focus and for work and for exercise.
And yet I actively avoid
the smoked varieties
of yerba mate because of the potential
carcinogenic effects of
the smoked varieties.
Glucagon-like peptide-1,
as I mentioned earlier,
can suppress appetite.
But what this paper shows is it does that
by at least two mechanisms
through parallel pathways.
What this paper shows is
that glucagon-like peptide-1
axon receptors in the body in a portion
of the nervous system called
the enteric nervous system,
E-N-T-E-R-I-C, enteric nervous system.
This is a component of your nervous system
that you don't really have control over,
it's autonomic or automatic.
GLP-1 binds to what are called
intestinofugal enteric neurons,
you don't need to know the name,
but those neurons do two things.
First of all, they cause
some gut distension,
so they actually make you feel full.
This is incredible, right?
A peptide, not actual physical food,
but a peptide that stimulates neurons
that cause changes in the
so-called mechanoreceptors
of the gut, of the enteric nervous system
and make people feel full.
So it can lead to actually mild,
or I suppose if levels
of GLP-1 are very high,
to major gut distension.
I think that the levels
of GLP-1 that would come
from drinking yerba mate
and hopefully from appropriate dosaging of
the synthetic forms of GLP-1
or drugs that stimulate
GLP-1 would cause mild,
not major, gut distension,
'cause major gut distension
would be uncomfortable.
So GLP-1 is acting at the level of gut
to increase gut distension,
and by way of a pathway
that goes from the gut
up to the hypothalamus, this
little cluster of neurons
about the size of a marble that sits above
the roof of your mouth, is
also suppressing appetite
through brain mechanisms.
So this is really beautiful, right?
You have a peptide, a small little protein
that's released in the gut
and that release within the
gut causes gut distension,
which makes you feel full.
And by way of neural
stimulation of the hypothalamus
also activates neural
pathways within the brain
that trigger satiety, the feeling
of having had enough food.
So to me, GLP-1 is both
impressive and important.
Why?
Because this recent category of drugs
that's now hitting the market
seems to adjust obesity or can
help people with weight loss
in order to help their health.
And it's doing so by at
least two mechanisms.
One is within the brain, and
the other is within the gut
and communication through the
so-called gut brain access.
Because again, these enteric neurons
are communicating to the
brain, the hypothalamus,
by way of this, what's called
the
sympatho-gastro-spinal-reticular-hypothalamic
pathway,
you absolutely do not
need to know all of that.
That's a mouthful,
that's enough to make
your mouth feel distended.
But at the same time,
things like yerba mate,
and I'm sure there are other
compounds out there as well,
but certainly yerba mate can
stimulate the release of GLP-1.
So for those of you that are looking
for some mild appetite suppression
and want to accomplish that
while also ingesting caffeine,
yerba mate might be a
good option for that.
And just know that it's
operating through two mechanisms,
on the body through mild gut distension
to make you feel full,
and on the brain to increase satiety
and make you feel less hungry.
And then for everybody, not just those
that are interested in
appetite suppression,
I think it's important to understand
that these parallel
pathways are fundamental
to how we are organized.
Another good example of this would be
when we are excited by
something positive or negative,
so it could be stressful or
we are positively aroused,
there is a parallel activation
of epinephrine, adrenaline,
both from your adrenals and
from an area in the brain
called the locus coeruleus.
So again and again, we see this in biology
and in neuroscience that
your brain and your body
are acting in concert.
They're acting together through mechanisms
that either are independent,
so separately in the brain
and separately in the body,
but directed towards a common goal,
or through communication
between brain and body,
and almost always that communication
is going to be bidirectional,
body to brain and brain to body.
So I think these results
are really interesting
and really important
for sake of weight loss,
for sake of appetite suppression,
and just generally for the
way that they illustrate
this very important theme
of the way that we are constructed
at a biological level
which is parallel pathways.
Before we begin, I'd like to emphasize
that this podcast is
separate from my teaching
and research roles at Stanford.
It is however part of my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer information
about science and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that
theme, I'd like to thank
the sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I've long been a believer
in getting regular blood work done
for the simple reason
that many of the factors
that impact your immediate
and long-term health
can only be assessed with
a quality blood test.
And nowadays, with the
advent of modern DNA tests,
you can also get insight
into, for instance,
what your biological age is
and compare that to
your chronological age.
And of course your biological age
is the one that's important
for your longevity
and your understanding of
your current health needs.
One major problem with most blood tests
and DNA tests out there however,
is that you get information
back about levels
of metabolic factors, levels
of hormones and lipids
and so forth, but you don't know exactly
what to do with that information.
InsideTracker solves that problem
through their personalized platform
which can tell you, for instance,
lifestyle factors like
fitness or nutrition
or supplementation that you can use
to bring the numbers into the ranges
that are ideal for your health needs.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can visit insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off any of
InsideTracker's plans.
That's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 20% off.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by ROKA.
ROKA makes eyeglasses and sunglasses
that are of the absolute highest quality.
The company was founded by
two all-American swimmers
from Stanford and everything about ROKA
eyeglasses and sunglasses were designed
with performance in mind.
I've spent a lifetime working
on the biology of the visual system
and I can tell you that your visual system
has to contend with a number
of very important challenges
in order for you to see clearly.
The designers of ROKA
eyeglasses and sunglasses
understand this
and for that reason, ROKA
eyeglasses and sunglasses
allow you, for instance, to move
from a shady area to a bright area
or from a bright area to a shady area
and still see everything
with crystal clarity.
Originally, their glasses and sunglasses
were designed for performance,
that is for running and cycling,
and as a consequence, the
eyeglasses and sunglasses
stay on your face even if you get sweaty
and they're extremely lightweight.
In fact, most of the
time, I don't even realize
that they're on my face.
I wear ROKA eyeglasses for
reading and for driving at night
and I wear their sunglasses
when I'm out during the day
and it's really bright and
I need to use sunglasses
in order to be able to navigate
in that bright sunlight.
If you'd like to try ROKA
glasses, you can go to roka.com,
that's R-O-K-A.com, and
enter the code Huberman
to save 20% off your first order.
Again, that's ROKA, R-O-K-A.com
and enter the code Huberman at checkout.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Blinkist.
Blinkist is an app that has
thousands of nonfiction books
condensed town to just 15 minutes each
of key takeaways that you
can read or listen to.
I'm a big believer in
reading physical books,
I actually own a lot of hard cover books
and paperback books and I
like holding them my hand
and flipping through the pages.
I also like listening to audiobooks.
But the reality is I don't have
a ton of time to read books
and I don't have a lot of time
to listen to entire audiobooks.
There are also a lot of books
that I've really enjoyed
in the past that I have
read in their entirety
but then I like to update myself
on the information on
every once in a while.
Blinkist has terrific books available.
For instance, I'm a big fan
of Tim Ferris's 4-Hour Body,
gleaned So much knowledge from that book.
Also from Nassim Taleb's
book, The Black Swan
and the great Matt Walker's
book, Why We Sleep,
which is a book that
I've read several times
and I actually listen to the synopsis of
on Blinkist over and over
because there's so many key takeaways.
With Blinkist you get unlimited access
to read or listen to a massive library
of condensed non-fiction books,
essentially all of the books
that you ever wanted to listen to,
and now you have time
because they're condensed
down to just 15 minutes each.
Right now, Blinkist has a special offer
just for Huberman Lab Podcast listeners.
If you go to blinkist.com/huberman,
you can get a free seven-day trial
and you can get 20% off a
Blinkist premium membership.
That's Blinkist spelled B-L-I-N-K-I-S-T,
blinkist.com/huberman to get 25% off
and a seven-day free trial.
Let's talk about bipolar disorder.
And today I'm going to
refer to bipolar disorder
interchangeably with bipolar depression,
although as you will soon learn,
not everyone with bipolar disorder
necessarily goes through highs and lows.
There is a subset of people who suffer
from bipolar disorder who
experience the manic phases,
the highly elevated mood and energy,
and then drop down to so-called baseline,
so they don't necessarily go
down into a depressive state.
They often will return to
a somewhat normal state.
In fact, we will talk about
the percentage of time
that people with bipolar disorder
tend to be symptom-free manic or depressed
in the context of the different categories
of bipolar disorder.
But as we wade into this topic
that is bipolar disorder,
I just want to give you a little bit
of the background statistics
to anchor us in just how
serious and prevalent
bipolar disorder is.
So bipolar disorder
impacts about 1% of people,
that might seem like a small percentage,
but if you think about a
room of a hundred people,
that means that at least one of them
is very likely to have bipolar disorder.
And as I mentioned earlier
in the introduction,
bipolar disorder is very serious.
It has a 20 to 30% greater
incidence of suicide
than the general population, which is,
first of all, extremely tragic
and extremely concerning.
So anyone that thinks they
might have bipolar disorder
or who knows someone with bipolar disorder
should be especially vigilant about this.
And we'll talk about some of the,
or signs and risk factors, age of onset,
et cetera, as we move forward.
So 1% of people have bipolar disorder.
The typical age of onset
is anywhere from 20
to 25 years old, although
it can be much earlier.
And the earlier the onset
of a bipolar episode,
which we will define in a few minutes,
the earlier the onset of that episode,
the higher likelihood
that the bipolar disorder
is going to be a stable feature
of that person's psychology going forward.
And yet, I also want to point out
that there are some very good treatments
for bipolar disorder that those people
could still benefit from.
There are basically two
kinds of bipolar disorder
referred to as bipolar 1 and bipolar 2.
So let's just talk about bipolar 1 first.
Bipolar 1 is characterized by
a fairly extended period of mania.
What is mania?
Mania is a period of very elevated mood,
energy, distractibility, impulsivity,
and some other symptomology
that we'll talk about
going forward.
But this manic episode is extreme.
This is a condition in
which the energy lift,
the mood lift, and the sort of impulsivity
and actions and words of the person
suffering from manic bipolar disorder
are very noticeable and very extreme.
Now a key thing, however,
is that it's not always noticeable
to the person suffering from it
that they are in this mode.
Sometimes they recognize
that, sometimes they don't,
but it's always highly
recognizable to other people
that the person suffering
from manic bipolar disorder
is not like other people.
So let's talk about bipolar
1 in a little bit more depth.
One of the key clinical criteria
or diagnostic criteria for bipolar 1
is that a person suffer
from these manic episodes
or display these manic episodes
for seven days or more.
That turns out to be very key.
The stability of that manic episode
for seven days or more turns
out to be very important.
And for those seven days,
the person is in an elevated mood,
expansive thought all day,
every day for those seven days.
Now there are a lot of reasons
why somebody could be in a manic mode.
It doesn't necessarily mean
that somebody has bipolar disorder.
In fact, someone could be in a manic mode
for seven days or more
and still not be diagnosed
with bipolar disorder.
Why?
Well, there are other things
that can create manic episodes,
things like traumatic brain
injury, things like seizure,
things like various prescription
drugs or illicit drugs,
things like amphetamine and cocaine,
that is not the same as bipolar disorder
even though from a
symptomology perspective,
they might look even identical.
So let's think about these symptoms
and the diagnostic criteria
that a psychiatrist would use
in order to ask whether
or not someone is manic
because they have manic
by bipolar disorder
or whether or not that person is manic
for some other reason, such
as traumatic brain injury,
illicit drugs, et cetera.
So typically a person would
be brought into a clinic
or a person would bring
themselves to a clinic
or meet with a psychiatrist,
it seems more likely that
they would be directed
toward a psychiatrist because oftentimes
people who are in a manic episode
just simply won't have the perspective
or the foresight to bring
themselves into the clinic.
And the psychiatrist is
going to start to evaluate
for a couple of different things.
But first of all, what they're
going to try and figure out
is whether or not the
person has at least three
of the following symptoms.
The first symptom is distractibility.
Is the person distractable?
Are they going from one thing to the next.
People who are in a manic episode
will be talking about a pen
and then they'll be talking
about something they saw
the other day and then
something they want to purchase
and then a place they're
going to travel to, et cetera,
but they are also very
prone to any stimulus
within the room.
Meaning a bell could go off
or there could be a
sound out in the hallway
and they'll orient to that.
And then they'll orient to the clinician
and then they'll orient to
something in their pocket,
so they're all over the place.
You could think of this
a little bit like ADHD
or attention-deficit disorder,
but it's very extreme.
So highly distractable,
highly impulsive, impulsivity
relates to actions.
So the person might be
fidgeting with something
and then they might try and leave the room
or the person might, if they
were out in the real world,
somebody might notice that the person
is going and purchasing
multiples of something that
would be unusual for someone
to purchase.
So for instance, I happen to know someone
whose ex-spouse had bipolar disorder
and their ex-spouse went out and bought
10 plus air fryers.
I mean, I think unless you're a restaurant
that's using a lot of air fryers,
the idea that you would need more than one
or two air fryers might
just seem a little bit
out of the norm.
And so that impulsivity can be purchasing,
it can be other things as well.
It can be booking 12 international
trips in one afternoon
or going and buying three cars, et cetera.
So impulsivity.
the other is grandiosity.
People who have manic bipolar disorder
who are in a manic
episode will often display
words of or actions of grandiosity.
And keep in mind, these are not lies
in the sense that the person isn't lying
in order to try and pull
one over on anybody,
these are actual beliefs
that the person comes to have
about their grandiose
position in the world
or grandiose opportunities
or potential in the world.
Typical forms of grandiosity
and manic episodes
would be that the person suddenly decides
that they are going to
win a Pulitzer Prize.
They are the person selected
to win a Pulitzer Prize.
They're going to write
a novel that afternoon,
and they're going to win a
Pulitzer Prize that year,
which is more or less
a delusion of grandeur.
The idea that someone could
do that in one afternoon,
I suppose it is possible in
the realm of all possibilities,
but it's extremely unlikely.
Other forms of grandiosity
that often present themselves
in people suffering from a manic episode
will be that they're
going to run for president
or that they are the
person that they believe
is selected by the
citizens of a given country
or by the universe to be the
president of that country
or to be present of the universe.
It sounds ridiculous, but
those sorts of delusions
of grandiosity are one condition
that often presents itself,
or one set of symptoms
that presents itself.
Flight of ideas are also
typical of manic episodes.
So this is a little bit
like distractibility,
but this would be people
talking extensively
about one thing and then switching
and talking extensively
about something else.
It would be as if I was doing this podcast
talking about manic bipolar disorder
and then suddenly switching to OCD
and then to deliberate cold exposure
and then to the role of sugar
and its impact on the brain, et cetera.
So essentially a random selection
of the different topics
that exist in science,
all of which I happen
to be very interested in
and curious about,
but just as we have
episodes of the podcast
that are about one or two topics,
and we focus on those in
a fairly narrow trench
of discussion,
somebody who has a flight of ideas
would be jumping between
categories and topics
in a kind of pseudo random way.
So they might take off
down a path of one thing
and then switch to another
without any transition
or with transitions that that don't have
any logical structure to them.
The other aspect of manic bipolar disorder
that often presents itself
in the manic episodes
are agitation.
People feeling extremely
physically agitated,
so a lot of shaking and moving about.
This can venture into
the realm of paranoia,
but a lot of agitation,
a difficulty sitting down and being still,
a difficulty in just looking,
feeling and acting calm.
And then another condition is no sleep.
And when I say no sleep, I mean no sleep
or very minimal sleep.
As incredible as it sounds,
people who are in a manic episode
can often go seven days
or more with zero sleep.
And a key feature of this zero sleep
is that they're not troubled by it.
They're not thinking, oh,
I'm suffering from insomnia
and I really, really want to sleep.
Sometimes that's the case,
but more often than not,
they are simply not sleeping.
They're staying up 24 hours
then another 24 hours,
it just continues for an entire week.
Again, inconceivable to those of us
that don't suffer from manic episodes.
I can only imagine how pulled
apart most of us would feel
under those conditions,
and yet they are just going
and going and going with no sleep,
up all hours, shopping, talking, running,
doing all sorts of different
things in the categories
of other symptoms that
we talked about before.
And it doesn't bother them
that they're not sleeping.
And then the last sort
of category of symptoms
that the psychiatrist is evaluating for
and seeing if they present
is rapid pressured speech.
The rapid pressured speech is something
that when you hear it, you recognize it.
This is somebody that almost
seems to be hitting you
with speech like machine gun fire,
it's coming at you, coming
at you, coming at you
and there's really no
room for conversation.
They're not offering any opportunity
for a back and forth, or if
there is a back and forth,
they might ask you how
you feel about something
and then you started, well, I,
[speaking gibberish]
then they're going to hit
you with another barrage
or a paragraph of information
or of just speech, that pseudo random.
So we've got distractibility, impulsivity,
grandiosity, flight of ideas, agitation,
no sleep, and rapid pressured speech.
For someone to be diagnosed
as in a manic episode,
they do not have to be engaging in
or displaying all of those symptoms.
They do however need to present
at least three of those symptoms,
and then in order to meet
the condition of bipolar 1,
they have to be presenting
those three symptoms
for at least seven days.
It could be longer, but
at least seven days.
Now, this seems pretty
straightforward, right?
At one level, the way that I describe this
and the way that it exists
in the clinical literature,
you could think, well,
this should be pretty easy to diagnose.
And yet there's a complication there
or a challenge there because
the psychiatrist, again,
has to determine that these manic episodes
are not due to something
other than bipolar disorder.
For instance, again, it could be TBI,
traumatic brain injury,
it could be seizures,
or meds or other sorts of drugs.
Corticosteroids, which
are often prescribed
for a number of immune
conditions or for wound healing
can also cause manic episodes.
So they have to determine that everything
that's happening meets the
criteria I described before,
three out of seven of
these symptom categories
for seven days or more
and that it can't be better explained
by something else going
on in that person's life
or immediate medical history.
That's very important.
Now, the other challenge,
and this is something
that's going to come up
again and again today, not
just in the description
of the biology of bipolar disorder,
but also the description
of different treatments
and treatment approaches,
is that typically, when
somebody is sitting
in front of a psychiatrist,
in particular for the first time
those two people are interacting,
the psychiatrist is just
getting one snapshot
of the person at that moment.
So the person could be on
day one of a manic episode,
the person might be on day
six of a manic episode,
the person could be transitioning
out of a manic episode,
or the person could be
suffering from a combination
of manic episode where,
because of the impulsivity
of bipolar disorder,
they went out and used illicit drugs.
They also used cocaine.
So the psychiatrist has
a serious challenge.
The psychiatrist has to determine
based on a conversation,
this isn't a blood test,
this isn't a measurement
that you can take on a scale
or with a biomarker, they
have to use language,
a conversation with somebody
who, by all accounts,
is pretty impaired at conversation
to determine whether or not
they're suffering from a manic episode
that is the consequence
of bipolar disorder.
You can imagine this in the real world,
as somebody says, well,
how long has it been
since you slept?
And the person starts to answer,
oh, well, the other day I
went down to the basement.
I was going to get something out of
the refrigerator and I
thought I might take a nap.
And then all of a sudden they're talking
about something completely different.
So they might not even have an answer.
So the psychiatrist has to
be a really good detective,
a benevolent detective,
but a detective nonetheless
in determining whether or not
these symptoms have existed
for seven days or more,
and whether or not they
meet the, at least three,
it could be more, but at least three
of the criteria of symptom categories
I talked about before.
Now, assuming that they do,
assuming that the patient
meets those criteria,
they are likely to be
diagnosed with bipolar 1.
Now bipolar 1 disorder
means they're having these
extended manic episodes,
seven days or more,
but it does not necessarily mean
that they are dropping into
a depressive episode as well.
This is a common misconception
about bipolar disorder
because as it's often called,
bipolar disorder is referred
to as bipolar depression,
and yet many people with bipolar disorder
don't necessarily experience
the deep depressive episodes.
Many of them do, but many of them do not.
So somebody can truly
be diagnosed accurately
with bipolar one,
even though they're only
experiencing manic episodes
and then dropping down to baseline.
Manic episode, then
dropping down to baseline.
That's very important to understand.
Now, the second category of
bipolar disorder is bipolar 2.
So BP-II or bipolar disorder
2 is somewhat different
than bipolar disorder 1.
First of all, it's
characterized most often
by the presence of both
manic episodes, mania,
and depressive episodes,
or what's referred to as hypomania.
Now, anytime in biology or
in medicine you hear hypo,
it's the opposite of hyper.
So we've got normal hyper and hypo.
Hypomania is a somewhat
suppressed level of mania.
So this is not going to be as extreme
as the mania that we typically think of.
And yet the hypo can
be due to the duration,
not the intensity of mania.
That's right.
Hypomania can mean a
lessened intensity of mania,
but it can also be used to refer to
a shorter duration of mania.
And in fact, that's
one of the key criteria
for bipolar 2.
Bipolar 2 is often diagnosed
on the basis of the
presence of manic episodes
that are lasting four days or even less.
So someone with BP-II might have four days
of this increased energy,
goal-directed activity,
they're irritable, they're euphoric,
they're not sleeping, et cetera,
but it's only lasting for about four days.
Or they could be having longer
extended periods of mania,
but they are hypomanic episodes.
They're not quite as intense
so the pressured speech
isn't quite as pressured.
The impulsivity isn't quite as severe,
et cetera, et cetera.
The other aspect of bipolar 2
is one that I had mentioned
briefly a moment ago,
which is that it's often associated
with the drops into
the depressive episode.
So people are going from manic episodes
for four days or less,
then they're dropping into a depression,
going back to normal, manic again.
I do want to point out however
that people who have
bipolar 1 can indeed go
from manic episodes to severe,
what we call major depression,
so they can oscillate like a sine wave,
really high highs, really low lows.
And very important to understand
in terms of understanding
both bipolar 1 and bipolar 2
is that it's not always a sine wave.
This is really important
and it's something that
frankly I did not know
until I started researching this episode
and talking to some psychiatrists.
I should mention, I've talked to several
board certified
psychiatrists in preparation
for this episode,
I'll give some references to them.
And in fact, some of them
are going to be coming
on the podcast as guests in the future
for more in-depth discussion about bipolar
and other psychiatric disorders.
But all the psychiatrists
I spoke to confirmed
what the other was saying, which was that
the way that bipolar disorder can present
can vary tremendously between individuals.
One person might go from very high highs
that last seven days or more,
to very low lows.
Bouts of depression, major depression
that can last two weeks or more.
Other people are rapid cycling by way
of three days manic, three days normal,
three days manic, and then dropping
into three days depression.
So you want to erase
that picture in your mind
that manic bipolar
disorder is this sine wave,
this cycling up and down
between mania and depression.
It can take a lot of different forms.
And again, this is a serious challenge
for the psychiatrist to
diagnose people because of that
fact that they're only getting a snapshot
of the person unless they've
known them for some time
and are working with them for some time.
But this is also especially important
for those of you that
either have bipolar depression
or suspect that you might,
or that know someone
with bipolar depression
or suspect somebody might
have bipolar depression,
AKA bipolar disorder.
Because if you're noticing that somebody
is very manic and then normal, well,
that's a very different picture
than somebody who's going from very manic
to very deep bouts of depression.
The very manic to deep bouts of depression
is easier to recognize
because of the extremes
of those highs and lows.
Now, this might seem somewhat obvious
to all of you as I describe it,
and yet it's very important as a, frankly,
a citizen of the planet
who knows other human beings
to keep an eye out for
these manic episodes,
because again, whether or
not it's four days or less,
or whether or not it's seven days or more,
these manic episodes really
are the defining criteria
of bipolar disorder,
AKA bipolar depression.
There are a couple other key features
about bipolar 1 and bipolar 2
that can allow us to get better insight
into whether or not somebody
has bipolar 1 or bipolar 2,
and that's the percentage of time
that people with bipolar
1 versus bipolar 2 spend
in a manic state, a depressed state,
or a symptom-free state.
And this is also important to discuss
because it turns out that people
with genuine diagnosed bipolar 1
or bipolar 2 are often symptom-free,
which again can make it difficult
for us as people that know them
or for people that are treating people
with bipolar disorder to
identify whether or not
somebody is in a manic episode
or a depressive episode,
or whether or not they
are headed into a manic
or depressive episode.
So the numbers on this have been studied.
This from a paper, actually two papers,
first author, Judd, J-U-D-D et al.
published some years ago, 20 years ago,
but the data hold up
really nicely over time.
These were both published
in Journal American Medical
Association Psychiatry.
So JAMA Psychiatry is a superb journal.
And basically people who
have bipolar 1 on average
spend about 50%, it's
actually 53% was the number
that was eventually converged upon,
but about 50% of their time symptom-free.
That's interesting, right?
Somebody who has genuine
bipolar 1 disorder
can spend as much as half of their life
symptom-free, sleeping normally,
speaking normally, et cetera.
About 32% of the time depressed,
And when we say depressed,
we mean major depression.
So severe challenges with waking up
at two or three in the morning,
and having trouble falling back asleep.
That's one of the defining
characteristics of depression,
or sleeping far too much,
having a hard time getting
out of bed in the morning,
suppressed appetite, suppressed libido,
suppressed motivation,
all the general symptoms
of major depression
which we'll talk about
a little bit more later
and in an upcoming episode
about major depression
in particular.
And then about 15% of their time
in this kind of manic
state or mixed manic state,
where they are showing
long, again, seven days or more bouts
of sleeplessness, irritability,
pressured speech, grandiosity, et cetera.
Contrast that with people
who have bipolar 2 disorder
who are spending about half of their time
in a depressed state.
So that's interesting, people
with bipolar 2 disorder,
while not always
displaying depressed states
or oscillations between mania or hypomania
and depressed states,
they tend to be in the
depressed state more often.
And again, this is major depression.
This isn't just a little bit of a low,
this is a serious depression
of their nervous system,
their mood, and as we say, their affect,
their outlook on life,
and that's one of the key
distinguishing features
of major depression is that
people's outlook on life
becomes very diminished in the sense
that they don't see a future.
You ask them about, how's work going?
How're your relationships?
And it's not just that they
feel that that's going poorly,
they really feel as if
there's no opportunity
for those things to improve.
Those people with bipolar 2
tend to be symptom-free
about 45% of the time.
Again, these are averages,
so about 45% of the time,
that's a considerable amount of the time.
And they tend to be in
these hypomanic states
only about 4 or 5% of the time.
Again, the criteria for BP-II, bipolar 2
is these four days or less
of mania or hypomania,
but only 4% of the time or 5% of the time
is a small enough sliver of the pie
that is these people's existence
that you could imagine why it would be
easy for them or other people
to overlook the fact that
they have bipolar disorder
and not major depression.
Think about it.
This is a person who, or I should say
a collection of people who are spending
about half of their time depressed,
close to half, 45% of
their time symptom-free,
and then about 5% of their
time in a hypomanic state.
So either shorten bouts of
high intensity mania or hypomania
that is of reduced intensity.
One of the reasons that I
mentioned these percentages
of time spent in a
symptom-free, depressed manic
or hypomanic state is
because one of my major goals
for today's episode is that
it will increase awareness
of whether or not you
or somebody you know,
could be a coworker, could
be family member, et cetera,
might be suffering from
bipolar 1 or bipolar 2.
I think it's fair to say
that if somebody is suffering
from bipolar 1,
that is likely to be revealed
or to reveal itself
before too long, because of the fact
that people have these
extended periods of mania
and mania is such an extreme state,
not just for the person
who's experiencing it,
but the way that it
presents is just so extreme
and out of the ordinary.
But bipolar 2, you can imagine
could really duck under the radar
of our awareness.
And you could imagine
that we might just think
somebody is low or depressed,
especially if that person
tends to self-medicate
with alcohol or other substances.
We might think, oh, they're
drinking more than often
more than usual, excuse me,
or they're spending more
time alone and isolating.
But then when they're in
their hypomanic state,
that might actually
present as normal to us
because they were in such
a depressed state before.
So it's very important that
we dial up our awareness,
that we have tune our
antennae to the possibility
that people out there who
might appear depressed
or that we haven't heard from in a while
might actually be suffering
from bipolar 2 disorder.
Before we move into a in-depth discussion
about the different kinds of treatments
for bipolar disorder,
I'd like to touch on just
a few additional aspects
of what bipolar disorder can do
in terms of its negative consequences.
And also talk about some
of the inherited risk
that is the genetic factors
and the environmental
factors that can contribute
to bipolar disorder.
In terms of the burden,
the very real, emotional, and occupational
and educational burden that can occur
for somebody with bipolar disorder,
that's actually been studied.
There's a measure of this,
it's called global burden
which is defined as the years lost
in engaging a normal life
due to some disability.
So that disability could be cancer
or that disability, in this
case, is bipolar disorder.
And basically the way
this sort of study is done
is that through questionnaires,
I should say quite
in-depth questionnaires,
there's a probing for whether
or not somebody has lost
two consecutive weeks or more
of interest in normal activities.
Now, for people who have depression,
that's a kind of straightforward
thing to address, right?
You ask somebody, when
was the last time you ate,
or when was the last time
that you went a few days
without food or lost interest
in relationships or work or
sex or things of that sort
and they answer and you can figure out
the amount of time that you've essentially
been withdrawn from normal
levels of activity for them.
With bipolar disorder, What it turns out
is that the global burden
of having bipolar 1
and even bipolar 2 is massive.
In fact, having bipolar disorder
sits as one of the highest risk factors
for being in the top 10
of all categories of disabilities
leading to global burden.
Put in plain English, what that means is
having bipolar 1 or bipolar 2 disorder
is extremely debilitating.
It really slows down one's life trajectory
unless it's treated properly.
Now, the other aspect of bipolar disorder
is its heritability.
And this gets into a little
bit of some tricky science
related to inheritability versus
the genetic contribution
of a given disease.
So that might sound like the same thing,
you think, okay, genes
relate to heritability,
heritability relates to genes,
but of course, everything about the way
that our nervous system
works and functions
and expresses itself,
healthy or otherwise,
is an interaction between our genes
and our environment.
And so typically the way
these studies are done
is you address what is the risk
of somebody having a given condition
in the general population?
We talked about that
before, bipolar disorder
is a 1% of the world's population.
Compare that to people who
have only major depression.
So this would be repeated bouts
of two weeks or more
of serious depression,
not just low mood or
something due to a life loss,
but major depression,
which is 10 to 17% of people
have major depression.
They suffer from major
depressive disorder,
compared to bipolar disorder
which, again, is 1%.
Now, you can address how much of the 1%
of bipolar disorder that exists is due
to genes versus environment
in a somewhat exact way.
This is never an exact science.
And the way that this is typically done
is to look at concordance,
that is the likelihood
that two identical twins
will both have a given condition
as opposed to two fraternal twins,
which have more different genes
than identical twins, of course.
And then two siblings who
have similar genes, of course,
but less similar than
identical or fraternal twins
and so on and so forth.
So what you basically do
is you evaluate the
probability that two people
in the general population
who are completely unrelated
will have the same
condition, versus two people
in the general population
who are very related,
identical twins.
And what you find is
that in identical twins,
if one identical twin
has true major depression
or major depressive disorder,
there's a 20 to 45% chance
that their identical twin will also have
major depressive disorder.
Now that tells you right there
that it can't all be genes,
that is not a gene for
major depression per se,
or if it is a gene or
a collection of genes,
that those genes are also subject
to environmental influences,
either prenatal, within the womb
or after children are born.
Now the large range there of 20 to 45%
could be due to any number of things.
It could be experimental,
meaning the techniques that
were used in experiments,
it could be due to regional differences,
one part of the world versus another.
There are a lot of different factors.
Right now, we probably
shouldn't delve into all that.
At some point, we'll
probably do an episode
all about the genetics of
nervous system heritability
and heritability of features
and mental health, et cetera.
But we can compare major
depression and the heritability
or the genetic concordance
between identical twins
in major depression and
bipolar disorder and ask,
if one twin of an identical twin pair
has bipolar depression,
what is the likelihood that
the other twin will have it?
And it turns out that
number is much higher.
It's 40 to 70% likelihood or probability
that if one twin has bipolar disorder,
that their identical twin will
also have bipolar disorder.
So again, the total
incidence of bipolar disorder
in the general population is much lower
than it is for major depressions,
1% for bipolar versus 10 to
17% for major depression.
But the genetic component is much higher,
40 to 70% for bipolar disorder
versus 20 to 45% for major depression.
I know I'm throwing a
lot of numbers out there,
but basically what this means
is that researchers have been
able to take those numbers
and filter them through a
number of different risk factors
that are related to early development,
ask questions like if two
twins were raised separately
or together, or in one part
of the world versus another,
or had a two parent household
versus one parent household,
evaluate a lot of different variables,
what they were able to discover,
and this has been shown again and again,
is that the genetic
contribution to bipolar disorder
is very, very high.
That is the heritability
of bipolar disorder is 85%.
So again, I want to be
really clear what this means,
the total occurrence in the
general population, fairly low,
still serious, 1%,
but fairly low compared to other things
like major depression.
However, if someone has bipolar disorder,
it's very likely that they inherited
some gene or sets of genes,
or more accurately, a
susceptibility within their genes
to environmental influences
that can trigger bipolar disorder.
There are a lot of
different ways to discuss
and to conceptualize heritability
so I want to be very careful with the way
that I'm wording this.
What this means is that
people with bipolar disorder
very likely have a gene, or more typically
it's going to be a set of genes
that creates a susceptibility
for bipolar disorder
to present itself.
Now, what environmental factors trigger
or increase that susceptibility
is not entirely clear.
This always seems to center back
onto the same sets of things like
early life stress, trauma, et cetera,
certainly those are going
to exacerbate the likelihood
that someone who has a genetic propensity
for bipolar disorder will express
that bipolar disorder
and its full array of symptomology,
but 85%, while very,
very high, is not 100%.
Again, 85%, while a very high number
for heritability is not 100%.
What that means is that
there is no single gene
or identified gene cluster
for bipolar disorder.
The reason I keep drilling
into this over and over
is that I think we can confidently say
that if someone has bipolar disorder,
that there was something
in their genetic lineage
that led to that, or that
very likely led to that,
and yet it's not like eye color
or some other physical feature,
which we can actually do the direct,
so it's called Mendelian genetics,
and figure out whether or not somebody
directly inherited that
gene from one parent
or the other parent.
So the takeaway here is that if you have
certainly an identical
twin, or a fraternal twin,
or a sibling or a parent,
or even a cousin or an uncle
that has bipolar disorder,
in particular bipolar 1,
well, then you need to be on the lookout
for bipolar disorder, perhaps in yourself
and for the family members of that person.
My goal within this episode up until now
has been to provide a
clear and detailed picture
of bipolar disorder and its various forms.
Before we start to talk about treatments
for bipolar disorder and some
of the neural circuit basis
for bipolar disorder,
I want to make sure that I
distinguish bipolar disorder
from borderline personality disorder.
We will do an entire episode
or maybe even several episodes
about borderline personality disorder.
Borderline personality disorder
can indeed present itself
in ways that resemble bipolar
disorder and vice versa,
but there's some key
distinctions that need to be made
because it turns out that bipolar disorder
and borderline personality disorder
are quite distinct in terms
of their defining criteria.
The key distinction between somebody
with borderline personality disorder
and bipolar disorder
is that in borderline
personality disorder,
there can be episodes that can
resemble mania or hypomania.
So periods of flights of ideas,
or where people are
spending money excessively
or sexually promiscuous in ways
that seem manic or could even be
a little bit manic or a lot manic,
and yet more often than not,
there is an environmental trigger
for those manic episodes.
That is distinctly different
from bipolar disorder
where the person will have manic episodes
without any need for a trigger.
There doesn't need to be a call
from someone saying, hey, let's
go on a vacation together,
or there's something coming up this Friday
that's really exciting,
or let's enter a relationship together
of one form or another.
The person with bipolar disorder
will have episodes of mania
or episodes of major depression
without any need for an external stimulus
or environmental trigger.
But the person with borderline
personality disorder,
almost always, again,
there's never an always
in biology and psychiatry,
but almost always is going
to exhibit flights of mania
or depressive episodes or
other types of mood shifts
that are dramatic and maladaptive
in response to things
that are coming in through
the external environment or relationships
of some kind.
In fact, one of the
defining characteristics
of borderline personality disorder
is this thing that's
referred to as splitting.
A good example of splitting in a person
with borderline personality disorder
is that they will feel that
they absolutely adore you
and want to spend all their time with you
and just think the world of you.
You can do no wrong.
And in fact, they
genuinely can feel that way
and can genuinely think
that way about you.
And then for whatever reason,
it could be a perception of something
that you did or something that you said
or suspicion that you're
thinking something about them,
they can suddenly shift
or split their emotions
in what's called move
you from a good object
or a can do no wrong
object to a bad object.
They'll suddenly decide that
you are cheating on them
or that you are being mean to them
or that you're insulting them
or that something that
you're doing is in violation
to their self worth,
their wellbeing, et cetera
and that can send them down a pathway
of being very angry, very
depressed, et cetera.
As I describe the contour of a person
with borderline personality disorder
as somebody who splits
very suddenly in response
to some environmental
trigger, real or perceived,
there's the risk, of course,
that it makes the person with borderline
personality disorder
sound like a bad person,
that they're very volatile.
And while they can be volatile,
I want to be very careful to point out
that the person with
borderline personality disorder
is also suffering in this context.
So while those sorts of relationships
with people with borderline
personality disorder,
whether or not they're
romantic relationships
or familial or coworkers, et cetera,
can be very challenged,
can be very high friction
because of the good object,
bad object shifts, et cetera,
it's bidirectional, meaning the person
with borderline personality disorder,
as you can imagine, is also going through
a lot of suffering.
At one moment, they feel
as if someone is wonderful
and can do no wrong
to them and they want to
be so strongly affiliated
with them, and then in the next moment,
they feel as if that
person is attacking them
through their actions or even
through their non actions.
So again, we will return
to borderline personality disorder
in a separate episode,
it's a serious disorder,
both for the person that has it
and for people around them.
Fortunately, there are
some emerging treatments
that are showing promise
and it's a fairly common disorder,
but it's important that we distinguish
borderline personality
disorder from bipolar disorder,
mostly on the basis of
this need for a trigger.
Again, in bipolar
disorder, there is no need
for a trigger to create a manic episode
or a major depressive episode,
they just happen or they can just happen.
Whereas in borderline
personality disorder,
almost always there's an external trigger
or a perception that something happened
in the environment or
that somebody is behaving
a certain way that dramatically shifts
the person with borderline
personality disorder
from one mode to the next.
As we move into our discussion
about the treatments for
and neural circuits
underlying bipolar disorder,
I want to just nail
down one more key point.
This is a very brief point
but it's perhaps the most
important point, which is
the highs and lows, or
we should say the highs,
these manic episodes, and sometimes lows,
'cause again, not everybody
with bipolar disorder 1 or 2
suffers from depressive episodes,
sometimes yes, sometimes no,
in particular in bipolar 2, yes,
but people with bipolar 1 can
have extreme manic episodes
and then just return to
normal as you recall.
Well, those extreme lows
and or extreme highs
of people with bipolar disorder
impact their lives in very negative ways.
This is essential and it's something
that we're going to return
to a little bit later
when we talk about the relationship
between bipolar disorder and creativity,
because it turns out that there's a quite
strong association there,
one that would almost lead you to believe
that being bipolar can be beneficial
in certain contexts, and yet,
on whole, having bipolar disorder
is extremely detrimental and challenging
to the person suffering from it.
And it's something that
we want to keep in mind
as we think about treatments
and the underlying biology.
Now I'd like to talk about
some of the treatments
for bipolar disorder.
And in the discussion of those treatments,
there's an absolutely incredible history
of the discovery of one
particular treatment
that still shows great
success in many patients,
although some people
can't take it for reasons
that we'll talk about.
And in the description of the discovery
of this treatment for bipolar disorder,
it also reveals to us that sometimes
treatments come to the
profession of medicine
and through science in ways that precede
the discovery of the underlying biology.
That's right, every once in a while,
someone will discover a
treatment for a disease
without any understanding
about the underlying biological basis
of that disease.
And in fact, that is the
case for bipolar disorder
and the treatment that we are referring to
is lithium.
Lithium, as some of you know,
is on the periodic table of elements.
It is indeed a naturally
occurring substance.
It actually arrived on
earth by way of star dust.
Yes, we are talking about
star dust on this podcast,
but if you'd like to learn more
about the origins of lithium
and how lithium arrived here on earth
for its discovery and
applications in psychiatry,
there's a beautiful talk
that exists on YouTube
and we'll provide a link to this
in the show note captions that describes
the history of lithium in terms
of its interplanetary travels
and arrival on earth.
This is a talk delivered by a physicist
who is expert in quantum mechanics
and is expert in lithium.
And it's a just wonderful
talk that I can refer you to,
less on the biology in that talk,
but certainly a lot about
lithium as an element.
So for those of you nerds like me,
that love to know how things
came to be here on the planet
in one form or another,
I'll encourage you to take
a brief listen to that talk.
We are going to discuss
lithium in the context
of its applications for
treatment of bipolar disorder.
And the discovery of
lithium as a treatment
for bipolar disorder is
truly a miraculous story
that I think everyone should know.
The key player in this
story is a physician
by the last name Cade, he
was an Australian physician.
And Cade has a very interesting
story in his own right.
Cade was an Australian psychiatrist
or Australian psychiatrist
who also was a soldier.
And during World War II,
after the fall of Singapore to Japan,
he became a prisoner of war
and he was a prisoner of
war from 1942 until 1945.
So he had some time for observation
and during his imprisonment,
he observed some of his fellow inmates
is going through pretty wild vacillations
in mood and energy,
essentially going from manic episodes
to depressed episodes, or
from manic to normal episodes.
And for one reason or another,
we don't know why because
I couldn't find any report
as to why he hypothesized this,
but he hypothesized that
there was some buildup
of some chemical in these people's brains
that then they would urinate out.
And that urinating out
of whatever chemical
was in there would allow
them to be more relaxed
and not manic.
In other words, Cade hypothesized
that there's a buildup of a chemical
in certain people's brains
that makes them manic
and they urinate that chemical out.
So eventually he got out of this prison,
as we mentioned in 1945,
and he started doing experiments
in addition to seeing
patients in his clinic.
And what he did is he
started to take urine
from people who exhibited mania
and urine from people who were not manic,
and he took that urine
and he would inject it
into guinea pigs as an experimental model.
And his general observation was that
there was something in the urine
that was indeed making
the guinea pigs more manic
if they were injected with
urine from a manic patient.
The exact measures that he was
taking in these guinea pigs
wasn't exactly clear.
This is at a time or an era in science
when you could just sort of report things
a little bit more subjectively,
although there were still
numbers and statistics,
it was a little bit more
of like case studies
and descriptions, but it turns out
that even though that all
seems a little bit loose,
it led to some incredible and
still important discoveries
for psychiatric health.
So what he figured out was that the urine
from manic patients
seemed to be more toxic
for these guinea pigs.
And he also knew that there
are two toxic substances
in urine, urea and uric acid.
So he was able to separate
the urea and uric acid
from people with mania
and patients that did not have mania.
And he figured out that the
urea was the same in both
these mentally ill, manic patients
and the non manic patients.
So it did not seem that urea
was the compound that was
creating these manic episodes
or related to manic episodes
or held the toxicity
so instead he focused on the uric acid.
Now in order to put the
uric acid into solution
so that he could inject
it into these guinea pigs,
he had to try a number
of different compounds
in order to dilute it.
It just so happens that,
and you chemists will
be familiar with this,
but there's certain
things that just don't go
into solution easily.
You put the powder in a vial,
you add some water or a
saline or another solution,
you mix it up and the powder
stays suspended in there,
it doesn't actually ever
become a clear liquid
that you can inject.
So in order to try injecting
different strengths
of uric acid,
he ended up using lithium
to assist in the dilution,
and lithium worked.
So what he basically was doing,
again for you chemists,
is he was taking uric acid,
he was adding lithium,
and making a solution of lithium urate.
this is a lot of details,
but this is important
because what he eventually found
is that when he diluted the uric acid
with lithium and created lithium urate,
lithium urate could actually
calm down these guinea
pigs that were injected
with the toxic urea.
He also found that lithium urate
had a generally calming
effect on these guinea pigs.
So now we're really
off in crazy territory,
we're talking about urine from patients
that's separating out urea and uric acid,
we're adding lithium to the uric acid,
we're injecting this into guinea pigs,
this is getting pretty
wild and pretty weird,
but this is medicine,
and from time to time,
this is medicine and science.
Cade was a good scientist in addition
to being a good physician,
and by good scientists,
I mean that he did control experiments.
Here he was injecting
lithium urate into animals
and seeing an effect,
but he knew that that
solution of lithium urate
contained not just the uric acid,
but it also contained lithium.
And so he quite appropriately asked,
maybe the lithium alone is
having this calming effect
on these guinea pigs.
And indeed, that was the case.
When he did the proper control experiment
and injected only lithium
solution into these guinea pigs,
they calmed down.
From there, he in sort
of 1940 style medicine,
this would not happen now,
he very quickly moved
from that animal model
into human patients and started
injecting human patients
with lithium or providing
lithium orally to those patients.
And lo and behold, found
an absolutely profound
and positive effect of lithium
in reducing symptoms of mania.
And as all good physician scientists do,
he wrote up his results.
And he wrote it up in a paper entitled,
Lithium Salts in the Treatment
of Psychotic Excitement.
Okay, back then they didn't call it mania,
they called it psychotic excitement.
This is a paper that was
published September 3rd, 1949
in the Medical Journal of Australia.
We will provide a link to this study,
is now a classic study in
the field of psychiatry.
It's a really wonderful paper to read.
And actually I encourage people,
even if you're not a
scientist or a clinician
to just take a quick
look at the second page
in this paper that we've
made available to you
where he describes each of
the various case studies
or the individuals that he looked at.
I'm not going to read these in detail now,
'cause it would take a
lot of unnecessary time,
but things like case seven,
MC, aged 40-years-old,
suffering from manic recurrent mania.
In this episode, he'd
been excited, restless,
and violent for over two months
and was interfering so often
that had to be confined to a single room
during the day.
So this is very debilitating,
what we now know to be bipolar depression.
He commenced taking
lithium citrate, 20 grains,
that's a measure of the amount of lithium,
three times a day.
In four days, he was distinctly quieter
and by February 13th, 1949,
appeared practically normal.
He continued well and
on February 20th, 1949,
the dose of citrate was
reduced to 10 grains,
et cetera, et cetera.
He left the hospital.
There are numerous descriptions
of this sort within this paper,
including some descriptions of patients
that did not see such success,
and including some
descriptions of patients
that suffered from some
negative side effects.
So that's important to point out as well,
but it's an absolutely wonderful paper
and it's an absolutely wonderful voyage
into the history of psychiatry
right down to the discussion where
in just three short paragraphs,
Cade really lays out the case for why
lithium is such a important discovery
in the treatment of what, at that time,
they were calling psychotic excitement
and what we now know to be
manic bipolar depression.
Lithium, I should mention,
has a number of important features,
but it also a number of
important side effects
that need to be considered.
First of all, it does have
a certain toxicity and
so levels of lithium
in the blood need to be
monitored extremely carefully.
So it's not the sort of thing that people
can just take at a given dose
and every patient responds the same,
there's a lot of oversight
and a lot of blood tests
that have to be done,
especially in the first three
months of lithium treatment.
I should mention that lithium treatment
is still used to some great
degree of success in many,
not all people suffering
from bipolar depression,
or bipolar disorder rather,
but there are a number of
important things that happened
between 1949 and present day
that prevented lithium
from reaching patients
that really needed it.
And that all can be summarized
in two or three short sentences.
Basically, by virtue of
the fact that lithium
is a naturally occurring element,
it could not be patented.
And as a consequence of that,
there wasn't a lot of potential profit
for drug companies to produce lithium.
In fact, still to this
day, it's very low cost,
and still to this day, no
one really owns the patent
for lithium in its purest form.
So that made it unattractive.
It turns out that the
FDA in the United States
didn't allow lithium to
be used as a treatment
for manic bipolar disorder until 1970.
So we're talking about a full 21 years
from the publication of this paper by Cade
in the Medical Journal of Australia
showing quite beautifully
the great potential in use of lithium
for quelling the symptoms
of bipolar disorder
until the first patients
in the United States
were starting to access lithium regularly.
And nowadays, of course,
lithium is available,
but still not able to be patented
'cause it's element number
three on the periodic table,
it's naturally occurring.
It's not literally falling
down from the stars as stardust
and going into pill form,
but rather it can be synthesized
in laboratories, but it is available.
It does show not only great
potential in many patients
but great application in many patients
despite its side effects.
So lithium really stands as
this kind of golden example
of a treatment that works,
at least in many individuals,
prior to an understanding
of the biological basis
of the disease for which
that treatment is needed.
Now with that said,
scientists and clinicians
have been quite rigorous
in trying to understand
why and how lithium works
in order to understand
the why and how of bipolar disorder.
This is the way that proper
medicine and science is done.
Even if there's an excellent
treatment for something,
it's important to understand
why that treatment works
because, first of all, not everyone
responds to that treatment.
Second of all, scientists
and physicians understand
that just because we have
one treatment that works,
if it has any side effects at all,
there is the possibility
for better treatments.
So it's not just about
trying to bypass a drug
that doesn't make much
money for drug companies,
I know a lot of people
think in those terms,
they think, oh, well,
there's this continued
search for better treatments
for bipolar disorder
even though lithium works
because lithium doesn't
allow drug companies
to make much money.
That's not really the case.
The fact of the matter
is is that the toxicity,
some of the other issues that
are created with lithium,
the fact that people need
the ongoing blood testing, et cetera,
really stimulates the
need, really an urgent need
for new and better treatments
for bipolar disorder.
And only by understanding
how lithium works
at the cellular level, at
the neural circuit level,
et cetera, do we really stand to find
those new discoveries.
If you were to do a literature search on
the actions and mechanisms of lithium
in terms of how it can calm people down
and reduce their manic episodes,
you would find an
enormous array of papers,
literally thousands of scientific studies
in animals and in humans,
which, for instance will tell
you that lithium treatment
will increase so-called BDNF,
brain-derived neurotrophic factor.
BDNF is often talked about in the context
of neuroplasticity,
the brain and nervous system's ability
to change in response to experience.
And indeed it does seem
that ingesting lithium
increases BDNF.
BDNF is what we call
permissive for neuroplasticity.
It doesn't create specific
changes in the brain,
meaning it's not going to
make your memory better
or your coordination better,
or your emotional state better per se,
what BDNF does is it permits the neurons,
the nerve cells and their
connections in the brain
to be more likely to change
if the proper environmental
conditions are met.
That is BDNF creates a kind of
buoyancy to neuroplasticity.
It opens the gates to neuroplasticity.
So lithium does increase BDNF,
we'll talk about why that's
important in the context
of the neural circuits involved
with bipolar disorder in a few minutes.
It also seems to be a
potent anti-inflammatory.
Now, inflammation is one of those words
that's thrown around extensively nowadays,
especially on social media
and especially as it relates
to any health condition,
it's like inflammation,
inflammation, inflammation,
always seems to be discussed
in the context of inflammation being bad.
But I do want to point
out that inflammation
is a natural adaptive
response to physical injury
to a cell or organ or tissue of any kind.
Inflammation is the basis by which
adaptations occur to exercise.
So if, for instance,
you were to weight train and use a heavier
than normal weight kind,
do a set to failure or create
some little micro tears
in the muscle that are healthy
in the sense that they
would create adaptations
and make that muscle stronger,
maybe even grow that muscle,
there's an inflammatory
response associated with that
that is critical to the
positive adaptation.
So inflammation isn't always bad,
although excessive, or as we say,
runaway inflammation is bad.
Lithium seems to be able to
suppress inflammation and,
importantly, it can suppress inflammation
in neural tissues and within
the brain in particular.
That is important.
And we return to that
and why it's important
in a little bit.
The other thing about lithium
is that lithium is neuroprotective,
that is it can prevent neurons from dying
under certain conditions.
Why would neurons die?
Well, there are a lot of
reasons why neurons can die.
There can be a physical
insult to the neurons.
You can get hit really
hard in the head, a bullet,
God forbid, can enter the
skull and kill neurons,
there are a lot of reasons
why neurons can die.
Neuroprotection is a
situation in which a neuron
is given some sort of chemical
or physical resiliency
that allows it to suffer an insult
and yet bounce back.
So it's very similar to
the way that we think
about psychological resiliency,
neuroprotection is an ability for neurons
to be better able to handle stress
of different kinds, in
particular, excitotoxicity.
There's a phenomenon in bipolar disorder
and a lot of other psychiatric conditions
in which hyperactivity
of certain brain areas
actually starts to kill off neurons.
Hyperactivity doesn't always do this,
but it turns out that if
certain brain circuits
are too active for too long,
some of the chemicals
associated with neuroactivity,
things like calcium and neurotransmitters
like glutamate can actually
kill the very neurons
that are active.
So it seems that lithium can prevent
some of that neurotoxicity.
Now, this turns out to
be particularly important
for this discussion about bipolar disorder
and the neural circuit
basis of bipolar disorder
because if we are just
take a step back and ask,
what's different in the brains of people
with bipolar disorder?
There are some very interesting answers
that start to emerge.
There are basically two
main neural circuits
that are present in normal individuals,
I say normal, I say that respectfully
to the people with bipolar disorder
by referring to people who do not suffer
from manic episodes or
from manic depression.
There are circuits that are present
in people with bipolar disorder
and in people that do not suffer
from bipolar disorder,
both of those circuits do the same thing
in both sets of individuals,
and yet in people with bipolar disorder,
there seems to be an atrophy or a removal
of certain neural connections over time
that leads to a situation in which people
with bipolar disorder become very poor
at registering their own internal state,
in particular, their emotional states
and their somatic states.
What we're referring to here
is something called interoception.
I've talked about this a little bit
on the Huberman Lab Podcast before,
but there are two modes of perception.
Perception, of course, is a attention
to something that's
happening in our environment
or to us on or within our body.
Exteroception is literally
an attention to things
that are happening beyond
the confines of our skin.
So seeing that person's face over there,
or seeing that color of leaf over there,
or hearing a sound over to my left,
that is exteroception,
perception of things
beyond the confines of one's skin.
Then there's interoception
which is perception of things
that are happening internally
like, how full does my gut feel?
How fast is my heart beating?
Some people can measure
that quite accurately
just by thinking about
it, other people can't.
How happy am I, how sad
am I, how energetic am I,
how lethargic am I, et cetera, et cetera.
So we are always existing in a balance
between exteroception and interoception,
but as it turns out, people
with bipolar disorder
over time, and especially into the second
and third decade of
having bipolar disorder
seem to have progressively
diminished levels
of interoception.
And that very likely is important
in their inability to
register, for instance,
that, wow, they are talking
at an excessive rate
or they haven't slept
in 5 or even 10 days,
or they haven't eaten in
a long period of time.
This atrophy of neural
circuits for interoception
is starting to emerge
as one of the defining
neural circuit characteristics
or underpinnings of bipolar.
Now I bridge to this conversation
about neural circuits
from the statement that
lithium can protect
against some of the neurotoxic effects
of neural circuits being very active.
Now this can get a little bit complicated,
but I promise I'm going to make it clear
for any of you that are
watching and or listening.
The reality is
that people with bipolar depression
very likely have a hyperactivity,
that is an increased level of activity
in certain circuits within the brain
early in the expression of their disease.
And that typically, as
I mentioned earlier,
sets in around the early
20s, although sometimes
that can be even earlier,
in the teens and so forth.
But that hyperactivity, we think,
leads to a toxicity and excitotoxicity
of certain elements of the neural circuits
that are responsible for interoception.
In other words,
the overuse of certain
circuits can lead to a
diminishing, an atrophy, or even a death
of certain elements within those circuits
and it appears that lithium,
through its anti-inflammatory
and neuroprotective effects
and through its ability to increase BDNF,
very likely protects us against some
of that atrophy of those
circuits for interoception.
So this isn't a case in which
people with bipolar have a neural circuit
or lack a neural circuit
and people without
bipolar are the opposite.
This is a case in which
everyone more or less
starts out the same,
but it seems that there's a hyperactivity
of certain neural circuits in people
with bipolar disorder that over time
actually causes those
circuits to diminish.
Now, this is very important because some
of the more recent longitudinal studies
doing brain imaging on people
with bipolar disorder and those without,
and doing that over time in patients
starting as early as their teens,
but into their 20s and
30s reveals just that,
that there can be hyperactivity
of circuits early on,
but then hypo, reduced activity
of those very same circuits
at a time 5 or 10 years later.
Again, this speaks to
the complicated nature
of bipolar disorder and
of psychiatry and linking
specific psychiatric disorders
to neural circuits in general.
Because if you have a situation in which
in one disease, let's just,
hypothesize here for a second
that for instance, in certain
forms of schizophrenia,
there's elevated dopamine
and where we to just reduce
the amount of dopamine, that
they would receive relief
from those schizophrenic symptoms,
well, that's all pretty
straightforward on the face of it,
but in this situation
with bipolar disorder,
what we're talking about is hyperactivity,
too much activity leading to hypoactivity
through death of those very circuits.
And so now you can
especially appreciate why
when the patient shows
up to the psychiatrist
or when the psychiatrist
shows up to the patient
in the total course of their disease
is going to be very important.
And then layer on top of that
the complexity of the fact
that the very defining characteristic
of bipolar disorder is that
there are oscillations in mood.
So now we need to think about treatments,
not just for the manic episodes,
but also treatments for
the depressive episodes.
And that's, in fact,
what psychiatrists do.
Turns out that they apply
different treatments
or combinations of treatments for patients
that are in manic episodes
versus depressive episodes
and they have to infer
all that from discussions,
again, just exchange of words
depending on when that person
walked into their office,
where they are in terms of manic episodes,
no symptomology or
depressive symptomology,
and whether or not they've
had that symptomology
for an extended period of time.
And then just to make the
situation even more complicated,
the very circuits that
atrophy that start to wane
and disappear in people
with bipolar disorder
are the circuits for interoception,
for understanding of what's
going on in one's own body.
So you can imagine if you
sit down and ask somebody,
well, how long have, has it been
since you've slept, that
person may genuinely not know.
Or if you ask the very depressed person,
how depressed are you?
That person may not be
able to articulate that.
So fortunately there are solutions to this
and the solution is that
more often than not,
the accurate understanding
of whether or not someone
has bipolar depression or not,
and what stage of the illness
they might be in or not
is going to depend on the
reports of people around them
and not the patient themselves,
hence the importance of
having a rather detailed
and admittedly a rather intense discussion
about the symptomology
of bipolar disorder,
so that you can have an understanding
of the people around you
and have an eye and an ear
to whether or not those
people might be suffering
from bipolar, and if so, at
what stage of the disease
they might happen to be at.
Now I'd like to talk a little bit more
about what is known
about the neural circuits
that lead to the manic states,
as well as the depressive states,
but mainly the manic
states of bipolar disorder.
We already discussed the
fact that interception,
registering of one's own internal emotions
and bodily states is diminished in people
with bipolar disorder.
But we haven't really talked
about the neural circuits
that are responsible for
that lack of recognition.
For that reason, I'd like
to point out a paper.
This is a fairly recent paper,
just came out this year,
but it's an excellent one,
Looking at the changes over
time in neural circuitry
in people with high genetic
risk for bipolar disorder,
and in particular in young people.
And studies of this sort are rare,
but are exceedingly
important because of the fact
that they track individuals over time.
The title of this paper is,
Longitudinal Changes in
Structural Connectivity
in Young People at High Genetic
Risk for Bipolar Disorder.
We will provide a link to this study
in the show note captions.
There are a lot of data in this paper,
in particular, neuroimaging data,
and it's quite extensive
in terms of analyzing
the so-called connectomics.
You've probably heard of genomics,
which is the analysis of
genes and their display
in different individuals or
different animals, et cetera.
You have proteomics,
which is the display of,
or the existence of different proteins.
So omics is a big thing now in science,
you kind of throw omics behind anything
and it becomes its own Wikipedia page,
which means it becomes its own thing,
so to speak, I say that
only partially in jest.
Nonetheless, connectomics
is the analysis of connections
between different neurons
and neural circuit elements.
And what this paper really showed
by analyzing the connectomics
of neural circuits
in the brains of many different people
with different categories
of, and onset of,
and severity of
bipolar disorder,
as well as controls in
different age groups, et cetera,
is that people who are
of particularly high risk
for having bipolar disorder
or that have full blown bipolar disorder,
have deficits and actually reductions
in the amount of connectivity between
what are called the parietal brain regions
and the limbic system.
Now, the limbic system
I've talked about before
in this podcast, if you're
not familiar with it,
I'll explain what it is in a moment,
it's simply a collection
of brain structures,
not one brain structure,
but a collection of brain structures
that generally are responsible
for shifting the overall
state that we're in
from states of more relaxed and calm
to states of more alert and focused.
The limbic system is intimately related
to the so-called autonomic nervous system,
which regulates our sleep wake cycles
and a number of other things
like our digestion, et cetera,
our level of hunger and on and on.
So the limbic system is really
kind of like a volume control
or as nerd scientists like to say,
a kind of gain control
on the overall level
or amplitude of alertness or calmness.
In fact, if we're very, very calm,
we are asleep or even more
calm, we can be in a coma.
If we are very alert, we can be wide awake
and ready to work and run, et cetera.
Or if we are very, very, very alert
by way of limbic autonomic interactions,
well, then we can be in anxiety.
We can be in full blown panic attack,
or we can be in mania.
We can have so much energy
that we feel like we don't need to sleep.
And in fact, disruptions in the circuitry
really seems to be what's going on
in people who have bipolar disorder.
Now, if disruptions in the circuitry
are present in the limbic system,
that doesn't necessarily
mean that the limbic system
is at fault because the way
that neural circuits work
is that different brain areas are talking
to one another through
electrical-chemical signaling,
and they're regulating one another.
And what this paper really tells us
is that there are elements
within the parietal lobe,
which is a kind of a section of the brain
that sits off to the side,
it's not really off to the side,
but in neuroanatomical nomenclature,
the parietal lobe is connected
in two ways, bidirectionally.
So parietal lobe is
connecting to limbic system
and limbic system is
connecting to parietal lobe.
And in people with bipolar disorder,
it seems that the parietal lobe
is able to exert less top down control,
that is less suppression
of certain elements
of the limbic system,
which, at least right now,
is leading researchers to hypothesize
that the limbic system is sort
of revving at higher levels.
It's kind of like RPM in your cars
or kind of redlining at
times and for durations
that are inappropriate
or at least abnormal.
So we have two major sets
of neural circuit deficits
or changes in people with bipolar.
Their lack of internal
awareness is reduced,
and that turns out to be,
by way of neural structures,
like the insula which is a brain region
that is connected in a very direct way
to our somatosensory cortex,
so the part of our cortex that
registers how we feel,
literally, sense of
touch and internal state.
So those circuits, excuse me,
for those for those of you listening
I just bumped the microphone, excuse me.
Those circuits are disrupted
in people with bipolar
and the top down control,
that kind of accelerator and break
on our overall levels of
energy are also disrupted.
Now that's all fine and good
because, well, it's true,
at least according to what the data
at this point in time tell us,
there may be new discoveries to come,
but that all seems to be the case,
but it doesn't tell us how to modulate
or change that circuitry.
It also doesn't tell us
how something like lithium
can actually benefit a
large number of patients
or how a good number
of the other treatments
for bipolar disorder, which
we'll talk about going forward
can benefit patients with bipolar.
So it appears that lithium is exerting
its positive effects on
bipolar depression treatment,
at least in part by preventing the loss
of certain neural circuits,
namely the neural
circuits for interoception
and the top down control
over the limbic system.
Now it turns out to be
examining lithium's effects
at an even more reductionist level,
we can gain really important
insight into what's going on
in bipolar depression and
some of the other treatments
for bipolar depression,
including behavioral treatments,
things like transcranial
magnetic stimulation,
and even some of the more natural
or so-called nutraceutical treatments
including things like high
dose omega-3 supplementation,
which we're going to
talk about extensively.
Now, in order to
understand what we're going
to talk about next, it's important
that everybody understand a
key concept of neuroplasticity.
And this is a key concept
regardless of whether or not
one is talking about bipolar depression.
In fact, it's something I think everybody,
every citizen of earth should know about,
and that's called homeostatic plasticity.
Homeostatic plasticity
is a particular form
of neuroplasticity in
which if a neural circuit
is overactive for a period of time,
there are changes that
occur at the cellular level
that lead to a balance or
a homeostatic regulation
of that circuit so that
it's no longer overactive.
Conversely, if a neural
circuit is underactive
for a period of time,
certain changes happen within
the cells of that circuit
to ramp up their activity
or make them more likely
to be active.
And whether or not a neural circuit
and the neurons within
it become more active
or less active in the context
of homeostatic plasticity
largely depends on one mechanism,
and it's a beautiful
mechanism that I'll make
very clear to you right now,
even if you don't have
a background in biology.
Neurons communicate with one another
by releasing so-called neurotransmitters,
which are just chemicals.
Those neurotransmitters are vomited out,
they're not actually vomited,
but they're spit out into
the so-called synaptic cleft,
often called the synapse.
The synapse is just a
little gap between neurons.
And when they are
released into the synapse,
they don't just stay there,
they actually park or bind to receptors
on what's called the postsynaptic neuron.
And depending on how many
receptors they bind to
and how many receptors
are available, et cetera,
they can have a greater or lesser effect
on the postsynaptic neuron.
This scenario of
neurotransmitters being released
into synapses then binding to receptors
on postsynaptic neurons and influencing
the electrical excitability
of those postsynaptic neurons
sits central to not just the
treatment of bipolar disorder,
but to all treatments of
all psychiatric conditions
and indeed to things like
neuropathic pain as well.
For example, the so-called SSRIs,
Prozac, Zoloft and others, et cetera,
stands for selective
serotonin re-uptake inhibitor.
What does that mean?
Well, serotonin is a neurotransmitter.
It's actually a
neuromodulator that's released
into the synapse, and then the SSRI,
the selective serotonin
re-uptake inhibitor
allows more of that serotonin
to sit within the synapse
for longer, it's a re-uptake inhibitor,
it prevents re-uptake by
the presynaptic neuron.
and that serotonin therefore can park in
or dock in the receptors, as it's called,
of the postsynaptic
neuron in greater numbers,
and have a greater impact
on that postsynaptic neuron.
So the drugs that are
used to treat depression
or other things of that
sort, things like SSRIs,
work by changing the
availability of neurotransmitter
in the synapse.
Other things like MAO inhibitors,
Monoamine oxidase inhibitors,
work a different way.
They inhibit the enzyme.
Anytime you hear ase in biology,
it's very likely an enzyme
which breaks things down.
so MAO inhibitors prevent the
breakdown, not the re-uptake,
but the breakdown of neurotransmitter
and therefore allow more neurotransmitter
to be available in the synapse
and influence the postsynaptic cell.
Homeostatic plasticity is
a form of neuroplasticity
in which overall circuits can
become much more excitable
or much less excitable by the addition
of more receptors in
the postsynaptic neuron
or by the removal of more receptors
from the postsynaptic neuron.
And the way this happens
is just beautiful.
It was first discovered
in the visual system
and the person primarily responsible
for the discovery of
homeostatic plasticity,
although there are several,
is a woman by the name of Gina Turrigiano,
she's a professor at Brandeis University.
And what the Turrigiano Laboratory showed
was that for instance, if we
are in the dark for a long
period of time, literally,
and we're not seeing much
for a long period of time,
there's an increase in
the number of receptors
in the postsynaptic neurons
so that a smaller amount
of light and excitability
within the visual system can lead
to greater amounts of
activity in the visual system.
Conversely, if there's an overactivity
or an increase in that
activity in the visual system
for some period of time,
then a number of receptors
in the postsynaptic neuron
are removed from that
postsynaptic neuron surface,
making any neurotransmitter
that's available
only able to bind the
receptors that are left
and have less of an
influence on those cells.
In other words, keeping a circuit
in so-called homeostatic balance
in a particular range of excitability.
Now, while that's a mouthful and an earful
and a concept-full, I don't know
if a concept-full is a
word, but in any case,
that's a lot to think about,
but all you need to know
is that if a neural circuit
is very active for a period of time,
in normal individuals,
there will be a reduction
in the amount of activity
by way of removing
receptors that bind neurotransmitter.
Whereas, if a neural
circuit is very quiet,
it's not activated for a period of time,
maybe your leg is in a cast for instance,
and you're not activating
your quadricep and calves
very much, well when that cast comes off,
sure, the muscle might be atrophied
but the nerves that connect to that muscle
are actually in a position
to influence that muscle
even more once you start using
that muscle or those muscles,
because whatever
neurotransmitter is released
now has the opportunity
to bind to more receptors,
in that case in muscle,
or in the case of brain circuits,
in postsynaptic neurons.
So homeostatic plasticity
is this beautiful,
balancing mechanism that makes
sure that neural circuits
are never too active nor
too quiet for too long.
And in a beautiful display of how
treatments can lead to a better
understanding of biology,
which can lead to the discovery
of even better treatments, lithium and
another compound, which
we'll talk about, ketamine
seem to exert their actions largely
through effects on
homeostatic neuroplasticity.
There's a wonderful paper that describes
all the nitty-gritty of this.
Certainly most people
listening, I'm guessing,
are not going to be
interested in all this detail,
but for those of you that you are
and you want to delve deep into this,
this paper was published in
Neuron Cell Press journal,
excellent journal,
it's titled, Targeting
Homeostatic Plasticity
for the Treatment of Mood Disorders.
And there's one particular
figure in this paper
that I'll just describe to you
in which measurements
were made from neurons
and the number of
receptors in those neurons,
it's done somewhat
indirectly through a method
that's detailed and
neuroscientists are familiar with.
Basically what it measures is how excited
a given neuron is, electrically
excited a given neuron is
to a given amount of neurotransmitter.
So that the amount of
neurotransmitter that's vomited
onto a neuron is
essentially kept constant,
and then the response
of the postsynaptic neuron is measured.
So it can be of one
level or higher or lower
depending on homeostatic plasticity.
And what this paper shows
and what's been shown
over and over again, is that
when neurons are exposed
to lithium for a period of time,
there is a reduction in the excitability
of the postsynaptic neuron,
that is neurons within the brain
become less excitable over
time if lithium is present,
whereas ketamine, which is
now a common FDA-approved,
at least in the US, it's
approved for the treatment
of major depression,
ketamine does the opposite.
Ketamine seems to increase
the number of receptors
in the postsynaptic neuron
and lead to greater levels
of excitability and electrical activity
within neural circuits
to a given fixed amount
of neurotransmitter.
So this is super interesting
because what it means
is that lithium is causing
circuits to be less active,
ketamine is causing
circuits to be more active.
And we know from excellent
clinical data now
that ketamine seems to be
a very effective treatment
for major depression, and for
the major depressive episodes
of people that suffer
from bipolar depression,
that includes these
major depressive episodes
of two weeks or longer of
suppressed mood, appetite,
sleep issues, et cetera.
Now, the key thing about ketamine
that's often not discussed
is that while its effects
are very potent, they are transient.
So one major drawback to
ketamine therapy for depression
is that it has to be done repeatedly,
and how repeatedly, or how often, rather,
depends, of course, on a discussion
between the psychiatrist and the patient.
This is not something
to cowboy on your own.
I know that, and many of
you are probably familiar
with the fact that ketamine
also is abused recreationally.
It is a so-called NMDA,
N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor antagonist,
so it blocks the very
receptor that's responsible
for neuroplasticity for
changes in neural circuits.
It also changes excitability
in neurons as I just described.
So ketamine is a very potent chemical
that has been shown over and over again
and is now FDA approved for the treatment
of major depression, but its
effects seem to be transient.
Lithium, as I described earlier,
seems to reduce the manic episodes
or the intensity of manic
episodes in symptomology,
in people with bipolar disorder,
it's doing that through neuroprotection.
So protecting neural
circuits from dying away
that initially are overactive
and that overactivity
causing excitotoxicity,
blocks that excitotoxicity, we believe.
And it seems to do that in part
by diminishing the amount of
activity in those circuits.
So this is a beautiful mechanistic story,
and it's the sort of story
that you'd love to have
for a great number of
psychiatric illnesses.
And fortunately we have
for bipolar disorder.
Overactivity of a given circuit
eventually leads to
neurotoxicity, excuse me,
lithium is preventing that
neurotoxicity by reducing
the number of receptors
in certain elements
within those circuits, so
called homeostatic scaling,
it's downregulating
the number of receptors
leading to less
excitability and preventing,
we think, excitotoxicity.
And in that sense, you can see exactly why
it's important to get lithium treatment
in there early for people
with bipolar disorder.
Ketamine as a treatment
for major depression
seems to be effective but transient.
And you can also see why
it would be important,
not just to reduce the manic episodes
for people with bipolar disorder,
but to also treat the depressive episodes.
So this is a key feature of the treatment
for bipolar depression
and for bipolar disorder.
there needs to be
treatment both of the mania
and of the depressive
episodes if they're present.
And fortunately, there are
excellent drugs to do that.
And I should mention
that ketamine and lithium
are just two of the drugs within the kit
that psychiatrists have access to.
There are many things, olanzapines
and a number of different,
including Clozapine.
Clozapine is an antipsychotic
which is commonly prescribed to
as a sedative in some
cases that allows people
in manic episodes to sleep.
It's classically described
as so called dopamine
receptor 4 antagonist,
although it does other things as well.
Clozapine has a number
of side effect features
related to white blood cell
and things of that sort that
require careful monitoring.
So there are an enormous number now,
literally dozens and
dozens of different drugs,
each designed to target
either the manic phase,
the depressive phase, or
some what we call acute
sort of early phases
versus ongoing treatments.
This is a vast galaxy of drug treatments
that really should be navigated,
I should say, absolutely
should be navigated
by a board certified psychiatrist.
And of course in close discussion
with both the person suffering
from bipolar disorder,
but also ideally the family members
of the person suffering
from bipolar disorder.
But I think, at least up until now,
we've focused on the two major pathways
for treatment, lithium and ketamine.
And we've talked about why
lithium and ketamine work,
that they're working on opposite ends
of this homeostatic scaling.
We talked a bit about the
circuits that are involved
in generating what we think
are the manic symptomology
and the lack of interception.
Why people can just
persist in staying awake,
awake, awake, not eating, et cetera.
Now you have in mind how
all that is put together.
And I think you have in mind,
some of the well-demonstrated treatments
for the different component
parts of bipolar disorder,
which now I'm hoping
you're also well versed in
based on our early, early discussion
of what constitutes
bipolar 1 and bipolar 2.
Now I would like to also talk about
some of the not so typical therapeutics
for bipolar disorder and
also point to the things
that have been tried and failed
for successful treatment
of bipolar disorder,
because some of those things
are often talked about and suggested,
especially in online communities,
and while it's not clear that any of them
are particularly hazardous on their own,
although some of them
do carry some hazards,
I do think it's important
because of the critical
time sensitive nature of bipolar disorder
and the urgency of
getting treatments early
to try and prevent some
of the longer lasting
neural circuit changes
that if people can avoid
some of the less effective or demonstrated
to be ineffective treatments,
that they stand to combat bipolar disorder
much more successfully.
First of all, a key point
about drug therapies
versus non-drug therapies
or talk therapies,
without question, drug therapies
are going to be most effective
when done also with talk therapies.
And we'll talk about which talk therapies
have been demonstrated
to be most effective.
There is some argument about
what I'm about to say next,
but in general, most
psychiatrists will tell you,
or certainly the ones I've
spoken to have told me,
that talk therapy on its own
is rarely, if ever effective
for bipolar depression
and bipolar disorder, whether
or not it's BP-I or BP-II.
That's just the reality of it.
Contrast that with our discussion
about obsessive-compulsive disorder,
which we talked about a few episodes ago,
if you haven't seen that episode,
We have an in-depth episode all about OCD
and obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
There it seems that drug
therapies and talk therapies
can be done independently
or in combination.
As expected, combined
drug and talk therapies
are more effective there
than either one alone,
but there are pretty impressive effects
of talk therapy alone provided
that they're initiated at the right time,
and it's the right form of talk therapy.
That's OCD, but in terms
of bipolar disorder,
it really seems that the
drug therapies are necessary,
at least in most all cases.
That said, talk therapies
are terrific augment
or support for those drug therapies
and sometimes can allow people
to take lower doses of
those drug therapies,
which turns out to be important
because of the side
effect profiles of a lot
of drug therapies and
sometimes the cost as well.
I guess we can think of cost
just as another side effect really.
There are both established
and more novel forms
of talk therapy being used, again,
in concert with drug treatments
for bipolar disorder.
Cognitive behavioral therapy is the one
that seems to be best,
at least by way of the
statistics and papers that exist.
It's also the one that's
been explored the most.
So one of the reasons
why it's often considered
the most popular or effective
is 'cause it's also been around longer
and it's been explored the most.
Cognitive behavioral therapy in general
is a progressive exposure of the patient
in a very controlled way,
in a clinical setting,
to some of the triggers or the conditions
that would exacerbate bipolar disorder.
Now, earlier I said borderline
personality disorder
has all these triggers
and triggered elements
from the external environment,
whereas bipolar disorder does not.
And that's still true, but
it is the case that somebody with bipolar
can have worse symptoms if life conditions
get worse or more stressful.
So cognitive behavioral therapy,
I mean the discussion about
and sometimes the direct exposure to
anxiety provoking elements of life
can be very helpful for
adjusting the responses
to those otherwise triggering events
and sometimes making the drug treatments
more effective even at lower doses.
There are also forms of therapy
including family-focused therapy,
which is especially important in terms
of bipolar disorder because
family members, provided
that they are not themselves
in a manic episode due to the
close heritability of bipolar disorder,
but family members can
often be excellent windows
into whether or not somebody
is doing well or poorly,
or is veering toward or is emerging from
a manic or depressive episode
because they understand that person,
they have a lot of data,
it could be purely subjective data,
but they have a lot of
exposure to how long
or well somebody's been
sleeping or eating, et cetera.
So family-focused therapy
involves other members
of the person suffering from
bipolar disorder's family,
as well as conversations
about family members
in a way that helps patients
with bipolar disorder navigate,
not just through manic episodes
and depressive episodes,
but start to learn to predict
what are the conditions
psychological, physical, and otherwise
that can trigger bipolar episodes.
And then there's a category of therapy
called interpersonal and
social rhythm therapy.
This is deserving of its
own entire episode really.
Interpersonal and social rhythm therapy,
it's sort of an expansion
on family-focused therapy,
although it's distinct
in certain ways as well,
and really focuses on how
people are relating to others
in their life, and in the workplace,
and in the school environment,
and also within the family, et cetera.
And I should say that a overall theme
that's emerging in
psychiatry and psychology
is to start wherever
possible to incorporate
more of the social aspects
and the interpersonal aspects.
In other words, not just talking to
and examining a patient
as one biological system,
one nervous system, one set
of chemicals, and one life,
but rather a set of
chemicals, neural circuits,
and a life that's
embedded in the chemicals
and neural circuits and
lives of other people.
Just by way of example, you can imagine
that if somebody is in a
very healthy relationship
or a very abusive relationship,
that that's going to strongly impact
the outcomes of manic episodes.
You can imagine that if
the financial situation
is one in which people can
recover from manic episodes,
I didn't mention this
earlier, but I should have,
forgive me, that oftentimes people
who are in a manic episode will go out
and spend immense amounts of money
that they simply cannot afford to lose.
And then the depressive
episodes that, in many cases,
follow are made far worse
by the financial anxiety
and the financial stress that results
from those manic episodes
of spending, et cetera.
And then of course, this carries over
to sexual promiscuity where
people might be dealing
with unwanted pregnancy or STIs, or
very fractured interpersonal dynamics
with existing or new relationships.
I mean, you can imagine
how these manic episodes,
as well as the depressive episodes
can really wick out into an
enormous amount of destruction,
which brings us back
to the initial criteria
of BP-1 and BP-2 is that
these manic episodes
are not a good thing.
These depressive episodes
They create this sense of euphoria
in the person experiencing mania,
or they create this sense
that anything is possible.
But at the end of the day,
and actually every day,
these episodes are quite maladaptive.
They really destroy people's lives.
And it's not just the life of the person
that's suffering from bipolar disorder.
And so hence cognitive behavioral therapy,
family-focused therapy and interpersonal
and social rhythm
therapies are the primary
three talk therapies that
are most often combined
with drug therapies in order to try
and really reduce the harm.
It's really all about harm reduction
from manic episodes and
depressive episodes.
One very exciting and emerging treatment
that does show great promise,
and in some cases, great outcomes,
for bipolar disorder is, believe it or not
electric shock therapy.
Electric shock therapy may sound barbaric,
and in fact, it tends to look barbaric,
although this is done in
the controlled setting
of a hospital.
If any of you have seen One
Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest,
the final scene or near
final scene in that movie
was Jack Nicholson with
the sort of bite protector
in his mouth and getting
electric shock therapy,
and it's as the name suggests,
it's a kind of inducing
a global seizure, either low
level or grand mal type seizure
in the patient's brain and nervous system.
You might ask, well, why
would one want to do that?
Well, it turns out that
this is a well-established,
and in many cases, very
effective treatment
for major depression.
Electric shock therapy is generally used
for treatment-resistant depression.
So these are people that
have no positive response
or ongoing positive
response to drug therapies
or other therapies.
Electric shock therapy is thought to work
primarily by stimulating the massive kind
of indiscriminate release of things
like serotonin, dopamine, acetylcholine,
a huge variety of neuromodulators,
as well as things like BDNF,
brain-derived neurotrophic factor
which then allows
neuroplasticity to take place.
Again, BDNF being permissive
for neuroplasticity.
The problem with ECT is
that it's really only useful
for treatment-resistant depression,
it doesn't actually
target the manic aspects
of bipolar depression
and bipolar disorder,
but nonetheless, is used when
drug treatments don't work.
Some of the negatives of
electric shock therapy
or electric convulsive therapy, ECT,
is the proper acronym
and way it's described
is that it's quite invasive, right?
This is something that you
need to go to the hospital for
and oftentimes there's some
inpatient care required
after the electric convulsive therapy.
It's a fairly high cost,
especially for those that
don't have insurance.
And of course it requires anesthesia.
For most people, that's
not going to be a problem,
but for many people
that could be a problem.
And there's often some
associated memory loss.
And so the memory loss,
the invasive nature of ECT
and the cost oftentimes rule
out ECT for most patients,
and that's why it's sort of a late stage
or kind of last resort type thing
for treatment-resistant depression.
Nowadays ketamine type
therapy is done repeatedly
or other treatments, for instance,
transcranial magnetic stimulation
which is basically non-invasive,
it's a coil that's placed on the outside
of the skull, excuse me.
And we can more accurately refer to it
as repetitive or rTMS,
repetitive transcranial
magnetic stimulation.
Transcranial magnetic
stimulation is a tool
that allows researchers and clinicians
to reduce the amount of activity
in specific neural circuits.
So they can actually
target the magnetic field
to particular neural
circuits to reduce activity
in those neural circuits.
Again, it's minimally invasive.
It has been shown to be effective
in both increasing
neuroplasticity in positive ways,
as well as reducing depressive episodes
and in a few instances in reducing
the amplitude or the
intensity of manic episodes
in people with bipolar disorder.
The problem is it's still
a very early technique.
There aren't a lot of
clinics and labs doing it.
I'm starting to see more advertisements,
literally commercial clinics
that are advertising rTMS or TMS.
I encourage you to approach
those clinics with caution.
I'm of the mind that if those clinics
are not either closely
or maybe even distantly
associated with a research institution
that's really up on the latest of rTMS,
you'd be wise to at
least do your research,
and explore, talk to other patients
who've done these treatments,
but certainly in university hospitals
and in clinical settings
and research settings,
rTMS is being used as
a way to, for instance,
reduce the activity of
certain limbic circuitries
so that people are just overall
less excitable and manic
or to activate because it can also be used
for activation now of
certain neural circuits.
Activate, for instance,
the parietal inputs,
the top down control
over the limbic system.
This is all happening right now.
So we have ECT, repetitive TMS or rTMS,
and then as I mentioned
earlier, ketamine therapies,
most of those are targeted
toward the depressive aspects
of manic depression.
So for people with bipolar disorder
that doesn't include depression,
those are going to be less effective,
but overall, it's going
to be the talk therapies
of the sort that we discussed
earlier, or a moment ago.
Plus drug treatments,
almost always lithium will be explored,
plus some treatments for
the depressive episodes
in particular if those
depressive episodes are present.
Nowadays, there's a lot of
excitement about psilocybin
which is a psychedelic.
In the US, psilocybin is still illegal.
It is not legal, meaning you
can get in a lot of trouble
for possessing it, certainly
for selling it, et cetera.
But psilocybin is being explored
as a clinical therapy in
certain laboratory settings
in particular, at Johns
Hopkins School of Medicine.
It's being explored in human patients
for the treatment of major depression,
for OCD I believe as well,
but certainly for major depression
and for eating disorders.
And it seems from the
initial wave of publications
from that work done by the
incredible Matthew Johnson
or Dr. Matthew Johnson, who was a guest
on this podcast before,
he's also been on the Tim Ferris Podcast,
he's been on the Lex Fridman Podcast.
Dr. Matthew Johnson came on this podcast,
he's talked about some of the work
with psilocybin for the
treatment of depression.
Very impressive results there.
And as you can imagine,
very impressive results
for the major depressive
episodes for bipolar.
However, at least to my knowledge,
again, to my knowledge,
there have not been any
controlled clinical trials
exploring psilocybin
for the mania associated
with bipolar disorder.
If someone out there is aware
of those clinical trials,
please let me know.
I'll do an update in a future podcast,
but right now, no knowledge from me
about psilocybin clinical trials
for the manic component
of bipolar disorder.
A number of people are
probably also going to wonder
about whether or not cannabis
or medical marijuana is
useful for bipolar disorder.
To address this, I looked
to some previous lectures
and some clinicians at
Stanford Psychiatry.
This question was asked of
them, and as it turns out,
cannabis does not seem to be effective
for the treatment of the manic phases
of bipolar disorder or for the treatment
of the major depressive component.
The only treatment perhaps,
or I should say the only situation perhaps
in which it might be useful,
and this is what was relayed to me,
is that it may help with
sleep in certain people
that are having trouble with insomnia,
though nowadays, it's far
more common for people
in manic episodes to be prescribed things
like Trazodone or other
benzos, benzodiazepines
in order to try and get sleep
within the manic episodes.
And benzodiazepines and
Trazodone, et cetera,
work largely through the
so-called GABA system.
This is a neurotransmitter
that causes reductions in
excitability of neurons,
hence why it's being used
to try and calm people down
and allow them to sleep
during their manic episodes.
So not a lot, or essentially no data,
supporting the use of
cannabis for the treatment
of bipolar disorder, per se,
nor data supporting the use of psilocybin
for the treatment of
bipolar disorder per se.
But I realize, as I say that,
that there are going to
be a number of people
that may have had positive
or negative experiences
with cannabis or psilocybin
as they relate to bipolar disorder.
So please, if you're
willing or comfortable,
put that, if you're comfortable,
into the comment section on YouTube.
And of course, if you
are aware of any studies
on cannabis or psilocybin
showing positive outcomes
for the treatment bipolar
disorder, please provide links
or PubMed ideas to those, I'd
love to peruse those studies.
There are two naturopathic,
or I should say,
nutrition, supplement-based
approaches to bipolar disorder.
They get talked about a
lot, and one of them shows
some interesting promise,
or effectiveness even,
in a limited context.
Before marching into this description
of these two compounds, in
fact before even mentioning
these two compounds,
I do want to emphasize
what's been said and written
about over and over again
and what was relayed to me
from expert psychiatrists.
It is not wise to rely
purely on talk therapy
or on natural approaches to the treatment
of bipolar disorder given
the intensity of the disorder
and the high propensity for suicide risk
in people with bipolar disorder,
it is a chemical and
neural circuit disruption,
and it needs to be dealt with head on
through the appropriate chemistry
and prescription drug approaches
from a board-certified psychiatrist.
I don't say this to protect me,
I say this truly to protect
those who either suffer from
or think they may suffer
from bipolar disorder
or if you know someone
who you think might suffer
from a bipolar disorder.
Now, all that is not to say
that there aren't useful
lifestyle interventions
that can support people
with bipolar disorder.
So I just briefly want to mention those.
And again, I'm lifting the
statements I'm about to make
from some excellent online lectures
from psychiatrists at
Stanford and elsewhere,
which essentially say that,
of course, of course, of course,
getting better sleep,
getting adequate exercise,
getting proper nutrition, having quality,
healthy, social interactions,
even getting regular sunlight in the day
and avoiding bright light at night,
all of those things are
going to braid together
to support the nervous
system and the psyche
of somebody with bipolar disorder,
but they braid together
to support the psyche
and the neurochemistry
and the neural circuits
of anybody and everybody.
So they have generally a modulatory effect
that is they're indirectly shifting
the likelihood that somebody
might have an episode,
or the intensity of an episode,
in particular, the depressive episodes.
You can imagine how someone who's heading
into a depressive episode,
maybe they're on a lower
amount of medication
or they haven't yet medicated
for the depressive episode of bipolar.
And now they're making sure
or their family is making sure
that they're getting exercise, sunshine,
eating correctly, social
engagement, et cetera.
Of course it makes perfect sense
why they would have
perhaps a shallower drop
into depression or maybe an offset
of depressive episode.
That said, most all, if not all people
with bipolar disorder are likely to need
some sort of drug therapy intervention
in order to help them.
So lifestyle factors are always important
in all individuals,
those suffering from
psychiatric conditions or not.
But in some conditions
of the mind and body,
those lifestyle interventions
can have a greater effect
in offsetting symptoms,
whereas in bipolar disorder,
I think it's naive, and
in fact, wrong to say
that lifestyle interventions alone
are going to prevent,
especially the extreme forms
of mania and depression.
Again, bipolar disorder being so serious
and carrying such high suicide risk,
we just have to point
this out again and again.
Now with that said,
there are two substances
generally found as supplements,
although there are other
sources of them as well,
including within nutritional sources
that have been shown, at
least in some studies,
to be pretty effective
in adjusting the symptoms
of bipolar disorder, and
those two things are inositol
and omega-3 fatty acids.
Now inositol is a compound
that is taken for a variety of reasons.
It's something we've talked
about on the podcast before.
I personally take inositol not because
I have bipolar disorder,
in fact I am quite lucky
that I don't have bipolar disorder,
but I take inositol, a 900
milligrams of myo-inositol
every third night or so in
order to improve my sleep.
It's something that I've
added to my sleep stack.
It's something that I
found greatly enhances
the depth and quality of my sleep.
And if I wake up in
the middle of the night
to use the bathroom, et cetera,
it's greatly enhanced my
ability to fall back asleep
when I want to go back to sleep.
It also seems to have a fairly potent
anti-anxiety effect during the day.
And as I discussed in our episode
about obsessive-compulsive disorder,
inositol has been used at high dosages,
again, I should say
myo-inositol has been used
at high dosages, at levels
of even 10, 18 grams,
those are massive dosages by the way,
to deal with certain symptoms
of OCD to limited success.
And I should mention that
high dosages of 10 or 18 grams
of inositol can cause a lot
of gastric discomfort, et cetera.
If you want to learn more about inositol
and its various uses, I encourage
you to go to examine.com
where there's the so-called
Human Effect Matrix,
and that Human Effects
Matrix will describe the many
places in which myo-inositol
and other forms of inositol
have been show shown to be effective
in, for instance, reducing anxiety,
enhancing sleep and on and on.
Myo-inositol is important
because myo-inositol,
and we can just say inositol,
is related to so-called
second messenger pathways.
I don't want to get too deep
into second messenger pathways,
but when certain substances
bind, like neurotransmitters
to a receptor on a cell surface,
oftentimes those receptors
themselves will open
and allow the passage of ions
and other things into a cell.
Oftentimes they will engage
what are called second messenger systems
that is they will trigger
mechanisms within the cell
to then go do other things.
This is probably something
we should get into
in real detail in a future episode
for those of you that
really want to nerd out
on cell-cell signaling, which
is a favorite topic of mine.
In any case, inositol is related
to a number of so-called
second messenger systems,
this handoff, or this kind of stimulating
of changes within a cell
that can inspire changes
in what's called membrane fluidity,
can actually make the membranes of cells,
the outside fence around a cell,
which is made up of fatty stuff,
it can change the fluidity,
meaning how readily things can float
around in the membrane.
You know, we think of cells as very rigid,
like there's a cell, there's a neuron,
or there's a immune cell,
but actually those cells
have a fatty outside,
in particular neurons
have a fatty outside.
It's a thin fatty outside,
it's called the cell membrane,
and things are floating
around in that cell membrane,
but it's kind of like jello
that hasn't quite fixed.
And so things like receptors
moving into the synapse
or moving out the synapse
for homeostatic plasticity,
things like the ability for certain genes
to be turned on in a
cell or not turned on,
can depend a lot on
things that are happening
in that cell membrane and how readily
things move around in the cell membrane.
One way to think about this whole picture
of membrane fluidity is that just imagine
that everyone of your
cells has this layer,
it's kind of a gelatinous-like layer
and there are lots of little rafts
floating around in there, but those rafts
are able to move more quickly
from one place to
another, or get more stuck
at one place or another,
depending on how set
that jello is.
Inositol
and lithium,
and as we'll talk about
next, omega-3 fatty acids
seem to change the fluidity
of those membranes,
in other words, they
allow things to move in
and out of those membranes
more readily or not.
And this is no surprise given that
those membranes are
made out of fatty stuff.
In particular, the membranes of neurons
are what called a lipid bilayer,
it's two layers of fat,
bi means two, lipid, fat.
And omega-3 fatty acids
of the sort that are found
in certain fish, and that
fatty fish in particular,
and that are found in fish oil
and cod liver oil, et cetera.
Omega-3 fatty acids, when we ingest them
are used for a lot of different things,
but they can be readily
incorporated into pathways
or directly incorporated
into cell membranes,
changing the way those cell membranes work
and if those cell membranes
are the cell membranes
of neurons, changing the
way that neurons work.
So the ability for fish oil,
and in particular, the
omega-3 fatty acids,
which come in varieties like EPA and DHA,
we'll talk about that in a moment,
have been explored at
relatively high dosages
for their ability to
offset some of the effects
of mania and to offset the effects
of depressive episodes
in bipolar disorder.
And actually, the data there
are pretty impressive, although,
although they are varied,
meaning you will find several studies,
and I'll mention a few,
that found no effect
of omega-3 supplementation
through fish oil,
usually it's capsuled fish oil,
although fish oil can
also be taken, excuse me,
in liquid form.
Oftentimes taking in liquid form
is the more cost efficient way to do it.
Taking in capsule form is the
more palatable way to do it,
because fish oil for a lot
of people doesn't taste good.
But nonetheless,
there are several studies that have shown
that supplementing with fish
oil or omega-3 fatty acids
at levels of, for instance,
four grams per day
for a period of time,
this is a study that we
will link in the show notes,
This is Murphy at al. 2012.
This is a fatty acid
supplementation of 70% EPA to DHA
actually worsen symptoms of mania
over a period of about 16 weeks,
which on the face of it
makes it seem like, okay,
omega-3 fatty acid supplementation,
very likely to not be
good for bipolar disorder.
And yet that was the manic phase.
When one looks at some
of the other studies
of omega-3 fatty acid supplementation,
there is, for instance, a
study published in 1999,
this is a much higher
dosage supplementation
with omega-3 fatty acid,
this is a 9.6 grams of fish
oil per day for four months.
And then actually greatly reduced symptoms
of bipolar depression
compared to the control
group which received olive oil,
olive oil is a different form
of fat, monounsaturated fat
but doesn't contain as much
of the omega-3 fatty acids and so forth.
So 9.6 grams of fish oil
per day over four months
is a lot of fish oil
to be ingesting on a given day.
This was a double blind study.
This was only carried out, I
should mention, in 30 subjects,
but it was males and females.
And the age range was pretty broad,
anywhere from 18 all the
way up to 64 years of age,
which is important given
the sort of longitudinal
or changes over time,
that one sees in bipolar disorder.
Here's the major takeaway,
supplementing with high dose omega-3s
does seem to be beneficial
for a good number of people
with bipolar disorder.
However, again, I want
to highlight, however,
it should not be viewed as
the only treatment approach
for bipolar disorder.
This goes back to what I was saying before
about the essential
need, in most every case,
for high potency
prescription drug treatments
prescribed by board
certified psychiatrists
for bipolar disorder.
However, omega-3 supplementation
does seem to improve
or reduce the depressive symptoms
in the major depressive
episodes of bipolar.
And there are a couple studies,
and we'll link to these
in the show notes as well,
that show that it may even improve
some of the manic episodes as well,
meaning it reduces some
of the manic symptoms.
Now I say all this from
a place of great caution,
because I know, especially
for listeners of this podcast,
there's a lot of interest
in the behavioral tools,
the supplement-based tools,
the nutrition tools that can
support bipolar disorder,
but I don't think I can
overemphasize enough
that especially for bipolar disorder
and the great risk of
suicide and suffering
and inappropriate spending,
or I should say maladaptive
spending and impulsivity
that's associated with bipolar disorder,
that it's hard to imagine a scenario
in which just talk therapy and fish oil
and lifestyle interventions
are going to completely
suppress or treat bipolar disorder.
People with bipolar disorder
really need to consider
the full picture of treatments,
the drug treatments,
the
talk therapy treatments,
and lifestyle treatments,
and nutraceutical, or we can say
supplement-based treatments
such as omega-3 supplementation
as a full and necessary picture
for dealing with their illness.
I'd be remiss, however,
if I didn't emphasize that
the omega-3 fatty acid
supplementation
is very interesting, not just in terms of
the subjective effects,
people saying they feel less depressed
or able to sleep better, or
maybe even some reduction
in manic symptoms,
there's actually been some
really good brain imaging
to try and understand how
omega-3 fatty acid treatments
are actually changing the brains
and neural circuits of
people with bipolar.
And I will put a reference to this.
This is a paper that was published
in the American Journal Psychiatry.
It's entitled, Omega-3
Fatty Acid Treatment
and T2 Whole Brain Relaxation
Times in Bipolar Disorder.
I don't have the opportunity
to go into a lot of detail
right now about what T2 whole
brain relaxation times are,
but basically when people go into a MRI
or f, functional MRI scanner,
excuse me,
magnetic resonance imaging scanner,
what they're getting essentially is pulses
of magnetic fields and the
way that brain structures
and neural activity can be evaluated
has a lot to do with
the sort of spinning, or not sort of,
it has to do with the spinning
and the relaxation times
of different elements,
literally the protons and
electrons within the neurons,
so it gets really detailed there,
and the relaxation time
is essentially looking
at how quickly some of that
spinning returns to rest.
And in particular,
the fact that the relaxation
times are different
for aqueous, that is liquid,
versus lipid, fatty versus other
components of brain tissue.
And basically what this study shows
is that the membranes of neurons
within the brains of these people
with bipolar disorder,
showed more fluidity,
more ability of things to move
in and around the membranes,
which we know is an important
component of neuroplasticity
in bipolar subjects that were treated
with omega-3 fatty acids as compared
to bipolar subjects that did not receive
omega-3 fatty acids.
And fortunately this study also include
a healthy comparison group where
they could essentially find
that people with bipolar
disorder who supplemented
with omega-3 had changes
at the cellular level
and the neural circuit level
that brought their brains
and neural circuits closer to that
of the healthy comparison subjects.
So while I don't want to
point to omega-3 fatty acid
supplementation as the
be-all end-all of treatment
for bipolar disorder, certainly it is not,
it does have a strong
mechanistic basis for
its possible support of neural circuitry,
of neuroplasticity, and in particular,
the ability to make
changes in cell membranes
that are very reminiscent of some
of the neural circuit changes
and changes in membrane fluidity
that are seen with lithium treatment
and other known
prescription drug treatments
that have been established now for decades
to be very effective for bipolar disorder.
So what that says is that
omega-3 supplementation,
while not the only intervention
that one should consider
is something to consider and
talk about with your doctor
and it's operating in powerful ways.
It's not just that it's
changing, for instance,
your gut microbiome, which is powerful,
but is indirect to the brain,
it does seem to be having
direct effects on neurons
and neural circuits.
Before we begin to conclude our discussion
about bipolar disorder,
I want to talk a little bit
about this word, disorder,
and this is a theme
that doesn't just relate
to bipolar disorder,
but other psychiatric disorders as well.
And when we think of a disorder,
we think of something that
is really detrimental to us.
Something that really impairs
our ability to function
in work, in school, in relationships,
and really starts to pull
down our health status
in a variety of ways.
And certainly bipolar
disorder meets those criteria.
However,
there is this idea that
things like bipolar disorder,
even things like
schizophrenia in some cases
are responsible for some
of the creative aspects
or the creative works
that have been observed
and carried out by human
beings for many centuries.
And believe it or not, there are good data
to support the fact that
certain aspects of mania
are associated with creativity.
Now, we are long overdue for
an episode about creativity,
its neural circuit
basis, its chemical basis
here on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
and certainly we will
have that conversation.
But in the meantime, I'd like
to just briefly touch upon
this idea that certain
occupations are associated
with a higher incidence
of bipolar depression.
And in fact,
it's been explored at a research level.
There are data pointed to the fact
that certain individuals
of certain occupations
tend to be more creative
and that creativity
is associated with, again, associated,
this isn't causal, it's
associated, correlated with
higher levels or incidents
of bipolar depression
and maybe even other forms of depression.
So this is a study
looking at mood disorders
in eminent individuals.
So these are people that are
not just good at what they do,
but are exceptional at what they do,
and explored the percentage
of people in given professions
with either depression or mania.
And this was actually a data set gleaned
from more than a thousand
20th Century Westerners
based on their biographies that were
reviewed by other people.
So it's a bit of an indirect measurement.
This isn't psychiatrist
data, this is data,
or I should say these are data
that were compiled from self reports
or from reads of self reports.
And they explored a number
of different professions.
So for instance, they looked
at people in the military
or people who were professional athletes
or natural scientists
or social scientists,
people who occupied
positions in public office,
or were musical performers,
artists, nonfiction
writers, poetry, et cetera.
There are a lot of professions here.
I will post this or I'll post a link to it
in the show note captions
for you to peruse,
but I'll just give you
a sense of the extremes
on this graph because
they're very interesting.
Turns out that if you were
to look at the profession
or I should say among the
professions they looked at
in this study, 'cause they
didn't look at all professions,
those in the military and those
who are professional athletes or had jobs
in the social or natural
sciences, of those,
there was a lower percentage of those
that had depression or mania.
In some cases like those who
were professional athletes
didn't seem to have, there
was no incidence of mania,
at least in this dataset,
whereas at the opposite
extreme of the graph,
those that were poets, so
these are eminent individuals,
people that were exceptional poets,
exceptional fiction writers,
exceptional artists or
non-fiction writers,
well there, especially for the poets,
you find that as many as 90%
of these very successful poets
had either depression or mania.
As high as 90%, that's incredible.
Contrast that with military
where it's as few as 10%
or professional athletes
where it's as few as 20%,
and for the professional
athletes, as I mentioned before,
none of them had mania.
So does this mean that being a poet
will make you manic or depressed?
Well, first of all, let's
look at the poetry category.
It turns out that 75%
of these eminent poets,
these highly accomplished
poets had major depression,
whereas only about 20% of
those poets had manic episodes.
So again, it's not that being a poet
is going to give you mania,
certainly we're not saying that,
it's not that being a poet is
going to give you depression,
but it turns out that
people with depression
and people with depression and mania
seem to gravitate towards poetry
or at least are very successful at poetry.
Again, associative, correlative,
no causal relationship here.
But it is really striking to see
how the creative
occupations, poetry, fiction,
art, non-fiction writing,
even though non-fiction
writing is about non-fiction,
it's still creative, music
composition, theater,
much higher incidents
of things like mania.
In fact, for the people
in theater, the actors,
even though the overall
occurrence of depression
and mania is lower
than that in poets, the fraction of those
individuals that have
mania is exceedingly high.
It's about 30% of those
that they looked at
who are actors,
have manic episodes or
have full blown mania.
So I'm referring to these
data because first of all,
I find them incredibly interesting,
right up until now we've been talking
about bipolar disorder
and other mood disorders
for their maladaptive effects.
And again, they're extremely maladaptive,
much, much higher instance
of suicide, et cetera,
but we'd be wrong to
say that certain aspects
of manic episodes don't
lend themselves well
to creativity or that certain aspects
of major depression don't
lend themselves well
to creativity or to the performing arts
or to poetry.
That said, in no way, shape or form,
do I believe that being
depressed is a good thing
or that being manic is a good thing.
Again, we return to the
basic foundational criteria
for bipolar disorder, major depression
which is that the pressured
speech, the not sleeping,
the incredible increases in energy
and the flights of ideas
are generally not going to lead,
or I think it's fair to say,
are not going to lead to good places.
In fact, often lead to bad places.
But we would also be wrong if
we didn't consider the fact
that there is a somewhat
inextricable relationship
between mania and creativity.
And it could be that hypomania
or brief periods of mania,
maybe even an hour a day
or 30 minutes a day of
composing or writing poetry,
maybe even some of the lows that we feel,
some of the sadness, some of the grief,
some of the nostalgia that we feel
provided that it's not pathologic,
that it's not persistent
for the four or seven days
that are diagnostic of bipolar 2
and bipolar 1 disorder respectively,
well, then we can start
to view emotional states
as something that can
actually lend themselves
to positive outcomes and
maybe even to creativity
and to improved occupations.
So it's important that
we have a nuanced view
of what sadness versus depression
versus major depression are,
it's important that we distinguish between
being erratic, being very energized,
and full blown bipolar disorder.
And I raise this for
another reason as well.
Nowadays, it's very common
to hear people saying, ah, you know,
that person is OCD.
Well, on the episode about OCD
that I did a few weeks back,
that you can find if you
like at hubermanlab.com,
in that episode, I pointed out that OCD,
obsessive-compulsive
disorder is very maladaptive.
I think it's number seven, as I recall
on the list of debilitating diseases,
all diseases in terms
of lost time at work,
suffering relationships, et cetera.
So it's a really serious condition.
And yet we often hear, oh,
that person is obsessive.
And as I pointed out,
there is obsessive-compulsive
personality disorder.
And then there is
obsessive-compulsive tendencies,
which actually benefit people,
but that is distinct from
obsessive-compulsive disorder
as a clinically diagnosed thing.
Similarly, we hear that, oh,
somebody's being bipolar.
You know, they're all over the place.
They're bipolar.
Well, that's a very subjective
label that people give
one another in passing,
more and more often I'm hearing this,
and yet bipolar disorder,
whether or not it's BP-1 or BP-2
are extremely maladaptive
and extremely associated
with high suicide risk.
So while I'm not here to police people,
I'm not certainly not the word police
or the nomenclature police,
I do think that whether or
not you refer to people as OCD
or as bipolar, et
cetera, that's up to you,
it's not my place to say,
but I do think it's important
that all of us understand
that these psychiatric
conditions carry with them
tremendous maladaptive weight.
So today we've really done a deep dive
into bipolar disorder
and to both the manic
and the depressive components
that are present or can be present
in bipolar disorder
and the different forms
of bipolar disorder and
some of the major treatments
for bipolar disorder,
in particular lithium and
its underlying mechanisms
and some of the neural
circuit and chemical basis
and neuroplasticity
basis of the treatments
for bipolar disorder, in
particular homeostatic scaling
or homeostatic plasticity.
All of that, of course, is
relevant to bipolar disorder
and I hope will be useful
in your understanding
and maybe even in your
pursuit of treatments
for bipolar depression,
bipolar disorder for you
or other people.
I also hope that it will be
useful in your understanding
of how brain circuits work
in normal conditions or in conditions
where there is no disease state
or maladaptive conditions.
Homeostatic plasticity
is present in all of us.
Membrane fluidity due to how
easily things move around
in the surface, the fatty
layers on the outside of neurons
and the movement of receptors
in and out of neurons
that is present in all of us.
The influence of omega-3 fatty acids
is central to that discussion.
As is the discussion about
various drug treatments
because even if you're
not somebody who's taking
a drug treatment or who is
pursuing a drug treatment
for bipolar disorder or
another psychiatric condition,
your serotonin levels,
your dopamine levels,
your acetylcholine
levels, all of these play
into what we call your
mental and physical health.
In fact, if any of you are interested
in the various categories
of neuromodulators
and tools to adjust those neuromodulators
under more standard
non-disease conditions,
we did an episode
on neurochemicals and how to control them.
You can find that at hubermanlab.com
along with all other episodes
of the Huberman Lab Podcast.
I should mention everything is timestamped
So you can navigate to the specific topics
and tools of interest to you.
And meanwhile, I just
want to thank all of you
for joining me on this voyage
through the biology and the
treatments for bipolar disorder.
I do hope you found it beneficial
both for yourself and for others.
I just want to remind
people that bipolar disorder
is an extremely serious condition.
If you suspect that you
have bipolar disorder
or you know somebody who does,
please make sure that you or they talk
to a qualified health professional.
If you're learning from and
are enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel,
that's a terrific, zero
cost way to support us.
In addition, please
subscribe to the podcast
on Spotify and Apple.
And on both Spotify and Apple,
you can leave us up to a five star review.
If you have suggestions about topics
you'd like us to cover or guests
you'd like us to interview
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
or if you have questions
about material already covered
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
please put that in the
comment section on YouTube,
we do read all the comments.
In addition, please check
out the sponsors mentioned
at the beginning of today's episode,
that's the best way to
support this podcast.
During today's episode, and certainly
on many previous episodes
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we talk about supplements.
Once again, while
supplements aren't necessary
for everybody, many people derive
tremendous benefit from them for things
like enhancing sleep and
focus and hormone support
and other aspects of
mental and physical health
and performance.
As I mentioned at the
beginning of today's episode,
the Huberman Lab Podcast
is happy to announce
that we partnered with
Momentous Supplements.
If you'd like to see our supplements
and the ones that we designed
in concert with Momentous,
you can go to livemomentous.com/huberman.
Please also check out
Huberman Lab on social media.
We are hubermanlab on both
Twitter and Instagram.
In both places, I cover science
and science-related tools,
some of which overlaps with the content
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
but much of which is distinct
from the information covered
on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
We also have a newsletter,
it's called the Neural Network Newsletter.
It's completely zero cost
and it contains summaries of podcasts
and some actionable
protocols from each podcast.
You can sign up for it by
going to hubermanlab.com,
go to the menu and click on
Neural Network Newsletter.
You can also see some examples
of previous newsletters there.
I should mention that by signing up,
you do provide your email,
but we do not share
your email with anybody.
And again, it is completely zero cost.
So once again, thank
you for joining me today
for our discussion about the biology
and treatment of bipolar disorder.
And last, but certainly not least,
thank you for your interest in science.
[upbeat rock music]