- [Andrew Huberman] Welcome to
the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools
for everyday life.
[bright upbeat music]
- I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a Professor of
Neurobiology and Ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today, we continue our
discussion of the senses.
And the senses we are going to discuss
are pain and pleasure.
Pain and pleasure reflect two
opposite ends of a continuum,
a continuum that involves
detection of things in our skin
and the perception, the understanding
of what those events are.
Our skin is our largest sensory organ
and our largest organ indeed.
It is much larger than any of
the other organs in our body.
And it's an odd organ
if you think about it,
it has so many functions.
It acts as a barrier between our organs
and the outside world,
it harbors neurons nerve
cells that allow us
to detect things like
light touch, or temperature
or pressure of various kinds.
And it's an organ that
we hang ornaments on.
People put earrings in their ears.
People decorate their
skin with tattoos and inks
and other things.
And it's an organ that
allows us to experience
either great pain or great pleasure.
So it's a multifaceted organ and it's one
that our brain needs to make
sense of in a multifaceted way.
So today we're going to discuss all that.
And most importantly, how you
can experience more pleasure
and less pain by
understanding these pathways.
We will also discuss things you can do,
and if you wish things you can take
that will allow you to
experience more pleasure
and less pain in response
to a variety of different experiences.
Before I go any further,
I want to highlight a particularly
exciting area of science
that relates to the skin and to sensing
of pleasure and pain,
but has everything to do with motivation.
Motivation is something that
many people struggle with,
not everybody, but most
people experience dips
and peaks in their motivation
even if they really want something.
How should we think about
these changes in motivation?
What do they reflect?
Well at a very basic level,
they reflect fluctuations
changes in the levels of a
chemical called dopamine.
Most of us have heard of dopamine.
Dopamine is a neuromodulator
meaning it modulates
or changes the way that
neurons nerve cells work.
Most of us have heard that dopamine
is the molecule of pleasure.
However, that is incorrect.
Dopamine is a molecule of
motivation and anticipation.
To illustrate how dopamine works,
I want to highlight
some very important work
largely carried out by the laboratory
of a guy named Wolfram Schultz.
The Schultz Laboratory has done dozens
of excellent experiments
on the dopamine system
and have identified something called
reward prediction error.
Although in some sense
you can think about it
as reward prediction variance.
Changes in the levels
of dopamine depending
on whether or not you expect a reward
and whether or not you get the reward.
So I'm going to make this very simple.
Dopamine is released
into the brain and body
and generally makes us feel
activated and motivated,
as if we have energy to pursue a goal.
And it is released into the brain and body
in anticipation of a reward.
Measurements of dopamine have been made
in animals and humans.
And what you find is that
when we anticipate a reward,
dopamine is released,
we will put in the work
to achieve that reward.
That work could be mental
work or physical work,
but when the reward arrives,
dopamine levels drop
back down to baseline.
That's right.
When we receive a reward,
dopamine levels go back down to baseline.
So the way to envision this
as you can just imagine
a sort of increase in dopamine
as we anticipate something
we're working towards it,
we're working towards a goal.
We're excited about seeing
somebody or meeting somebody
or receiving some reward
and then the reward comes
and dopamine goes down.
Now that's all fine and good,
but there is a way to
get much more dopamine
out of that process and therefore a way
to have much more
motivation, energy, and focus
because those are the
consequences of elevated dopamine.
The way to do that is to
not deliver the reward
on an expected schedule.
So experiments have been done
where there's an anticipation
of a reward, there's work,
and then the reward
only arrives every other
or every third about of work, okay?
So this would be like
getting a pat on the head.
If you're a dog or a,
perhaps a child or an adult,
or getting a monetary reward
only for every third project
or every third race that you win.
Pick any kind of goal.
It doesn't matter.
These molecules don't care
about what you're pursuing.
They are a common currency of
different types of activities.
That's a regular reward schedule,
and it will not alter the
pattern of dopamine release
that I described before.
However, if the reward
arrives intermittently
almost randomly, so
you anticipate a reward
as a maybe it might come, it might come.
Then you work, work, work,
work, work, no reward.
You repeat the work, work,
work, work, work, work,
and then you get a reward.
So some trials, you do
some trials, you don't,
and it's completely random.
Under those conditions, the amplitude,
the amount of dopamine that's
released into your system
and the motivation to
continue working hard
or playing whatever kind
of game you're playing,
doubles or triples.
And this is the basis of
things like slot machines
and gambling.
And this is why so many
people will give so much
of their money up to casinos
and the casinos always win.
Sometimes people walk away with more money
than they came to the casino with,
but the vast majority of the time,
the house wins as they say.
And it's because they understand
intermittent reward schedules.
And you can apply this to stay motivated
in your own pursuits.
Rather than thinking about
the pleasure of a reward,
understand that dopamine
is released in response
to anticipation reward, and
that is the fuel for work.
And every once in awhile at
random remove the reward.
That's the way to continue
to stay motivated.
Not to reward every action or every goal.
And this is also true,
if you're trying to train up
children or train up players
on a team, you should
not celebrate every win.
I know that's a little counter-intuitive,
we're going to go more into
the biology of dopamine
and how it relates to the pleasure system
later on in the podcast,
but for now understand
intermittent reward schedules
harness the biology of dopamine
in ways that can allow you
essentially infinite motivation over time.
Before I go any further,
I want to acknowledge that
this podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer information
about science and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the sponsors
of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I've long been a believer in
getting regular blood work done
for the simple reason that
many, if not all of the factors
that impact your immediate
and long-term health
can only be analyzed from
a quality blood test.
And nowadays with the advent of DNA tests,
you can get further
knowledge into the mechanisms
that are going on in your body
and how those mechanisms are changing
as they relate to metabolism and hormones
and other aspects that
profoundly impact your wellbeing.
The problem with most
blood tests, however,
is that you get information
back and it will tell you
whether or not your levels
of something are higher, low,
or within range, but it doesn't
give you any directives.
It doesn't tell you what to
do with that information.
With InsideTracker has
this wonderful feature.
It's a very easy to use
dashboard that has suggestions
about lifestyle factors, exercise,
nutrition, supplementation, et cetera,
that one could take in order
to adjust those numbers
according to your personal goals.
So the whole thing is made very easy.
In fact, they can come to
your home to do the blood test
and DNA test if you like.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman.
And if you do that you'll get 25% off
any of InsideTracker's plans.
Just use the code huberman@checkout.
And I should also mention that
through August 15th, 2021,
you can get a free inner age test.
That's a measure of your biological age
according to your DNA and other factors
with any purchase from
InsideTracker store.
So go to insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off
any of InsideTracker's plans and up to up
and through August 15th, you
can get a free inner age test.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Helix Sleep.
Helix makes mattresses and pillows
that are ideally suited
to your sleep needs.
Everybody's different.
Some people sleep on their sides,
some people sleep on their stomach,
some people sleep on their back,
some people run warm during the night,
some people run cold.
If you go to the Helix's
website, helixsleep.com,
you can take a quick two-minute quiz,
and then it will tell you
what your ideal mattress is.
It will match you to your ideal mattress.
I did this and I matched to
the so-called Dusk mattress.
I like a mattress that's
not too firm nor too soft.
I tend to run hot during the night
and I tend to sleep on
my side or on my stomach.
I started sleeping on a Helix mattress
about nine months ago,
and I'm sleeping better
than I ever have before.
So if you're interested
in upgrading your mattress
to one that's ideally
suited to your sleep needs,
go to helixsleep.com/huberman,
take their two-minutes sleep quiz,
and they'll match you to
a customized mattress.
And you'll get up to $200
off that mattress order,
and two free pillows.
They have a 10-year warranty
and you get to try out
the mattress for a 100 nights risk-free,
they'll even pick it up for
you if you don't love it,
but I think you really will love it.
So again, if you're interested,
go to helixsleep.com/huberman
for up to $200 off
and two free pillows.
Today's episode is also brought
to us by Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an
all-in-one vitamin
mineral probiotic drink.
I started drinking Athletic
Greens way back in 2012.
And so I'm delighted that
they're sponsoring the podcast.
The reason I started
drinking Athletic Greens
and the reason why I still drink
it once or even twice a day
is because it takes care of all
my foundational nutritional needs.
It includes vitamins,
minerals, and probiotics
which are important
for the gut microbiome,
this colony of bacteria,
healthy bacteria that we
all have living in our guts.
And when that bacteria is healthy,
our brain functions better,
our immune system functions better.
There is now a lot of
research to support that.
Athletic Greens taste delicious.
I mix mine with water and a
little bit of lemon juice.
And as I mentioned, I drink
it once or twice a day,
usually in the morning and
again in the afternoon.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and claim a special offer.
That special offer is a
year supply of vitamin D3K2.
There's now a robust literature
showing that vitamin D3
is critical for various
aspects of our health,
metabolic health, endocrine
health, et cetera.
And you'll also get
five free travel packs.
When you travel mixing up Athletic Greens
is made really easy by
these little travel packs.
You just put them in a jar
or other a water bottle,
mix it with water.
It's very easy to do on a
plane or in the et cetera.
Again, go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
to get the Athletic Greens,
the five free travel packs
and the year supply of vitamin D3K2.
So let's talk about pleasure and pain.
I think we all intuitively understand
what pleasure and pain are.
Pleasure generally is
a sensation in the body
and in the mind that
leads us to pursue more
of whatever is bringing
about that sensation.
And pain is also a sensation
in the body and in the mind
that in general leads
us to want to withdraw
or move away from some
activity or interaction.
That's not always the case.
Some people actively seek out pain.
Some people somehow
can't seem to engage with
or experience pleasure,
but most people operate on this
basis of pleasure and pain.
Scientists would call
this appetitive behaviors,
meaning behaviors that lead
us to create an appetite
for more of those behaviors
and aversive behaviors,
behaviors that make us want
to move away from something.
The simplest example of
that would be putting your
hand near a hot flame, at some point,
there would be a reflex or a deep desire
to withdraw your hand.
Tasting something delicious
in general makes us want
to eat more of that thing.
Interactions with other
people that we find delicious,
also make us want to interact
with those people more.
None of this is complicated
or sophisticated.
This is simply to illustrate
the fact that pleasure and pain
tend to evoke opposite responses,
opposite behavioral responses
and opposite emotional responses.
So how does that come about?
Well, it really comes
about by an interaction
that starts at one end of
our body, meaning our skin
and the other end of
the organs of our body,
which is deep within the brain.
So let's consider these
two ends of the spectrum
of pleasure and pain
and what they contribute
to those experiences of pleasure and pain.
The organ that we call the
skin, as I mentioned earlier,
is the largest organ in our body.
And throughout that
organ, we have neurons,
little nerve cells.
Now to be really technical about it,
and the way I'd like you to understand it
is that the so-called cell
body meaning the location
of a cell in which the
DNA and other goodies
the kind of central factory of the cell,
that actually sits right
outside your spinal cord.
So all up and down your
spinal cord on either side
are these little blobs of neurons,
little collections of neurons.
They have a name if you'd like to know
for you aficionado or
those who are curious,
they're called DRGs dorsal root ganglia.
A ganglion is just a
collection or clump of cells.
And those DRGs are really
interesting because they send
one branch that we call an axon,
a little wire out to our
skin, also to our muscles
into our organs, but here
we're talking about the skin.
They send a wire out to our
skin and that wire literally
reaches up into the skin.
It's actually in our skin
and they have another wire
from that same cell body
that goes in the opposite direction,
which is up to our brain
and creates connections
within our brain in the
so-called brainstem.
What this means is that
the neuron in your body
that we call the DRG
that sends a wire an axon
to sense what's going on in your big toe
and then sends another axon
in the opposite direction
into the base of your brain,
that is the largest cell in
your entire body of any kind.
Fat cell, muscle cell,
nerve cell, et cetera.
Is extremely long cells.
It can be a meter or more depending
on how tall you happen to be.
So we have these cells that have wires
they go off in two different directions
and the wire that's within
our skin will respond
to any number of different
categories of stimuli.
These wires are positioned within the skin
to respond to mechanical forces.
So maybe light touch,
some will only send electrical activity up
toward the brain in
response to light touch.
Meaning if you press on
the skin really hard,
they don't respond.
You stroke the skin lightly
with your fingertips
or a feather and they
respond very robustly.
Others respond to course
pressure, the hard pressure,
but they won't respond to a
light feather, for instance.
Others respond to temperature.
So they will respond
to the presence of heat
or the presence of cold or
changes in heat and cold.
And still others respond
to other types of stimuli,
like certain chemicals on our skin.
Many of you have probably
experienced the sensation
of eating a hot pepper.
Well, I don't recommend doing this,
but were you to take a
little slice of jalapeno
or other hot pepper, habanero
pepper or something like that
and rub it on your skin, you
would actually feel something
at that location.
And that's because that
pepper doesn't just create
a sensation within your mouth,
it will create a similar
sensation on your skin.
So these neurons are amazing.
They're collecting information
of particular kinds
from the skin throughout the entire body
and sending that information
up toward the brain.
And what's really incredible,
I just want you to
ponder this for a second.
What's really incredible
is that the language
that those neurons use
is exactly the same.
The neuron that responds to light touch
sends electrical signals
up toward the brain,
the neurons that respond
to cold or to heat
or to habanero pepper, they only respond
to the particular thing that
evokes the electrical response.
I should say that they only respond
to the particular stimulus, the pepper,
the cold, the heat, et cetera,
that will evoke an electrical signal,
but the electrical signals
are a common language
that all neurons use.
And yet, if something cold
is presented to your skin,
like an ice cube, even if
you don't see that ice cube,
if your eyes are closed, or
someone comes up behind you
and puts an ice cube
against your bare skin back,
you know that that sensation,
that thing is cold.
You don't misperceive it as
heat or as a habanero pepper.
So that's amazing.
What that means is that
there must be another element
in the equation of what
creates pleasure or pain.
And that element is your brain.
Your brain takes these electrical signals
and interprets them.
Partially based on experience,
but also there are some
innate meaning some hard wired
aspects of pain and pleasure sensing
that require no experience whatsoever.
A child doesn't have to fall down but once
to know on that first fall, that hurt.
They don't have to touch a flame,
but once and the very first
time they will withdraw
their hand from the flame.
So no prior experiences required.
Other things prior experience is required.
For instance, if you're somebody that has
an intense, intense
aversion to spicy foods,
that's probably because you've
tasted spicy foods before.
Likewise, if you really like sweet foods,
it's probably because
you've tasted them before.
So you can start to make predictions
based on prior experience,
but the pain and pleasure system
don't need prior experience.
What they need is a
brain that can interpret
these electrical signals
that can take these electrical
signals and somehow create
what we call pleasure
and pain out of them.
So what parts of the brain?
Well, mainly it's the
so-called somatosensory cortex.
The portion of our neocortex,
which is on the outside of our brain,
that kind of bumpy part, not kind of
if you have a normally formed
brain, it will be bumpy.
If you have a smooth
brain that's not good.
Some animals just have a smooth brain.
Humans have a bumpy brain,
which means it has a
very large surface area.
And those bumps are 'cause
you squeezed it like a pizza
and clump and you bunched it all up
and put inside the skull.
That's good.
That means you have a lot of neurons.
And in your somatosensory cortex,
you have a map of your
entire body surface.
That map is called a homunculus.
And if we were to take your cortex
and lay it out on a table,
I've actually done this with the cortices
of various animals and humans included.
What you would find is that
there's literally a map
of your entire body surface.
But it wouldn't look exactly like you,
this map would be very distorted.
Why would it be distorted?
Well, certain areas of your body
have a much denser
innervation as we call it,
or put simply many more
of these sensory wires
from these DRGs within your skin.
So this map of you that
exists in your brain,
and you do have one of these
on each side of your brain,
so you have two of
these maps to homunculi,
that is you, it's your
representation of touch
including pleasure and pain.
And in that map, your lips are enormous.
And your back is very, very small.
And the area around your eyes
and the area representing your
face is absolutely enormous.
So you would look like some
sort of odd, weird clay doll
from some sort of bizarre
late night animation thing.
And just imagine the
psychedelic experience of that
character of you and that's
what it would look like.
But it's not randomly organized.
To the contrary, it's highly organized
in a very particular way,
which is that the areas of your skin
that have the highest density
of the sensory receptors
are magnified in your brain.
So it's sort of like having more pixels
in a certain part of a camera than others,
and in doing that
allowing higher resolution
in this case of touch, not a vision,
but of touch sensation in
certain parts of your body.
What are the areas that are magnified?
Well, the lips, the face,
the tips of the fingers,
the feet, and the genitals.
And so this map of you
has very large lips, face,
tips of fingers, bottoms
of feet, and genitals.
And that's because the innervation,
the number of wires that go
into those regions of your body
far exceeds the number of
wires for sensation of touch
that go to other areas of your body.
You can actually experience
this in real time right now
by doing a simple experiment that we call
two-point discrimination.
Two-points discrimination is your ability
to know whether or not
two points of pressure
are far apart, near each other,
or you actually could perceive incorrectly
as one point of pressure.
You might want a second
person to do this experiment.
Here's how you would do it.
You will close your eyes,
that person would take two fine points.
Don't make them too sharp, please.
So it could be two pencils
or pens or the backs of pens.
Two pens I'm holding in my hands.
If you're just listening to
this, I'm just holding two pens.
My favorite pens, these
pilot, V5 or V7, which I love.
If you were to close your eyes
and I were to take these two pens
and put their points close
together about a centimeter apart
and present them to the top of your hand,
I'm going to just going
to do that now to myself.
You, even though your eyes were closed,
you would be able to perceive
that that was two points
of pressure presented simultaneously
to the top of your hand.
However, if I were to do this
to the middle of your back,
you would not experience them
as two points of pressure.
You would experience them as
one single point of pressure.
In other words, your two point
discrimination is better,
is higher on areas of your body
which have many, many
more sensory receptors.
You are more sensitive at those locations.
Now this makes perfect
sense once you experience it
or you hear about it.
However, most of us
don't really appreciate
how important and what a
profound influence this change
in density of receptors
across our body surface has.
And we can go a step further
and describe another feature
of the way that you're built and the way
that you experience pleasure and pain,
which is called the dermatome.
The dermatome is literally the way
in which your body surface is carved up
into different territories.
Much like a map of the
United States is carved up
into different territories
of states and counties, et cetera.
The dermatome is the way in which neurons
connect to different parts of your body.
Now, you've actually experienced
the dermatome before.
The dermatome is when you have a neuron
that connects to a
particular area of the body
and that neuron doesn't just
send one little wire out
like one little line
and go up into the skin
to detect mechanical, or
thermal, or chemical stimuli.
It actually sends many
branches out like a tree.
But remember those
branches of the tree come
from one single neuron.
Now, occasionally what will
happen is you will experience
something like cold, or
heat, or pain, or tingling
on a patch of your body.
And occasionally that patch
of body will actually have
a very cleanly demarcated boundary,
a very stark boundary
with the areas around it.
A good example of this would
be the herpes simplex 1 virus,
which if one has this virus,
and I should mention that
somewhere between 80 and 90%
of people have this virus,
this is not a sexually transmitted virus.
This is a virus is transmitted
very easily between people
through various forms of
contact non-sexual contact,
it's present in children,
it's present in adults
and most people get it, some
get symptoms and some don't
some get recurring symptoms, some don't.
We can talk about that
at the end, if you like,
but this virus lives on what's called
the fifth cranial nerve also
called the trigeminal nerve.
The trigeminal nerve sends
branches out to the lips,
to the eyes, and to certain
portions of the face.
So for those of you listening,
I've just kind of put my
right hand across my face
and to sort of simulate
the three branches,
the trigeminal aspect of this nerve.
So tri three.
Now, when the herpes virus
flares up, as they say,
in response to stress or other factors,
the virus inflames that nerve
and people experience tingling
and pain on the nerve.
Sometimes they'll get a
cold sore or a blister
on their lip or near their mouth,
sometimes they'll get
a collection of those.
And that's because that
dermatome is actually inflamed.
Now other people will experience
something like shingles.
It's a fairly common viral infection.
And what they'll notice
is they'll get a rash
that has a boundary.
It's like, they'll get a bunch of bumps,
sometimes blisters, and
it'll have a sharp boundary.
That boundary exists because
the virus exists on the nerve.
And so it actually is boundaried
with the neighboring area of the body
that's receiving input from another nerve
and that one doesn't have
the virus living on it.
So anytime you see a rash or
a pattern on the body surface
on the skin that has a
pretty stark boundary,
chances are that's an event
that's impacting the dermatome.
I've experienced this before
then not through herpes simplex,
but through the experience
of having a lot of blood
sort of aggregating in a kind of a segment
across the front of my
face, it was really bizarre.
I looked in the mirror and I
thought, what is going on here?
I was having an allergic
reaction to something I'd eaten.
And that allergic reaction
clearly was affecting one
of the nerves and therefore the dermatome
and what it showed up was,
it was almost like someone
had drawn lines on my face
that said, okay, this rash
or this reaction rather
can happen here, but not in
a region right next to it.
Whenever you see that chances are
it's a reaction of the
nerves of the dermatome.
So you'll start to see
these things more and more
when you start to look for them.
You don't always have to
have a viral infection
to experience this.
Sometimes you'll just experience tingling
or even a pleasant sensation,
and it will be restricted
in kind of a strict boundary
on one location or your body
surface and not another.
Not corresponding to an organ like,
okay, this arm or just your
feet or something like that.
But just a segment.
It's almost like someone
outlined a particular area
of her body surface.
That's the dermatome.
So you've got sensors in the skin
and you've got a brain
that's going to interpret
what's going on with those sensors.
In fact, we can take an
example of a sudden rash
or inflammation at one
location, the dermatome,
and we can ask what would make it hurt?
What would make it worse?
What would make it go away?
And believe it or not, your
subjective interpretation
of what's happening has
a profound influence
on your experience of pleasure or pain.
There are several things that
can impact these experiences,
but the main categories are expectation.
So sort of whether or not
you thought or could expect
that this thing was
going to happen, right?
If someone tells you
this is going to hurt,
I'm going to give you
an injection right here,
it might hurt for a second.
That's very different and
your experience of that pain
will be very different than
if it happened suddenly
out of the blue.
There's also anxiety, how anxious,
or how high or low your level
of arousal, autonomic arousal,
that's going to impact your
experience of pleasure or pain.
How well you slept and where you are
in the so-called circadian
or 24-hour cycle.
Our ability to tolerate
pain changes dramatically
across the 24-hour cycle.
And as you can imagine is
during the daylight waking hours
that we are better able to tolerate,
we are more resilient to pain,
and we are better able
to experience pleasure.
At night our threshold
for pain is much lower.
In other words, the amount of mechanical
or chemical or thermal
meaning temperature stimulated
that can evoke a pain response
and how we rate that response
is much lower at night.
And in particular, in the hours
between 2:00 AM and 5:00 AM,
if you're on a kind of
standard circadian schedule.
And then the last one is our genes.
Pain threshold and how
long a pain response lasts
is in part dictated by our genes.
And later I'm going to discuss this myth
or whether or not it's really a myth
as to whether or not certain
people in particular red heads,
people who have reg
pigmented hair and fair skin,
whether or not their
pain thresholds differ.
And to just give you a
little sneak peek into that,
indeed they do and it's
because of a genetic difference
in a particular gene, in a
particular pattern of receptors
in the skin that are
related to the pigmentation
of hair and skin.
So we have expectation,
anxiety, how well we've slept,
where we are in the so-called
24-hour circadian time
and our genes.
So let's talk about
expectation and anxiety
because those two factors
can powerfully modulate
our experience of both pleasure and pain
in ways that will allow us to
dial up pleasure if we like
and to dial down pain, if indeed
that's what we want to do.
So let's talk about
expectation and anxiety
because those two things
are somewhat tethered.
There are now a number
of solid experiments,
both in animal models and in humans
that point to the fact that
if we know a painful stimulus
is coming, that we can better
prepare for it mentally
and therefore buffer or
reduce the pain response.
However, the timing in which
that anticipation occurs
is vital for this to happen.
And if that timing isn't quite right,
it actually can make the
experience of pain far worse.
So here I'm summarizing a
large amount of literature,
but essentially if subjects are warned
that a painful stimulus is coming,
their subjective experience of
that pain is vastly reduced.
However, if they are
warned just two seconds
before that pain arrives,
it does not help.
It actually makes it worse.
And the reason is they
can't do anything mentally
to prepare for it in that
brief two second window.
Similarly, if they are warned
about pain that's coming
two minutes before a
painful stimulus is coming
electric shock or a poke or
cold stimulus or heat stimulus
that's pretty extreme,
that also makes it worse
because their expectation
ramps up the autonomic arousal.
The level of alertness
is all funneled toward
that negative experience that's coming.
So how soon before a painful stimulus
should we know about it if the goal is
to reduce our level of pain?
And the answer is somewhere
between 20 seconds
and 40 seconds is about right.
Now, I'm averaging across a
number of different studies,
but if you have about
20 seconds or 40 seconds
advance warning that
something bad is coming,
you can prepare yourself for that,
but the preparation itself and the arousal
that comes with it,
the kind of leaning in,
okay, I'm either going to relax myself
or I'm going to really
kind of dig my heels in
and kind of meet the pain head on.
That seems to be the optimal window.
This can come and useful
in a variety of contexts,
but I think it's important
because what it illustrates
is that it absolutely cannot
be just the pattern of signals
that are arriving from
the skin, from these DRGs,
these neurons that connect to skin
that dictates our experience
of pain or pleasure.
There has to be a subjective
interpretation component,
and indeed that's the case.
So let's talk about the
range of pain experiences.
And from that, we will understand better
what the range of pleasure experiences are
that different people have
because we are all different
in terms of our pain threshold.
First of all, what is pain threshold?
Pain threshold has two dimensions.
The first dimension is the
amount of mechanical or chemical
or thermal stimulation
that it takes for you or me
or somebody else to say,
I can't take that anymore.
I'm done.
But there's another element as well
which is how long the pain persists.
I'll just describe myself for example,
I don't consider myself somebody
who has a particularly
high pain threshold.
I don't think it's
particularly low either,
but I wouldn't consider myself somebody
that has a particularly
high pain threshold.
When I stubbed my toe against
the corner of the bed,
it absolutely hurts.
But one thing that I've noticed is
that I have very sharp
inflections, very high inflections
in my perception of pain, and
then they go away quickly.
I don't know if that's adaptive or not.
It's probably not,
but my experience of pain is
very intense, but very brief.
Other people experience pain in a much
kind of slower rising,
but longer-lasting manner.
And to just really point
out how varied we all are
in terms of our experience of pain,
let's look to an experiment.
There been experiments done
at Stanford School of Medicine
and elsewhere, which
involved having subjects
put their hand into a
very cold vat of water
and measuring the amount of time
that they kept their hand in that water.
And then they would tell the
experimenter very quietly,
how painful that particular stimulus was
on a scale of one to 10
so-called Likert scale
for your aficionados.
That simple experiment
revealed that people experience
the same thermal in this
case, cold stimulus,
vastly different.
Some people would rate it as
a 10 out of 10 extreme pain.
Other people would rate it
as barely painful at all,
like a one.
Other people, a three other
people, a five, et cetera.
Now what's interesting is
that the same thing is true
for experience of a hot, painful stimulus
120 degree hot plate, where you
have to put your hand on it,
and then at some point
you remove your hand.
Some people are able to keep their hand
on there the whole time, but
people rate that experience
as very painful, a little bit painful
or moderately painful
depending on who they are.
Now, that's interesting,
probably not that surprising, however,
but what is very interesting is that
when the same experiment
was done on medical doctors
or medical doctors in training,
they too of course experienced pain
through a range of subjective experiences.
Some of them just like any
other person off the street
said a particular stimulus
of a particular temperature
was very painful, other said
it wasn't painful at all
and some said it was moderately painful.
And that turns out to be vitally important
for the treatment of pain
because pain is not an event in the skin.
Pain is a subjective,
emotional experience.
You may have heard that we
have a particular category
of these DRGs that innervate the skin,
which are called nociceptors.
Nociceptor comes from the word
noci, nocere I believe it is,
which means to harm.
However, nociceptors don't
carry information about pain,
they carry information about
particular types of stimuli
impacting the skin.
And then the brain assigns
a value of valence to it,
a label and says that's painful.
And where people draw the
line between not painful
and painful varies.
Now, because physicians are people
and because physicians treat pain,
what we know from a lot of data
now is that if someone comes
into the clinic and says they're
experiencing chronic pain
or whole body pain or
acute pain after an injury
or one location, it doesn't
really matter what the cause is
or even if there's a cause at all,
how the doctor reacts to that
report of the patient's pain
will dictate in many cases
the course of treatment.
And of course doctors, their
goal is to treat the patient
to going to the patient's
needs, not their own.
And that's what good doctors do.
However, it's been found and
I think now there is work
being done to try and change this,
but if a doctor has a very
high threshold for pain,
their interpretation of
somebody else's report of pain
is going to be different.
They might not discount
the patient, right?
This doesn't necessarily
mean that they think, oh,
this person their pain is
irrelevant, probably not.
In fact, from having a
high threshold for pain,
if someone comes in and
says, I'm in extreme pain,
that doctor probably thinks,
wow, this has to be
really, really extreme,
but they can be talking about
two different experiences.
Similarly, if a physician has
a very low threshold for pain,
and someone comes in and says,
yeah, I'm experiencing
some pain in my back.
I've got the sciatica thing, but yeah,
it's a little bit uncomfortable.
It's like a, I don't know
like a four out of 10.
Well, that physician might
interpret that four out of 10
as a pretty extreme sense of pain
or pretty extreme experience of pain.
And so you can start to see
how the subjective nature
of pain can start to have real impact
on the treatment of pain
because treatment of pain
is carried out by physicians.
In fact, there is no
objective measure of pain.
We can ask how long
somebody can keep their hand
on a hot plate or in a cold bath.
You can do various experiments.
They even have some extreme experiments
where they'll shave a portion of the leg
and they'll put on a very
painful chemical compound
and see how long people can tolerate that.
These are very uncomfortable
experiments as you can imagine,
but in general, we don't have a way
of measuring somebody else's
subjective experience of pain.
There is no blood pressure measure.
There's no heart rate beats
per minute measure of pain.
So one of the great
efforts of neuroscience
and of medicine is to try and come up
with more objective measures of pain.
Similarly, pleasure is something
that we all talk about.
Ooh, that feels so good, or I love that
or more of that please or less of that,
but we have no way of
gauging what other people
are experiencing except what
they report through language.
And so this is really just to illustrate
that this whole thing around
pain isn't a black box.
We do have an understanding
of the elements.
There are elements in the skin,
there's elements of the brain,
there's expectation,
anxiety, sleep, and genes,
but that it is very complicated.
And yet there are certain principles
that fall out of that complicated picture
that can allow us to better
understand and navigate
this axis that we call
the pleasure-pain axis.
So rather than focus on just
the subjective nature of pain,
let's talk about the
absolute qualities of pain
and the absolute qualities of pleasure
so that we can learn how to
navigate those two experiences
in ways that serve us each better.
First of all, I want to
talk about heat and cold.
We do indeed have sensors in our skin
that respond to heat and cold.
And for any of you that
have entered a cold shower
or a cold body of water of any
kind or ice bath, et cetera,
you will realize that getting
into cold is much harder
if you do it slowly.
Now, despite that people
tend to do it very slowly.
I have noticed an enormous
variation with which people
can embrace the experience of cold.
I noticed it because I do
some work with athletes
and I do some work with military
and I do some work with
the general public.
And one of the best tests of
how somebody can handle pain
is to ask them to just
get into an ice bath.
It's not a very sophisticated experience,
but it really gets into the
core of the kind of circuitry
that we're talking about, both
in the skin and in the brain.
Some people regardless of
sex, regardless of age,
and regardless of physical ability
can just get into the cold.
They're somehow able to do it.
Now, I don't know what their
experience of the cold is.
And neither do you.
You only know your experience,
but they're able to do that.
Some do it quickly, some do it slowly.
Others find the experience
of cold to be so aversive
that they somehow cannot
get themselves in.
They start quaking, they start complaining
and many of them just simply get out.
They can't do it.
Some don't even get in past their knees.
This isn't necessarily
about pain threshold,
but it's related to that.
I think it can be helpful
to everyone to know
that even though it feels
better at a mental level
to get into the cold
slowly and people ask, oh,
I just want to get in slowly,
I want to take my time.
It is actually much worse
from a neuro-biological perspective.
The neurons that sense cold respond
to what are called relative
drops in temperature.
So it's not about the absolute
temperature of the water.
It's about the relative
change in temperature.
So as you move from a
particular temperature,
whether or not it's in the
air next to an ice bath
or cold shower, or from a
body of water that's warm
to a body of water that's colder,
or sometimes in the ocean,
you'll notice it's warm.
And then as you swim out further,
you'll get into a pocket of
water where it's much colder.
That's when the cold receptors
in your skin start firing
and sending signals up to your brain.
Therefore, you can bypass
these signals going up
to the brain with each relative
change one degree change,
two degrees change, et cetera,
by simply getting in all at once.
In fact it is true and maybe
you've been told this before,
and it is true that if
you get into cold water
up to your neck,
it's actually much more comfortable
than if you're halfway in and halfway out.
And that's because of the
difference in the signals
that are being sent
from the cold receptors
on your upper torso,
which is out of the water
in your lower torso.
Now, I wouldn't want anyone to take this
to mean that they should just jump
into an unknown body of water.
There are all sorts of
factors like currents,
and if it's very, very cold, yes, indeed.
You can stop the heart.
People can have heart attacks from getting
into extremely cold water,
like a melted mountain stream
that's been frozen all winter,
or has been very, very cold or
as a snow pack going into it.
If very cold, you can
indeed have a heart attack.
So please be smart about
how cold and what bodies
of cold water you happen
to put yourself into.
But it is absolutely true
that provided it safe,
getting into a cold water
is always going to be easier
to do quickly and is going to be easier
to do up to your neck.
In fact, you actually want to
get your shoulders submerged.
There are a number of
other things you can do
if you really want and it's safe to do.
You can put your face under and activate
the so-called dive reflex,
which also makes the tolerance
of cold easier believe it or not.
So it's very counterintuitive.
It's like getting into water
faster and more completely
you will experience as less
uncomfortable, less cold.
And indeed that's the case.
And that's because these cold receptors
are measuring every relative
drop in temperature.
So every single one is
graded as we say in biology,
it's not absolute.
As an additional point, if
you're sitting in a body
of cold water and it's not circulating,
you'll notice that you start
to warm up a little bit.
Or even if you feel like
you're freezing cold,
if you move and that water
around you moves, of course,
then you'll notice it's got even colder.
And that's because
there's a thermal layer.
You're actually heating up the water
that surrounds your body
like a halo around every
aspect of your body.
A sort of silhouette of you of heat
where you're heating that water.
When you move, you disrupt
that thermal layer.
Now heat is the opposite.
Heat and the heat receptors in your skin
respond to absolute
changes in temperature.
And this is probably because our body
and our brain can tolerate
drops in temperature
much better than it can tolerate
increases in temperature safely.
So when you move from say a
standard outdoor environment,
I mean, here in the States
we measure in terms of Fahrenheit.
So maybe it's a 75 or an 80
degree, or even 90 degree day,
and you get into a 100 degrees sauna,
or if you're in a cool
air conditioned building
and you go outside and
it's very warm outside,
you sort of feel like the heat
hits you all at once, boom.
Hits you all at once, kind
of like a slap in the face,
but then it will just stay at that level.
Your body will acclimate to
that particular temperature.
However, if that temperature
is very, very high,
you'll notice that your
experience of that heat
and your experience of
kind of pain and discomfort
and your desire to get out of that heat
will tend to persist.
You don't really adapt in the same way.
And certain people who are really good
at handling very hot
sauna, get better at this.
You learned to calm your
breathing, et cetera,
lower your autonomic arousal.
Obviously you don't want to
let your body temperature
go too high because
neurons cook, they die.
If neurons die, they don't
come back and that's bad.
Many people unfortunately harm
themselves with hyperthermia.
Everyone has a different threshold
for this, but in general,
you don't want your body
temperature to go up too high.
That's why a fever of like 103 starts
to become worrisome 104.
You really get concerned if and it goes
up into that range or higher,
that's when you need to
really cool down the body
or get to hospital so
they can cool you down.
Heat is measured in absolute
terms by the neurons.
So gradually moving into heat makes sense,
and finding that threshold,
which is safe and comfortable for you,
or if it's uncomfortable,
at least resides within
that realm of safety.
So that's heat and cold,
and those are sort of non-negotiables.
You can try and lower
your level of arousal.
In fact, many people who
get into a cold shower
and ice bath I think the recommendation
that I always give is that
you have two possible approaches to that.
You can either try and relax yourself,
kind of just stay calm within the cold,
or you can lean into it.
You can actually take mental steps
to generate more adrenaline
to kind of meet the demands of that cold.
And at some point we'll
do a whole episode on
how to use cold and heat
to certain advantages
we've done a little bit
of this in past episodes
using the cold to
supercharge human performance
and things of that sort.
But in general, cold is
measured in relative terms.
And therefore getting in all
at once is a good idea provided
you can do it safely.
And heat is measured in absolute levels
by your brain and body and therefore
you want to actually
move into it gradually.
So it's the kind of the inverse
of what you might think.
One of the most important
things to understand
about the experience of pain
and to really illustrate
just how subjective pain really is,
is that our experience of
pain and the degree of damage
to our body are not always correlated.
And in fact, sometimes can
be in opposite directions.
A good example of this would be x-rays.
We all occasionally get
x-rays at least in the US
we get x-rays when we go to
the dentist from time to time,
and the occasional x-ray might be safe
depending on who you are
provide you're not pregnant, et cetera.
I've gone to the dentist.
They put you in the chair,
they cover you with the lead blanket,
and then they run behind the
screen to protect themselves.
And they beam me with the
x-rays to get a picture
of your teeth and your jaws
and your skull, et cetera.
Well, if you were to get too many x-rays,
you could severely damage
the tissues of your body,
but you don't experience any
pain during the x-ray itself.
In contrast, you can think
that your body is damaged
and experienced extreme pain
and yet your body can have no damage.
A classic example of this was published
in the British Journal of Medicine,
in which a construction worker fell from
I think it was a second
story, which he was working
and a nail went up and through his boot
and he looked down and
he saw the nail going
through his boot and he was
in absolute excruciating pain.
They took him to the hospital
and because the nail was
so long and because of
where it had entered,
it exited the boot, they
had to cut away the boot
in order to get to the nail.
And when they did that,
they revealed that the nail had passed
between two of his toes.
It had actually failed to
impale his body in any way.
And yet the view, the
perception of that nail
entering his boot at one
end and exiting the boot
at the other was sufficient
to create the experience
of a nail that had gone through his foot.
And the moment he realized
that that nail had not gone
through his foot, the pain
completely evaporated.
And this has been
demonstrated numerous times.
People that work in emergency rooms
actually see variations on this.
Not always that extreme,
but many times what we see
and how we perceive that wound
or that event has a profound influence
on how we experience pain.
And I mentioned this,
not just because it's a
kind of sensational and fantastic example
of this extreme,
subjective nature of pain,
but also because it brings
us back to this element
which is, we don't know
how other people feel.
Not just about pain, but about pleasure.
We think we do, we have some general sense
of whether or not an event ought
to be painful or pleasurable,
but actually we barely
understand how we feel
let alone how other people feel,
and we can be badly
wrong about how we feel
meaning we can misinterpret
our own sense of pain
or our own sense of pleasure
depending on what we see
with our eyes and what
we hear with our ears.
So we hear a scream like a shrill scream,
and we think it must be pain.
And if we look at something
that's happening to somebody
and it fits a prior category
or a prior representation
of what we would consider
painful stimulus,
well, then we think that
they're an extreme pain,
but actually they might
not be in pain at all.
Now this highly subjective nature of pain
and the way in which we
use our visual system
to interpret other people's
pain and our own pain
has actually been leveraged
to treat a very extreme form
of chronic pain.
And it's an absolutely fascinating area
of biology and neuroscience.
And it's one that we can
actually all leverage
toward reducing our own levels of pain
whenever we are injured.
Or believe it or not,
even in chronic pain.
To describe this area of science requires
a kind of extreme example,
but I want to be clear that
even if you don't suffer
from this extreme example,
there's relevance and a
tool to extract for you.
The extreme example is
that of an amputated digit,
meaning one of your fingers or your toes,
or of an amputated limb.
So people that have digits or
limbs that are gone missing
from an injury or surgical removal,
will often have the experience
that it's still there.
The so-called phantom limb phenomenon.
Now, why would that be?
Well, when you remove a
particular finger or limb,
obviously that finger and limb is gone
and the dorsal root ganglion neuron
that would normally send a wire out
to that particular region of the body,
that wire is no longer
there because that portion
of the body is no longer there.
And in some cases, those neurons die
almost always, but not always.
However, the map your
so-called homunculus,
your representation of yourself
in the brain is still there.
And this map, the so-called homunculus map
that you have in that
I have is very plastic.
It can change.
And so as a consequence areas of the map
that adjacent to one another
can actually start to invade
other areas of the map.
So for instance, there
are neuroimaging studies
that have documented that somebody
that has say a complete
removal of their left arm,
the representation of
their left arm still exists
in the cortex.
And experimentally if one is to stimulate
that area of the cortex, that person,
and if that person were you,
would experience having that arm
that it were being stimulated,
even though it's not there.
Now, someone who has an
amputated arm doesn't need
to have their brain stimulated
in order to have the experience
of that phantom limb being present.
In fact, many people who have
limbs that were amputated
feel as if that limb is still present
even though obviously it's not.
And no matter how many
times they look to the stump
and just see a stump,
somehow it doesn't reorganize
that homunculus so-called
central brain map.
Now, that would be fine.
You might even think that would be better,
better to think you have the arm there
than to feel as if it's missing,
and yet many people who
have amputated limbs
report phantom limb pain.
They don't feel that the arm
is just casually draped next to them.
They feel as if it's bunched
up and it's an extreme pain.
In fact, this kind of contorted stance
that I'm taking right here in my chair
is not unlike the way that
these patients described this.
They feel as if it's kind of cramped up,
it's very uncomfortable for them.
Now, and absolutely creative
and you could even say genius scientists
by the name of Ramachandra.
That's actually his last name,
his complete name is a
little bit more complicated.
So you all almost always hear
Ramachandran referred to as
Ramachandran or V.S Ramachandran
because his full name
is Vilayanur Subramanian Ramachandran.
So a lot of letters in
there, a lot of vowels,
but Ramachandran is a neuroscientist.
He was actually a colleague of mine
when my lab was formerly
at the University of
California, San Diego.
Has done a lot of work on
this phantom limb phenomenon.
And Ramachandra actually started
off as a vision scientist.
And he understood the
power of the visual system
in dictating our experience
of things like pain and pleasure.
And so what he developed
was a very low technology
yet neuroscientifically
sophisticated treatment
for phantom limb.
It consisted of a box, literally a box
that had mirrors inside of it.
And the patient would put
the intact hand or limb
into one side,
and obviously they couldn't
put the amputated limb
into the other side, but
because of the configuration
of the mirrors, it
appeared as though they had
two symmetric limbs inside the box.
And then he would have
them look at that limb
and move it around.
And as they would do this,
they would report real time movement,
or I should say real time
perception of movement
in the phantom limb.
Now this is absolutely
incredible but makes total sense
when you think about
the so-called top down
or contextual modulation
of our sensory experience,
remember it's anticipation, it's anxiety,
it's interpretation of what's happening
that drives our perception
of what's happening.
And so, as he would have these patients
move their intact limb to
a more relaxed position,
the patients would feel
as if the phantom limb were relaxing.
And this was used successfully
to treat phantom limb pain
in a number of different people.
It didn't always work.
And you can imagine sometimes
it might be a little
trickier like for a leg
although there have been leg
boxes that have been developed
and arranged for this purpose.
And what was remarkable
is that they could finish
these experiments and have
the patient, the person
enter a state of relaxation,
reduced the pain in the phantom limb,
and it would stay there
even though, of course,
as they exited the mirror box,
they would go about their
life and use their intact limb
for its various purposes.
I love this experiment
because it really speaks
to the subjective nature
of pain and pleasure.
It speaks to the power
of the visual system,
like what we see just like the nail
through the boot experiment.
What we see profoundly
impacts our experience
of pleasure and pain in this case pain.
Now, there's another aspect
to the phantom limb experience
and of these maps, the
so-called homunculus maps
in the cortex that Ramachandran worked on,
which has very interesting
and reveals the degree
to which these maps are
plastic or can change
in response to experience.
Turns out that because of the locations
of different body part
representations within these maps,
certain parts of our body that
normally we don't think of
as related can start to
create merged experiences.
What do I mean by that?
Well, Ramchandran described a patient
who had a somewhat odd experience
of having lost their foot.
So they actually had their foot amputated
about midway up the Achilles.
So lower portion of the calf and foot.
I don't recall what the reason
was for having it removed.
And fortunately for this patient,
they did not experience pain
in that portion of their body,
but rather they confided in him
that whenever they would have sex,
they would experience their
orgasm in their phantom foot
in addition to in their
genitals, of course.
And Ramachandra understood
the homunculus map.
And he understood that this
was because the representation
of the foot within the homunculus
actually lies adjacent to,
and is somewhat interdigitated with
it actually kind of merges
with the representation
of the genitalia.
Now that's a weird situation.
And yet you now know that
the density of innovation
of the feet and the genitalia,
as well as the lips and
the face are actually
the highest sensory innervation
that you have in your entire body.
And this speaks to, I think,
a more important general
principle for all people
of the experience of pleasure or pain,
which is that an aspect
of our pain or pleasure
can be highly localized.
It can be because of a cut
to a particular location
on the body or it can
because of a fall injury
or a kind of bruise on
one side of our body.
And yet our experience
of pleasure and pain
can also be an almost
a body-wide experience.
And yet it's always most rich.
It's always most heightened
in these regions of our body
that have dense sensory innervation.
So we experience pain
and pleasure according
to local phenomenon receptors in the skin,
and this homunculus map
that has all these different territories,
but because of the way that
those territories are related,
this kind of wild example of
somebody experiencing orgasm
in their phantom foot speaks
to the larger experience.
The more typical rather
experience that I should say
that all people have,
which is that pleasure can be body-wide
or we can experience it in our face
or the bottoms of our feet
and other areas of the body
that we experience pleasure
and similarly with pain.
And that brings us to the
topic of whole body pain,
not just localized pain, as
well as whole body pleasure
not just localized pleasure.
There are a number of
examples of whole body pain
that people suffer from.
And one common one is called fibromyalgia.
I want to just first share
with you a little bit
of medical insight.
A few months back, I did an Instagram live
with Dr. Sean Mackey
who's an MD medical doctor
and a PhD at Stanford School of Medicine
that was recorded and
placed on my Instagram.
If you want to check it out,
we can provide a link to
that in the show notes.
Dr. Mackey is the Chief
of the Division of Pain
at Stanford School of Medicine.
So he's a scientist.
He studies pain and he
treats patients dealing
with various forms of
pain, whole body pain,
like fibromyalgia, acute pain, et cetera.
And he shared with me
something very interesting,
which is that anytime you
hear or see the word syndrome,
that means the medical
establishment does not understand
what's going on.
A syndrome is a constellation of symptoms
that point in a particular direction
or some general set of directions about
what could be going on,
but it doesn't reveal a true
underlying disease necessarily.
It could be aggregative diseases
or it could be something else entirely.
And I want to make sure that I emphasize
the so-called psychosomatic phenomenon.
I think sometimes we hear psychosomatic
and we interpret that as
meaning all in one's head.
But I think it's important to remember
that everything is neural,
whether that's pain in your body
'cause you have a gaping wound
and you're hemorrhaging out of that wound
or whether or not it's pain
for which you cannot explain it
on the basis of any kind of injury.
It's all neural.
So saying body, brain, or psychosomatic
it's kind of irrelevant.
And I hope someday we
move past that language.
Psychosomatic is interesting.
There was a paper that
was published in 2015,
and then again in 2020 a different paper
focused on the so-called
psychogenic fevers
or psychosomatic effects.
I just briefly want to mention this
because it relates back to pain.
These studies have shown
that there are areas
of the so-called thalamus,
which integrates and
filter sensory information
of different kinds.
And within the brainstem,
an area called the DMH
and I can also provide a link
to this study if you like,
that shows that there is
a true neurological basis.
There are brain areas and
circuits that are related to
what's called psychogenic
fever when we are stressed.
And in particular, if we
think that we were injured
or that we were infected by something,
we can actually generate a true fever.
It is not an imagined fever.
It is our thinking generating
an increase in body temperature.
And so this has been called psychosomatic.
It's been called psychogenic,
but it has a neural basis.
So when we hear syndrome and
a patient comes into a clinic
and says that they suffer for instance,
from something which is
very controversial frankly
like chronic fatigue syndrome,
some physicians believe that it reflects
a real underlying medical
condition, others don't.
However, syndrome means
we don't understand.
And that doesn't mean
something doesn't exist.
Fibromyalgia or whole
body pain for a long time
was written off or kind of explained away
by physicians and scientists
frankly, my community
as one of these syndromes.
It couldn't be explained.
However, now there is
what I would consider
and I think others would
and should consider
from understanding of at
least one of the bases
for this whole body pain.
And that's activation of
a particular cell type
called glial.
And there's a receptor on these glial
for those of you that want to
know called the toll 4 receptor
and activation of the
toll 4 receptor is related
to certain forms of whole
body pain and fibromyalgia.
Now, what treatments
exist for fibromyalgia.
And even if you don't
suffer from fibromyalgia,
and even if you don't know anyone who does
this is important information
because what I'm about to tell you relate
to how you and your body,
which is you of course
can deal with pain of any kind.
And there are actually things
that one can do and take
that can encourage
nerve health in general.
In other conditions like
diabetic neuropathy,
but in all individuals.
So there are clinical data
using a prescription drug.
This is work that actually was done
by Dr. Mackey and colleagues.
The drug is called naltrexone.
Naltrexone is actually
used for the treatment
of various opioid addictions
and things of that sort,
but it turns out that a very low dose,
I believe it was a one 10th
the size of the typical dose
of naltrexone has been
shown to have some success
in dealing with and treating
certain forms of fibromyalgia.
And it has that success
because of its ability
to bind to and block these
toll four receptors on glial.
So this so-called syndrome
or this thing that previously
was called a syndrome, fibromyalgia
actually has a biological basis.
It was not just inpatients heads.
And I really tip my hat to
the medical establishment
including Dr. Mackey and others
who explored the potential
underlying biologies
of things like fibromyalgia
and are starting
to arrive at treatments.
Now, I'm not a physician, I'm a professor,
so I'm not prescribing anything.
You should talk to your doctor of course,
if you have fibromyalgia
or other forms of chronic
or whole body pain to explore
whether or not these low dose
naltrexone treatments are right for you.
But I think it's a beautiful
case study if you will,
not a case study of an individual patient,
but a case in study of linking
up the patient's self-report
of these experiences and using science
to try to establish clinical treatments.
There's another treatment,
or I should say there's another approach
that one could take.
And again, I'm not recommending
people do this necessarily.
You have to determine what's
right and say for you,
I cannot do that.
There's no way your
situation's very far too much,
and it would be outside of my wheelhouse
to prescribe anything, but
there's a particular compound
which in the United States
is sold over the counter
and in Europe is prescription.
It's one that I've talked
about on this podcast before
for other purposes.
And that compound is acetylcarnitine.
Acetylcarnitine as I
mentioned is by prescription
in most countries in Europe
and the US you can buy
this over the counter.
There is evidence that
acetylcarnitine can reduce
the symptoms of chronic whole body pain
and other certain forms of acute pain
at dosages of somewhere
between one to three
and sometimes four grams per day.
Now acetylcarnitine can be taken orally.
It's found in 500 milligram capsules,
as well as by injection.
By injection in the States
in the United States that is
also requires a prescription
or requires a prescription I should say.
The over-the-counter forms
are generally capsules
or powders.
Those apparently do not
require a prescription.
There are several studies
exploring acetylcarnitine
in this context, as well
as for diabetic neuropathy.
And what's interesting about
acetylcarnitine is it's one
of the few compounds that isn't just used
for the treatment of pain,
but has also been shown
in certain contacts
to improve peripheral
nerve health generally.
And for that reason, it's
an interesting compound.
I've also talked about
acetylcarnitine on here previously,
because it has robust effects
on things like spur motility
and health, including the
speeds at which sperms swim,
how straight they swim
turns out that swimming
for sperm is more efficient
if they swim straight,
as opposed to like those
kids in on the swim team,
they're like banging up
against the lane lines
and zigzagging all over the place.
So it does turn out to be the
case that the quickest route
between any two places is a straight line
and the good sperm know that,
and the less good sperm
don't seem to know that.
And acetylcarnitine seems to
facilitate straight swimming
trajectories as well as speed of swimming
and overall sperm health.
And there is evidence from
quality peer reviewed studies
showing that acetylcarnitine
supplementation can also be
beneficial for women's fertility
in ways that it affects
perhaps we don't really
know the mechanism,
health and status of the
egg or egg implantation.
There are a large number of
studies on acetylcarnitine.
You can look those up
on Pub Med, if you like,
or on examine.com.
There are some studies that I don't think
are included there which are
particularly interesting.
One that I just would like
to reference the last name
of the first author is
Mahdavi M-A-H-D-A-V-I.
The title of the paper is
Effects of l -Carnitine Supplementation
on Serum Inflammatory Markers
and Matrix Metalloproteinases Enzymes
in Females with Knee Osteoarthritis.
So this is a randomized double
blind placebo controlled
pilot study that showed
really interesting effects
of short term supplementation
of acetylcarnitine.
Longer term, the effects
were less impressive.
So it's pretty interesting
that this compound has
so many different effects.
How could it have these effects?
Well, it appears that
it's having these effects
through its impact on the
so-called inflammatory cytokines.
Inflammatory cytokines for
those of you that don't know
are secreted by the immune system
in response to different stressors,
physical stressors, mental stressors too
food that you eat that isn't good for you.
The so-called hidden sugars.
Yes, will increase inflammation
if they're ingested too often,
or in amounts that are
too high in quantity.
Things like Interleukin 1 beta,
things like C-reactive protein,
things like interleukin 6.
Interleukin 6 is kind of the
generic inflammatory marker
that all studies refer to.
And yet there are other interleukins,
please note that there
are other interleukins
like interleukin 10 that
are anti-inflammatory.
So immune system can secrete
inflammatory molecules
to deal with wounds and stress and things.
And in the short term that's good,
and in the longterm that's bad.
And it can secrete anti-inflammatory
cytokines like IL10.
And these matrix metalloproteinases,
it's kind of a mouthful,
but these matrix metalloproteinases
are very interesting.
Anytime you see A-S-E, ASE
that's generally an enzyme,
which means that these
compounds in this case,
these matrix metalloproteinases are used
to break down certain
elements around wounds
and scoring which might
sound like a bad thing,
but in some cases is good
because it allows certain cells
like glial cells so-called microglia
to come in like low ambulances,
like low paramedics and clean up wounds.
So scarring and inflammation
is kind of a double-edged sword.
It can be good, but too much scarring.
If it contains a wound too much,
doesn't allow the
infiltration of cell types
to move in and take care of
that wound and heal it up.
So it appears that L-carnitine
is impacting a number
of different processes,
both to impact pain
and perhaps, and I want
to underscore perhaps,
but there are good studies happening now,
perhaps accelerate wound healing as well.
As long as we're talking about acute pain
and chronic pain and supplementation
and non-prescription drugs,
at least in the United States
that people can take to deal
with pain of various kinds,
I'd be remiss if I didn't mention the two
that I get asked most often about,
which are agmatine and
S-adenosyl-L-methionine,
which is sometimes called SAMe.
Both of those have been
shown to have some impact
categorized on examine as notable impact
on various forms of pain,
due to osteoarthritis,
or due to injury of various
kinds of indifferent subject
population, men, women, people
of different ages, et cetera.
SAMe in particular has been interesting
because it's been shown head to head
with drugs like Naproxen and
other drugs of that sort,
which are well established
and sold over the counter
in the US to work at least as well
as some of those compounds
at certain doses.
But it's also shown that SAMe
and some of those things take more time
in order to have those effects.
In fact, head to head
with things like Neproxin
have been shown that they
can take up to a month
in order to have the
pain relieving effect.
Now, whether or not that
makes them a better choice
or a worst choice really
depends on your circumstances.
I'm certainly not recommending
that anybody take anything,
but I do think it's interesting
and important to point out
that things like
agmatine, things like SAMe
have been shown under
certain circumstances
to be beneficial for pain and
they are outside the realm
of prescription drugs.
I think this is a growing area of
some people call them supplements,
some people call them nutraceuticals.
Look, at the end of the
day these are compounds
that affect cellular processes.
And the more that we understand
how they affect those cellar processes
as we now do for things
like acetylcarnitine,
I think the more trust
that we can put into them,
or the more to which we
might want to avoid them
because of some of the side effects
or contra-indications that
those compounds could have.
If you're interested in
those other compounds,
I do invite you as I always
do to check out examine.com,
but also to do your
research on those compounds
by simply putting them into Google
or putting them into PubMed,
which would be even better.
And if you are going to go into PubMed,
if you're going to
start playing scientist,
which I do encourage you to do,
I would encourage you to
not just read abstracts,
but if you can, if the
studies are freely available,
I realized not all of
them are freely available
to try and read those studies
at least to the extent that you can.
There's a particularly nice
study that you might look at
that was published in
2010 in Pain Medicine,
which is Keynan et al K-E-Y-N-A-N,
which looked at the safety and efficacy
of dietary agmatine sulfate
on lumbar disc associated radiculopathy
not laughing at the condition.
It's a painful condition that describes a,
it's a kind of a range
of symptoms that relate
to pinching of nerves.
The spinal columns,
I was laughing at my pronunciation of it.
That particular study is quite good.
And the conclusion of that
study that they drew was that
there were limited side effects
and that dietary agmatine sulfate is safe
and efficacious for treating
and alleviating pain
and improving quality of life
and lumbar-disc associated pain.
However, there were very
specific dosage regimens
that were described there
and duration of treatment.
And so you should not take
anything that I say or that study
to mean that you can just
take this stuff willy-nilly
or at any concentration
of course, or dose.
You always want to pay attention
to what the science says.
That paper fortunately is
freely available online.
And we will also provide
a link to that study.
For those of you that
are interested in SAMe
and its usage for the treatment
of various types of pain,
and perhaps other benefits,
a number of companies
have stopped making SAMe
instead what they're now
focusing on is what they think
is a better or more
bioavailable alternative,
which is 5-methyltetrahydrofolate
or 5-MTHF.
This molecule is necessary
for converting homocysteine
to methionine, which is
then converted to SAMe
so rather than taking SAMe directly,
the idea is to take
something that's upstream
of SAMe and make more SAMe
endogenously available.
This is a different strategy.
I've talked about this strategy before
for increasing other things
like growth hormone, et cetera.
There's always this
question of whether or not
in trying to increase the
amount of a particular molecule
in the body, whether or not
taking that specific molecule
was the best thing or
working further upstream
as it's referred to
working on the precursor
or increasing the levels of the precursor
is the better way to go.
It appears that this
5-MTHF is the strategy
that people are now taking in
place of taking SAMe directly.
So in other words, they're taking this
in order to get elevated levels of SAMe.
Now, I'd like to turn our attention
to a completely non drug, non
supplement related approach
to dealing with pain.
And it's one that has existed
for thousands of years.
And that only recently has the
Western scientific community
started to pay serious attention to,
but they have started to
pay serious attention to it.
And there is terrific mechanistic
science to now explain
how and why acupuncture can work very well
for the treatment of
certain forms of pain.
Now, first off, I want to
tell you what was told to me
by our director or Chief
of the Pain Division
at Stanford School of
Medicine, Dr. Sean Mackey,
which was that some
people respond very well
to acupuncture and others do not.
And the challenge is
identifying who'll respond well
and who won't respond well.
Now, when I say won't respond well,
that doesn't necessarily
mean that they responded
in a negative way, that
it was bad for them,
but it does appear that
a fraction of people
experienced tremendous pain
relief from acupuncture
and others experience
none at all or very little
to the point where they have to seek out
other forms of treatment.
The science on this is still ongoing.
There was actually an excellent
paper published on this
in the Journal of the
American Medical Association,
one of the premier
medical clinical journals.
And it basically reinforced the idea
that you have responders
and non-responders.
A number of laboratories
have started to explore
how acupuncture works.
And one of the premier
laboratories for this
is Qiufu Ma's lab at
Harvard Medical School.
Qiufu has spent many years
studying the pain system
and a system that's
related to the pain system,
which is the system that
controls our sensation of itch.
Just as a brief aside about itch,
itch and pain are often co
associated with one another.
I was recently in Texas,
and I will tell you,
they have some mean mosquitoes.
They're small, but
whatever they're injecting
into your skin.
Well, here I am talking now
about my subjective experience
of pain, whatever they
injected into my skin
felt to me like the most
extreme mosquito bites
I've ever had, not while
they were biting me,
not while they were
injecting the venom, but boy,
those Texas mosquitoes make me itch.
How do they do it?
Well, their venom creates little packets
of so-called histamine that travel around
those packets are called mast cells,
little packets of histamine
that go to that location
and make me and presumably you
want to scratch those mosquito bites.
I scratch mine you scratch yours,
but we both scratch our mosquito bites.
And when we do that, the
histamines are released.
That gets red and inflamed
and the itch even worse.
The inflammation is actually
caused by the histamine.
Well, that experience of
inflammation and pain and itch
is what we call a pyrogenic experience.
So we we have pain which is
nociception, essentially,
I know that the pain of aficionado
always get a little upset
because they say, oh,
there's no such thing
as as a pain receptor,
it's no susceptive receptors
and pain is subjective experience.
Yes, I acknowledge all that.
But for fluency, let's
just think about pain
as a certain experience and
itch as a separate experience,
but they often exist together
because those mosquito bites
were what I would call painful,
or at least not pleasant.
They didn't just itch,
they were also painful nuts
because itch brings with it inflammation
and inflammation often
brings with it pain relief,
but it can also bring with
it the sensation of pain.
So itch and pain are
two separate phenomenon.
It was actually discovered
through a really interesting
phenomenon that relates to something
that is actually consumed
in supplement form,
which is this tropical legume.
It's actually a bean
called Mucuna pruriens.
That's M-U-C-U-N-A that's
one word P-R-U-I-E-N-S
Mucuna pruriens is a bean,
it's as legume that this bean
is 99% L-DOPA.
It's dopamine or rather it's
the precursor to dopamine
and people buy this stuff
and take it over the counter
as ways to increase
their levels of dopamine.
It does make you feel
really dopamine doubt,
meaning it makes you feel a
little high and really motivated
and really energetic
a lot like other drugs
that will do that.
I don't necessarily recommend
taking Mucuna pruriens.
I personally don't like taking it.
Doesn't make me feel good.
I crash really hard when I take it.
But on the outside of
this bean is a compound
that makes people itch.
So they remove this when you
take it in supplement form.
In fact, it's usually in capsule form,
but the outside of this
bean, it's like a hairy bean.
And those little hairs contain a compound,
which was actually used
to study and identify
these itchy receptors in the skin.
So we don't have time to go
into all the details of itch,
but it's pretty interesting
that you have these compounds
out in nature that can make us itch.
Inside them they have dopamine.
I mean, this is really weird,
but plant compounds are really powerful.
So don't let anyone tell
you that because something's
from a plant or an earth
that it's not powerful.
There are very powerful
plant and herb compounds.
Mucuna prurien being one of
them with dopamine on the inside
and itchy stuff on the outside.
Now, what does this all
have to do with acupuncture?
Well, Qiufu Ma's lab
has not just identified
the itch pathway, this pruritus
genes as they're called,
which causes itch and
the pyrogenic phenomenon
of itch being separate from pain.
His lab has also studied how
acupuncture causes relief of,
but also can exacerbate pain.
Now, the form of acupuncture
that they explored
was one that's commonly in
use called electroacupuncture.
So this isn't just putting little needles
into different parts of the body.
These needles are able to
pass an electrical current,
not magically, but because they have
a little wire going back to a device
and you can pass electrical current.
Here's what they found.
This is a study published
in the journal neuron
Cell Press journal, excellent
journal, very high stringency.
So what Qiufu Ma's lab found
was that if electroacupuncture
is provided to the abdomen,
to the stomach area,
it creates activation of what are called
the sympathetic ganglia.
These have nothing to do with sympathy
in the emotional sense has to
do with the stress response.
Sympa just means together.
So it activated a bunch of
neurons along the spinal cord.
And the activation of
these neurons evolves
neural adrenaline and something
called NPY neuropeptide Y.
The long and short of it is
that stimulating the abdomen
with electroacupuncture was
either anti-inflammatory
or it could cause inflammation.
It could actually exacerbate
inflammation depending
on whether or not it was
of low or high intensity.
Now that makes it a very
precarious technique.
And this may speak to some of the reason
why some people report
relief from acupuncture
and others do not.
However, they went a step further
and stimulated other areas
of the body using electroacupuncture.
And what they found is that
stimulation of the legs
of the hind limbs, as
it's called an animals,
and the legs in humans caused a circuit,
a neural circuit to be activated that goes
from the legs up to an area
of the base of the brain
called the DMV not the DMH,
which I mentioned earlier,
but the DMV like you go to the DMV,
which is a miserable experience
for most people, forgive me,
DMV employees, but let's be honest
most people don't enjoy
going to the DMV as patrons,
but we have to so we go.
The DMV and low intensity stimulation,
this electroacupuncture of the
hind limbs activated the DMV
and activated the adrenal glands,
which sit at top of your
kidneys and cause the release
of what are called catecholamines.
And those were strongly anti-inflammatory.
In other words, electroacupuncture
of the legs and feet can,
if done correctly, be anti-inflammatory
and reduce symptoms of pain.
And can we think accelerate wound healing
because activations of these
catecholaminergic pathways
can accelerate wound healing as well.
So the takeaway from this is
that while there are thousands
of years and millions of
subjects involved in explorations
of electroacupuncture and acupuncture,
Western medicine is
starting to come into this
and start to explore underlying mechanism.
Now, for those of you
that love acupuncture
and are real proponents of it,
it's worked for you, you might say,
well, why does Western medicine
even need to come into this?
Why should they even be exploring this?
But we should all be
relieved that they are
because what's starting to happen now
is that as the mechanistic basis for this
is starting to come to light,
insurance coverage of
things like acupuncture
is starting to emerge as well.
And this is in contrast to other therapies
for which there's a lot
of anecdotal evidence,
but very little mechanistic understanding.
One example of that would
be laser photo biomodulation
the use of lasers of
different types really
to treat pain and to
accelerate wound healing.
A lot of people claim that
this can really help them.
However, most places,
at least in the States,
won't cover this with insurance
or don't perform this in standard clinics.
And the reason is the underlying
mechanism isn't known.
I'm not going to get into the
argument about whether or not
mechanistic understanding
should or should not be required
in order to have insurance
coverage of things that work.
That's not what this is about.
And that actually will
be a boring discussion
because I'm shouting at
a tunnel through you.
And I wouldn't be able
to hear you shout back
no matter what your stance on that is,
but just trust me when I
say that I am both relieved
and delighted to hear that
excellent medical institutions
like Stanford are starting to
think about electroacupuncture
and how it can work.
That places like Harvard
Medical School are starting
to explore this at a mechanistic level.
And I do believe that
there's an open-mindedness
that starting to emerge for instance,
the National Institutes of Health,
not only has an institute
for mental health
and cancer research and an eye institute,
but now complementary
health, the so-called NCCIH.
National Institutes of
Complementary Health
that is exploring things
like electroacupuncture,
meditation, various supplements
and things of those sort.
I do think that we're entering
a new realm in which things
like pain and pain management
will be met with more openness
by all physicians, at
least that's my hope.
So please take that into
consideration right now.
The mechanistic evidence
for laser photobiomodulation
is not strong.
One of the major issues
or the barriers to that
is that most of the
studies that are out there
were actually paid for by companies
that build devices for
laser photobiomodulation.
And so we really need
independent studies funded
by federal institutions that have no bias
or financial relationship
in order to gain trust
in whatever data happen to emerge.
There is a technique that at one time
was considered alternative,
but now has a lot of mechanistic science
to explain how it works,
and it does indeed work
for the treatment of chronic
and also for acute pain.
And that treatment is hypnosis
in particular self-hypnosis.
Now, my colleague at Stanford
in fact, my collaborator,
Dr. David Spiegel, our
Associate Chair of Psychiatry
has devoted his professional life
to developing hypnosis
tools that people can use
to help them sleep better, focus better,
stay motivated, et cetera.
While most people hear
hypnosis and they think,
oh, this is stage hypnosis.
People walking around like chickens
are being forced to laugh
or fall asleep on command, et cetera.
This is completely
different than all that.
This is self hypnosis
and there are now dozens,
if not more quality peer
reviewed studies published
in excellent journals done by Dr. Spiegel
and others at other universities.
It really all has to do
with how self-hypnosis
can modulate activity
of the prefrontal cortex
and related structures like the insula.
The prefrontal cortex is involved
in our executive function
as it's called, our planning,
our decision making,
but also how we interpret context,
what the meaning of a given sensation is.
And that's extremely powerful.
I just want to remind
everybody that the currency
of the brain and body has not changed
in hundreds of thousands of years.
It's always been dopamine,
serotonin, glutamate,
GABA, testosterone, estrogen.
What's changed are the contingencies,
the events in the world
that drive whether or not
we get an increase or decrease
in testosterone or estrogen,
the events in the world
that dictate whether or not
we get an increase or
a decrease in dopamine.
Believe me, the events
that drove those increases
and decreases were very
different even a 100 years ago
than they are now.
And as we create new things and
societies change, et cetera,
they will continue to exchange information
in the same currency, which
is dopamine, serotonin,
and all these other
neuromodulators and chemicals.
Hypnosis takes advantage of this
by allowing an individual,
you, if you like
to change the way that you
interpret particular events
and to actually experience
what would be painful
as less painful or not painful.
And that's just the example of pain.
Hypnosis is powerful
for other reasons too.
It actually can help
rewire neural circuits
so that you don't experience as much pain
so that you can sleep
faster, focus faster.
If this is all sounding very fantastical
well, it's supported by data.
The data are that when
people do self-hypnosis
even brief self-hypnosis
of 10 or 15 minutes,
a few times a week, maybe
even returned to that hypnosis
by just using a one minute a day hypnosis,
they can achieve significant
and often very impressive
degrees of pain relief in chronic pain
whether or not that chronic pain arises
through things like fibromyalgia
or through other sources.
If you want to check this out,
there's a wonderful zero cost resource
that's grounded in this work.
It's the app reveri.com.
So R-E-V-E-R-I.com.
There you can download a zero cost app
for Apple phones or for Android phones.
And there are a variety of
different hypnosis scripts.
These are actually self hypnosis scripts,
and you'll actually hear Dr.
David Spiegel talking to you.
He can teach you about
hypnosis and how it works.
There are links to scientific studies
that web address that I
gave you before reveri.com.
You can see the various studies
and the various write-ups
related to those studies
and how this all works.
And they're simple protocols.
You just click on a tab and
you listen to the self-hypnosis
and it will take you into hypnosis.
And several of those hypnosis
grips have been shown
clinically to relieve certain
patterns of chronic pain.
So it's a powerful tool,
and I encourage you not
to write off the non-drug
non supplement tools
as less than powerful
because indeed many people
experience tremendous relief from them.
And of course, they also can be combined
with drug treatments
if that's right for you
or with supplements and things
of that sort to treat pain,
if that's right for you.
So again, electroacupuncture
now often supported
by insurance, not always, but often.
Great mechanistic data starting to emerge.
Hypnosis, terrific tool.
There's even the self-hypnosis
tool that one can access
through the zero cost app Reveri
and lots of great clinical data
and scientific mechanistic data.
There are neuro imaging studies showing
that different brain areas
are activated in hypnosis
the so-called default network,
kind of where your brains is kind of idols
and the different circuits
that are active in at rest
shift with hypnosis and shift long-term
in ways that positively conserve you.
And then these things like
laser photobiomodulation
still more or less in that
experimental medical community.
I should say, Western Medical
Community, not so certain,
but hopefully there will be data soon,
and hopefully those data
will point to mechanisms
that allow the insurance companies
and other sort of medical
bodies to support them
if indeed they have a mechanistic basis.
I just want to briefly touch on
a common method of pain relief
that speaks to a more general principle
of how things like electroacupuncture,
and also some of these
new emerging techniques
of kind of like active tissue release
and this principle that
you hear a lot about
in sports medicine now that
when you have pain or injury
at one site, that you
should provide pressure
above and below that site.
You may have seen this in the
Olympics, which is ongoing now
where people will put tape on their body
at certain locations oftentimes.
The logic or what they're
saying is that this is designed
to create relief in a joint or in a limb
that's below the tape, not
necessarily under the tape,
but above or below.
So for instance, if there's
pain in one shoulder,
sometimes we'll put it
on the trapezius muscle
or things of that sort.
It turns out that there
is a basis for this
because of the way that
these different nerves run in
from the skin and from the
muscles up into the spinal cord
and into the brainstem providing pressure
on one nerve pathway can
often impact another pathway.
And the simplest and most
common example of this is one
that we all do
instinctually or intuitively
even animals do this.
This is something that in the
textbooks is all is called
the Gate Theory of Pain
developed by Melzack and Wall
kind of classic theory.
Basically we have receptors in our skin,
the so-called C fibers, that's just a name
for these little wires that come
from a particular class
of DRGs that's very thin
that brings about certain kinds
of nasal scepter information.
I want to say pain information,
but then the pain people believe
are not their pain people.
Sometimes they're a pain
because what they tell me
is they're on pain
receptors okay, nociceptors
That information comes in C fibers
and what happens when we injure something
well, provided that we won't
damage it worse by touching it,
oftentimes what we will do is
we will rub the source of pain
or the location in which
we were experiencing pain.
And it turns out that's not
an unuseful thing to do.
When we rub our skin or an area,
or we provide pressure nearby it,
we activate the so-called A fibers,
the bigger wires and
neurons that innovate,
meaning they jut into that area of skin.
And those A fibers, the ones that respond
to mechanical pressure
actually are able to inhibit
those C fibers, the ones that are carrying
that so-called pain information.
So rubbing an area or providing
pressure above or below
an injury actually provides
real pain relief support
for the location of
that injury or that pain
because of the way that
these different patterns
or these different types
of neurons interact
with one another.
And when I say it inhibits it,
I don't mean that it like shouts at it,
what it does is it releases
it's literally kind of
like vomits up a little
bit of a neurotransmitter
called GABA.
And GABA is a
neurotransmitter that inhibits
it quiets the activity of other neurons.
And so it's acting as kind
of an analgesic, if you will,
it's acting as its own
form of drug that you make
with your body to quiet the
activity of these pain neurons.
So rubbing a wound
provided it doesn't damage
the wound worse or providing
pressure above or below
typically it's above a particular injury
can have a real effect in
relieving some of the pain
of that injury.
And some people have speculated
this as through fascia,
or this is through other
bodily organs and tissues.
And it might be we're going to
do a whole episode on fascia.
It's extremely interesting tissue,
but right now it seems
that the main source
of that pain relief is through
this A fiber inhibition
of these C fibers
so-called Melzack and Wall
Gate Theory of Pain if
you'd like to look it up
and learn about that further.
Now, let's talk about a phenomenon
that has long intrigued
and perplexed people
for probably thousands of years.
And that's redheads.
You may have heard before that
redheads have a higher pain
threshold than other individuals.
And indeed, that is true.
There's now a study that
looked at this mechanistically.
There's a gene called the MC1R gene.
And this MC1R gene encodes
for a number of different proteins.
Some of those proteins
of course are related
to the production of melanin.
This is why redheads often not always,
but often are very fair skinned.
Sometimes have freckles, not always.
And of course have red hair.
Some people are really intense ginger's
not psychologically or emotionally
intense perhaps that too,
but meaning their hair is very, very red.
Others, it's a lighter red.
So of course there's
variation here, but this gene,
this MC1R gene is associated
with a pathway that relates
to something that I've talked
about on this podcast before
during the episode on hunger
and feeding and this is POMC.
POMC stands for pro-opiomelanocortin
and POMC is cut up.
It's cleaved into different hormones,
including one that
enhances pain perception.
This is melanocyte stimulating hormone.
And another one that
blocks pain beta endorphin.
Now, if you listen to the
episodes on testosterone
and estrogen and the episodes
on hunger and feeding,
some of these molecules
will start to ring a bell.
Things like melano
stimulating hormone relate
to pigmentation of the skin
relate to sexual arousal, et cetera,
but it turns out that in red heads,
because of the fact that
they have this gene,
this MC1R gene, the POMC
Pro-opiomelanocortin,
that's cut into different hormones,
melanocyte-stimulating hormones
and another one beta endorphin.
Beta endorphin should cue you to the fact
that this is in the pain pathway.
The endorphins are endogenously made,
meaning made within our body opioids.
They actually make us feel numb
in response to certain kinds of pain.
Now, not completely numb,
but they numb or reduce
our perception of pain
because of the ways in
which they are released
from certain brain centers.
We'll talk about those
brain centers in a moment.
So what's really interesting
is that this study showed
that the presence of these
hormones is in everybody.
We all have melanocortin 4,
we all have beta endorphins.
We all have POMC et cetera,
but red heads make more of
these endogenous endorphins.
And that's interesting.
It allows them to buffer
against the pain response.
I have a personal anecdote
to share with you about
this red head and heightened levels
of pain tolerance phenomenon.
Obviously I'm not a redhead.
I don't dye my hair, but
my partner for many years
was a red head and still is a red head.
She had bright red hair and
had that since childhood.
Well, we had the fortunate experience
of becoming friends
with Wim Hof and family.
They actually came out to
visit us and did a series
of seminars in the bay area.
This was in 2016, as I recall.
And my partner, she had
never done an ice bath.
She had never done any kind
of real cold water exposure
experience before, but as
one particular gathering
as is often the case when women's around,
there was an ice bath and a
number of people were getting
into this thing.
This was actually before a dinner event.
And I think for most people
who have never done an ice bath
getting in for 30 seconds
or a minute is tolerable,
but it takes some effort.
It takes some willpower
and take some overcoming
that pain barrier 'cause
it is a little bit painful.
Not a lot.
Some people can stay in longer
three minutes, five minutes
without much discomfort.
What was incredible is
that without any desire
to compete with anybody else,
my partner redhead got into the ice bath
and just like sat there for 10 minutes.
In fact, at one point she
just kind of turned to me
and said, "I don't really feel pain.
I'm not really in pain."
And Wim loved this.
Wim thought it was great.
He thought it was the most
terrific thing in the world.
And he got back in the ice bath
and they became fast friends,
and I think they're
probably still fast friends.
So in any event, that's an end of one.
What we call an anecdata example.
Anecdata is not really a term
that we should use too much
'cause it's N of one
anecdotes are just that.
They're just anecdotes.
But it's been described many
times in various clinics
by anesthesiologists, by
observation of coaches, et cetera,
that redheads men and
women who are redheads
seem to have this higher pain threshold.
And it does seem to be because
their body naturally produces
ways to counter the pain response.
They produce their own endogenous opioids.
Now this of course should not
be taken to mean that redheads
can tolerate more pain and
therefore should be subjected
to more pain, all it means
is that their threshold
for pain on average, not all of them,
but on average is shifted higher
than that of other individuals.
And it remains to be
determined whether or not
other light skin, light haired individuals
also have a heightened
level of pain threshold.
And I should mention because
I mentioned the ice bath
that of course pain threshold is something
that can be built up and
provide you do that safely
in ways that aren't damaging your tissues
because of course, pain is a signal
that is designed to help you
to keep from harming yourself,
but provided that you can
do that in a way that's safe
and doesn't damage your tissues,
increasing your pain threshold
through the use of things
like ice baths is something
that really can be done.
It has a lot to do with these contextual
or top-down modulations of the experience.
You can tell yourself
that this is good for me,
or I'm doing this by
choice or whatever it is.
You can distract yourself.
There are a huge number of different ways
that one could do that.
One of the more interesting ways
for which there are actually
really good scientific data
come from my colleagues,
Sean Mackey's Lab.
And that actually looked at
how love and in particular,
the experience of obsessive
love could actually counter
the pain response, not just
in redheads, but in everybody.
So that study I'll just briefly describe
it involved having people
come into the laboratory
and experience any one or a number
of different painful stimuli,
but they had selectively
recruited subjects
that were in new relationships
for which there was a
high degree of infatuation
so much so that the people
couldn't stop thinking about
or communicating with that new partner
up to 80% of their waking
time, which is a lot.
That constant obsessing about that partner
was correlated with.
It wasn't causal necessarily,
but was correlated with
the ability to sustain
higher levels of pain
than people who were in
more typical non obsessive
forms of love, longstanding relationships,
where there wasn't long
obsessive love rather.
And of course in this study,
there were a lot of good control groups.
They included a distractor,
they included people
obsessing about other things,
their pet, et cetera.
They included other forms
of love and attachment,
but it does seem that
certain patterns of thinking
can allow us to buffer ourselves
against the pain response.
And that should not be surprising.
Certain forms of thinking are
associated with the release
of particular neuromodulators
in particular dopamine.
And dopamine, it may
seem is kind of the thing
that underlies everything, but it's not.
Dopamine is a molecule that's associated
with novelty expectation,
motivation, and reward.
We talked about this at the
beginning of the episode,
that it's really the molecule
of expectation and motivation
and hope and excitement
more than it's associated
with the receival of the reward.
Well, dopamine is coursing
throughout the brain
at heightened levels and
coursing throughout the body
at heightened levels when we fall in love.
This probably has some adaptive mechanism
that ensure paired bonding between people
or who knows, maybe it ensured not bonding
to multiple people.
Nobody really knows how dopamine functions
in terms of pair bonding,
but it is known that
when people fall in love,
new relationships create
very high levels of dopamine.
And that's probably the mechanistic basis
by which these people were able
to buffer the pain response
by thinking about their partner
or this new relationship
that they're in almost
obsessively or obsessively.
Now that raises a deeper question
we should always be asking.
Yeah, but how, how?
Well, the dopamine system
can have powerful effects
on the inflammation system.
And it doesn't do this
through mysterious ways.
It does this by interacting
through the brainstem
and some of the neurons
that innervate the spleen
and other areas of the body,
that deploy cells to go combat infection,
inflammation, and pain.
And the ways in which
dopamine can modulate pain,
and in this case, this particular study
transform our experience of pain.
Maybe even to something that's pleasureful
is not mysterious.
It's really through the
activation of brainstem neurons
that communicate with areas of our body,
that deploy things like immune cells.
So for instance, we have
neurons in our brain stem
that can be modulated by
the release of dopamine
and those neurons in the
brainstem control the release
of immune cells from
tissues like the spleen
or organs like the spleen.
And those immune cells can
then go combat infection.
We've heard before that when we're happy,
we're better able to combat
infection, deal with pain,
deal with all sorts of things
that essentially makes us more resilient.
And that's not because dopamine
is some magic molecule,
it's because dopamine
affects particular circuits
and tells in a very neuro-biological way
in a biochemical way tells
those cells and circuits
that conditions are good.
Despite the fact that
there's pain in the body
conditions are good.
You're in love or conditions are good.
You want to be in this experience.
Or conditions are good
this is for a greater cause
that you're fighting or suffering
for some larger purpose.
So all of that has existed
largely in the realm
of psychology and even
motivational literature
in this kind of thing,
but there's a real
mechanistic basis for it.
Dopamine is a molecule that
can bind to receptor sites
on these brain areas.
Those brain areas can then
modulate the organs and tissues
of the body that can allow
us to lean into challenge.
And those challenges can be infection,
it can be physical pain, it
can be long bouts of effort
that are required of us.
And I think many people
have described the feeling
of being newly in love as a
heightened level of energy,
a capacity do anything.
I mean, the whole concept
of a muse is one in which
some individual or some
thing either imagined or real
enters our life and we
can use that as fuel.
And that fuel is chemical fuel
and that chemical fuel is dopamine.
And it really does allow
for more resilience
and can even transform
the experience of pain
or what would otherwise be pain
into an experience of pleasure.
So, along those lines,
let's talk about pleasure.
With all the cells and
tissues and machinery related
to pain, you might think
that our entire touch system
is designed to allow us to detect pain
and to avoid tissue damage and well,
a good percentage of
it is devoted to that.
A good percentage of it is also devoted
to this thing that we call pleasure.
And that should come as no surprise.
Pleasure isn't just
there for our pleasure.
It serves adaptive role,
and that adaptive role relates to the fact
that every species has a primary goal
which is to make more of itself
otherwise it would go extinct.
That process of making more
of itself sexual reproduction
is closely associated with the sensation
and the perception of pleasure.
And it's no surprise that not
only is the highest density
of sensory receptors in and
on and around the genitalia,
but the process of
reproduction evokes sensations
and molecules and perceptions
associated with pleasure.
And the currency of pleasure exists
in multiple chemical systems
but the primary ones
are the dopamine system,
which is the anticipation of pleasure
and the work required
to achieve the ability
to experience that pleasure,
and the serotonin system
which is more closely related
to the immediate experience
of that pleasure.
And from dopamine and serotonin
stem out other hormones
and molecules, things like oxytocin,
which are associated with pair bonding.
Oxytocin is more closely associated
with the serotonin system biochemically
and at the circuit level
meaning the areas of the brain
and body that manufacture
a lot of serotonin,
usually not always, but
usually contain neurons
that also manufacturer and make use
of the molecule oxytocin.
Those chemicals together
create sensations of warmth,
of well being, of safety.
The dopamine molecule is
more closely associated
with hormones like testosterone
and other molecules involved with pursuit
and further effort in order
to get more of whatever
could potentially cause
more release of dopamine.
So this is a very broad strokes,
no pun intended description
of the pleasure system.
There are of course,
other molecules as well.
One in particular that's very interesting
is something called PEA.
PEA, it stands for Phenethylamine
sometimes also referred
to as Phenethylamine
depending on who you
are and where you live,
how you pronounce it
doesn't really matter.
PEA is a molecule, which
is incredibly potent
at augmenting or increasing the activity
of certain cells and neural circuits
that relate to the pleasure system.
PEA has purportedly been
thought to be released
in response to ingestion of
things like certain forms
of dark chocolate.
Some people take it in supplement form.
It's a bit of a stimulant,
but it also seems to heighten
the perception of pleasure
in response to a particular
amount of dopamine
and or serotonin.
So for instance, in a kind
of a arbitrary experiment
and units type example,
if a given experience evokes a particular
amount of serotonin and dopamine
and gives rise to a subjective
experience of pleasure
of say level three out of 10,
the ingestion of PEA prior to
that experience can increase
the rating of that experience
as more pleasureful.
Maybe a four or a five, or even a six.
And PEA is known to be present in
or I should say it's releases stimulated
by a number of different
compounds, such as dark chocolate,
certain things like
aspartame and certain people
can actually increase the
amount of PEA released.
Some of these glutamate related
molecules like aspartame
or things are in the glutamate pathway
can increase PEA release.
And then some people
will actually take PEA
in supplement form for its
mild stimulant properties
as well as for increasing
the perception of,
or the ability to experience pleasure.
It's not a sledgehammer.
It's not like dopamine itself.
People that take things
like Mucuna pruriens, L-DOPA
or drugs of abuse, which I
certainly don't recommend
things like cocaine or amphetamine
experience tremendous
increases in dopamine,
not so much increases in serotonin.
Some people will take
serotonin in precursor form
like 5HTP or serotonin itself,
or they'll take the amino acid
precursor like tryptophan.
I'm not saying these
things as recommendations
for increasingly one sense of pleasure,
I'm describing them
because of what they do
generally falls into two categories.
The first category is
to raise the foundation,
what we call the tonic level
of dopamine and serotonin.
So if levels of serotonin
and dopamine are too low,
it becomes almost impossible
to experience pleasure.
There's a so-called anhedonia.
This is also described as depression.
Although it needn't be
long-term depression.
So certain drugs like antidepressants
like Wellbutrin Bupropion
as it's commonly called
or the so-called SSRI,
the serotonin selective
re-uptake inhibitors
like Prozac, Zoloft and
similar will increase dopamine
and serotonin respectively.
They're not increasing the
peaks in those molecules.
What we call the acute
release of those molecules,
what they're doing is they're
raising the overall levels
of those molecules.
They're raising the sort of foundation
or the tide if you will,
think about it as your mood
or your pleasure rather
is like a boat, and if it's on the shore
and it can't get out to sea,
unless that tide is high enough,
that's kind of the way to
think about these tonic levels
of dopamine and serotonin.
Now, most of us fortunately,
do not have problems with our
baseline or autonic levels
of dopamine and serotonin release.
Things like PEA in that case
will cause a slight increase
in that tide and make the
ability of certain experiences
to increase dopamine
further more available.
What we call this in neurosciences
so-called gain control.
I can kind of turn up the volume,
bring us closer to the threshold
to activate certain circuits.
And this is really what we mean
when we say a neuromodulator, okay?
This is why when you are
very happy about something,
let's say you're out with your friends.
You're really excited.
Maybe depending on where
you live and what's going on
in your area of the world right now,
like I have a niece and she's
been locked up in quarantine
for a long time recently
because it was deemed safe.
She got to go to summer camp.
I have never seen that kid so happy
to spend with her friends.
She was so excited and
it was really amazing
to see how excited she was.
Her baseline levels of
dopamine were clearly up
so much so that when she saw her friends,
she literally started squealing.
They were squealing, she was squealing.
Everyone was squealing.
I wasn't squealing.
I would admit it if I was squealing.
I wasn't squealing, but it
was such a delight to see
and I'm sure that made
my dopamine levels go up,
which was, she was just so
excited such that anything
and everything felt like
an exciting stimulus.
This is pleasure, right?
And I don't want to
write off the experience
from an neuro-biological
reductionist standpoint,
quite the opposite.
It's really beautiful to
see again this principle
that different experiences
and the experience of pleasure
from different things.
Seeing your friends for the first time,
summer camp for a kid,
whatever it might happen to
be use the same currency,
dopamine use the same currency serotonin.
And this is a principle that I hope
in listening to this podcast
and even some of it's repetitive features
from one episode to the next.
I'm hoping that those will
start to embed in your mind
that the brain and body
use these common currencies
for different experiences.
So yes, if your dopamine and
serotonin, or I should say
if your dopamine and or
serotonin levels are too low,
it will be very hard to achieve pleasure
to experience physical
pleasure or emotional pleasure
of any kind.
That's why treatments of the sort
that I described a minute
ago might be right for you.
Obviously we can't determine
if they're right for you.
It's also why they have side effects.
If you artificially
increase these molecules
they're associated with pleasure,
oftentimes you get a lack of motivation
to go seek things like food.
People don't get much
interest in food 'cause
why should they if their
serotonin levels are already up.
Again, there's a ton of
individual variation.
I don't want to say that
these antidepressants
are always bad.
Sometimes they've saved lives.
They've saved millions of lives.
Sometimes people have side effects
that make them not the right choice.
So it has to be determined
for the individual.
Things like PEA or a more subtle effect.
I should mention PEA
supplementation is something
that a number of people use
but it's very short-lived.
Because of the half-life of
this molecule was very brief,
the effect only lasts
about 20 minutes or so.
Things like L-dopa, Mucuna pruriens
lead to longer baseline
increases in dopamine.
But remember, any time
you raise a baseline,
you reduce the so-called signal to noise.
What it means is if you're riding around
at really high dopamine, at first,
everything will start to seem exciting
like my niece and seeing her
friends for the first time.
Everything's exciting.
But then what will happen
is when your dopamine levels
return to more normal levels,
it will take a much
greater dopamine increase
of much bigger event,
more novel, more exciting
in order to achieve the sense that
what you're experiencing is pleasureful.
And this is because of the relationship
between pleasure and pain.
Now, in a future episode
we are going to go deep
into this relationship
between pleasure and pain,
but just briefly as a precursor to that
and because it's relevant
to the conversation
that we've been having,
you might want to be
wary of any experience,
any experience, no matter how it arrives,
chemical, physical, emotional,
or some combination,
you might want to be wary
of letting your dopamine go
too high and certainly you want to be wary
of it going too low.
Because of the way that
these circuits adjust.
Basically every time that the
pleasure system is kicked in
in high gear, an absolutely
spectacular event,
you cannot be more ecstatic.
There is a mirror symmetric
activation of the pain system.
And this might seem like
an evil curse of biology,
but it's not.
This is actually a way to
protect this whole system
of reward and motivation
that I talked about
at the beginning of the episode.
It might sound great to
just ingest substances
or engage in behaviors
where it's just dopamine,
dopamine, dopamine,
and just constantly be motivated,
but the system will eventually crash.
And so what happens is when
you have a big increase
in dopamine, you also
will get a big increase
in the circuits that underlie
our sense of disappointment
and re adjusting the balance.
And with repeated exposure
to high levels of dopamine,
not naturally occurring wonderful events,
but really high chemically
induced peaks in dopamine,
high magnitude, chemically
induced peaks in dopamine.
What happens is those peaks in dopamine
start to go down and down and
down in response to the same,
what ought to be incredible experience.
We start to what's called
habituate or attenuate,
and yet the pain increases in size.
And this has a preservative
function in keeping us safe,
believe it or not.
But what I just described
is actually the basis
of most if not all, forms of addiction
something that we will deal with
in a future episode in depth.
So what should you think about all?
How should you think about pleasure
and how should you think about pain?
What is too much pleasure?
Well, that's going to differ
from person to person,
but to the extent that one
can access pleasure repeatedly
over time, ideally without
chemical augmentation,
certainly not excessive
that means that this pleasure
system is tuned up well
and can continue to experience pleasure.
However, if you find yourself engaging
in the same behavior over and over again,
but achieving less and
less pleasure from it,
chances are you want to adjust down
how often you engage in that behavior.
And or adjust down your
expectation of reward
every time you engage in that behavior.
What do I mean by that?
Well, at the beginning of the episode
I talked about how dopamine
will allow us to get
into bouts of hard work.
We will work very hard to pursue a reward,
and that's really what dopamine does.
And then when the reward comes
that doesn't increase our dopamine.
In fact, our dopamine levels go down.
One of the key things that we can all do
to adjust our ability
to experience pleasure
is to engage in that
intermittent reward schedule.
You can either adjust
down the peak in dopamine,
meaning not let yourself
ever get too happy,
but that's no fun, right?
Life is about occasionally achieving
or experiencing ecstasy,
but every once in a
while, remove the reward.
And of course, I don't
mean ecstasy the drug
that's a separate matter.
The MDMA trials are a separate matter.
Very interesting, I want to be clear.
I meant psychological and physical ecstasy
of the natural sort.
I've immense interest in what's
going on in the MDMA trials,
but just for clarity purposes,
that's a separate topic that we will cover
in an episode very soon.
So how do you adjust this dopamine system?
Well, every once in a while at random,
not in a predictable way,
you remove the reward
and that will keep you
and your dopamine system
tune up in the proper ways.
The gain of the dopamine
system, as we say,
will be adjusted so that you can continue
to experience dopamine and serotonin
when you actually get the reward.
This can be translated into a huge number
of different domains,
but I want to give some
examples because I'm sure
that many of you are asking,
wait, what does this actually mean?
Okay, let's say you're a student,
or this could be a student in academia,
or this could be a student
of a physical practice.
Every once in a while when
you do something really well,
maybe that's even just
showing up to the practice
rather than pat yourself on the back,
just tell yourself
yeah, that's the minimum
that's expected of me.
When everyone's excited about
something that you're doing,
maybe you're excited about it,
try and adjust down your
excitement a little bit.
I know this might seem counterintuitive,
but you're preserving the
ability to experience excitement
in a variety of contexts.
Let's say you get a big monetary award.
Well, that's great.
I'm happy for you.
And that's wonderful.
However, you should be a little bit wary
if you care about your dopamine system
and you care about your ability
to get subsequent monetary
rewards, excuse me,
awards rewards doesn't
matter which through effort,
if you want to be able
to maintain the ability
to exert effort, well,
then you probably wouldn't
want to run out and
immediately buy something
with that monetary reward.
In other words, you
wouldn't want to layer on
more dopamine release, okay?
You might, but you might not.
You might skip it.
What you'll find then
is that your motivation
is essentially infinite.
This is what I described at
the beginning of the episode.
And again, it's because
dopamine is this currency.
It's like these days you
hear a lot about Bitcoin,
and Ethereum, and
Dogecoin, and USs dollars,
and Euros and other stuff.
But the currency that you use in your body
doesn't matter what
external currency those are.
In fact, as you watch the value
of different currencies go up
whether or not it's cryptocurrency
or standard currency,
the value is actually
reflective of the dopamine
that exists inside of people.
So all the excitement
about a particular currency
crypto or otherwise is
really just dopamine.
That's the currency that we all use.
And there's no negotiating that.
That's just the way that we're built.
Now, to give yet other examples.
Let's say you're teaching other
people how to do something
and they do something exceptionally well.
If you reward them every single time.
and in particular, if you
reward them with something
that's even greater than the
experience of what they did.
So let's say kids win a soccer game
and they're ecstatic.
They're jumping all over the place.
They're super excited and you reward them
with an even bigger
experience, a celebration,
you are actually inhibiting their ability
to perform the same set of activities
that led them to the win if,
and I really want to underscore
if you reward them every time.
Of course we should
reward kids and each other
and ourselves for our accomplishments,
but you don't want to do it every time.
And sure there will be some disappointment
from suddenly removing the
reward that you expected,
but that's exactly the point.
That's what keeps these
circuits tuned up properly.
Now there's the other form of pleasure,
which is the more immediate visceral
or sensory experience of pleasure.
This is distinct from goals
and goal-directed behavior.
I'm talking about the
immediate experience.
This is more of the serotonergic system.
There are other systems involved too,
but this is also the system
that draws out those endogenous opioids
from a particular structure.
We have a structure in the
back of our brain called PAG
P-A-G, it's the periaqueductal gray area.
Very interesting brain area
that is associated with pain,
but also with pleasure because
under certain conditions,
it deploys endogenous opioids and gives us
a kind of blissed out feeling.
This is not like the opioids
of the opioid epidemic sort
that people take and
unfortunately have led
to tremendous amounts
of suffering and abuse.
These are endogenously released opioids.
These are the kinds of
opioids that come out
from long distance bouts of
physical exercise and running.
These are the opioids that are deployed
in response to giving birth
and overcoming the tremendous
pain of childbirth.
So PAG is very contextual
and there are few types
of stimuli or I should
say events in life...
I'm really showing my nerdy side.
There are a few types of stimulate,
I'm talking about experiences
that evoke endogenous opioid
release from PAG.
One is sexual activity.
Sexual activity can
increase pain threshold.
And here I am not suggesting
or getting involved
in anyone's particular proclivities
or personal experiences.
You're welcome to editorialize
this however you like,
however, what I'm talking
about are animal data
and yes, human data as well,
that show that pain
thresholds are increased
anytime PAG is activated
because of the release
of these endogenous opioids.
There's also the immediate experience
of whether or not a
particular form of touch
is pleasureful or not.
And there there's some
very interesting biology
that relates to really
how those little wires
from those DRGs innovate our skin.
Work studies I should say
done by David Ginty's lab
at Harvard Medical School,
the Ginty lab has spent years working
on the somata sensory
system, the touch system
has identified a particular
category of neurons
that innervate the skin
and then those neurons
of course send that information
up to the brain too.
And they actually respond
to direction of touch.
Now, some of you might be more sensitive
to this than others, but it turns out that
certain hairs like to be
deflected one way versus another.
Whether you like cats or not,
you can do this experiment.
You can pet a cat in the
direction that they're fur lies.
So it lies down in a particular direction.
You'll notice that there's actually a gene
that dictates that the hairs lie down
in a particular direction.
And if you pet them in a way that's
co-operating with that direction.
So not pushing the hairs up,
but rather stroking the
hairs on the back of the cat.
Well, you'll notice as
they often like that.
Not all cats some cats are pretty grouchy,
but if you stroke their hair,
they will often per,
they'll often push into you.
If you were to stroke their
hair in the opposite direction,
pushing the hairs up against the direction
that they want to lie down,
cats do not like that.
And it turns out that people
don't like that either.
Some people do like to
have their hair pushed
in a direction against the direction
in which it wants to lay down.
But there is more typically response
a feeling like it's
pleasureful for instance,
when someone brushes or combs their hair
in the direction that
it wants to lay down.
And that's because the way
in which these neurons,
they innovate these hairs
sends information up
to the brain bifurcates actually,
it splits into brain centers
that evoke a sense of pleasure
or a sense of not pleasure.
It's not necessarily pain.
So you might find that certain
people are very particular.
They like to be touched in a
certain way, but not others.
You might be one of those people.
And areas of our skin
that have high density
of receptors are very, very
sensitive in a real way,
in a real sense of the
word to patterns of touch
and whether or not a touch
is too firm or too light.
And that will be modulated
by overall levels of arousal.
And when I talk about arousal,
what I'm talking about is how
alert or how sleep we are.
It is impossible to experience pain
when we are deep in sleep.
I don't mean sleeping like
of the typical night's sort.
I mean, of the anesthesia sort.
That's the purpose of anesthesia
to bring the brain and body
into a deep plane of
rest, very deep in fact,
and it's very hard if
not impossible to achieve
or experience pleasure when
we are in a very low state
of arousal as well.
When we are in heightened
states of arousal,
we can achieve pain,
we can experience pain
and we can experience pleasure.
And under those heightened
states of arousal,
we are more sensitive.
Literally the passage
of electrical signals
from those locations on the body
that have heightened degrees
or higher degrees, I should say
of receptors, use your imagination.
They include the lips, the
face, the feet, and the genitals
and nearby areas, literally nearby areas.
Under conditions of higher
arousal two things happen,
the ability to achieve
or experience pleasure
at those locations goes up
and our tolerance and our
threshold for pain also goes up.
So the principle here is that
as our levels of arousal,
that foundation of
arousal goes up or down,
so too goes up and down our ability
to achieve pleasure and pain.
And so these two extremes of
being deep within anesthesia
or another extreme as asleep
or an heightened levels of arousal,
our ability to achieve pleasure and pain
are going to scale according to those.
And this is why, and I'm
certainly not suggesting this,
but this is why some
people will take stimulants
or drugs of abuse that increase arousal
in order to achieve
pleasure of other kinds.
The problem is is that
those drugs in particular
are things like cocaine and
methamphetamine and amphetamine
become their own form of reinforcement
so much so that the
person doesn't seek out
any other form of excitement or arousal.
So today we weren't
talking about addiction.
We weren't necessarily
talking about motivation,
but we touched on those
topics as sort of a precursor
of what's to come.
We talked about the pathways
in the skin and in the brain
and elsewhere in the body
that control our sense
of pleasure and pain.
We described a number of
different tools ranging
from hypnosis to different supplements,
to electroacupuncture
and various other tools
that one could use to modulate your sense
of pleasure or pain.
And of course, in thinking about pleasure,
we have to think about the dopamine system
and the serotonin system
and some of the related chemical systems.
I realized that today's podcast
had a lot of scientific details.
We've timestamped everything for you
so that you don't have to
digest it all at once of course
I don't expect that everyone would be able
to understand all these
details all at once.
What's more important
really is to understand
the general principles of how something
like pleasure and pain work.
How they interact, and
the very seldom systems
within the brain and body
that allow them to occur
and that modulator or change
their ability to occur.
And of course your subjective experience
of pleasure or pain.
So I do hope that this was
on hole more pleasureful
than painful for you.
If you're enjoying this podcast
and you're learning from it,
and you'd like to support us,
you can do that in a
number of different ways.
Some of which are totally cost-free.
The first one is please
subscribe to the YouTube channel.
That really helps us.
In addition, you can leave
us comments and suggestions
for future podcast episodes
on the YouTube channel.
You can also subscribe
on Apple and or Spotify
or all three that would really help us.
And on Apple, you can leave
us up to a five star review
and leave us feedback.
There are other ways to
support the podcast as well.
We have a Patreon that's
patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
And there you can support the podcast
at any level that you like.
In addition, please check out our sponsors
that we mentioned at the
beginning of the podcast.
We only work with sponsors and brands
that we absolutely love their products
and that we wholeheartedly endorse,
and that we use ourselves.
In addition, we've partnered with Thorne.
Thorne as a supplement company,
and we've partnered with them
because they have the
highest levels of stringency
in terms of the quality of
the ingredients they use
and the quantity of the
ingredients they use.
By quantity I mean that unlike a lot
of supplement companies out there,
the amounts that are listed
on the bottle are absolutely
what you find in those capsules
and tablets in the bottle.
If you go to Thorne that's
T-H-O-R-N-E/U/Huberman,
you can see the supplements that I take
and you can get 20% off
any of those supplements
as well as any of the other
supplements that Thorne makes.
Just go into the Thorne
site through that portal,
thorne/u/huberman and
even if you navigate off
from that location in the site,
you'll get 20% off any of the
items that you might select
from other locations
within the Thorne site.
If you're not already
following us on Instagram,
it's Huberman Lab at Instagram,
and there I do various
tutorials about neuroscience,
offer neuroscience related
tools all backed by science.
And last but not least,
I thank you for your time and attention
and thank you for your
interest in science.
[bright upbeat music]