- [Andrew Huberman] Welcome
to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
- My name is Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of neurobiology
and ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however part of my desire and effort
to bring zero-cost to consumer
information about science
and science-related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and inform your health goals.
I'm a big believer in
getting blood test taken,
because it's simply the only
way to get in-depth data
about your metabolic factors, hormones,
all the things that inform your immediate
and long-term health.
Nowadays, there are
also excellent DNA tests
that can further inform you
about your immediate and long-term health.
Now the problem with most
blood tests out there
is that you get information
back, you get a lot of numbers,
and they'll tell you whether or not
your numbers are in normal
range or high or low,
but they don't inform you
what steps to take as a consequence.
In addition, they can
often be very confusing,
what all the factors are
and what they really mean.
InsideTracker has a
dashboard and a platform
that makes interpreting all
that information really easy.
It also points you in the direction
of certain lifestyle factors,
exercise, nutrition et cetera,
that you might want to change
in order to bring the numbers
into the ranges that you want.
So InsideTracker is something
that I've been doing for some time now,
and it's really helped
me inform the choices.
For instance, I've swapped out
some of the foods that
I was eating regularly.
I found out I was actually too high
in certain vitamins and minerals,
I was too low in others.
It's really helped me adjust my diet
and my exercise regimes.
And it really gives me the confidence
that I'm on the path to long-term health.
So if you want to try InsideTracker,
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off any of
InsideTracker's plans.
Use the code Huberman at checkout,
that's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off any of InsidTracker's plans
and use the code Huberman at checkout.
Our next sponsor is ExpressVPN.
ExpressVPN is a virtual private network
that keeps your data safe
and secure and private.
It does that by routing
your internet activity
through their servers and encrypting it
so that no one can see or sell your data.
I started using ExpressVPN
because my bank account got hacked.
I still don't know
exactly how it happened,
but it was an absolute mess.
I lost money,
I lost a lot of time.
I wouldn't want to have
it happen to anybody.
When that happened,
I talked to my friends
in the tech community
and they told me that even though
you think your internet
connection is secure
oftentimes it's not.
So I tend to use internet connections
on planes, in hotels, in
cafes, but also at home.
And I was told that even at home,
your data may not be
as secure as you think.
And so with ExpressVPN, your
data is absolutely secure,
so are your online activities.
The great thing is
you don't even notice that it's operating,
it's running in the background.
You just turn it on and it
goes without you realizing
that your data is being protected,
it doesn't interfere with any
of your online activities.
So I use ExpressVPN when I travel,
anytime I'm outside the
house, when I'm at work
and when I'm at home.
If you want to try ExpressVPN,
you can go to expressvpn.com/huberman.
And if you do that, you'll
get an extra three months free
on one of their one-year packages.
That's expressvpn.com/huberman
to get three months free
on a one-year package.
The final sponsor of today's
podcast is Magic Spoon.
Magic Spoon is a zero-sugar,
grain-free, keto-friendly cereal.
As I've mentioned before on the podcast,
I'm neither ketogenic, nor am
I all-meat, nor am I vegan.
The way I eat is that
early in the day I fast,
and then sometime around
noon I eat my first meal,
and that meal is always low carbohydrate,
and then throughout the day,
I maintain a low carbohydrate diet.
The fasting and low carbohydrate
diet during the daytime
optimizes alertness and wakefulness,
I want to be awake and be able to work.
And then at night is when
I eat my carbohydrates,
'cause it facilitates
the transition to sleep.
So for me, Magic Spoon is a
terrific snack in the afternoon.
I'll sometimes even have it with lunch.
And the reason I like it
is because it tastes really delicious,
and it's compatible with the keto-friendly
or keto-like meals that
I eat throughout the day.
They come in a variety of flavors,
cocoa, fruity, peanut butter, frosted.
I particularly like the frosted
because it tastes like
donuts, in my opinion,
and I love donuts.
As a consequence,
I love Magic Spoon cereal.
I can consume it.
It tastes like a pastry and
it has zero grams of sugar,
and it's compatible
with this nutritional
regimen I mentioned earlier.
If you want to try Magic Spoon,
you can go to magicspoon.com/huberman
to grab a variety pack.
Use the code Huberman at checkout
and get $5 off your order.
That's magicspoon.com/huberman,
and use the code Huberman to get $5 off.
This month, we're talking all
about the science of emotions
and tools related to
the science of emotions.
We've talked about the science
of stress and resiliency,
tools to access more calm,
tools raise your stress threshold,
to become more resilient.
We've talked about motivation
and the role of the dopamine system.
I'd like to make a couple of announcements
about some new resources.
The first one is that
we have now captioned
all the Huberman Lab episodes
in English and in Spanish.
We were able to do that,
thanks to your support of
our sponsors and on Patreon.
So now, all of the podcasts
have a captioning feature on YouTube,
and those were done by experts.
So while there might be
the occasional error,
for the most part, they're very precise.
We've done that
so that people that prefer to
consume the content in Spanish
or that like to read the content
from the English subtitles can do so.
And we're going to continue
to expand the number of
languages that are captioned
for the Huberman Lab Podcast.
So we want to thank you for that resource.
It's now available for all episodes.
In addition, in previous episodes
I've talked about NSDR
or non-sleep depressed.
NSDRs come in in a variety
of different forms,
there's self-hypnosis.
I've pointed you to some
resources for that previously.
There's yoga nidra.
NSDR is really about
achieving calm quickly,
and doing that in a self-directed
way, for many reasons,
in order to access sleep more readily,
in order to de-stress very deeply,
in order to replace
sleep that you've lost.
It also seems to aid neuroplasticity.
It can enhance
the rearrangements of
connections in the brain
that occur during learning,
there's scientific support for that.
There's a link in today's
episode caption to a new site.
This is a YouTube video
that was brought free of cost
by the folks over at Madefor,
a company that's been a sponsor
of the podcast previously.
So this is an NSDR script
that doesn't contain any of the intentions
or some of the more typical
language of yoga nidra,
instead it's focused purely
on the breathing protocols,
as well as includes a sort of body scan
where you direct
your attention to different
locations around your body.
It has all the core elements
of non-sleep deep rest,
but is distinct from yoga nidra.
I just offer this to you as a resource.
If you'd like to use it,
it's about 30 minutes long,
and should be very effective
in bringing you into
deep states of relaxation
for all the reasons I mentioned before.
So let's talk about emotions.
Emotions are a fascinating
and vital aspect of our life experience.
It's fair to say that emotions
make up most of what we think
of as our experience of life,
even the things we do,
our behaviors and the places we go,
and the people we end up
encountering in our life,
all of that really funnels
into our emotional perception
of what those things mean,
whether or not they made us happy
or sad or depressed or
lonely, or were all inspiring.
Now one thing that is absolutely true
is that everyone's perception of emotion
is slightly different.
Meaning, your idea of happy
is very likely different
than my idea of what a
state of happiness is.
And we know this also for
color vision, for instance,
even though the cells
in your eye and my eye
that perceive the color red are identical
right down to the genes that they express,
we can be certain based
on experimental evidence,
and what are called
psychophysical studies,
that your idea of the most intense red
is going to be very different
than my idea of the most intense red
if we were given a selection
of 10 different reds
and asked which one is most intense,
which one looks most red,
and that seems crazy,
you would think that
something as simple as color
would be universal, and yet it's not.
And so we need to agree at the outset
that emotions are complicated
and yet they are tractable.
They can be understood.
And today we're going to talk about
a lot of tools to
understand what emotions are
for you to understand what
your emotional states mean
and what they don't mean.
And in doing that, that will
allow you to place value
on whether or not
you should hold an emotional
state as true or not true,
whether or not it has
meaning or it doesn't,
as well as whether or not
the emotions of others
are important to you in a given context.
We're going to talk a
lot about development.
In fact, we're going to center
a lot of our discussion today
around infancy and puberty.
We're also going to talk about tools
for enhancing one's emotional range
and for navigating difficult
emotional situations.
I'm not a clinical psychologist,
I'm not a therapist,
but I do have some
background in psychology.
And today I'm going to be drawing
from the psychology greats, not me,
but from the greats of
psychology who studied emotion,
who studied emotional development,
and linking that to the
neuroscience of emotion.
Because nowadays we understand
a lot about the chemicals
and the hormones and the neural circuits
in the brain and body
that underlie emotion.
So while there's no
one single universally
true theory of emotion,
at the intersection of many
of the existing theories,
there are really some ground truth.
So today we're going to
visit those ground truths.
We're going to talk about the
tools that emerge from them.
And we're going to talk about
some absolutely wild and wacky experiments
that people are doing out there right now,
that I don't necessarily recommend you do,
of inhaling different types of hormones
and trying to get attached more quickly.
You're actually going to do
some experiential stuff today if you like.
There's some things that
you can do in real time
while listening to the podcast,
in order to tap into
some of the mechanisms
that I'll be referring to.
So today's going to be very interactive
in a way that previous
podcast episodes have not.
If we want to understand emotions,
we have to look at where
emotions first develop.
In fact, this is a critical central theme
if you want to understand
brain science and psychology.
There's a rule in neuroanatomy.
Because if you look at 50
different brains of humans
or you compare the brains
of dogs and humans,
there are a lot of differences.
Certain things are the same
but certain things are different.
And the rule that every
good neuroanatomist knows
is that if you want to understand
what a part of the brain does,
you have to address two questions.
First, you have to know what connections
does that brain area make?
What is it connected to?
Where does it get inputs from
and where does it send inputs?
So for instance, if there's
an area of the brain
that gets direct input from
the neurons in the nose,
you can be pretty certain
that it has some role in analyzing smell
in measuring something about odors
or analyzing something about odors.
Now if it also gets input from the eye,
you can also conclude that it gets input
from the visual system that it cares about
light and photons.
This is sort of obvious.
And yet you need to
know that connectivity,
and you need to know what's called
the developmental origin
of that structure.
You need to know where it
was early in development,
because things move around
a lot as the brain develops.
The brain, of course
is this more or less squishy thing
floating around in some liquid
that stuffed inside your skull.
And as a consequence,
things move around a lot.
They are not always in the same place
in two different species
or two individuals of the same species.
So you have to know
where they started out,
because where they started out
informs what they do as well.
And when we're talking about emotions,
we cannot point to one area of the brain.
We can't say that's the area of the brain
that's responsible for emotions.
There is this so-called limbic system
that has been linked to
emotions in various ways.
We're going to talk about that today.
But the limbic system
is just one component
of the inputs to create emotions.
It's not the place for emotions.
You can't go in and lesion
one location in the brain
and eliminate emotions entirely,
just doesn't work that way.
So, first of all, we have to ask,
what are the circuits for emotion?
What are the brain areas for emotion?
And nowadays there's a
lot of debate about this.
For years, it was thought
that there might be circuits,
meaning connections in the brain
that generate the feeling of being happy
or circuits that generate
the feeling of being sad, et cetera.
That's been challenged.
In fact, Lisa Feldman Barrett
has been the person who's
really challenged this head-on,
and has very good evidence
for the fact that such
circuits probably don't exist.
And yet I think there's good evidence
for circuits in the brain,
such as limbic circuits and other circuits
that shift our overall states
or our overall level of
alertness or calmness,
or whether they're not,
they bias us toward
viewing the outside world
or paying more attention
to what's going on inside our bodies.
If none of this makes sense right now,
I promise it will make sense soon.
But the important thing to understand
is that emotions do arise
in the brain and body.
They arise because there
are specific connections
between specific areas
in the brain and body.
And if we want to understand
how emotions work,
we have to look how emotions are built.
And they are built during
infancy, adolescence, and puberty,
and then it continues into adulthood.
But the groundwork is laid
down early in development
when we are small children.
So let's think about
what happens to a baby
that comes into the world.
A baby comes into the world.
You were born into this world
without really any understanding
of the things around you.
Now, there are two ways that
you can interact with the world
and you're always doing them more or less
to some degree at the same time.
Those are interoception,
paying attention what's
going on inside you,
what you feel internally,
and exteroception,
paying attention to what's
going on outside you.
Hold that in mind, please.
Because the fact that
you're both interocepting
and exterocepting is true
for your entire life,
and it sets the foundation
for understanding emotions.
It's absolutely critical.
As an infant,
you didn't have any
knowledge of what you needed.
You didn't understand hunger,
you didn't understand toys
when you first came into the world,
you didn't understand cold
or heat or any of that.
When you needed something, you
experienced that as anxiety.
You would feel an increase in alertness
if you had to use the bathroom.
you would feel an increase in alertness
if you were hungry,
and you would vocalize,
you would cry out, you would act agitated.
You might cue, you might do
a number of different things,
but all you knew was what
you were feeling internally.
And then your caregiver,
whoever that might've been
would respond to that.
So you would feel some agitation,
a caregiver would come
and make a decision,
Oh, you need food, and give you milk,
or change your diaper
or wrap you in a blanket
if you were cold,
but they didn't know if you were cold,
they could just assume that you were cold.
So this is actually really
important to understand
that a baby, when you were a
baby, and when I was a baby,
we didn't have any sense
of the outside world
except that it responded to our
acts of anxiety essentially.
Now this isn't Freudian theory,
There are components of it
that are embedded in Freudian theory,
but all developmental
psychologists agree that
babies lack the ability
to make cognitive sense
of the outside world,
but in this feeling of anxiety
and registering one's own internal state,
and then crying out to the outside world,
either through crying
or subtle vocalizations,
or even just cuing, making some noise,
we start to develop a relationship
with the outside world
in which our internal states,
our shifts and anxiety
start to drive requests,
and people come and respond
to those requests, hopefully.
And the reason I say hopefully
is that we've all heard
presumably about these cases of neglect.
There are a lot of cases
where if you neglect a baby,
you neglect an adolescent or a teenager,
development doesn't go well,
and we'll touch on some of those.
But those are really extreme cases.
They're sort of like the
parallel to experiments
that are often done in the
laboratory with animals,
where you've probably heard
of these enriched environments
where they'll give mice a bunch of toys,
and they'll give them
some different foods
every once in a while,
and they'll house them
together with other mice.
And then what you find
is that the animals,
they will say, "Oh, their brain is thicker
and their neurons have more
branches to them and all that."
But that's really comparing
deprivation with normalcy.
What we want to center on today instead
is what happens when things go well,
and why things might not go well
in certain circumstances is interesting.
But to me, not as interesting
as what healthy emotional
development looks like.
And if you haven't achieved
healthy emotional development,
what can be done as an intervention
at later times in order to rescue that?
So the baby, you as a baby,
you're flopping around there in your crib,
you're getting care where you need it
and when you need it, presumably,
and this gets to the basis
of what emotions are about,
which are emotions are
really about forming bonds
and being able to predict
things in the world.
That's really what emotions are about.
Whether or not the baby
feels angry or happy or sad,
we don't know, we can
guess, but we don't know.
In fact, most of the time we
don't even know how we feel,
let alone how other people feel,
and that's true for adults.
So if I asked you how you feel right now,
I don't know that you could tell me
in any kind of rich
language that I would say,
"Oh I really understand."
If you said you were very, very depressed
or very, very happy,
I'd have some sense because
of how extreme that is,
but I don't know that I would really know,
and I don't think you know
how I feel right now either.
I could be furious right now
or I could be very happy,
you don't have any idea.
And of course, we have these
things called expressions,
our pupils dilate.
There are various cues of how people feel.
We're going to talk about those cues,
but you really don't know.
And at this point I
actually just want to pause
and mention a really interesting tool
that is trying to address this question
of what are emotions and
what do they consist of,
that you can use if you like.
This is an app,
I didn't develop it,
I don't have any relationship to them,
but the app was developed
by people at Yale,
by groups at Yale who do research,
and it's called Mood Meter.
And it's actually quite interesting.
I think it's either free or it's 0.99.
Again, no business relationship to them.
But what they're trying
to do is put more nuance,
more subtlety on our words,
and our language for emotions,
and be able to allow you
to predict how you're going
to feel in the future.
And it's actually quite interesting.
I'm on the app right now, and
I know you can't see this,
but it's called Mood Meter.
And you can find on Apple or Android.
And you go into and it asks you,
it says to me, "Hi, Andrew,
how are you right now?
And I click the little
tab that says I feel.
And I can either pick high
energy and unpleasant,
high energy and pleasant,
low energy unpleasant
or low energy pleasant.
And I would say right now I
feel high energy pleasant.
So I just revealed to you how I feel.
So I click on that,
and then it gives you a gallery of colors,
and you just move your
finger to the location
where you think it matches most.
And as you do that, little words pop up.
I know some people are
listening to this on audio only.
So it say motivated, cheerful, inspired.
I would say, I'm feeling
right now, cheerful.
So you click that and then you
just go to the next window,
and it just says, what are you doing?
And this feels like play to me,
but I'm going to call it work.
And then that's it.
And then what it does
is it basically starts
to collect data on you.
You're giving it information.
And it starts to link
that to other features
that you allowed access to if you like,
and it starts helping
you be able to predict
how you're going to feel
different times a day.
It's actually quite
accurate in certain ways,
quite interesting.
And it points to a couple of
really interesting features,
which is that we don't
really have enough language
to describe all the emotional states,
and yet there's some core truths
to what makes up an emotion.
And I want to review that
twice during today's podcast,
because this can really help people,
kids and adults understand better
what they're feeling and why,
and when best to engage
in certain activities,
and thankfully, when best to
avoid certain activities too.
So the way this works is the following.
You need to ask yourself at any point,
you could do this right now if you like,
what's your level of autonomic arousal?
Autonomic arousal is just the continuum,
the range of alert to calm.
So if you're in a panic right now,
you are like 10 out of
10 on the arousal scale.
If you're asleep,
you're probably not
comprehending what I'm saying,
although maybe a little bit.
But let's say you're very drowsy,
you might be at a one or a two.
So you always have to ask,
where are you on the arousal scale?
And then there's this other
axis, this other question,
which is what we call valence.
Now valence is a value.
Do you feel good or bad?
I would say I feel pretty good right now.
On a scale of one to 10,
I'm like, I dunno, I feel like a seven.
Got good night's sleep last night,
had a good walk with
Costello this morning,
I'm fed, I'm hydrated.
I feel good,
So I'm like a seven.
So I'm alert and I feel pretty good.
And then there's a third thing,
which is how much we are interocepting
and how much we are exterocepting.
So how much our attention
is focused internally
on what we're feeling and how
much it's focused externally.
And this is always going
to be in a dynamic balance.
So for instance, if you're
really, really stressed,
oftentimes that puts you in a position
to be really in touch with
what's going on in your body.
If you start having a lot of somatic,
a lot of bodily sensations,
like your heart is beating so
fast that you can't ignore it,
then you're really strongly interoceptive.
But also sometimes you're really stressed
because someone's stressing you out
or somebody sends you a text message
or makes a comment about
a YouTube thing you posted or something,
and you're really triggered by it.
That never happens to me.
But if it does happen to you,
then you're exterocepting.
So these three things,
how alert or sleepy you are, that's one,
how good or bad you feel, that's two,
and then whether or not
most of your attention
is directed outward,
or whether or not it's directed inward.
And much of what we call emotions
are made up by those three things.
And so let's return now to development,
but tuck that away and just
kind of think about it,
alert versus asleep, good versus bad,
and focused internally
or focused externally.
Because when I looked at
all the theories of emotion
that were out there,
there were a lot of
different components to them,
but they all seem to center back
to these same three features
in some way or to some degree or another.
And it can be very powerful to understand
and look at your emotions
through that lens.
So let's return to the infant.
There's the baby in the crib.
It's mostly interocepting.
As caregivers bring it
what it needs, you hope,
milk, diaper changes, et cetera,
a warm blanket if it's cold,
pull off the blanket
when the baby's fussing and it's too warm,
'cause babies get too warm also,
it starts to exterocept.
Excuse me, I misspoke,
I want to be very clear,
it starts to exterocept.
The baby starts to look
into the outside world
and start making predictions.
It starts wondering how much
it needs to cry or predicting,
"Well, if I cry like a little bit,
then mom comes over and I get my milk.
Or if I cry a lot, mom doesn't
come over and give me milk,
so I need to really scream
at the top of my head."
So babies are starting to
evaluate and do all this,
but they're not doing it consciously.
They're doing this strategically
in order to relieve anxiety.
And I won't propose that that's
what we do into adulthood.
But a lot of what we do in adulthood
is when we feel something,
we start exterocepting.
Some people are much better
at just sitting as a container
and just interocepting
and paying attention to what
they're feeling internally.
But most people do a little
bit of a balance of both.
We don't feel good,
so we look for an item or food
that might make us feel better.
We're feeling anxious
heading into the dentist
or something like that,
so we text somebody.
We do this almost reflexively,
it's not always conscious.
So infants do this, and
we continue to do this.
We start to now balance our interoceptive
and exteroceptive focus,
looking inward and looking outward.
And as we do that,
we're starting to figure
out what gets our needs met.
Remember, emotions are
really there to form bonds
and to make predictions.
And so our needs are going to
be met to some degree or not.
Sometimes sadly there is neglect.
Sometimes people don't show up for us
the way that we would like.
And in general, our responses to that
have to do with whether or not
we predict whether or
not they would or not.
When we expect something
and it doesn't happen,
It's a big let down.
That was the discussion
about dopamine last episode.
So the many theories of emotion,
the triune brain theory,
that you have a primitive
and involved brain,
something that's a little bit
on shaky ground these days.
The idea that Darwin proposed,
that there are these universal
expressions of emotions.
The work of Helen Fisher on love,
that you have circuits in the brain
for lost circuits in the brain,
for love and circuits in the
brain for long-term bonds,
as well as the work of
Lisa Feldman Barrett,
saying that emotions are contextual,
that they have a social component.
And I'll be talking more about this,
but the work of Allan Schore,
a clinical psychologist
and researcher at UCLA,
about right brain, left brain,
and its role in emotional development.
All of them have strong elements
of this idea of paying attention
to what's going on inward and outward.
As a young creature, an
infant and young toddler,
you were mainly focused inward,
and you started to understand
what was going on outward
as a way of predicting what
would bring you relief,
what would remove your anxiety.
And that's where the fundamental
rules of your experience,
your emotional experience were laid down.
And I realized that's a lot of information
and it's somewhat of an academic talk,
but there were two tools in there
that I just want to highlight,
one is the Mood Meter app.
If you're interested in, it
can give you some insight
into the different kinds
of nuance within emotions
and allow you to actually
predict emotional states,
if you want to try that
and you might find that interesting.
The other one is this idea that
there are three axes two emotion,
three continuum that interact,
the level of alertness and calmness,
how good or bad you feel,
and whether or not you're mainly
focused inward or outward,
because those are going
to form a useful tool kit
for the information going forward.
So now let's talk about
what kind of baby you were,
because that actually informs
your emotionality now.
These are classic.
They're actually famous experiments
done by Bowlby and Ainsworth.
Anyone that study psychology
or has taken a psychology class
might have learned about this.
This is this classic experiment
of what was called the strange
situation task in which,
and I'm describing it very
coarsely here, I realize.
But a mother and child
come into the laboratory.
Yes, this is now also
been done with fathers.
The baby and the mother or
father play together for a bit,
and then the mother leaves.
The mother leaves for some period of time
and then comes back.
And the research is devoted
to understanding the response of the child
when the caretaker,
the mother or the father
returns, most all children,
not every child, but
most children will cry
when their primary caretaker leaves.
They don't like that.
And there are good reasons for that.
They formed a bond and an attachment.
And we will talk about
some of the deeper chemical
reasons for those bonds.
However, the experiment is focused
on the return of the caregiver.
Because Bowlby and Ainsworth,
and many of their scientific
offspring and colleagues
identified at least four
patterns that babies display
when their caretaker returns,
and they group these
into group a, b, c, d,
so much so that the kids
were referred to as a babies,
b babies, c babies or d babies.
You may know which one you were.
But the categories are really interesting.
The first babies are the a babies.
So these were kids
that would get upset when
their caretaker would leave.
But when their caretaker would return,
the infant would respond with happiness,
with what looked like delight.
They would go to the caretaker.
They seemed happy.
If they had been fussy before
or sad, they felt relieved.
These are referred to
as secure attached kids.
So they have a healthy
response to separation,
and they have a healthy response
to re-engaging with the caretaker.
The b babies as they're called
were less likely to seek
comfort from their caregiver
when the caregiver would return.
So they would sometimes
continue to play with their toys
or if they had an adult in the room
while the parent was gone,
they would stay with them.
It was sometimes complicated and nuanced,
but these were referred
to as avoidant babies.
Don't run away with any conclusions
about the language here just yet.
It's not clear that avoidant
babies become avoidant adults,
but bear with me.
The c babies would respond to
the return of the caregiver
with acts of annoyance.
They seemed kind of angry.
So it wasn't that they ignored them,
they seem kind of angry.
And those were referred
to as ambivalent babies,
not to be confused with a babies.
These are the c babies,
were the ambivalent babies.
So the infant's reaction
to the returning caregiver
were inconsistent.
It seemed like they wanted
to bond with them again
but that they seem kind of annoyed.
I think we've all felt this way before
with people that we care very much about,
especially people we care very much about.
And then the third category, the d babies,
were the disorganized babies,
that's what they call them.
They weren't disorganized
and that they were messy,
the child avoided
interactions with everyone
and acted fearful when
the caregiver returned,
and their behavior didn't really change
whether or not the
caregiver was there or not.
And that fourth category was
actually added rather late
in the course of this research.
I should mention these
experiments have been repeated
with a huge variety of different contexts.
There was work done by Mary Main
at UC Berkeley and many others,
looking at all sorts of
variations on this theme.
But over time, it made it clear
that certain babies
are able to feel secure
upon re-engaging with their
caregiver and others don't,
or they're confused about it.
So we probably don't know
whether or not you were
an a, b or c, d baby,
unless you were in these experiments
and somehow you had that knowledge.
But this work, this classic work
opened up a huge set
of important questions
that relate to what is the reestablishment
of the bond really about.
I mean, what's actually
being figured out here
is not whether or not there
are four categories of babies,
that's interesting,
but it presumably is more interesting
to focus on what is it that
defines a really good bond,
a secure attachment, or
an insecure attachment
or an avoidant attachment.
And the four things are
gaze. literally eye contact,
and doesn't have to be
direct beaming eye contact
with no blinks like people
have accused me of before.
It can just be gaze,
people look at each other,
you see couples, they look at each other,
they don't always stare each
other long periods of time,
sometimes they do.
Vocalizations, so what
we say and how we say it.
Affect or emotion,
so the way that we express
it, crying, smiling
et cetera, and touch, those four things.
And you probably could
add a fifth dimension
once language and written
language develops,
which is written word,
exchange of letters,
exchange of texts,
exchange of things of that
sort, emails, are another way
in which people can bond.
But gaze, vocalization, affect
and touch are really the core
of this thing that we call
social bonds and emotionality.
Now that's important.
We know for instance
that there are brain areas
like the fusiform face area
which is deep in the brain
that is responsible for
the processing of faces.
Children's recognition of
their parents' faces and voices
is extremely accurate and strong.
Likewise, parents recognition
of their child's vocalizations
not just voices, but cries are remarkable.
If you've ever had the
experience of being at a party
with somebody who has small children
and you're talking to them,
and all of a sudden they
hear something but you don't,
it's as if they've got wolf hearing,
and all of a sudden, they go
running into the other room.
And indeed the kid is like, I don't know,
some kid is beating up their kid
or their kid's beating up some other kid,
or the kid injure themselves
or feels emotionally injured.
This perception of voices.
There's very good evidence
to support the fact that we are tuned
to the frequencies of voices
and vocalizations of
people that we care about.
It's not just true in rodents
and in birds and other mammals,
it's definitely true in humans as well.
And babies are very tuned in
to the sound of their mother's voice,
even, yes, while they're in the womb.
There's this whole world of
what's called mother-ease,
which is the particular
style of speech that mothers
and other caretakers now
we know use with children.
So those are the core elements.
How you look at somebody
and how they look at you,
what you say, what they say,
what they seem to be feeling,
and how that makes you
feel, smiles, frowns.
If you know someone really
well, you can read inflections,
like even little subtle things like,
mm, they don't really believe me,
or, oh they're really excited by this,
or, oh, now I know what they're thinking.
That kind of processing,
some people are better at it than others,
but everyone's better at doing that
with people that we recognize and know.
In fact, couples come to know
each other exceedingly well,
so much so that it can both benefit
and injure their relationship
to constantly be making these perceptions.
But there's a range.
Some people are more tuned
into this than others.
And that probably has roots
in the sorts of attachments
that you form early on.
So Bowlby and colleagues
develop these a, b, c, d thing.
And it has a lot to do
with face processing
and gaze and vocalizations and touch,
all of those happen on
return with the mother,
but they weren't parsing those,
they weren't looking at them individually.
So this raises a really
interesting question, which is,
what is it when we feel something?
Is it because of something
that happened spontaneously
in us, it's a memory,
or it's something that we
realize, we saw on the internet
or we got news about somebody?
Nowadays people get so much information
about the people they know,
both the people they like and dislike
by way of viewing online activities.
So they're exterocepting,
and then it's impacting
your internal state.
And it's clear
from most all of the
theories of emotional health,
that an ability to recognize
when your own internal state
is being driven primarily
by external events,
as important for being able
to emotionally regulate.
People who are constantly
being yanked around by the
external happenings in the world,
you would say are emotionally labile,
they are not in control of their emotions,
even if they're calm all the time,
if that calmness only arrives
because they're in a placid environment
and then you put a cracker
in that environment
and they freak out, well,
then they're not really calm.
Their calm in so far
as there isn't something
disturbing in the environment.
So how much the outside environment
disrupts your internal environment
has everything to do
with this balance of interoception
and an exteroception.
And it very likely has roots
in whether or not you were secure attached
or insecure attached,
disorganized or ambivalent as a baby.
And of course, you can't
travel back in time and know,
but there are some hints
as to what kind of
emotionality each of us has
by examining two periods of development,
one is adolescence and puberty
and the other is adulthood.
So while we can't travel back in time,
there is an exercise that you can do
to address at least in this moment,
whether or not you have
a bias for exteroception
or a bias for interoception,
whether or not you are better
at least in this moment,
at paying attention
to what's going on
internally or externally.
And of course, this will
vary with circumstance.
I think we all know people
that, maybe it's you,
you go to a party and you get there,
and everyone seems to be talking
and having a really good time,
and you're wondering whether or not
you have any food in your teeth
or whether or not there's
something on your face
or whether or not your hair is right
or whether or not you said
something the wrong way,
whether or not you're turning red.
People also experience this
a lot with public speaking.
It's not just about learning
to clamp your level of stress,
it's also about how much
you're exterocepting,
how much you're out of
your head, they call it.
But how much you're focused
on the events around you
versus the events inside you.
Actually, it's interesting
when you talk to people who
are very effective athletes
or they have very high
stress high consequence jobs,
they talk about this notion
of getting out of your head.
You only have so much
attentional resource,
and it can be split between two things,
you'll see that in a moment.
They can be anchored to one thing.
It can be fully focused on
what's going on internally
or it can be fully focused on
what's going on externally.
And if you want to be
effective in the world,
effective being in quotes,
it is useful when in very
dynamic environments,
especially social environments,
to have a lot of your
attention focused outward
as opposed to trying to pay attention
to whether or not you're
saying things correctly
or the tambour of your own voice,
that is more or less destructive
for the ability to engage socially.
So here's the exercise.
You can do this.
Please don't do this if you're driving.
But let's just try and illustrate
or allow you
to experience this interoceptive,
exteroceptive balance,
and the extent to which you can move
interoception and
exteroception deliberately.
If you close your eyes right now
and concentrate on the contact
of any portion of your body
with say the chair or your car seat,
although please, again,
don't do this while you're driving,
anywhere that you are,
even if you're just standing
up or you're in the kitchen,
you're laying on the couch,
and trying to bring as
much of your attention
to that point of contact as possible.
And then from there,
you're going to move your
attention even more deeply
into say the sensation of
what's going on in your gut.
Are you full?
Are you empty?
Are you hungry?
Are you not?
Is your heart beating, at what rate?
What's the cadence of your breathing?
Basically bringing your
focus and attention
to everything at the surface
of your skin and inward.
So I'm going to do a rare thing
on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
I'm going to introduce about
five to eight seconds of silence
in order to allow you
to do that a little bit.
Now this is an exercise
that you can continue afterward
if you want to extend
how long you do this.
But now try and do something that,
for most people actually
is a little bit harder,
which is to purely exterocept,
put your eyes or your ears, or both
on anything in your
immediate space, one thing.
And I would restrict that
thing to something small enough
that at least in your field of view
it would occupy 20% of your field of view.
So it doesn't have to be a pinpoint
unless the pin is right in front of you
and you're holding it real close.
I would say, look across the
room, pick a panel on the wall
or a leg of a table or something,
and try and bring
as much of your attention
to that as possible.
And again, I'll take about
five seconds of silence
to allow you to exterocept.
So what you probably found is that
you were able to do that,
but that some degree of
interoception is maintained.
It's hard to place 100% of your attention
on something externally,
unless it's really exciting, really novel.
If you've ever watched
a really great movie,
presumably you're exterocepting
more than you're interoceptive
until something exciting happens
and then you feel something.
You're actually tethering
your emotional experience
to something external.
And now you can also do this dynamically.
You can decide to focus
internally and externally.
You can decide to split
it 50%, 50% or 70/30.
You can develop a heightened
ability to do this.
And the power of doing that
is actually that when
you are in environments
where you feel like you're
focused too much internally
and you'd like to be
focused more externally,
you can actually do that deliberately.
But as you notice, it takes work,
it involves taking your
attentional spotlight,
and what we call the
aperture of your attention,
and narrowing that
aperture to either the self
or something externally
or splitting the two.
And yet there are practices
that have been developed that center on
moving interoception and exteroception
from one being more heavily
weighted than the other,
more focused outward
or more focused inward.
And it's dynamic.
And the circuits in the brain
that underlie intero and exteroception
aren't exactly known,
but they are anchored in
the areas of the brain
that are involved in attention,
like the frontal eye fields
and areas that when you
third-person yourself,
when you can see yourself doing something,
like if you put your hand
out in your environment
and you focus on your hand,
you know that that's your hand
as opposed to some random object.
There are areas of the brain
that are involved in that,
in recognizing location of self
relative to the rest of your body.
These exercises are really
what are at the core
of these development of emotional bonds.
Because as we mentioned
before, these four things,
the gaze, vocalization, touch and affect,
those are happening very dynamically.
So if somebody winks at you,
you're paying attention to their wink,
but then you also notice how you feel.
Then they might say something,
then you might say something,
this is very dynamic.
So if it seems overwhelming
to try and interocept an exterocept
and then shift the balance,
you do that all the time.
Your brain and nervous system
are fantastic at doing this.
Now, some people have a very hard time
breaking out of a very
strongly interoceptive mode.
Some people have a harder time
breaking out of their exteroceptive mode.
It's very interesting note
the extent to which we have biases
in how interoceptive or
exteroceptive we are.
Remember those three axes
that we talked about earlier,
you have valence, good or bad,
you have alertness, alert or calm,
and you have interoceptive
or exteroceptive bias.
And it's going to differ across the day,
it's going to differ across the lifetime.
It's certainly going to differ
according to whatever it
is that you're engaged in.
But early in development,
you start off with this
interoceptive bias.
You are starting to develop
expectations, predictions
about how the outside
world is going to work.
And you are trying to
figure out the reliability
of outside events in people.
And where things are reliable,
when people are reliable,
we are able to give up
more of our interoception.
There's literally trust
that our interoceptive needs
our internal needs will be met
through bonds and actions of others.
This starts to veer toward
the discussion about neglect and trauma.
We are going to devote entire episodes,
probably an entire month
to trauma and PTSD.
But those have roots in what
we're talking about now.
And it's important to internalize
and understand what
we're talking about now
in order to get the most out
of those future conversations.
So if all of this seems like
a lot of information and very complicated,
I just invite you to pay
attention from time to time
how much you happen to be
interocepting or exterocepting,
because emotions and the
intensity of those emotions
will grow or shrink
depending on how much we're interocepting.
If we are feeling extremely sad,
and there is an outside
event that made us sad,
chances are there's going to be a balance,
but that the extreme
grief, the extreme sadness
is going to lead us to
mostly interoceptive.
Whereas when we're
feeling extremely happy,
the same is true.
Something great happens in the world,
and we're just going to feel it.
Most of our perception,
most of our awareness is going
to be on our internal state.
So we are always tethered
to the outside world
to some degree or another.
That was true when you were an infant,
and it was true when
you were an adolescent,
and it's true as an adult.
So now I want to just pause,
just shelve the discussion
about interoception,
exteroception for a moment.
And I want to talk about
what is arguably the second most, if not,
equally important aspect
of your development
as it relates to emotionality
and as it relates to
this, what I call trust,
but this ability to predict
whether or not things in the outside world
are reliable or not reliable
in terms of their ability
to help you meet your interoceptive needs.
And that period is puberty.
So up until now, we've been
talking mainly about psychology,
not a lot of biology,
not a lot of mechanism.
And now we're going to transition
into talking about mechanism,
hormones, receptors, et cetera.
Puberty is a absolute biological event.
It has a beginning, and it
has a specific definition,
which is the transition
into reproductive maturity.
So there are a lot of hormonal changes.
Yes, there are also a
lot of brain changes.
And most people don't realize it,
but the brain changes occur first.
The brain turns on the hormone systems
that allow puberty to occur.
Puberty is occurring earlier nowadays
than it did in the past.
The current numbers
that I was able to find
is that in females and girls,
the transition is starting around age 10,
whereas in boys, it's about age 12,
that's going to differ
by way of a number of different factors.
Those are averages.
So it depends on where
you are in the world,
depends on all sorts of things.
One of the primary triggers for puberty
is actually body fat.
This is interesting.
The peptide hormone, leptin,
some people call it a peptide,
some people call it a hormone,
but it meets both definitions
depending on how you look
at it, is made by fat.
So leptin had a lot of
popularity in the '90s,
because it was discovered
as being produced by fat,
and it was seen in animal studies
that it could promote leanness.
It actually communicates to the brain
that there's enough body fat
in order to allow the metabolic factors
and processes to occur
to liberate more fat.
This is why people have trouble
losing that last five pounds.
It's because leptin levels are very low.
This was actually the basis
for the whole cheat day, refeed thing,
that the idea was if you
eat a lot for one day a week
while dieting hard,
that you can signal to the brain
that there's enough leptin.
I don't know if that's the reason
or whether or not the cheat days
just provided some psychological
relief, probably both.
But in any case, leptin
is made by body fat.
And when there's enough leptin,
it signals the brain to trigger puberty.
There was a paper
published in the mid '90s
in the Journal Science, excellent journal,
showing that leptin could be
injected into younger females
that would not have yet gone into puberty.
And you could accelerate the
onset of puberty with leptin.
So more body fat, the
earlier puberty, that's true.
Leptin is also involved
in various growth effects
in the body generally.
And it's interesting, very obese children
don't necessarily undergo puberty earlier.
Sometimes they do, but they
do tend to be larger boned.
Their bones actually grow more quickly,
and they tend to have higher bone density
because leptin is also
involved in bone density.
The whole issue of onset of puberty
also has some really
interesting social effects.
And I want to really highlight
that most of these effects,
also called pheromone effects.
Remember a hormone
is a substance secreted from
one area of the body, travels,
and impacts tissues and
cells elsewhere in the body.
A pheromone is a chemical
that's released by one member of a species
that goes and acts on
and impacts other members of that species
or even other species.
So for instance, rodents are very good
at detecting the urine
and the scent markings of large carnivores
that want to eat them.
So that's a pheromone interaction.
Whether or not they're
pheromonal effects in humans
is very debated.
I did a post on this on
Instagram a little while ago
about some pheromone effects
that were reported in humans.
And I had a couple of
people come at me saying,
"Look, it's never really
been shown in humans
that there's a pheromonal vomer,"
what's called the vomeronasal organ.
There's something called Jacobson's organ.
It's rudimentary.
Some people have it, some people
don't, very controversial.
So I want to point out
that human pheromone
effects are controversial.
Although I think there's, in my opinion,
there's ample evidence for them,
synchronization of menstrual cycles.
Many people report,
then people say there's some studies
that show that it's not true.
Then there've been some
data showing very impressive
pheromonal effects of female partners
being able to detect the odor
of their significant others
on t-shirts that were
washed several times.
So they can't consciously perceive it,
but they say this one smells like them,
this one smells like my partner.
And indeed, the match
was way above chance.
So there does seem to be
weak pheromonal effects
at least in my opinion
when I look at the data,
but much more needs to be done.
So one of the more
interesting pheromone effects
that impacts puberty, at
least in animal models
is the so-called Vandenbergh
effect, which is,
if you take a pre-pubertal female,
so a female that has not
undergone sexual maturation,
and you introduce a novel male
that is not the father or
a brother, not a sibling,
she will undergo puberty
almost immediately.
So this is really striking.
For years,
this was thought not to
occur in primate species,
but there was a paper published last year
in Current Biology, Cell Press
journal, excellent journal,
showing that mandrills, a
particular type of primate,
they exhibit this Vandenbergh effect.
There are also all sorts
of other pheromone effects.
There's the most infamous one
is called the Bruce effect,
where the introduction of a novel male
to a pregnant female animal
causes spontaneous miscarriage.
And that effect seems
to be protected against
by the presence of the father.
This interpretation of this,
and I want to really highlight
that these are animal studies,
but the way this works
is that if a pregnant female
is in the company of the
male that impregnated her,
then her young are protected
by his scent presence or
his pheromone presence.
But if he's gone and
a novel male shows up,
there's a tendency for her
to spontaneously miscarry,
and essentially for the fetus to be lost.
Now, whether or not this occurs in humans
is still very controversial,
but nonetheless,
these pheromone effects exist.
And that one is called the Bruce effect,
named after Hilda Bruce,
who is the scientist that discovered it.
The one that's relevant
to the puberty discussion
is the Vandenbergh effect,
which I mentioned a few minutes ago,
which is a novel male showing up,
has to be a sexually competent male,
so he has to have already
passed through puberty,
and his presence triggers
activation of puberty
in a female that otherwise
would have remained
pre-pubertal for longer.
Again, whether or not this
happens in humans is unclear.
Well, what can we be sure about
when we think about puberty?
Puberty is triggered by a
number of different factors.
There are changes in GABA
expression in the brain,
an inhibitory transmitter.
One of the more interesting molecules
that triggers puberty in all individuals
is something called kisspeptin,
K-I-S-S-P-E-P-T-I-N, kisspeptin.
Kisspeptin is made by the brain.
And it stimulates
large amounts of all different hormone
called GnRH, gonadotrophin-releasing
hormone to be released.
Gonadotropin-releasing hormone
then causes the release of another hormone
called luteinizing hormone or LH,
which travels in the bloodstream
and stimulates the ovaries of
females to produce estrogen
and the testes of males
to produce testosterone.
Kisspeptin has other effects as well.
But those are some of the main ones
as they relate to puberty.
This is interesting,
because at this point,
the testes in males
start churning out tons of testosterone
in order to trigger
the development of secondary
sexual characteristics,
body hair and all the others,
deepening of voice, et cetera.
And in females, estrogen is
doing various other things,
breast development, et cetera.
Normally, in an adult,
somebody who has passed puberty,
a big increase in
gonadotropin releasing hormone
and luteinizing hormone would
eventually be shut down,
because the way that the brain works,
the hypothalamus and the pituitary
are actually measuring how
much hormone is in the blood.
And if testosterone or estrogen
or any other hormone goes too high,
they shut down
the release of things
like luteinizing hormone.
It's called a negative feedback loop.
Basically is like a
thermostat in the house.
It's more complicated than that,
but once levels get too
high in the blood stream,
it shuts down.
But kisspeptin is able to drive
very high levels of these
hormones in an ongoing way
so that puberty can
commence and can continue.
And incidentally,
kisspeptin has now become
yet another of the panoply of hormones
and peptides and cocktails
that athletes take
in order to try and stimulate
natural hormone production,
essentially to create their own
performance-enhancing drugs endogenously.
No judgment there, but that's a fact,
there's a lot of kisspeptin used.
I truly not suggesting anyone do this,
but people are buying
and injecting kisspeptin
for the specific reason
that even past puberty
can stimulate the large increases
in things like estrogen,
large increases in testosterone
and things of that sort.
Has a number of psychological effects too,
seems to have big effects
on libido, et cetera.
All these things of course
are subject to feedback loops,
so they don't work indefinitely.
And I'm going to highlight,
again, I'm not suggesting anyone do it,
but I do like to pay
attention to what's out there.
And kisspeptin, because it
wasn't discovered that long ago
is one of the things that
you don't often hear about
when people talk about
performance-enhancing drugs
or therapeutic endocrinology.
These things also have therapeutic uses
in the endocrine setting.
So for instance, kids
that don't undergo puberty
or kids that are hypogonadal
or adults that are hypogonadal,
they're not making enough hormone
will take things like
kisspeptin among other things.
So that's how puberty happens
at the biological level,
gets triggered by leptin and kisspeptin.
And then this young child
is now a different
creature to to some extent,
not just because
they're reproductively
competent, of course,
but because there's a shift
in a number of the things that
underlie these social bonds,
there's a market shift
in a number of the things
that allow children and adults
to engage in predictive
behavior about each other.
And the whole nature of
adolescence and puberty
is to take a child that was a generalist
and to make them a specialist.
And this is very important
as it relates to the
conversation about emotionality.
But it's important in terms
of aspects of brain function
and in terms of learning
and in terms of who
each and every one of us
will and has become.
In adolescents and in childhood,
sure, there are some genetic biases,
hair color, eye color,
height, and things like that.
A lot of that's programmed
into the genome.
There are other genetic
biases too of course,
that we inherit.
But it's in adolescents in puberty
that we go from essentially
being somewhat good at a bunch of things
or somewhat poor at a bunch of things,
to be coming very good at a few things
and very poor at a lot of other things.
And that's because
of the relationship to
puberty and neuroplasticity,
this ability to change the
brain in response to experience
is starting to taper off
such that by our early 20s,
it's harder to achieve.
Now, the transition from
generalist to specialist
is one aspect of adolescence and puberty,
but the other is the formation
of social and emotional bonds.
And most of what consumes the minds
and waking hours of adolescents
and children who have gone through puberty
and going through puberty
is questions about how they
relate to social structures,
who they can rely on,
and how they can make reliable
predictions in the world,
now that they have more urgency
that they are physically changed.
In fact, you could argue
that puberty is the
fastest rate of maturation
that you'll go through at
any point in your life.
It's the largest change
that you'll go through
at any point in your life
in terms of who you are,
because your biology has
fundamentally changed
at the level of your brain
and your bodily organs,
all your organs from the skin inward.
So I want to visit a
little bit of the research
about some of the core needs that occurred
during puberty and adolescence,
not just for parents
or for the people that might
be in puberty and adolescence,
but also so that people can reflect
on which of the sort of boxes
were checked off for them
as they approached emotional maturity.
So there's a terrific review article
that was published in the
journal Nature, which is,
if not the premier,
then certainly among the
top three premier journals
in the field of science
about the biology of
adolescence and puberty,
as well as some of the
core needs and demands
that have to be met
for successful emotional
maturation during that time.
We will provide a link to that,
but I just want to highlight
a few of the things that they
place in the final table.
I don't want to go through
all the results right now,
because you could do that
on your own if you like.
They mainly highlight
a lot of the changes in
neurons and neural circuits.
For instance, I'll just highlight one,
there's a connection
between the dopamine centers in the brain
and an area of the brain
that's involved in emotion and dispersal.
Dispersal is very interesting.
What you observe in animals and humans
is that around the end of adolescence
and during the transition to puberty,
both because of changes in the
brain and changes in hormones
there's an intense desire
on the part of the child
to get further and further
away from primary caregivers,
not permanently, they always return,
similar to a child that walks off
and then looks back and
sees if everything's safe
and then continues on.
During adolescence and puberty,
both in animals and in kids,
it almost seems like
there's a bias for action,
and the action
is always in a direction away
from the primary caregiver.
Now, as soon as I say that,
I can just imagine in my mind
that somebody out there saying,
"Well, no, my kid as
soon as they hit puberty,
they just want to stay
home with us all the time."
That's not typical.
It happens, but it's not typical.
Mostly there's a desire
to start spending more time with friends,
more time with peers and
less time with adults.
And I find it extremely interesting
to note that that's not
just true in humans,
that's true in other primate species.
That's true in rodents.
That's true in almost every
other mammalian species.
So there's something about these hormones
that don't just allow sexual reproduction.
They don't just change the brain
and bodily organs and the shape of us,
they also bias us towards dispersal,
getting further and further away
from primary caregivers in particular.
So parents of teenagers
or future teenagers,
it is not just normal,
it is baked in to the biology of humans
to disperse around adolescents
and in the teen years.
So again, I just want to
highlight a few of these,
what were listed
as intervention strategies
to promote healthy
adolescence and puberty.
It's very interesting
because the entire article,
I should mention who wrote
this article, apologies.
One of them is a friend of mine.
So the first author is Ronald Dahl,
not the children's book
author, I'm assuming,
no, from the School of Public Health
at University of California, Berkeley
and Nicholas Allen, Linda Wilbert
and Anna Balanoff Suliman,
forgive me for the
pronunciation of the last one.
I know Dr. Wilbert quite well.
She's done the work on dispersal,
is quite well known for that work,
and it's a very extensive review,
but I think you'll find it accessible.
A lot of changes and
thickness of the brain
at different stages, et cetera.
But I think most people will be interested
in what that translates
to in the real world.
And what's interesting is during puberty,
there's increased connection,
connectivity as we call it
between the prefrontal cortex,
which is involved in
motivation and decision-making,
being able to suppress action
for making long-term goals possible,
as well as dopamine
centers and the amygdala.
So there's this really broad
integration and testing.
I think this is the key element here,
testing of circuits
for emotions and reward
as they relate to decisions.
And I think that's useful because
when you look at the behavior
of adolescents and teens,
they are testing social interactions,
they are testing physical
interactions with the world.
Oftentimes they're engaging
in unsafe behavior.
I would never try and justify that
with the underlying neurology,
but the neuroscience points
to increased connectivity
between areas of the brain that
are related to emotionality
and to threat detection like
the amygdala, but also reward.
So it's a time of testing behaviorally
how different behaviors
lead to success or not.
It's how different behaviors
lead to fear states or not.
Now, of course you could say that
of any stage of development,
but it seems like puberty is
a very, very heightened stage
in which testing of contingencies,
good or bad is taking place.
And of course it's operating in a body
that's now more capable than the infant.
So an infant can damage
themselves through error,
but it's harder for them
to damage themselves
through deliberate planning.
That's why it's important of course,
to lock up all the
medications in the house,
make sure infants can't get to them,
but it's not likely that the infant
is going to devise an
extremely diabolical plan
to get into the cabinet to
get a certain substance.
Whereas a teenager might.
So you can start to map the neurology
onto some of this emotional exploration.
I do realize that this
episode is about emotions.
Puberty is a time in which
the internal state of
the person or the animal
is being sampled and tested against
different exteroceptive events,
only now they are able
to guide those events with more urgency.
It's no longer just about
whether or not the caregiver
is bringing you milk or bringing you food.
Now, of course, the parents will all say,
"Yeah, but I'm paying for
everything that they're doing.
I'm paying for the car and
I'm paying for the food."
Ah, true.
But the biology doesn't
care about the source,
the child or the adolescent is now able,
the teen really, is able to now sample
many, many more exteroceptive
events through behavior.
So some of these
recommendations are interesting.
The theory is that one of the motivations
is to learn to mitigate the
risk of famine and malnutrition.
As teenagers get older,
they start questioning
whether or not their parents
are everything they thought they were,
whether or not they're the
greatest thing that ever was
or the worst thing that ever was, perhaps.
Including whether or not
they will be able to
provide them resources.
So they test whether or not
they can actually feed themselves,
whether or not they
can support themselves.
Although rarely not,
certainly it happens,
but rarely are they really
taking care of themselves.
Although some teens are forced
to take care of themselves
of course, because parents
and other caretakers aren't available.
The recommendations that
map to the biology include,
there's been a big push for
later start times in schools
to match their shifts in circadian rhythms
and the need for extended sleep.
Something we talked about
during the sleep episodes.
To insist on sleep interventions for youth
who are at increased risk
for mental health problems.
Almost every mental
health issue is supported
by getting regular quality
sleep of sufficient duration.
Sufficient duration is going
to vary from person to person.
Leveraging different kinds
of social relationships
that reinforce positive behavior.
This is starting to sound like
kind of a boiler plate stuff.
And yet, really the goal is during puberty
to encourage as many
safe forms of interaction
that allow children, teens,
really and adolescents,
I keep calling them children,
but what I mean are children
going through puberty,
that allow them to test
this thing of autonomy
so that they can start
to make good assessments
about their exteroceptive
events that they are selecting
and how those make them feel internally.
So they're essentially doing a buffet.
The buffet has now broadened
to not just include the
events and experiences
that their parents and
other caretakers bring them,
but they can now expand the buffet
into things that they
can provide themselves.
And so adolescence and puberty
is really seen as the
period of development
in which one self-samples
for these two elements
that we talked about at
the beginning, which are,
how do I form bonds and
how do I make predictions
about what will make me feel good
at a level of interoception.
Some of that might sound
a little transactional,
that all we're trying to do
is figure out how we can bond with people
so we can get what we need
so we can feel how we need.
I think that's true to some extent,
of course, there's a richer,
more abstract aspect to
relationships too, which are,
in relationships you can access
things you couldn't do
before, you can cooperate.
There's things like teamwork.
You can do all sorts of things.
But in terms of the biology,
it's clear that there's
this stage of development
where more autonomy,
more physical capability
is triggered by these
hormone changes in the brain,
and these peptide changes
in the brain and body.
And that nonetheless
brings us back to the exact same model
that we started with in infancy,
of alert or calm, feel good or feel bad,
primarily exterocepting,
primarily interocepting.
So I keep going back to this,
I'm sort of like a
repeating record on that,
because the same core algorithm,
the same core function is at
play throughout the lifespan.
And that's a useful
framework in my opinion,
because it allows you to
sort through all the data
and information that's out there about,
well, this area, the
astria terminalis is active
or the basal lateral amygdala is active
or gray matter thickening
or this hormone or that hormone,
and return to a kind of kernel
of certainly not exhaustive truth,
it doesn't cover all
aspects of emotionality,
but at least establishes some groundwork
from which you can start to evaluate
how different behaviors might
or might not make sense,
how certain emotional responses
might or might not make sense,
regardless of the age of
the person or the organism.
A discussion about emotions
would not be complete
without talking about the
right brain, left brain stuff.
And this is a very interesting
aspect of sociology,
psychology and neuroscience.
There's a theory of emotional development
that I find particularly interesting,
which is from Allan Schore at UCLA,
that talks about
how most of our testing
of bonds and relationships
is this seesawing back and
forth between very dopaminergic,
so driven by dopamine
or serotonergic, driven
by serotonin states.
And this starts with infant and
mother or infant and father.
I talked a little bit about
this in the previous episode,
but just to remind you,
or for anyone that didn't hear about it,
that during development,
healthy emotional development
clearly begins with an ability
for the caretaker and child
to be in calm, peaceful,
soothing, touch-oriented,
eye gazing type of behaviors.
Those really drive serotonin,
the endogenous opioid system,
oxytocin, things are very calming
and are centered around
pleasure with the here and now,
as well as excited states of
what we're going to do next.
There's actually a characteristic sign
of the dopaminergic interaction,
where both caretaker
and child are wide-eyed,
the pupils dilate.
That's a signature of arousal.
They get really excited.
Oftentimes the baby will look
away if it gets really excited
those are signatures of
dopamine release in the body,
and in adolescents, these
same things carry forward,
where their good bonds
are achieved through
hanging around, watching TV,
playing video games
or texting together or talking,
whatever it is
that the soothing local
activity happens to be,
as well as adventure and
things that are exciting,
so it could be sports,
it could be shopping,
it could be a summer adventure.
It could be the next big thing.
And so this kind of
seesawing back and forth
between the different reward
systems seems to be the basis
from which healthy
emotional bonds are created.
And I invite anyone
who's interested in this
to look up some of Dr. Schore's work.
I think I misspoke on the last episode.
He's not a psychiatrist,
he's a clinical psychologist
and psychoanalyst,
but has deep routings in neuroscience.
So I think a fascinating aspect.
But the way it's framed in his book
and in some of the language
around right brain, left brain.
And we've all heard this stuff before,
that the right brain is thought
to be the emotional side.
This is the characteristic
thing that you hear out there.
That the right brain is holistic,
that it's emotive,
and that the left brain is
logical, sequential and analytic.
And that's not what Schore was proposing.
There are some right brain,
left brain differences.
But the idea that the right brain
is synthetic, holistic and emotive,
and that the left brain
is logical, sequential
and analytic is false.
There is zero neuroscience
evidence for that whatsoever.
We're going to address this in more detail
during a month talking about learning
and memory and dementia,
but let's talk about some truths,
some differences between the
left brain and right brain,
because we can't have a
discussion about emotion
without doing that.
The left brain, at least for
people who are right-handed
is linguistically dominant.
Meaning, most of language
is centered in the left side of the brain
for right-handed people.
If you are a left-hander
and you were forced to
become right-handed,
chances are this is still true,
because of when language
gets laid down in the brain.
For left-handers,
people that naturally
write with their left hand
and always did,
language is still mostly in
the left side of the brain,
but it's also found more often
in the right side of the brain.
So it's not as lateralized as we say,
it's kind of distributed between both.
So right-handers,
most of your language
is coming from the left
side of your brain.
Left-handers, it's probably
a little bit more evenly distributed.
And there are some variations,
whether or not you're a
hook righty or a hook lefty,
there's all sorts of nuance to this,
but that's the general aspect.
So language tends to be centered
in the left side of the brain.
And that includes
lexicon, grammar, syntax,
all of it, except for one.
And we'll talk about
one aspect of language
that seems to be more right brain.
That's very interesting.
There does seem to be
some arithmetic advantage.
So ability in math in the
left side of the brain.
And I'm going to talk about
how all this was discovered in a minute.
And the right brain, however,
is linguistically primitive.
Most people don't realize this
because the right brain
is always described
as the emotive side,
it's super emotional and holistic,
but it's actually
linguistically primitive.
And there's a way
that that's been teased
out through experiment.
It's very good at
manipulating spatial things
and visual spatial tasks.
It's primarily handling that stuff,
but it sort of non-language
except one aspect.
And there isn't a ton
of evidence for this,
but the evidence is
strong, which is prosody.
Prosody is the LILting
and falling of language.
So a good example would be Italian.
I don't speak Italian.
I only know a little bit of Italian,
but the most of the Italian I know
is when my Italian
colleagues have said to me,
[speaks in foreign language],
which means like what
are you trying to say,
what are you saying?
I think I'm getting that right.
Basically they're saying
I don't speak Italian,
which is true.
Or because one of them knows
I loves Costello very much,
they always say [speaks
in foreign language],
which means big, lazy guy,
which accurately captures Costello.
So even those few examples,
[speaks in foreign language],
there's a lot of LILt and fall in Italian,
other languages, not so much.
And it varies by language.
One of the reasons I find
Italian so beautiful,
not the Italian I speak,
but the Italian that other people speak
so beautiful to listen to
that that prosody
and the shifts in intonation
are really quite remarkable.
It's almost like a singing song
listening to them speak.
And I used to like to go
to scientific meetings.
And I always hang out with the Italians,
'cause I had some good
friends in Italian labs,
but also 'cause they always
knew where the best food was,
their standards for food are incredible.
They would rather starve
than eat terrible pasta,
and the pasta they do find
and that they're willing
to eat is always fantastic.
But in addition to that,
they always brought a guitar.
They were a lot more fun
than a lot of my other colleagues
to hang out with at meetings.
So in any event,
the right brain is doing things
that are more about manipulating
spatial information.
And I'll talk about this
more in a future episode.
This was discovered in
split-brain patients,
the people that lack connection
between the two sides of the brain,
this had to be teased out
through very complicated experiments.
People like Roger Sperry who
won a Nobel Prize for this,
who was at Caltech,
Mike Gazzaniga and others
figured out these lateralized differences.
but let's just try and demolish the myth
that the right side is synthetic
and holistic and emotive,
and that the left side is
logical, sequential, and analytic,
that you're a left brain
person or a right brain person.
Nothing could be further from the truth.
There's no scientific
evidence to support that.
And there's a few lesion studies
that can tease out effects
that make you think
that's what's happening,
but the really careful work
points in a totally different direction.
We can't have a complete conversation
about emotions and bonds
and social connection
without talking about oxytocin.
Oxytocin has come to such prominence
in the last decade or so,
and seems to be everywhere.
Anytime you hear a discussion
about neuroscience in the
brain or hormones in the brain,
oxytocin is released in response
to lactation in females,
it is released in response
to sexual interactions.
It is released in response
to non-sexual touch.
It's released in males and females,
and indeed it's involved in pair bonding
and the establishment of
social bonds in general.
How it does that seems to be
by matching internal state.
It seems to both increase
synchrony of internal state somehow,
maybe it sets a level of
calmness or alertness.
That seems like a reasonable hypothesis,
as well as raising people's awareness
for the emotional state of their partner.
And again, this brings us
back to this alertness calmness axis
and this interoceptive,
exteroceptive axis.
In order to form good bonds,
we can't just be thinking
about how we feel,
we also need to be paying
attention to how others feel,
and we're evaluating a match.
We're trying to see whether or not
there seems to be some sort
of synchrony between states.
And oxytocin, both seems
to increase that synchrony
and increase awareness for
the emotional state of others.
Now I know many of you
are probably screaming mirror
neurons, mirror neurons.
Mirror, neurons, as some of you may know,
and some of you perhaps may not,
are neurons that were
discovered in animals and humans
for their ability to respond
when people engage in
certain physical actions
like lifting of a pen,
but the same neurons would respond
when somebody watched
someone else lift a pen.
So they were really mirrors of,
were representing mirrors of behavior,
both in self and in others.
Mirror neurons are very controversial.
There are many neuroscientists
who I respect a lot,
who don't think they exist,
because they look at the data,
and the data, at least in their mind
were over interpreted
in the realm of empathy
and in assigning value to the
emotional states of others.
And when I look at the literature,
my opinion is that indeed
there are neurons in the brain
that clearly represent
the actions of others,
but it's not clear
that they're wired into the
emotion and empathy system
in any direct way.
And I think the growing
consensus is that mirror neurons,
while the name is terrific
and it's so catchy,
and encompasses so much
of what you would love
for it to encompass,
but that the data don't
really support that.
But this is controversial,
and I'm perfectly happy
to get experts on here
that could debate it better than I could.
There are however neurons in the brain
that were discovered by my colleague,
Keren Haroush at Stanford
when she was working in Noam Ziv's Lab,
that clearly point to the
fact that primate species
are making assumptions
and are trying to predict the behavior
of other members of their species.
It's an experiment,
I don't have time to
go into in real detail,
we should probably just get Keren on here.
For those of you
that are familiar with
the prisoner's dilemma,
which is really a model of cooperation,
you can either cooperate
or one member of a given
interaction can cooperate
and the other one won't,
where you can both not cooperate.
There are ways in which
you can solve this,
so-called prisoner's dilemma,
by looking at previous behavior
and making predictions about
the likely next behavior
that the other individual will engage in.
And there do seem to be neurons
that are doing these sorts of
predictions or computations.
Again, I'll go into this in
more detail in the future.
So rather than thinking
about mirror neurons,
like neurons for empathy,
I think it's more correct
to think about neurons
that are trying to predict
the behavior of others.
And that's, as we said,
one of the core features of emotions,
which are to establish bonds,
and through those bonds,
to be able to predict behavior.
So oxytocin is one
component of this ability
to predict others' behavior
and to guide our own behavior.
So here's some experiments
that involve the administration
of intranasal oxytocin.
Now I think you need a prescription,
although in some places you don't.
There are people who are
taking intranasal oxytocin
in order to try and increase
the depth of bonding.
And I don't recommend you do that.
I've never tried that.
Whatever oxytocin I've released,
I've made without an intranasal
exogenous application.
But what's been reported
is increased positive
communication among couples.
So people have taken
intranasal oxytocin in studies.
So that study,
for those of you like,
was published in Biological Psychiatry,
which my psychiatry colleagues
tell me is a fine journal.
And the title is
intranasal oxytocin increases
positive communication
and reduces the stress
hormone cortisol levels
during couple conflict,
they have them fight,
or they have them fight
with and without oxytocin.
So interesting.
Very much in line with
the idea that oxytocin
is the "trust hormone."
That's sort of in keeping with that.
That was a 2009 paper.
There's other evidence, for instance,
that men report a greater sense
of connection and intimacy
with their partners during sex
after taking intranasal oxytocin.
There are studies in autistic children.
Giving them intranasal oxytocin as a way
to try and help them establish
better social connection
and "empathy" or theory of mind.
I've talked about theory of mind before,
were understanding of what other children
and adults are experiencing.
Oxytocin does seem to create
these general effects,
and how nuanced they are in
one situation or another,
I don't know.
I'm aware and I was told,
and I'm definitely not recommending this,
that there's a marketed
oxytocin ketamine nasal spray.
Now I have no idea.
Maybe someone can put in the comments
why you'd want to combine
oxytocin and ketamine.
I can't imagine why.
Ketamine is a dissociative anesthetic
that's used for the treatment of PTSD.
It used to be used as a recreational drug.
It's very similar to PCP,
seems quite dangerous in fact.
I don't know why those two
things would be combined,
why one would want to combine them.
But there are products out there
that seem to combine those two things.
And I'm not certain why one would do that,
but it's interesting to
note that it's happening.
A particularly interesting
study about oxytocin is that,
that was published in the
journal, Neuroscience,
which is a good journal,
that oxytocin modulates
social distance between males and females.
So that's interesting.
What they did is they gave oxytocin
to people that were in
monogamous relationships,
and then they evaluated
the extent to which the,
in this case,
the males in those relationships
would pay attention to visual attention
to attractive other potential partners.
And it seemed like
that the general takeaway from this study
is that oxytocin administration
seemed to promote monogamous behavior.
So behavior that wasn't in line
with monogamy of the
relationship that they were in
as opposed to a foraging
for potentially new mates.
Now of course, these are
somewhat artificial experiments
or very artificial experiments,
depending on how you interpret them.
But the general theme
is that oxytocin is promoting monogamy,
it's promoting pair bonding,
it's promoting
a understanding of the
internal state of others,
which requires enhanced exteroception
for those particular others.
So not just generally
having them look everywhere
and see what's going on in the world,
but particularly paying attention
to the emotional states of others.
I'm sure several of you will be asking,
"Well, what can I do
to increase oxytocin,"
if that's your goal.
There's some evidence.
And I invite you again
to go to examine.com or
another such site like PubMed
if you want to forage PubMed,
that vitamin D is required
for proper production,
and in some cases
can increase levels of
oxytocin when supplemented,
which is interesting.
And that believe it or not, melatonin,
or old friend melatonin,
which I have pushed back against
as a supplement for sleep,
because of what I view
as untoward side effects
of melatonin in most cases,
but it seems like melatonin in some cases
can prime the system
for slightly increased oxytocin release.
There's even one report,
although it didn't look that strong to me
that low doses of caffeine
could increase oxytocin release.
But that to me falls under the category
of what was once described
as a drug when injected
into a person or animal
is always effective at
producing a scientific paper.
Meaning that you can get a result,
but the result isn't always so robust.
So you always want to read past
the titles and the abstracts
and get into the meat of the paper.
And when I did that,
the effects were pretty negligible
with caffeine on oxytocin.
But it's interesting that
vitamin D and melatonin
may have some positive
effects on oxytocin release.
But like I said,
many people are just taking oxytocin
directly through these intranasal sprays.
I'm pretty sure it's prescription
in most places, but check.
And again, I'm not
recommending anybody do that.
I've never tried it.
I don't know that I will.
I think I'm going to stick with
the oxytocin that I've got.
The other molecule that we make
that's extremely important for
social bonds and emotionality
is one that we're going to talk about more
in the month on hormones,
that's vasopressin.
Vasopressin suppresses urination.
It's made by the body,
but it was developed as a treatment
for something called diabetes insipidus,
where people urinate excessively,
and they actually risk dehydration
and they can lose a lot of
electrolytes, et cetera.
So it causes water retention.
Alcohol consumption inhibits vasopressin.
So large amounts of alcohol,
many people excrete, a
lot of fluid and so forth.
Vasopressin has effects
on the brain directly.
It actually creates
feelings of giddy love.
It also increases memory
in very potent ways.
There's a whole biohacking community
that has been dabbling with
vasopressin for some time.
I have never tried it.
I certainly don't recommend it.
It is prescription.
It is a pretty serious
compound to start messing with,
because it has so many
different effects in the body.
It's interesting because it
creates the sense of giddy love.
It's also used somewhat as an aphrodisiac,
so it's similar to oxytocin.
It also has very interesting effects
on monogamous or non-monogamous behavior.
This, again, we will
revisit in the future.
But there's a beautiful set of experiments
that have been done in
a little rodent species
called a prairie vole.
It turns out
there are two different
populations of prairie voles,
some are monogamous,
they always meet with the
same other prairie vole,
and some are very robustly non-monogamous,
they mate with as many other
prairie voles as they can.
And turns out that levels of vasopressin
and/or vasopressin receptor
dictate whether or not
they're monogamous or not.
And there's actually some
interesting evidence in humans.
When people report their behavior,
assuming they're reporting accurately,
that vasopressin and vasopressin levels
can relate to monogamy
or non-monogamy in humans as well.
We're going to talk about
this in the month on hormones.
If we're talking about the
neuroscience of emotions,
we have to talk about the vagus nerve.
I described what the vagus
nerve is in a previous episode,
that it's these connections
between the body and the viscera,
including the gut, the heart, the lungs
and the immune system and the brain,
and that the brain is also
controlling these organs.
So it's a two-way street.
There's this big myth out
there that I mentioned before,
that stimulating the vagus in various ways
leads to calmness.
That it's always going to calm you down.
And that is false.
I just want to repeat
that is completely false.
In fact, it was just
paper, yet another paper
published the other day,
which is fantastic, which
is from David McCormick Lab
up at the University of Oregon.
It's published in Current
Biology, excellent journal,
showing, I'm just reading the title,
vagus nerve stimulation
induces widespread cortical,
the neocortex and behavioral activation.
I've read the paper, it's fantastic.
It illustrates yet again,
stimulation of the vagus
increases dopamine release,
increases activation
of the brain alertness.
It is a stimulant of alertness,
it is not calming people down.
Now this is interesting
in light of emotionality
because of work that's
been done by many groups,
but in particular,
I'm going to focus on the
work of a colleague of mine,
Karl Deisseroth at Stanford,
who's a psychiatrist,
but has also developed a lot of tools
to adjust the activity
of neurons in real time
using light and electrical
stimulation and so forth.
I'll refer you to an
article in the New Yorker
that was published about
this a few years ago
I'm going to read a brief excerpt.
I'll put the link in the caption as well.
He's talking to an extremely
suicidal depressed patient
who has a small device implanted
that allows her to adjust
her vagus nerve activity.
Now vagus stimulation
was originally developed for
the treatment of epilepsy.
It's now being used for
various other purposes.
Vagus stimulation can even
increase plasticity, it seems.
So again, increasing activity of the vagus
increases alertness,
and it's just incredible to
see what happens in real time
to emotionality when
the vagus is stimulated,
again, not calming, but
activating alertness.
They're in his office and they're talking,
and he asks her how she's doing,
and she describes how
she's been doing previously
as "going pancake,"
which for her just means
totally laid out flat,
not much going on.
She talks about how she
doesn't want to pursue a job.
She's really depressed.
And he says in typical
good psychiatrist fashion,
"Well, that's a lot to think about,"
that's actually the quote.
And they talk about her
blood pressure, et cetera.
And then she says,
mood's been down, just spiraling down,
talks about insomnia,
bad dreams, low appetite.
So this is severe depression.
This is what we call major depression.
And then she requests,
"Can we please go up to
1.5 on vagus stimulation?"
She'd been receiving 1.2 milli amps
of stimulation every five
minutes to 30 seconds
but was no longer able
to feel the effects.
So he says,
"Okay, I think we can go up a little,
you're tolerating things well."
They start the stimulation and,
"In the course of the next few
minutes," her name was Sally,
"underwent a remarkable
change, her frown disappeared.
She became cheerful,
describing the pleasure she'd had
during the Christmas holiday
and recounting how she'd recently
watched some YouTube videos of Deisseroth.
She was still smiling and
talking when the session ended,
and they walked out to
the reception area."
So this is just by stimulating
and activating the vagus.
Now why am I bringing this up?
Well, for several reasons, one
is the vagus is fascinating
in terms of the brain body connection,
two, I'd like to, trying
to dispel the myth
that vagus stimulation
is all about being calm,
it's really about being alert.
I don't know how that
originally got going backwards,
but it's about being alert.
And once again, level of
alertness or level of calmness
is impacting emotion,
that this axis of alertness and calmness
is one primary axis in emotion.
It's not the only one,
because there's also this
valence component of good or bad.
Those two aren't the only ones,
because there's also this component
of interoceptive, exteroceptive
that we talked about earlier.
And there will be others too.
Again, it's not exhaustive.
But I find it fascinating,
and it really brings us
back to where we started,
which is what are the
core elements of emotion,
and what can you do about them?
And before we close up today,
I just want to make sure that
even though I've mentioned some tools,
I talked about the Mood Meter app,
I talked about oxytocin
and some of the things
that impact oxytocin,
I talked about some of the ways
that you can conceptualize emotions.
This business of how you
conceptualize emotions
is really the most powerful
tool you can ever have
in terms of understanding
and regulating your emotional state.
If you're willing to try and
wrap your head around it,
I realize it's not the
simplest thing to do.
But rather than think of
emotions as just these labels,
happy, sad, or depressed,
thinking about emotions, excuse me,
as elements of the brain and body
that encompass levels of alertness
that include a dynamic
with the outside world
and your perception of
your internal state.
And starting to really
think about emotions
in a structured way
cannot only allow you to understand
some of the pathology
of when you might feel
depressed or anxious
or others are depressed and anxious,
but also to develop
a richer emotional experience to anything.
Now of course, I don't expect that
as you're out there
interacting with friends
and you're watching TV
and experiencing life,
that you should be parsing
every bit of your experience
in some sort of reductionist
and mechanistic way.
That's not the goal here.
But for those of you
that are practitioners,
teachers of any kind,
for those of you that are kids,
for those of you that
are trying to understand
what your emotional life
and your consciousness,
dare I say the word,
really consists of,
I do believe that these
are fundamental elements
that are well-supported by the science
across a variety of researchers
doing things from a variety
of different perspectives
and some of whom agree with one another
and some of whom don't.
So I offer it to you as
a source of knowledge
from which you can start
to think about your emotional
life differently, I hope,
as well as others
in a way that builds more
richness into that experience,
not that detracts from it.
One last point as it relates to that,
many of you have asked me
about psychedelic therapies
that are now emerging, things
like psilocybin and MDMA,
we are of course
going to dive into that topic deeply.
We have an expert guest coming
on to discuss that topic.
Those compounds clearly affect
the aspects of emotionality
that we were talking about today,
calmness, alertness, valence, good or bad,
interoceptive, exteroceptive positioning.
And so rather than just do a
kind of cursory exploration
of those compounds
and what the therapeutic
and scientific community
is thinking about them
and how they function,
I think it's more important
to embed that framework in our thinking
so that when we address psychedelics
and we address other sorts of therapies,
cognitive behavioral therapy,
different types of emotive therapies
that relate to individuals
and couples et cetera,
that we are able to think about them
with some sort of structure and rigor
rather than just talk about
them as a bunch of chemicals
that produce these amazing experiences
that people need to tell you about.
Because if there's one truth,
it seems that psychedelic
seem to promote activity
of storytelling about
psychedelic experience.
But that itself is not really
what the therapeutic community
and the academic communities
are interested in,
they're interested in trying to understand
the universal truths,
the universal biological
shifts and psychological shifts
that occur in the clinical
use of those compounds.
And so we're going to hold off for now,
but we will get to them.
Once again, we've covered
an enormous amount of material today.
It's really the equivalent of two
if not three university
lectures in one podcast episode.
I want to thank those of you
that have supported the podcast
and point to ways in which
all of you can support the podcast.
Many of these are cost-free.
The first is to please
subscribe on YouTube
and as well to hit the
notifications button
so that when we release new videos,
which typically is every Monday
for the full length episodes,
but we also know how short clips,
that you'll be notified.
As well if you could subscribe
on Apple and Spotify,
and leave us a review on Apple.
You have the opportunity to
leave us a five-star review
if you think we deserve
a five-star review.
Please tell your friends
and family and co-workers
about the podcast
if you think the material
would be of interest and
informative for them,
and if you want to send them
links, that's terrific too.
We also have a Patreon account.
It's patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
And there you can support us
at any level that you like.
In addition, if you could
check out our sponsors,
we always provide links to
those sponsors in the captions.
That's the best way to
support the podcast.
And several of you have
asked about supplements.
I talk about supplements
in various episodes.
We've partnered with Thorne
because we think Thorne
has the very highest levels of stringency
in terms of the purity of the contents
and the amounts of the contents.
They really put in the bottle
what's listed on the bottle,
which is not true for a lot
of supplement companies.
If you want to see the
supplements that I take,
as well as get a discount on those
or any of the other
supplements that Thorne makes,
you can go to thorne.com/u/huberman,
and you can get 20% off
any of those supplements
or any of the other
supplements that Thorne makes.
So that's Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E
dotcom slash the letter U
slash Huberman
to get 20% off any
supplements that Thorne makes.
And last but certainly not least,
I want to thank you for
your time and attention.
And thank you for your
interest in science.