[upbeat music]
- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
I'm Andrew Huberman, and I'm
a Professor of Neurobiology
and Ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer information
about science and science-related tools
to the general public.
Along those lines,
I want to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Athletic
Greens, which is an all-in-one
vitamin mineral probiotic
liquid supplement.
I've been using Athletic Greens since 2012
because I really like getting
my total vitamin mineral
base covered in one
easy to consume product.
It also tastes really good.
I mix mine with a little
bit of lemon juice.
I've been doing that
well over a decade now.
And the inclusion of probiotics
is important to me because
there's a lot of data out there right now
about the importance of gut health
for the immune system for, mood.
And so by combining all
these things in one product
you get all those things at once.
If you want to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and that will give you a special offer
where you will get a year supply
of liquid vitamin D3 and K2
vitamin D3 has been shown to be important
for various aspects of immune function
as well as other biological functions.
And so once more, if you
want to try athletic greens
and get the year supply of vitamin D3 K2
just go to athletigreens.com/huberman.
The other sponsor of today's
podcast is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a way to
measure metabolic factors,
hormones, and DNA related factors
by way of blood tests and saliva
in order to assess one's health.
I'm a big believer in blood
tests and saliva tests
for assessing one's health
markers, because I like data.
And there's really no other way to measure
what's going on in one's body
without taking the occasional
blood test or saliva test.
You can guess what's going on
but if you really want to know
what's going on under the hood
InsideTracker can be of great help.
One of the problems with a
lot of products out there
or just regular blood testing
is that you get a lot of
data back about the levels
of various hormones,
metabolic factors, et cetera,
but you don't know what
to do with those data.
Great thing about InsideTracker
is provided in a format.
They have an online dashboard
that given your particular
levels of various things
directs you
toward potential lifestyle related changes
like changes in exercise, or
changes in sleep patterns,
or changes in nutritional patterns,
that can really help move
those markers and those numbers
on those metabolic factors,
hormones, et cetera
in the direction that you want.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker
you can go to insidetracker.com/huberman.
And if you do that,
you'll 25% off their program at checkout.
Okay, let's get started.
Today is episode three of the podcast
and it is office hours.
Office hours as many of you
know, it's where students
come to the office of the professor,
sit down and ask questions,
requesting clarification about
things that were confusing,
or to simply go down the
route of exploring a topic
with more depth and detail.
I asked for your questions to be listed
in the comment section of
the previous two episodes
of the podcast on YouTube,
as well as on Instagram.
And I first of all just want to thank you
for the many questions,
they are excellent.
We read them all.
We distilled from that
large batch of questions
to two types of questions.
Questions that were asked very often
and were light very often with
a little thumbs up like tab
as well as questions that we
thought could really expand
on the topics that we've
covered previously.
And today we're going
to cover both of those.
If we did not get to your
question, please don't despair.
We will keep track of those.
And we have several more
episodes devoted to this topic
of sleep and wakefulness and learning
during the month of January, maybe even,
leaking over a little bit
into the month of February.
So, we have time that's
one of the unique formats
of this podcast is that
we have time for dialogue,
we have time for your questions
and we have time to really
go deep into these topics.
It's official Costello is
sleeping in the background.
So if you hear snoring, Costello
is going to be keeping time
with his deep and melodic snoring.
There he goes.
So the questions that we
received, I batched crudely
into a couple of different categories,
light, exercise, supplementation,
temperature, learning,
plasticity, and mood, and sort
of mood related disorders.
There were a lot of questions about those.
Before we begin any of this
I want to point out something that I,
I always say it sounds like boiler plate
but it's important not just to protect me
but to protect you, which is
that I am not a physician.
I'm not a medical doctor.
I don't prescribe anything,
including behavioral protocols.
I'm a professor.
So I profess a lot of things
based on quality peer reviewed studies.
You should take that information.
You should filter it
through whatever it is
that you currently happen
to be dealing with,
whether or not that's health
or illness, you should consult
with a licensed healthcare
professional before you add
or remove anything from
your daily life protocol.
I'm not responsible for your health.
You are, so be smart with this information
and be a stringent filter, as we say.
Okay, very well let's get
started on the actual material.
Somebody asked, what is the
role of moonlight and fire,
I'm presuming they mean fireplace
or candle or things of that
sort, in circadian rhythms.
Is it okay to view moonlight at night
or will that wake me up?
Will a fire in my fireplace
or using candle light
be too much light.
Great question, also
offers me the opportunity
to share with you
what I think is a quite
beautiful definition
of what light is in a quantitative sense.
So I've mentioned a few
times the use of apps
and light meters and things
to measure things like locks,
which sometimes are also
described in terms of Kendals.
So those are the two units
for measuring light intensity.
Typically lux, L-U-X is the, is the unit.
And so before we go forward
and discuss this many lux
or that many lux, I want to
just tell you what a lux is
because it relates to this question.
One lux equals the illumination
of one square meter surface
at one meter away from a single candle.
Think about that.
So somebody actually decided at some point
that the amount of illumination
at one square meter surface,
one meter away from a single
candle, that equals one lux.
So when we talk about 6,000
lux of light intensity
or 10,000 lux of light
intensity, now you have a kind of
a reference or a framework that
would be the equivalent of,
you could think of it as 6,000 candles
all with their light intensity shown
on one square meter from
one meters distance away.
Or of course, if it was
a different number of lux
it would be a different number of candles.
So you get the idea.
Here's the great thing.
It turns out that moonlight, candle light,
and even a fireplace, if you
have one of these roaring fires
going in the fireplace,
do not reset your circadian clock at night
and trick your brain into
thinking that it's morning
even though if you've ever
sat close to a fireplace
or even a candle, that
light seems very bright.
And there are two reasons for
that that are very important.
The first one is that
these neurons in your eye
that I discussed in the previous episode
these melanopsin ganglion cells
also called intrinsically
photosensitive ganglion cells.
Those cells adjust their
sensitivity across the day,
and those cells respond best
to the blue-yellow contrast
present in the rising and setting sun,
so-called low solar angle sun,
also discussed in the previous episode,
but those cells adjust
their sensitivity such that
they will not activate
the triggers in the brain
that conveyed daytime signals
when they view moonlight,
even a full moon a really
bright moon or fire.
Now this does raise an
interesting kind of thought point,
which is, you know, a lot of people talked
about lunacy and the fact that
when there's a full moon out
people act differently
and behave differently.
There's a lot of lore around that.
There's actually a little bit
of quality science around that
that maybe we can address in the future.
But, moonlight is typically
not going to wake us up
too much, except maybe
the moon is really full
and really bright, there's
possibility for that.
So, providing you're not going
to burn down the structure
you're in, you're not going
to burn down the forest,
enjoy your, your fireplaces,
enjoy your lights from candles.
And those are perfectly safe
without disrupting your circadian rhythm.
Because we talked about
just how crucial it is
to avoid bright lights
between the hours of about
10:00 PM and 4:00 AM.
Except when you need to view
things for sake of safety
or work or so and so forth.
I also received a lot of
questions about red light.
Now, I think I was asked those questions
because red light is used
in a number of different
commercial products
where these products
tend to include a sheet,
of very bright red lights.
That one is supposed to
view early in the day.
And there are various claims attached
to these red light devices
that they improve mitochondrial function,
that they improve metabolism there-
I'm going to be really honest
and I can't name brands,
and I'm not going to
name particular studies.
'Cause what I'm about to say
about these studies is
not particularly unkind
but let's just say that none
of the studies that I've seen
except for one that I'll
talk about in a moment,
pointing to the positive
effects of red light
on the visual system are
published in blue ribbon journals.
They tend to be published in journals
that I had to work hard to find.
I'm not sure what the peer
review and stringency level is.
Now, that's not to say
red light isn't beneficial
because there is one study in particular
that came from Glen Jeffrey's Lab
at the University of College, London
it was published last year.
Glen is somebody I happen to know
is an excellent reputation,
excellent vision scientist,
what this study essentially showed.
And again, this is a study that
I very much liked the data
and think it was done
with very high standards.
What this study shows is
that, viewing red light
for a few minutes each morning
can have positive effects on mitochondria
in a particular retinal cell
type, that tends to degenerate
or decline in function with age in humans.
And that cell type is the photoreceptor.
The photoreceptor is a
type of cell in your eye
that sits at the back of the eye.
It's kind of some distance
away from the ganglion cells.
And it's the cell that
converts light information
into electrical signals that the rest
of the retina and brain can understand.
These are vitally important
cells without them,
people are blind.
And many people's vision
gets worse with age.
In particular, age related
macular degeneration
but also related to some other factors
including photo receptor functionality
just getting worse with time.
And what Glen showed was
that red light flashes
delivered in particular early in the day
but not late in the day can
help repair the mitochondria.
Now this study needs more support
from additional studies of course.
They are doing a clinical trial.
They did report on what I
think it was 12 patients.
And so the work is ongoing,
but that was very interesting.
And it points to some
potentially really useful things
about red light.
However, most of the questions I got
about red light for sake of office hours
were about the use of red
light later in the day.
So here's the deal, in principle red light
will not stimulate the
melanopsin retinal neurons
that wake up the brain and circadian clock
and signal daytime.
However, most of the red lights
in particular the red lights
that come on these
sheets of these products
that people are supposed
to view them in order to
access a number of
proclaimed health effects,
those are way too bright
and would definitely wake
up your body and brain.
So if you're going to use those products
and I'm not suggesting
you do, or you don't,
but if that's your thing,
you would want to use those
early in the day.
Who knows you might
even derive some benefit
on mitochondria function
in these photo receptors.
But if you're thinking about red light
for sake of avoiding the
negative effects of light
later in the day and at night,
then you want that red light
to be very, very dim,
certainly much dimmer
than is on most of those
commercial products.
Now, do you need red lights? No.
Although red lights are rather convenient
because you can see
pretty well with them on,
but if they're dim, they won't
wake up the circadian clock.
They won't have this
dopamine disrupting thing
that we talked about in
the previous podcast.
So there's a role for red light
potentially early in the day
and for mitochondrial repair
in the photoreceptors,
there's a role for dim red light
later in the day and at night.
So you're starting to notice
a theme here which is that,
there's no immediate prescription
of look at these light,
it's look at these lights potentially
if that's what you want to
do at particular times of day
and we're particular intensities.
It brings us back to the blue light issue
which is so many people are obsessed
with avoiding blue light, but you actually
want a ton of blue light early in the day
and throughout the day.
So don't wear your blue blockers then
or maybe even don't wear them at all.
And at night, it doesn't matter
if you have blue blockers on
if the lights are bright
enough, then you're still
going to be activating
these cells and mechanisms.
I just want to add something
about the science behind
the blue blocker confusion.
So these melanopsin retinal
cells do react to blue light.
That that is the best stimulus
for one of these
melanopsin cells, which led
to the belief that blue
blockers would be a good thing
for preventing resetting of
the circadian clock at night
and deleterious effects
of screens, et cetera.
However, the people
that made these products
fail to actually read the
papers from start to finish
or if they did, they didn't
comprehend a critical element
which is that most of
those papers early on
took those neurons out
and put them in a dish.
And when they did that,
they divorced those neurons
from their natural connections in the eye.
It turns out in your IMI right now,
because that's what we care
about, these cells exist
and the cells respond to blue light
but also to other wavelengths of light
because they not only
respond directly to light
as they do in a dish, they also respond
to input from photo receptors.
So if you talk to anyone in
the circadian biology field,
they'll tell you, "Oh,
yeah this blue light thing,
has really gotten out of control."
Because people assume that
blue light is the culprit
because blue light is the best stimulus.
That doesn't mean that blue
light is the only stimulus
that will trigger these cells, okay?
So like many things a
scientific paper can be accurate
without being exhaustive.
And a lot of claims about
products can be accurate,
but not exhaustive.
So blue light during the day is great.
Get that screen light, get that sunlight
especially getting overhead lights.
I'll talk about all this
in the previous podcast,
but at night you really want
to avoid those bright lights.
And it doesn't matter if it's
blue light or something else.
And so there was a real confusion about
the papers and the data when most
of those product
recommendations were made.
Okay.
While we're on that topic,
let's talk about light
in other orifices of the body.
I made a kind of a joke about
this, the last podcast episode
but a couple of people
wrote to me and said,
well, I've seen some
claims that light delivered
to the ears into the ears
or the roof of the mouth
or up the nose can be beneficial
for some setting circadian rhythms, no.
Not directly anyway.
And this is a great opportunity
for us to distinguish
between what is commonly
called the placebo effect
but a more important way to
think about any manipulation
behavioral or otherwise
that you might do is
the difference between
modulation and mediation.
There are a lot of things that
will modulate your biology.
Putting a couple of lights up your nose,
please don't do this.
Might modulate your biology by way
of the stress hormone that's released
when you stuffed those
things up your nose.
Remember earlier a previous
podcast, I said that
virtually anything we'll face
shifts your circadian rhythm
if it's different and dramatic enough.
So the question is, is
it the light delivered
up the nose or through the ears
or some other orifice that's
mediating the process?
Is it actually tapping
into the natural biology
of the system that you're
trying to manipulate?
And this is where I like to distinguish
between real biology and hacks.
I don't like the word hack
or frankly neuro hacking or bio hacking.
I just don't like the
term because a hack is
is using something for a purpose
for which it was not intended, right?
But where you can kind
of, it's kind of a cheat
and that's not how biology works well.
So I try and distinguish
between things that really
mediate biological processes
and things that Modulate them.
There are a number of
commercial products out there
with some studies attached to them,
claiming that light delivered
to the ears or wherever can
adjust your wakefulness
or adjust your sleep.
I've looked at those papers again,
I'm probably going to lose
some friends by saying this
but maybe I'll gain a few as well.
Not blue ribbon journals, frankly,
oftentimes read the small print.
There was a conflict of
interest clause there
related to commercial interests.
If somebody disagrees
with me outright on this
and can send to me a peer reviewed paper,
published in a quality journal
about light delivered anywhere,
but the eyes of humans
that can mediate circadian,
rhythms, wakefulness et cetera,
I'm more than happy to take a look at that
and change my words and stance on this
and do it publicly, of course.
But until then I'm guessing that
the proper controls were not done
of adjusting for heat
that could be delivered
which can definitely
shift circadian rhythms.
We're going to talk about temperature
and other things like that.
So light to the eyes folks is
where these light effects work
in humans, in other animals,
they have extra ocular photo
reception in humans, no.
And just be mindful, I mean,
I'm not trying to encourage people
to avoid certain products in particular
but just be mindful of this difference
between modulation and mediation.
A mediating, a process
through a hard wired
or long-standing biological
mechanism is really
where you're going to see the
powerful effects over time.
I also, as you've probably noticed,
I really tend to favor behavioral tools
and zero cost tools first,
and getting those dialed
in before you start,
plugging in and swallowing
and putting things
in various places just
to really figure out
how your biology works and explore that,
unless there's of course a clinical need
to take a prescribed drug in which case,
by all means, listen to your doctor.
Okay, a huge number of
people asked me about
what about light through windows?
And I actually did an
Instagram post about this look,
setting your circadian clock with sunlight
coming through a window
is going to take 50
to 100 times longer.
If you want the date on that,
I'd be happy to send you
to the various papers that were described
in the previous podcast that
Jamie Zeitzer from Stanford.
And I have discussed also elsewhere
but here's really the key thing with us.
Do the experiment.
You can download the free app Light Meter.
You can have a bright day outside
or some sunlight hold up
that app, take a picture.
It'll tell you how many lux
now, you know what lux are.
It will tell you how many
lux are in that environment.
Now close the window.
And if you want close the
screen or don't open the screen
you can do all sorts of experiments.
You'll see that it will at
least half the amount of lux.
And it doesn't scale linearly.
Meaning let's say I get
a 10,000 lux outside,
5,000 looking out through an open window
and then I closed the
window and it's 2,500 lux.
It does not mean that you just
need to view that sunlight
for twice as long if it's
half as many lux, okay?
It's not like 2,500 lux
means you need to look
for 10 minutes
and 5,000 lux means you
look for five minutes.
It doesn't scale that way
just because the biology
doesn't work that way.
Best thing to do is to
get outside, if you can,
if you can't next best thing to do
is to keep that window open.
It is perfectly fine to
wear prescription lenses
and contacts.
Why is it okay to wear
prescription lenses and contacts,
when those are glass also,
but looking through a window,
diminishes the effect.
Well, we should think about this.
The lenses that you wear
in front of your eyes
by prescription or on your eyes
are designed to focus the
light on to your neural retina.
In fact, that's what near-sightedness
is, is when the image
because your lens
doesn't work quite right.
The image falls in front
of the neural retina,
wearing a particular lens in front of that
focuses the lens onto your
retina onto these very neurons.
So they can communicate that to the brain.
It's Costello is loving this light.
He's deep in sleep.
And if we, maybe we
could play him some tones
and he'll remember it
later, based on the studies,
we're going to talk about in a little bit.
I don't know how we'd know
if he remembered it or not,
but prescription lenses are fine.
In fact, they're great for this reason
they're actually focusing
the light onto the retina.
So think about this logically
and all of a sudden it makes
perfect sense your glass window
or your windshield or the
side window of your car,
it isn't optically
perfect to bring the image
and the light onto your retina.
In fact, what it's
doing is it's scattering
and filtering light in particular
the wavelengths of light that you want.
So, if you live in a low light environment
lots of questions about this.
We talked about this, the previous podcast
but just get outside for longer or,
and/or use really bright lights inside.
Okay, so let's think about
why I'm making some of
these recommendations
because I think it can really empower you
with the ability to change your behavior
in terms of light
viewing and other things,
depending on time of year,
depending on other lifestyle factors.
The important point to understand
is that early in the day,
your central circadian clocks
and all these mechanisms are
looking for a lot of light.
I mean, they don't have
a mind of their own,
but it needs a lot of light to
trigger this daytime signal,
alertness et cetera.
And early in the day, but
not in the middle of the day,
you can sum or add photons.
So there's this brief period
of time early in the day,
when the sun is low in the sky
when your brain and body are expecting
a morning wake up signal
where let's say, it's
not that bright outside.
Someone sent me a picture or
a little movie of their walk
in England, and it was pretty overcast
and they were using
light meter and they said
it's only about 700
lux or maybe even less.
And I said, well, stay outside longer.
But when you get inside, turn
on the lights really bright
and overhead lights in particular,
because those will be best for
stimulating these mechanisms.
And that's because at least
for the first few hours of the day,
you can continue to some
or add photon activation
of the cells in the eye and the brain.
In the middle of the day, once
the sun is overhead, or even
if you stay inside all morning,
and then you're in the
circadian dead zone,
which sounds terrible and it is terrible.
You doesn't matter if you
get a ton of artificial light
or even sunlight,
you're not going to shift
your circadian clock.
You're not going to get
that wake up signal.
And then in the evening,
you want to think about
this whole system as being vulnerable
to even a few photons of light
because of their sensitivity
to light really goes up at night.
And I talked last time
about how you can protect
against that sensitivity by
looking at the setting sun
and watching the evening sun,
even if it's not crossing the horizon
around the time of sunset.
And that's because it adjusts
your retinal sensitivity
and your melatonin pathway
so that light is not as
detrimental to melatonin at night.
Think about the afternoon
sunlight viewing as kind of a,
I think of it as kind of
a Netflix inoculation.
It allows me to watch a little bit
of Netflix in the evening,
although it's very
hard to watch a little bit
of anything on Netflix.
It seems like there's some
other neuro-biological process
that going on there where I have to watch
episode after episode after episode.
But in any case, you can protect yourself
against some of that bad
effect of light at night
by looking at light in the evening.
It really does adjust down
the sensitivity of the system.
Okay.
I want to talk about seasonal changes
in all these things as they
relate to mood and metabolism.
So depending on where
you are in the world,
Northern hemisphere, Southern hemisphere
at the equator or closer to the poles,
the days and nights are going
to be different lengths.
That just makes sense.
But that translates to
real biological signals
that impact everything from
wakefulness and sleep times
but also mood and metabolism.
So here's how this works.
Now, after seeing the previous
episode of the podcast
and paying attention here, you are armed
with the knowledge to
really understand how it is
that believe it or not, every
cell in your body is tuned
to the movement of the
planet relative to the sun.
So as all of you know,
the earth spins once every
24 hours on its axis.
So part of that day
were bathed in sunlight
depending on where we are
the other half of the day
or part of the day we're in darkness.
The earth also travels
around the sun 365 days
is the time that it takes, one year,
to travel around that sun.
The earth is tilted.
It's not perfectly upright.
So the earth is tilted on its axis.
So depending on where we
are in that 365 day journey
and depending on where we
are in terms of hemisphere,
Northern hemisphere, Southern hemisphere,
some days of the year
are longer than others.
Some are very short, some are very long.
If you're at the, at the equator
you experience less variation
in day length and therefore nightlife.
And if you're closer to the poles,
you're going to experience
some very long days.
And you're also going to
experience some very short days
depending on which poll you're at
and what time of year it is.
The simple way to put this
as depending on time of year
the days are either getting
shorter or getting longer.
Now, every cell in your
body adjusts its biology
according to day length, except
your brain, body and cells
don't actually know
anything about day length.
It only knows night length.
And here's how it works.
Light inhibits melatonin powerfully.
If days are long and getting longer,
that means melatonin is reduced.
The total amount of melatonin is less
because light is more,
therefore melatonin is less.
If days are getting shorter,
light can't inhibit melatonin as much,
through the summing of photon mechanisms
that we talked about before,
and that melatonin
signal is getting longer.
So every cell in your body actually knows
external day length and
therefore time of year
by way of the duration
of the melatonin signal.
And in general, it's fair to
say that in diurnal animals,
meaning animals like us
that tend to be awake
during the daytime and
not nocturnal animals,
which tend to be awake at night.
The longer the melatonin
signal, the more depressed
not necessarily clinically depressed,
although that can happen
but the more depressed
our systems tend to be.
Reproduction, metabolism, mood,
turnover rates of skin cells
and hair cells all tend to be diminished
compared to the spring and summer months
for some Northern hemisphere,
spring and summer months,
or the times in which days are very long.
And there's less melatonin that tends to,
in almost all animals,
including humans, more breeding,
more hormone elevation of the hormones
that stimulate breeding reproduction
and fertility metabolism
is up, lipid metabolism
fat-burning is up,
protein synthesis is up.
These things tend to
correlate with the seasons.
Now, some people are very, very
strongly tied to the seasons.
They get depressed,
clinically depressed in winter
and light therapies are very
useful for those people.
Some people love the winter
and they're happiest in winter
and they feel kind of depressed in summer.
Although that is far more rare.
That doesn't mean depression
cannot exist in the summer,
but when we're talking
about seasonal depression
that tends to be true.
It's more depression in winter.
Now there's other things that
correlate with seasonality.
Suicide rates tend to
be highest in the spring
not in the winter,
but that has to do with some of the more
complicated and unfortunately
tragic aspects of suicide
which is that oftentimes
people will commit suicide
not at the very depths
of their energy levels,
but as they're emerging from
those depths of low energy.
So we'll talk about
suicidality and mood disorders
in a later podcast season,
meaning a month later.
But for now, just understand that
everybody is going through
these natural fluctuations
depending on the duration
of the melatonin signal.
Now this might lead you to say, "Well,
then I should just really
get as much light as I can
all the time and reduce melatonin
feel great all the time."
Unfortunately, doesn't work that way
because melatonin also
has important effects
on the immune system.
It has important effects
on transmitter systems
in the brain, et cetera.
So everybody needs to
figure out for themselves
how much light they need early in the day
and how much light they need to avoid
late in the day,
in order to optimize
their mood and metabolism.
There is no one size fits all prescription
because there's a range
of melatonin receptors,
there are a range of
everything from metabolic types
to genetic histories,
family histories, et cetera.
There is no one size fits all prescription
but by understanding that
light and extended day length
inhibit melatonin and melatonin tends
to be associated with a more depressed
or reduced functioning of
these kinds of activity driving
and mood elevating signals,
and understanding that
you have some control
over melatonin by way of
light, including sunlight
but also artificial light,
and that should empower you
I believe, to make the adjustments
that if you're feeling low you might ask,
how much light am I getting?
What am I getting that light?
Because sleep is also important
for restoring mood, right?
So you need sleep.
You can't just, just crush
melatonin across the board
and expect to feel good because
then you're not going to
fall asleep and stay asleep.
Melatonin, not incidentally comes from,
is synthesized from serotonin.
Serotonin is a neurotransmitter
that is associated
with feelings of well-being
provided to proper levels,
but well-being of a particular kind.
Well-being associated
with quiescence and calm
and the feeling that we
have enough resources
in our immediate kind of conditions.
Is the kind of thing that
comes from a good meal
or sitting down with friends
or holding a loved one,
or conversing with somebody
that you really bond with.
Serotonin does not stimulate action.
It tends to stimulate stillness.
Very different than the
neuromodulator dopamine
which is a reward feel good neuromodulator
that stimulates action.
And actually dopamine is the cursor
to epinephrin, to adrenaline
which actually puts us into action.
There it's actually made
from dopamine, right?
So, you can start to think how about light
as a signal that is very powerful
for modulating things
like sleep and wakefulness
but also serotonin
levels, melatonin levels.
And I talked about this previously
but I'll mention once more,
that light in the middle of the night
reduces dopamine levels to the point where
it can start causing problems
with learning and memory and mood.
That's one powerful reason
to void bright light
in the middle of the night.
Okay.
Seasonal rhythms have a number of effects
but humans are not
purely seasonal breeders.
Unlike a lot of animals,
we breed all year long.
In fact, there's a preponderance
of September babies
in my life, not actual babies,
because they're born in September
which means that they were
conceived in December,
without knowing the details
we can fairly assume that.
And December, at least in
the Northern hemisphere
at days tend to be shorter
and nights tend to be longer.
So clearly humans aren't seasonal breeders
but there are shifts in
breeding and fertility
that exist in humans,
but also much more
strongly in other animals.
So seasonal effects vary.
Some of you will experience
very strong seasonal effects
others of you will not.
I think everybody should be taking care to
get adequate sunlight and to
avoid bright light at night
throughout the year if possible.
Throughout this podcast
and in previous episodes,
I've been mentioning neuromodulators,
things like serotonin and dopamine
which tend to buy a certain brain circuits
and things in our body to
happen in certain brain circuits
and things in our body not to happen.
One of the ones I've mentioned
numerous times is epinephrin
which is a neuromodulator that
tends to put us into action,
make us want to move.
In fact, when it's released
in high amounts in our brain
and body, it can lead
to what we call stress
or the feeling of being stressed.
Several people ask me,
what's the difference
between epinephrin and adrenaline.
Adrenaline is secreted
from the adrenal glands
which sit right above our kidneys.
Epinephrin is the exact same molecule
except that it's released
within the brain.
And so people use these
phrases or these words
rather interchangeably, epi means near
or on top of sometimes and neph, neph
Anytime you see nephron
or ph it means kidney.
So it means near the kidney.
So epinephrin actually
means near the kidney.
So it was used originally
to describe adrenaline,
but epinephrin and adrenaline
are basically the same thing
and they tend to stimulate
agitation and the desire to move.
That's what that's about.
Which brings us to the topic of exercise.
Got a lot of questions about exercise.
What forms of exercise are
best for sleeping well?
When should I exercise et cetera.
There's a lot of them individual
variability around this,
but I can talk about what I
know from the science literature
and what I happened to do myself.
There are basically two forms of exercise
that we can talk about although, of course
I realize there are many
different forms of exercise.
There's much more nuance to this,
but we can talk about
cardiovascular exercise,
where the idea is to repeat a movement
over and over and over continuously.
So that'd be like running, biking, rowing
and cycling this kind of thing.
Or there's a resistance
exercise where you're moving,
lifting, presumably putting down also
things of progressively
heavier and heavier weight
that you couldn't do
continuously for 30 minutes.
So cardiovascular exercise is typically
the more aerobic type exercise
and resistance exercise
of course is the more
anaerobic type exercise.
And yes, there's
variation between the two.
Most studies of exercise have
looked at aerobic exercise
because that's basically the
thing that you can get a rat
or a mouse to do.
You know what's really
weird about rats and mice,
they like to run on wheels so much,
that someone actually did this study,
it was published in
science they put a wheel,
a running wheel in the middle of a field
and mice ran to that wheel
and ran on the wheel.
They turns out that what
they like is the passage
of the visual image of the
bars in front of their face,
which I find kind of remarkable
and troubling because it
seems so like trivial,
but anyway they love aerobic exercise.
And so most of the studies
were done on these mice
that love running on wheels.
Whereas so far as it's
been challenging to find
conditions in which mice
really liked to lift weights
or we'll do it in a laboratory.
So any weight bearing exercise studies
really have to be done in humans.
And since humans are
what we're interested in,
there are some studies
looking at these two things
and when they tend to work best.
Now you will see some
places aerobic exercise
is best done in the morning
and weight training is
best done in the afternoon.
I think there's far more
individual variation than that.
I think there are however,
a couple of windows
that the exercise science literature
and the circadian literature points to as
windows related to body temperature
in which performance, injury,
in which performance is optimized
injury is reduced and so on.
And those tend to be 30
minutes after waking.
And that probably correlates
with the inflection in cortisol
associated with waking whether or not
you've gotten light or not,
three hours after waking,
which probably correlates to
the rise in body temperature
sometime right around waking.
And the later afternoon,
usually 11 hours after waking
which is when temperature tends to peak.
So some people like to
exercise in the morning.
Some people like to
exercise in the afternoon.
It really depends.
I think for those of us
with very busy schedules,
it's advantageous to be
able to do your training
whenever you have the
opportunity to do it,
unless you can really
control your schedule.
And so I would never want
these recommendations
to seem like recommendations,
what I'm really describing
are some opportunities,
30 minutes after waking,
three hours after waking
or 11 hours after waking
has been shown at least in some studies
to optimize performance, reduce injury
and that sort of thing.
But you really have to figure
out what works for you.
A note about working out
first thing in the morning.
Last time we talked about
non-photo phase shifts.
If you exercise first
thing in the morning,
your body will start to develop
an anticipatory circuit.
There's actually plasticity
in these circadian circuits
that will lead you to want to wake up
at the particular time that you exercised
the previous three or four days.
So that can be a powerful tool
but you still want to get light exposure.
Because it turns out that
light and exercise converged,
so giving even bigger, wake up
signal to the brain and body.
So you might want to think about that.
Some people find if they
exercise late in the day
they have trouble sleeping
in general intense exercise does that,
whereas the kind of lower
intensity exercise doesn't.
I found some interesting literature
that talked about sleep need and exercise.
I found this fascinating that
if one is waking not feeling
rested and recovered from
and yet sleeping the same
amount that they typically have,
it's quite possible that
the intensity of exercise
in the proceeding two or
three days is too high.
Whereas if one can't recover
no matter how much sleep they get,
they're just sleepy all the time,
I realized these things are correlated
that the volume of
training might be too high.
Now I'm not an exercise scientist.
We should probably get Andy
Galpin or somebody else on here,
who's really an expert
in this kind of stuff.
I do realize as soon as
anyone talks about exercise
or nutrition publicly,
they're basically opening themselves up
to all sorts of challenges
because you can basically find support
for almost any protocol in the literature.
What I've looked at was
two journals in particular,
International Journal Chronobiology
and journal Biological Rhythms.
Excuse me, to assess these parameters
that I I've mentioned
just just a moment ago
because the studies tended
to be done in humans.
They were fairly recent and they came from
groups that I recognized as well as
knowing that those
journals are peer reviewed.
Many of your questions were
about neural plasticity
which is the brain and nervous
system's ability to change
in response to experience.
There was a question
that asked whether or not
these really deep biological
mechanisms around wakefulness,
time of waking sleep, et cetera
were subject to neuroplasticity
and indeed they are.
Some of that plasticity is short-term
and some of it is more long-term.
There's a really good
analogy here which is,
if you happen to eat on
a very tight schedule
where every day say it
8:00 AM, noon and 7:00 PM
is when you eat your food
not suggesting you do this
but let's say you were to do
that for a couple of days.
After a few days,
you would start to
anticipate those meal times
where no matter where
you were in the world,
no matter what was going on in your life
about five to 10 minutes
before those meal times,
you would start to feel hungry
and even a little agitated,
which is your body's way
of trying to get you to forage for food.
And that's because of some peptide signals
that come from the
periphery from your body,
things like hypocretin norexin
that signal to the hypothalamus
and brainstem to make you active
and alert and look for
food and feel hungry.
So there's kind of an
anticipatory circuit,
that's a chemical circuit,
but eventually over time,
the neurons, the neural circuits
that control hypocretin orexin
would get tuned to the neural circuits
that are involved in eating
and maybe even smell and taste
to create a kind of eating circuit
that's unique to your
pattern, to your rhythms.
The same thing is true for
these waking and exercise
and other schedules, including
all trade-in schedules.
If you wake up in the morning
and start getting your
sunlight, you start exercising
in the morning or you
exercise in the afternoon,
pretty soon, your body will
start to anticipate that
and start to secrete
hormones and other signals
that prepare your body
for the ensuing activity
of waking up or going to sleep.
So if you get onto a pattern or a rhythm,
even if that rhythm
isn't down to the minute,
you'll find that there's
plasticity in these circuits
and it becomes easier to wake up early.
If that's your thing or
exercise at a particular day
if that's your thing.
That's the beauty of neuroplasticity.
A number of people ask,
"What can I do to increase plasticity?"
And that really comes in two forms.
There's plasticity that
we can access in sleep
to improve rates of learning
and depth of learning
from the previous day or so.
And there's this an SDR
non-sleep deep breaths
that can be done without
sleeping, to improve rates
of learning and depth
of retention, et cetera.
So let's consider those both
and you can incorporate
these protocols if you like.
Again, these are based on
quality peer reviewed studies.
First, let's talk about learning in sleep.
This is based on some work that
I'll provide the reference for
that was published in the journal Science.
Excellent journal, Matt
Walker also talks about some
of these studies done by others
in his book "Why We Sleep".
The studies just to remind you are
structured in he following
way an individual
is brought into a laboratory, Lowe does a
spatial memory task.
So there tends to be a screen
with a bunch of different
objects popping up on the screen
in different locations.
So it might be a Bulldog's
face that might be a cat,
and it might be an Apple
than it might be a pen
in different locations.
And that sounds trivial easy
but with time you can
imagine it gets pretty tough
to come back a day later and remember,
if something presented in a given location
was something you've seen
before and whether or not
it was presented in that
location or a different location.
If you had enough objects
and changed locations enough,
this can actually be quite difficult.
In this study, the subjects either just
went through the experiment
or a particular odor
was released into the room
while they were learning
or a tone was played in the
room while they were learning.
And then during the
sleep of those subjects
the following night and
the following night,
so this was done repeatedly
for several nights,
the same odor or tone was played
while the subjects were sleeping.
They did this in different stages of sleep
non-REM sleep and rapid eye
movement, sleep REM sleep.
They did this with just the tone in sleep.
If the subjects had the
odor but not the tone,
they did it with putting the tone,
if they had had the odor while learning.
So basically all the controls,
all the things you'd want
to see done to make sure
that it wasn't some indirect
effects, a modulatory effect.
Okay.
And what they found was that
providing the same stimulus,
the odor, if they
smelled an odor or a tone
if the subjects heard
a tone while learning
if they just delivered that odor or tone
while the subject slept, rates of learning
and retention of information
was significantly greater.
This is pretty cool.
What this means that you can
cue the subconscious brain,
and the asleep brain to
learn particular things
better and faster.
So how might you implement this?
Well, you could play
with this if you want.
I don't see any real challenge
to this provided the
odor and is a safe one
and then doesn't wake you up
and the tone is a safe one,
and doesn't wake you up.
You could do this by having
a metronome, for instance,
while I'm learning something,
playing in the background
or particular music
and then have that very
faintly while you sleep.
So you could apply this
if you like and try this.
There are a number of groups I think now
that are trying this
using tactile stimulation.
So slight vibration on
the wrist during learning
and then the same vibration
on the wrist during sleep.
It does not appear that
the sensory modality,
whether or not it's odor or auditory tone
or tactile stimulation,
some as a sensory stimulation,
whether or not it matters.
It's remarkable because it really shows
that sleep is an extension
of the waking state.
We've known that for a long time
but this really tethers those two
in a very meaningful and actionable way.
So I think I'll report back to you
as I learned more about these studies,
but that's what I know
about them at this point.
As long as we're there
we might as well talk about dreaming
'cause I got so many
questions about dreams.
A couple of you, we want to
ask me what their dreams meant.
Look, I don't even know what
my dreams mean half the time.
I occasionally will wake up
from a dream and remember it.
If you want to remember
your dreams better,
if you're somebody who has challenges
remembering your dreams,
you can set your alarms
that you wake up in the middle of this
one of these 90 minute
cycles which toward morning
tend to be occupied almost
exclusively by REM sleep.
Remember early in the night,
you have less REM sleep
than later in the night.
But you want to get as
much sleep as you can
'cause that's healthy.
So I don't know that you
want to wake yourself up.
Some people find that
writing down their thoughts immediately
first thing in the morning
allows them to relater
spontaneously remember
their dream they had.
There's some literature on that.
The meaning of dreams is a
little bit controversial.
Some people believe
they have strong meaning
other people believe that they can be
just spontaneous firing of
neurons that were active
in the waking state and
don't have any meaning.
There are good data to show
that when you learn spatial,
new spatial environments that
there's a replay of those
environments, so-called place
cells that fire in your brain
only when you enter a
particular environment,
that those are replayed in
sleep in almost direct fashion
to the way that things were activated
when you were learning that spatial task.
Dreams are fascinating, they're
were paralyzed during dreams
which brings us to another question.
Somebody asked about sleep paralysis.
We are paralyzed for much of our sleep,
so-called atonia so presumably
so we don't act out our dreams.
Some people wake up and
they're still paralyzed.
I've actually had this happen to me
not very many times, but a few times.
And then they jolt themselves awake
and it actually is quite terrifying.
I can say from personal
experience to wake up
be wide awake and you cannot
move your body at all.
It's really quite frightening.
There are a couple of
things that will increase
the intrusion of atonia
into the wakeful state
which is essentially
means you're waking up
but you can't, you can't move.
One is marijuana, THC, a
I'm not a marijuana smoker.
I'm not a copper.
I don't know the legality where you live.
So I'm not saying one thing
or another about marijuana.
I'm just, the fact that
I had that experience
without marijuana means that
it can happen regardless,
but marijuana smokers, for whatever reason
maybe it has something to do
with the cannabinoid receptors
or the serotonin receptors
downstream of the motor pathways.
I don't know.
I couldn't find any literature on this
but marijuana smokers
report, higher frequency
of this kind of paralysis and wakefulness
as you transition from
sleep to wakefulness.
I suppose probably
one could learn to get
comfortable with it.
For me, it was terrifying, 'cause I'm just
used to being able to
move my limbs fortunately
and I wasn't able to,
and it's a quite a thing,
let me tell you, okay.
some other questions
about neuroplasticity.
So the other form of neuroplasticity
is not the neuroplasticity
that you're amplifying
by listening to tones or
smelling odors in sleep,
but the neuroplasticity
that you can access
with non sleep deep rest.
So NSDR, non sleep deep rest
as well as short 20 minute naps,
which are very close
to non sleep deep rest
because people rarely drop
into deep States of
sleep during short naps,
unless they're very sleep deprived.
NSDR has been shown to
increase rates of learning
when done for 20 minute bouts for a proxy-
to match an approximately
90 minute about of learning.
So what am I talking about?
90 minute cycles are
these ultradian cycles
that I've talked about previously.
And we tend to learn very well
by taking a 90 minute cycle
transitioning into some focus
mode early in the cycle,
and it's hard to focus and then deep focus
and learning feels almost
like agitation and strain
and then by the end of
that 90 minute cycle,
it becomes very hard to maintain focus
and learn more information.
There's a study published
in Cell Reports last year.
Great journal, excellent
paper showing that
20 minute naps or light sleep
of a sort of non sleep deep
rest taken immediately after
or close to it, doesn't have to be
immediately after you
finished the last sentence
of learning or whatever
it is, or bar of music.
But you know, a couple of
minutes after transitioning
to a period of non sleep deep rest,
where you're turning off the
analysis of duration path
and outcome has been shown
to accelerate learning
to a significant degree.
Both the amount of information
and the retention of that information.
So that's pretty cool,
because this is a
cost-free, drug-free way of
accelerating learning without
having to get more sleep.
But simply by introducing
these 20 minute bouts.
I would encourage people
if they want to try this
to consider the 20 minutes
per every 90 minutes
of ultradian learning cycle,
there you're incorporating
a number of different
neuroscience backed tools
90 minute cycles for focused learning.
It could be motor, it could be cognitive,
it could be musical, whatever,
and then transitioned
to a 20 minute non sleep
deep rest protocol.
I just want to cue you the
fact that in last` episode
in the caption on
YouTube, we provided links
to two different yoga nidra,
non sleep deep rest protocols
as well as hypnosis protocols
that are clinically backed
from my colleague David Spiegel
at Stanford Psychiatry Department.
All those resources are free.
There are also a lot of other
hypnosis scripts out there.
I like the ones from Michael Sealey
S-E-A-L, I think it's
E-Y, maybe it's just L-Y,
you can find them easily on YouTube,
clinical hypnosis scripts
meaning not stage hypnosis.
They're not designed to
get you to do anything.
In fact they're just designed to
help rewire your brain circuitry.
Now, how does hypnosis work that way?
This has a lot to do with sleep because
it engages neuro-plasticity
by bringing together
two things that normally are
separate from one another,
one is the alert focused wakeful state
where you activate the learning.
And then there's the deep
rest where the actual
reconfiguration of the neurons
and synopsis takes place.
Hypnosis brings both the focus
and the deep rest component
into the same compartment of time.
It's a very unique state in that way.
So hypnosis kind of
maximizes the learning about
and the non sleep deep
breasts bow and combines them.
But of course that requires
some guidance from a script
or from a hypnotist
clinically, a trained hypnotist
and it becomes hard to
acquire detailed information.
It's more about shifts in state,
like fear to states of calm
or smoking to quitting smoking,
anxiety around a trauma
to release of anxiety around a trauma
rather than specific information
learned in hypnosis, okay?
So hypnosis seems more about
modulating the circuits
that underlie state as opposed
to specific information.
Although I would not be surprised
if there weren't certain forms of hypnosis
that could increase retention and learning
of specific information, but I'm not aware
of any of those protocols out there yet.
Which brings us to the
next thing about learning
and plasticity which is
nootropics, AKA smart drugs.
[sighs]
This is a big topic that sigh was
a sigh of concern about
how to address nootropics
in a thorough enough, but
thoughtful enough way.
Look, I have a lot of
thoughts about nootropics.
First of all, it means
smart drugs, I believe.
And I don't like that phrase because
let's just take a step back
and think about exercise.
You just say, I want to
be more physically fit.
What does that mean?
Does it mean I would ask for
more specificity, I'd say,
Do you want to be stronger?
Okay, maybe you need to lift
heavier objects progressively.
Do you want more endurance
very different protocol
to access endurance.
Do you want flexibility?
Do you want explosiveness or suppleness?
Huge range of things that
we call physical fitness.
Maybe you want all of those.
If we were talking about emotional fitness
we would say, well,
inability to feel empathy
but probably also to
disengage from empathy
because you don't want to be tethered
to other people's emotions all the time.
That's not healthy either.
You would think about being able
to access a range of
emotions, but for some people
their range into the sadness
regime is really quite vast
but their range into the happiness regime
might be kind of limited.
For other people who are in a manic state,
it might be, they can
access all that happy stuff
but not the sadder stuff.
So I'm speaking by way of analogy here.
But if we say we're
talking about cognitive
and cognitive abilities we have to ask,
okay, creativity, memory.
We tend to associate
intelligence with memory.
And I think this goes
back to like spelling bees
or something, the ability to
retain a lot of information
and just regurgitate information
which will get you some distance
in some disciplines of life.
But it won't allow you creative thinking,
it's necessary for creative thinking.
You need a knowledge base, right?
You can't just look up everything
on Google, despite what
you know, certain educators
or so-called educators say,
you need a database so that
you can have the raw materials
with which to be creative.
So necessary to have memory
but not sufficient to be creative, right?
The creative could have a
poor memory for certain things
but certainly not for everything.
They can't have anterograde
and retrograde amnesia.
They'd be like the
goldfish that every time
around the tank, it, you know
I can't remember where it's at.
I actually don't know that
they've ever done that experiment
by the way, but you know,
so no disrespect to goldfish
but you know, so you get the idea.
You've got creativity, you have memory,
you have the ability
to task switch, right?
You have the ability to
strategy development, strategy implement.
So the problem I have with
the concept of a nootropic
or a smart drug is it's not
specific as to what cognitive
algorithm you're trying to engage.
We need more specificity.
That said, there are elements to learning
that we've discussed here before
that are very concrete things like
the ability to focus and put the blinders
on to everything else that's happening in
around you and in your head mainly, right?
Distractions about things
you should be doing,
could be doing or might be doing
and focus on what you need to do.
And then that's required for
triggering the acetylcholine
neuromodulator that will then allow you to
highlight the particular
synopsis that will then
later change in sleep.
So no nootropic allows
you to bypass the need
for sleep in deep rest.
That's important to understand.
So I daydream about a day
when people will be able
to access compounds that are safe,
that will allow them to
learn better meaning,
to access information, focus better,
as well as to sleep better
and activate the plasticity
from the learning about.
Right now most nootropics
tend to bundle a bunch of things together.
Most of them include some
form of stimulant, caffeine.
Episode two, I'll tell you more probably
than you ever wanted
to know about caffeine,
adenosine and how that works.
So refer there for how caffeine works.
But stimulants will allow
you to increase focus
up to a particular point.
If you have too little
alertness in your system,
you can't focus, too much however,
you start to cliff and focus drifts, okay?
So you can't just ingest more
stimulant to be more focused.
It doesn't work that way.
Most nootropics also
include things that increase
or a desire to increase acetylcholine.
Things like alpha GPC and
other things of that sort.
And indeed, there's some evidence
that they can increase acetylcholine.
I refer you again to
examine.com the website to
evaluate any supplements or
compounds for their safety
and their effects in humans
and animals, free website
as well as with links to studies.
So we need the focus component.
We need the alertness component.
The alertness component
comes from epinephrin,
traditionally from caffeine stimulation.
The acetylcholine stimulation
traditionally comes
from Coleen donors or alpha
GPC, things of that sort.
And then you would want to
have some sort of off switch,
because anything that's going to really
stimulate your alertness,
that then provides a crash.
That crash is not a crash
into the deep kind of restful slumber
that you would want for learning,
it's a crash into the kind of,
let's just call it lopsided
sleep, meaning it's deep sleep
but it lacks certain
spindles and other elements
of the physiology sleep spindles,
that really engage the learning process
and the reconfiguration of synopsis.
So right now, my stance
on nootropics is that
maybe, maybe for occasional
use, provided it's safe for you,
I'm not recommending it, but in general
it tends to use more of a shotgun approach
than is probably going to be useful
for learning and memory in the long run.
A lot of people ask about
Modafinil or armodafinil
which was designed for
treatment of narcolepsy.
So right there, it tells
you it's a stimulant.
And yes, there is evidence, it
will improve learning memory.
Modafinil is very expensive.
Last time I checked our Modafinil
I think is the recent
released a generic version
of this that's far less expensive.
Most of these things look
a lot like amphetamine
and many of them have the
potential for addiction
or can be habit forming.
But more importantly,
a lot of those things
also can create metabolic
effects by disruption
to insulin receptors and so forth.
So you want to approach those with a
strong sense of caution.
Now, there are the milder
things that act as nootropics
that I mentioned, some
of them like alpha GPC.
Some people like Gingko.
Gingko gives me vicious
headaches, so I don't take it.
So people really differ.
Last podcast, I recommend
magnesium threonate
if you were exploring supplements
I'm not recommending anything directly.
I'm just saying if you're
exploring supplements,
magnesium threonate seems
among the magnesiums
to be one of the more
bioavailable and useful for sleep.
I recommended it actually
to a good friend of mine,
it gave him at very low dose,
he had stomach issues with it.
He just had to simply stop taking it.
So there's variability there.
You just, it gave him
some stomach cramping
and just didn't feel good on it.
Stopped it, he felt better.
Other people take magnesium
threonate and feel great.
I was asked, do magnesium need to be taken
with or without food or before sleep?
If you're going to go that route
it should be taken 30 to
60 minutes before sleep,
'cause it's designed to make you sleepy.
And I'm not aware that it
has to be taken with food,
but again all of this has
to be run by your doctor
and this is your healthcare to govern not,
these are not strict
recommendations so look into it.
But magnesium threonate,
most people I recommend it to
have benefit from it tremendously.
Some people can't tolerate
it, so you have to find out.
There were a number of questions
about other supplements
designed to access deep sleep,
in part to access neuroplasticity,
but now I'm just sort of
transitioning from neuroplasticity
to these compounds that
can regulate sleep.
One of them that I discussed
at the end of the last podcast,
I got a lot of questions about is apigenin
A-P-I-G-E-N-I-N, apigenin.
If you will look in the literature
the way it works is it
increases some of the enzymes
associated with GABA metabolism.
It actually, GABA's an
inhibitory neurotransmitter.
It's the neurotransmitter
that is increased
after a couple alcohol
drinks containing alcohol.
And that shut down the forebrain.
Apigenin is a derivative of the camomile.
I think that the proper pronunciation
of this is metric caria kemo mila.
Although I always feel like
I should be using a Spanish accent.
Whenever I say something like that
other related things that
impact the GABA system
and increase GABA or
things like passion flower
which is [speaks in foreign language].
[chuckles] I don't know why
the Italian, is that Italian.
Anyway, my Italian
colleagues, please forgive me.
I have some very close Italian friends
and colleagues in Genoa.
I butchered the Italian, sorry.
In any event apigenin and
passion flower found in a lot of,
a lot of supplements designed
to increase sleepiness
and sleep because, and
they work presumably
because they increase GABA.
Actually they work on chloride channels
rather than give you a whole lecture
on membrane biophysics in neurons.
I'll just say that when
neurons are really active
it's because sodium ions,
salt rushes into the cells
and causes them to fire electrically.
The cells tend to become
less active as more chloride
which is a negatively charged ion.
This is probably taking
some of you back to the
either the wonderful times
or traumas of high school physics.
The chloride is negatively charged so,
it tends to make cells
less electrically positive,
'cause carries a negative charge
and hyperpolarizes the neuron.
So apigenin works through
these increasing the activity
of these chloride channels.
Passionflower works by
increasing the activity
of these chloride channels
and GABA transmission.
It tends to increase this
inhibitory neurotransmitter
that shuts off our thinking
our analysis of duration path and outcome.
So if you're going to explore these things
I suggest you at least know how they work.
You at least go to examined.com
that you talked to your doctor about them.
Some people asked about serotonin
for getting to sleep and staying asleep.
Now I understand the rationale here.
Just like I understand the
rationale of taking something
like Macuna Purina or
L-DOPA to increase dopamine
but sometimes what works on paper
doesn't really work in the real world.
I personally have tried
taking a supplement
which was Al tryptophan, which
is the precursor to serotonin
or five HTP, which is
designed to increase,
it is serotonin basically.
You're just a one biochemical step away
from actually taking actual serotonin.
And I'll be honest the sleep that I had
with increased serotonin
by way of tryptophan or
five HTP was dreadful.
I fell asleep almost immediately.
You say, well, that's great.
And 90 minutes later, I woke up
and I couldn't sleep almost for 48 hours.
Now that was me, I have
a pretty sensitive system
to certain things and not to other things.
Some people love these things.
So you really have to be thoughtful
and explore them with
that kind of awareness
of being thoughtful and
realizing that what works for you
might not work for everybody
and what works for everybody
might not work for you.
Okay?
I'd like to continue by talking about
the role of temperature
in sleep, accessing sleep,
staying asleep and wakefulness.
But first I want to tell a joke.
Because I think this joke
really captures some of the
critical things to understand
about any self-experimentation
that you might do.
So this is a story that was told to me
by a colleague of mine who's
now a professor of Caltech
not to be named.
So there's a scientist
and they're in their lab.
And they're trying to understand
how the nervous system works.
So they go over to a tank
and they pick up a frog,
and they take the frog and
they put it down on the table
And they clap.
[claps]
And the frog jumps.
So they think for awhile,
they pick up the frog, okay.
They go over to the
cabinet and they take out
a little bit of a paralytic
drug and they inject it locally
into the back leg, set
it down and clap. [claps]
And the frog jumps,
but it kind of like jumps
to the side a little bit.
They pick it up, they inject the paralytic
into the other back leg.
They clap again, the frog jumps,
but it really doesn't jump well that time,
it kind of drags itself forward.
So they pick it up and
they inject the paralytic
into the remaining two legs.
They set it down and they clap
and the frog doesn't jump.
And they go,
"Oh my goodness! The legs
are used for hearing."
Now they publish the paper.
Paper comes out in a great
journal, news releases.
It's a really big deal,
their career takes off.
20 years later, a really
smart graduate student
comes along and says, "Yeah
but that's loss of function.
It doesn't really show gain of function."
So let's take a closer look.
So they repeat the first
experiment and checks out,
everything happens the same
way, but then they take the frog
and they inject a drug into
all four legs that turns off
the paralytic, right?
It's an antagonist.
They set the frog down, they
clap, and the frog jumps
and they go, "Oh my goodness! It's true.
The legs really are for hearing."
Now, first of all, I want
to make the point that
this is not to illustrate that science
is not a good practice, it is.
We need to do loss of function
and gain and function experiments.
But just to show that
correlation and causation
is complicated.
You need to do a variety
of control experiments,
and you really need to figure
out what works for you.
And so while science can
provide answers about what works
under very controlled
conditions, it doesn't
and can never address all the situations
in which a given compound,
a given practice will or won't work.
And it's not just individual variability
is that there are a number
of different factors.
You all of course know
that light can activate
and shift your circadian
rhythm, but so can exercise,
so can food.
The last point I want to
make is an important one,
which is that no frogs were hurt
in the telling of this joke.
Okay. So let's continue.
I want to talk about temperature.
Temperature is super
interesting as it relates to
circadian rhythms and
wakefulness and sleep.
First let's take a look
at what's happening to our
body temperature across
each 24-hour cycle.
In general, our temperature
tends to be lowest
right around 4:00 AM and starts
creeping up around 6:00 AM,
8:00 AM and peaks sometime
between 4:00 PM and 6:00 PM.
Now that varies from person
to person, but in general
if we were to continuously
monitor or occasionally monitor
temperature that's what we would see.
Now what's interesting is
that even in the absence
of any light cues or meal
cues, we would have a shift.
We would have an oscillation
or a rhythm in our temperature.
They would go from high to low.
This is why the idea that we're all 96.8
and that's our correct temperature.
Forget that. That is no longer true.
It never was true.
It depends on what time of
day you measure temperature.
However, there is a range
which is within normal range,
I think most of us associate
fever with somewhere around
100, 101 103, that's concerning.
And we will be very concerned
if temperature drop too low as well.
The way that the temperature
rhythm that's indogenous,
that's within us and
rhythmic no matter what,
the way it gets anchored to
the pattern I described before,
or being lowest at 4:00 AM
and increasing again around,
through the day until about
four to 6:00 PM is by way
of entrainment or matching
to some external cue,
which is almost always going
to be light, but also exercise.
Now you may have experienced
this temperature rhythm
and how quickly it can become uninterested
or it can fall out of entrainment.
Here's an experiment I
wouldn't want you to do
but you've probably
experienced this before,
where you wake up, it's sunny outside,
and maybe you have some email
or some things to take care of
or maybe you didn't sleep
that well the night before
and so you stay in doors.
You don't change anything
about your breakfast,
you don't change anything about
your within home temperature
or anything like that.
And somewhere right
around 10 or 11 o'clock
you start feeling kind of
chilled, like you're cold.
Well, what happened was
the oscillators, the clocks
in your various tissues that
are governed by temperature
and circadian rhythm are
starting to split away
from your central clock mechanisms.
So it's actually important
that your temperature match day length.
Now there's another way
in which temperature matches,
oh daytime, excuse me.
There's also an important way
in which temperature matches
day length in general
as days get longer, it
tends to be hotter out.
Not always, but in general,
that's the way it is.
And as days get shorter, it
tends to be colder outside.
So temperature and day length
are also linked metabolically.
They're linked biologically
they're linked, excuse me,
and atmospherically they're linked
for the reason that we talked about before
about duration of day length
and other climate features and so forth.
So one of the most powerful things
about setting your
circadian rhythm properly
is that your temperature
will start to fall
into a regular rhythm.
And that temperature
has a very strong effect
on things like metabolism
and when you will feel
most willing and interested
in exercising, typically
the willingness to exercise
and engage in any kind of
activity mental or physical
is going to be when that rise
in temperature is steepest.
When the slope of that line is greatest.
That's why 30 minutes after waking
is one of those key windows,
as well as three hours after waking.
And then when temperature actually peaks
which is generally, generally
about 11 hours after waking.
So this is why we say that
temperature and circadian rhythm
are linked but they're actually
even more linked than that.
We've talked before about
how light enters the eye,
triggers activation of
these melanopsin cells,
which then triggers activation
of the super charismatic nucleus,
the master circadian clock.
And then I always say the
master circadian clock
informs all the cells
and tissues of your body
and puts them into a nice cohesive rhythm.
But what I've never answered
was how it actually puts them
into that rhythm.
And it does it two ways.
One is it secretes a peptide.
And peptide is just a
little protein that floats
through the bloodstream
and signals to the cells.
Okay, we're tuning your clock.
Kind of like a little,
we know watch store,
the watch store owner
would tune the clocks.
But the other way is it
synchronizes the temperature
under which those cells exist.
So temperature is actually the effector
of the circadian rhythm.
Now this is really important because
changes in temperature by way
of exercise, by way of eating,
but especially by way of exercise
can start to shift our circadian
rhythm pretty dramatically.
But let's even go to in
a more extreme example.
Nowadays, there's some
interest in cold showers
and ice baths, not everybody
is doing this I realize.
People seem to either
love this or hate this.
I don't mind the cold dunk thing.
I get regular about this from
time to time and I'll do it.
I haven't been doing it recently.
It's always painful to do
the first couple of times
then you get kind of used to it.
However, I've taken people to
a cold, dunk or an ice bath.
I have a family member who wouldn't get in
literally passed her toes.
She was like, this is
just too aversive for me.
Some people really like the
cold, people very tremendously.
Getting into an ice
bath is very interesting
because you have a rebound
increase in thermogenesis.
Now you should know from
the previous episode
that as that temperature increases,
it will shift your circadian rhythm
and which direction it
shifts your circadian rhythm
will depend on whether
or not you're doing it
during the daytime or late in the day.
If you do it after 8:00 PM,
it's going to make your day longer, right?
Because your body and your central clocks
are used to temperature
going up early in the day
and throughout the day and
peaking in the afternoon.
If you then increase that further
or you simply increase it
over its baseline at 8:00 PM
after temperature was already falling,
even if it's just by a half a
degree or a couple of degrees
or you do that with exercise
doesn't have to be with the ice bath,
you are extending, you are
shifting forward your phase,
delaying your clock.
You're convincing your clock
and therefore the rest of your body
that the day is still going, right?
You you're giving it the
perception, the cellar
and physiological perception
that the day is getting longer.
And you will want to
naturally stay up later
and wake up later.
Now you might say, "Wait
I do an ice bath late at
night, and I feel great.
And I fall deeply asleep."
Well, cold can trigger
the release of melatonin.
There's a rebound increase in melatonin.
So that could be the cause of that effect.
You have to see what works for you,
but if you do the ice bath early
in the day and then get out
you will experience a more rapid rise
or cold shower early in
the day, a more rapid rise
in your body temperature that
will phase advance your clock
and make it easier to get
up early the following day.
So for those of you that are
having trouble getting up
and this is going to
almost sound laughable
but a cold shower first
thing in the morning
will wake you up, but that's
waking you up in the short term
because of a different mechanism
which I'll talk about in a moment,
but it also is shifting your clock,
it's phase advancing your clock
in a way that makes you
more likely to get up
earlier the next day, okay?
So in other words,
increasing your temperature
by getting in an ice bath
or cold shower or exercising
which causes a compensatory
increase in body temperature.
Think about the normal
pattern of body temperature.
Low around 4:35 AM starts to
peak right around waking start,
excuse me, starts to
increase right around waking
then steep slope, steep slope to a peak
around four to 6:00 PM and then drops off.
If you introduce an
increase in body temperature
by way of cold exposure early in the day,
let's say 6:00 AM or 5:00 AM
if you're masochistic enough
to get into a cold shower
at that time more power to you,
it's going to make, you want
to wake up about half hour
to an hour earlier the next
day than you normally would.
Whereas if you do it while
your temperature is falling,
it will tend to delay and
make your body perceive
as if the day is getting longer.
These are phase advances and phase delays.
We're going to get into
this in far more detail
when we talk about jet lag
and shift work in episode four
as well as other other things.
But temperature is,
again is not just one tool to manipulate
wake up time and circadian
rhythm and metabolism.
It is the effector.
It is the way that the
central circadian clock
impacts all the cells
and tissues of your body.
If you want to read further about this
and you're really curious
about the role of temperature
work by Joe Takahashi
who used to be at Northwestern University
and is now at UT Southwestern in Dallas,
incredible scientist and
has really worked out
a lot of the mechanisms around temperature
in circadian rhythms.
You can just Google his name
and you'll see a whole
bunch of studies there.
I want to talk about
cold and cold exposure
because there's a great
misconception about this
that actually you can
leverage once you understand
how to use cold to either
increase thermogenesis
and fat loss, metabolism,
or you can use it for
stress, mitigation and mood.
And it really depends
on one simple feature
of how you approach the
ice bath or cold shower.
If you get into an ice bath or cold shower
and you are calming yourself
you're actively calming
the autonomic nervous system.
Maybe through some deep breathing,
maybe through visualization,
maybe you sing a song.
You know, people do this stuff.
They use various tools.
Some people find paying attention
to an external stimulus is more helpful.
You know, thinking about something
not the experience of the cold,
other people find that
directly experiencing the cold
in its most intense form and
kind of "going into the cold"
is the best way to approach it.
It really varies for people.
There's no right or wrong
way to go about this.
But the goal of using cold
exposure for stress inoculation
and to raise your stress threshold
to be able to tolerate heightened levels
of real life stress, not the
ice bath, but real life stress
like work stress and
relational stress, et cetera
is by suppressing the activation
of the so-called
sympathetic nervous system,
meaning the alertness or stress system.
That involves buffering
or trying to resist the shiver response.
The shiver response is
an autonomic response
designed to generate heat, presumably,
and actually that is what it does
in order to counter the cold.
So when you use cold exposure
and you're kind of muscling through it,
or you're learning to relax within it
as a form of stress inoculation,
that's great and works
quite well for that purpose.
And there's a reason why
cold exposure is used
in a variety of forms of
military stress inoculation,
most famous of which of
course is the Navy seal buds,
a strep test really,
which is screening procedure
for becoming a seal
involves a lot of exposure to cold water.
However, if you're interested
in using cold exposure
for fat loss and thermogenesis,
you want to do the exact opposite thing.
There was a paper published
in nature two years ago
which showed that cold induced shiver,
the actual physical shiver
activates the release of
a chemical in the body from
muscle called succinate
S-U-C-C-I-N-A-T-E.
Succinate travel in the
bloodstream and then goes
and activates a particular category of fat
not the typical kind pink or white fat
that we think of is
like blubber in humans.
That the stuff that people will seem to
generally want less of,
except for those genetic freaks
that seem to have none of it
depending what they consume.
Congratulations.
Brown fat is called Brown fat
because it's actually
dark under the microscope.
It's rich with mitochondria
and it exists mostly
between the scapulae
and in the upper neck.
And it generates thermogenesis
and heat in the body.
It's rich with a certain category
of agile anergic receptor,
in insanely epinephrin binds
to adrenergic receptors.
These Brown fat cells increase metabolism,
it's called Brown fat thermogenesis
and cause fat burning,
burning of other kinds of fat,
the pink and white fat.
So what does this all mean?
This means if you want to use the ice bath
in order to increase
metabolism, shiver away.
If you want to use the
ice bath or cold shower
in order to stress
inoculate, resist the shiver
and learn to stay calm
or "muscle through it".
I mean, I don't know that
anyone's ever really talked
about this publicly because
I think the data are so new.
And I think that people
assume that the ice bath
or cold exposure is just one thing.
Here I've talked about it three ways
to shift your circadian rhythm
depending on whether or not
you're doing it early in the day
while your temperature is
still rising or at its peak
or after that peak, in order
to extend the perception
of your day as continuing
and make you want to go
to sleep later and wake up later.
Now, and then the third
way of course is to either
activate brown fat thermogenesis
and increase metabolism.
I suppose the fourth way would be to
increase stress tolerance
or stress threshold, okay?
But remember, temperature is the effector
of circadian rhythms.
Light is the trigger.
The super charismatic nucleus
is the master circadian clock
that mediates all these changes,
also influenced by non-photic influence
like exercise and feeding
and things of that sort.
But temperature is the effector.
Now you can also shift your
circadian rhythm with eating.
When you travel and you
land in a new location
and your schedule is inverted 12 hours.
One way that we know you
can shift your rhythm
more quickly is to get onto
the local meal schedule.
Now that probably has
to do with two effects.
One or changes in temperature inducer,
eating induced increases
in body temperature.
Now you should understand
why that would work
as well as eating has this
anticipatory secretion
of beta, of hyper cretin orexin
that I talked about it earlier.
So, if this is getting a
little too down in the weeds,
don't worry about it.
I will get more into this in episode four
of how to shift one's rhythm.
But I would love for people
to understand that light
and temperature are the
real heavy duty leavers
when it comes to moving
your circadian rhythm
and sleep times and activity schedules
and exercise and feeding can help,
but really temperature and light,
with light being the primary
one are the most important
when it comes to sleep and wakefulness.
Many people asked questions
about food and neurotransmitters
and how those relate to
sleep, wakefulness and mood,
which is essentially 25 hours
of content for me to cover.
But I'm going to try and distill
out the most common questions.
We've talked a lot about
neuromodulators like dopamine,
acetylcholine and norepinephrine.
You may notice in those
discussions that the precursors
to say serotonin is tryptophan.
Tryptophan actually comes from the diet.
It comes from the foods that we eat.
tyrosine is the precursor to dopamine.
And then once we ingest them
those compounds are
circulated to a variety
of different cells and tissues,
but it is true that our food
and the particular foods we can influence,
things like neuromodulator
levels to some extent,
it's not the only way,
because there are also enzymes
and biochemical pathways
that are going to regulate
how much tyrosine gets
converted into dopamine
and there are elements of
the dopaminergic neurons,
the dopamine neurons
themselves that are electrical
that have influence on this as well.
But there are a couple fair
assumptions that we can make.
First of all, nuts and meats
in particular red meats,
tend to be rich in things
like tyrosine, right?
That tells you right there,
that because tyrosine is
the precursor of dopamine,
and dopamine is the
precursor of norepinephrine,
and epinephrine that those
foods tend to lend themselves
toward the production of dopamine
and epinephrin and the sorts of things
that are associated with wakefulness.
Now, of course, the
volume of food that we eat
also impacts our wakefulness.
If we eat a lot of anything,
whether or not it's ribeye
steaks, rice, or cardboard,
please don't eat cardboard,
your stomach if it's
very distended it will
draw a lot of blood into your
gut and you will divert blood
from other tissues and
you'll become sleepy.
So it's not just about food content,
it's also about food volume, all right?
Fasting states generally are
associated with more alertness,
epinephrin so forth and fed
states are generally associated
with more quiescence and
relaxation, serotonin,
and the kind of things that
lend themselves more towards
sleep and less toward alertness.
Foods that are rich in
tryptophan tend to be things
like white meat, turkey,
also complex carbohydrates.
So if you like you can start experimenting
depending on what foods you eat.
You can start experimenting
with carbohydrate rich meals
for accessing sleep and
more depth of sleep.
This is actually
something I personally do.
I tend to eat pretty low
carbs during the day.
I actually fast for until about noon.
Not because I have to work to do that,
but because I'd rather just drink caffeine
and water during that time.
And then sometime around noon
I can't take it anymore and I'm hungry.
And I eat and I try and eat low carb-ish
unless I've worked out extremely hard
in the previous two
hours, which I rarely do,
although I do it sometimes.
And that meal is then
designed to prolong my period
of wakefulness into the late afternoon.
And then sometime around dinner time
which for me is around 6:37 PM, 8:00 PM.
Sometimes as late as 9:00
PM, I tend to eat things
like white meat, fish, pastas,
rice, that kind of thing.
My favorite food of all
for accessing tryptophan
is actually a starch.
It's actually a vegetable.
And it's the croissant, which
is my favorite vegetable.
I don't eat those all
the time, but I love them
and they seem to increase
dopamine as well.
I've never actually done
the mass spectrometry
on a croissant, but they
definitely increase tryptophan
and relaxation for me.
In all seriousness, low
carbohydrate/fasted/ketogenic diets
tend to lend themselves toward wakefulness
by way of increasing epinephrin,
norepinephrine, adrenaline
dopamine, and things of that sort.
Carbohydrate rich meals.
And I suppose we talked about
meals as opposed to diet
tend to lend themselves more
toward tryptophan, serotonin
and more lethargic states.
There is very limited
evidence that I am aware of
that carbohydrates should
be eaten at one time a day
as it relates to metabolism, et cetera.
I'm sure that will open up
a certain amount of debate.
If you work out very hard
and you deplete glycogen,
then this all changes.
So some people are working out very hard
in depleting glycogen
and other people are not.
That gets way outside the context
of this particular podcast,
but yes indeed different foods
can bias different neuromodulators
and thereby can modulate awaking
or our feelings of
lethargy and sleepiness.
There are a couple effects
of food that are independent
or I should say a couple
of facts of eating,
'cause the food won't
do it when it's sitting
across the table, but of
eating that are powerful
for modulating circadian,
rhythm, wakefulness, et cetera.
And that's because every time we eat
we get eating induced thermogenesis
regardless of what we eat.
Now that eating induced thermogenesis
and increase in metabolism,
which is an increase
in temperature really,
is probably greatest for amino
acid rich foods like meats,
but also other types of foods.
It's a minimal increase
in body temperature
compared to say cold exposure or exercise.
Now, whether or not it's
a quarter of a degree
or half a degree or a degree,
it really depends on the individual.
And of course there are
blood sugar effects.
There are things like whether or not
you are type one or type two diabetic,
whether or not you're insulin resistant,
whether or not like there's a kid who
interns on the podcast
here, who's 17 years old
and I'm convinced that he can eat anything
and he just seems to like burn it up
and he's growing it every time.
Actually the other day, he
walked into the other room
and two days later, he
walked out of the same room.
He came out in between of course,
but and I was like, you're grow?
And he was like, you know,
but he's at that stage where
he's just growing.
Food is going to affect a
teenager very differently
than it's going to affect
a full-grown person.
So, in general, starchy
carbohydrates, white meat,
such as turkey, some fish
increased tryptophan,
therefore serotonin, therefore
more lethargic states more calm.
Meat, nuts and there are
probably some plant-based foods
that I'm not aware of and I apologize,
I should read up on this that
also are high in tyrosine
that can increase things like dopamine,
norepinephrine, epinephrin alertness.
So you can vary these however you like.
Most people I think are eating
a variety of these things
in a given meals.
And there are other
parameters of nutrition
that are important too.
Volume of food for the reasons
that I mentioned before,
the volume of food in the
gut, less food in the gut
whether or not it's empty
or a small amount of food
which tend to correlate with wakefulness.
Large volumes of food of any
kind will tend to correlate
and drive the calming response
and that's by way of this
nerve pathway called the vegas.
We actually have sensory fibers
in the gut that communicate
to a little protrusion of neurons
that sit right next to the
juggler called the nodose ganglia
N-O-D-O-S-E unlike Costello,
it's no dose right now he's all dose.
Nodose actually means
having many protrusions
and it's like kind of a
lumpy collection of neurons.
A ganglia is just a collection of neurons.
And then it goes into the
brain stem and then forward
in the brain to the areas of
the brain they're involved
in production of various neuromodulators.
So what we eat and the volume of food
are both signaling to the brain.
It's not just one or the other.
And then there's also this
eating induced thermogenesis.
And now, you know, from the
discussion about temperature
that if you're eating early in the day
you're tending to shift
your rhythm earlier.
So that you'll want to wake
up earlier the next day
if you're eating very late in the day,
even if you can fall asleep after that,
there's a tendency for
you to want to sleep later
the next day.
Now this of course is all
going to be constrained by
when your kids need to eat,
and when your spouse needs to eat,
and when your friends need to eat,
or if you live alone or what
other things you're doing,
if you're like me and you
kind of don't eat until noon
then eat sometime around noon.
And then I'm terrible about meals.
I just start eating the ingredients
while I'm supposed to be cooking
and then eventually they're all gone
and I guess that's a meal.
It varies.
Some people are neurotically attached
to a particular meal schedule.
Some people are not.
I take my light exposure
schedule far more seriously
than I take my meal schedule.
Although in general, try
and eat healthy foods
for the most part croissants included.
I was asked several times whether or not
men and women or males and females
differ in terms of these
neurotransmitter phenotypes
and the rhythms of sleep and temperature,
or we could probably devote a whole month
and we probably will
devote an entire month
to what are called sex differences
because those tend to be related to things
we absolutely know like
XX, or XY chromosomes
or XYY in some cases
are double X chromosomes
as opposed to gender, sex
and karyotype as we call it
genetic makeup is crystal clear.
There are things that
correlate with one or the other
but it's complicated
and it's not something
that's been explored in
what I think is enough detail.
Actually recently, I guess
it was about five years ago,
the national institutes of
health made it a mandate
that all studies use sex
as a biological variable,
and actually explore both sexes of mice,
both sexes of humans when
doing any kind of study
because there was a bias
towards only using male animals
or male subjects prior to that time.
So a lot of data now coming out
revealing important sex differences
that I think are going
to have powerful impact
on health practices, et cetera.
Response to drugs,
response to just different
sleep schedules, et cetera.
Perhaps the most salient and obvious one
is that during pregnancy
females experience a whole range
of endocrine and neuro effects
and we definitely will
devote a month to pregnancy
and childbirth and child rearing.
And for that, I'd really like
to bring in some experts.
I've got terrific colleagues
at Stanford and elsewhere
that work on these things,
so that we can go into
those in more depth.
So I'm not blowing off those questions.
I'm just, I'm kind of
pushing them down the road
a little bit where I can give
you a more thorough answer.
So as we finish up, I
just want to offer you
the opportunity to do an experiment.
We've talked about a lot of variables
that can impact sleep and wakefulness.
And in keeping with the
theme of the podcast
we are going to continue to
talk about sleep and wakefulness
and tools for those, and the
science behind those tools
as we go forward.
But there are really just
four simple parameters
that you have control over,
that you can immediately start to record
and take note of just
to see how you're doing
with these things.
With no judgment or perhaps no change
to what you're actually doing.
It might be interesting, just
a suggestion to write down
for each day when you went
outside to get sunlight
and when you did that, relative to waking.
So you would write down,
like the way I do this
in my calendar is I'll
write down that I don't
get exact about it.
I might say, I woke up at 6:15 and then I,
as I'll put a W 6:15,
and then SL for sunlight
and you'll sometimes
get outside right away.
Other times I'm less good at that.
And I'll go out around, let's say seven
and for how long, I don't maybe
like 10, 15 minutes or so.
And then I'll put a little check
at the times that I
eat my so-called meals.
Although, as I mentioned,
sometimes my meals are
a bunch of small checks
that just kind of extend
through the late hours of the day.
Yours might be more
confined to certain times.
And then you might just take
note of when you exercised,
just put down an E for when you exercise.
Weight training or aerobic exercise.
And you might note when you
might've felt chilled or cold
if you do, or you might've
felt particularly hot,
or if you woke up in the middle of night,
when you felt particularly hot.
And then the last thing
you might want to do
is just write down
if and when you did a non
sleep deep rest protocol,
an STR protocol, that could be meditation,
that could be yoga nidra,
that could be hypnosis.
Anything that you're using to deliberately
teach your nervous system,
how to go from more alertness
to more calmness in the waking state,
even if it's waking up in
the middle of the night
and doing an SDR protocol
or in the afternoon,
or first thing in the
morning to recover some sleep
and ability to perform
DPOs that you might've lost
from a minimal or poor night's sleep.
So you're going to rite
down when you woke up,
when you viewed sunlight,
that might be in the morning
and the evening, or just
the morning, hopefully
it's the morning and the
evening, when you exercised,
when you eat your meals and using a simple
record keeping scheme like W
for waking, SL for sunlight
maybe you come up with a
system where it's a check
or an X or something for exercise.
This is not designed to make
you neurotically attached
to tracking all your behaviors
and everything you do.
I for instance, don't track what I eat.
In particular, I kind of
know what works for me
and I'd just try and
stay within that range.
But by doing this you can start to reveal
some really interesting patterns.
Patterns that no answer that
I could provide you about
any existing tool or
protocol could counter.
It's really about taking
the patterns of behaviors,
of waking, and light viewing, and eating,
and exercise and superimposing that on
what you're learning
in this podcast and elsewhere of course
and what you already know
and trying to see where
certain problem or problems or
pain points might be arising.
Maybe you're eating really late in the day
and you're waking up
in the middle of the night, really warm.
Well, now you would say,
"Well, that could be due to
kind of an increase in temperature
that is extending my day
or maybe you start to find
that using cold exposure
early in the day is great for you,
but using it late, if
it's too late in the day,
that's not great.
Or if you're into the sauna or it's even
like some people, including
myself, if I take a hot shower
or sit in a hot tub or
a sauna late at night,
well then I get a compensatory
decrease in body temperature
and I sleep great provided
I hydrate well enough,
'cause that can be kind of
a dehydrating thing to sit
in hot, hot conditions.
But if I do the sauna early in the day,
unless I exercise immediately afterward
then I tend to get the temperature
drop, which makes sense
because when you get in the
sauna, you're get vasodilation.
You throw off a lot of heat and then you
generally get a compensatory
drop in temperature.
If you do that early in
the day, that's right
about the time that temperature
is trying to entrain the
circadian clocks of your body.
That's what happens to me.
Other people, it might
be slightly different
and some people have more
resilient systems than others.
So I just encourage you to
start becoming scientists
of your own physiology of
your own brain and body
and seeing how the
various tools that you may
or may not be using are
effecting your patterns of sleep,
your patterns of
attention and wakefulness.
It's vitally important
that if you do this,
that you know that it's
not about trying to get
onto an extremely rigid schedule,
it's really about trying
to identify variables
that are most powerful
for you, and that push you
in the direction that you want to go.
And changing the variables
that are pushing your body
and your mind in the directions
that you don't want to go.
Self experimentation is
something that should be done
slowly, carefully, you don't
want to be reckless about this.
And this is where I would
say manipulating one
or two variables at a time
is really going to be best
as opposed to changing of
a dozen things all at once
to really identify what it is
that's most powerful for you.
As always, thank you so
much for your questions.
We are going to continue
to answer questions.
I certainly didn't get to all of them
but we tried to get to
most all of the ones
that were frequently asked.
Episode four of the podcast,
I'm going to get into,
shift work, jet lag and
age dependent changes
in sleeping and wakefulness and cognition.
So for those of you with kids,
for those of you that are kids
for those of you with older
relatives or who might be older
meaning probably when
you start to get into
late '60, '70 and '80 is
when there's some marked
biological shifts in
temperature regulation
and things that relate to sleep.
And for those of you that travel,
we're going to talk about jet lag.
The shift work discussion
might seem only relevant
to those that work nights, but
actually that's not the case.
Most people because of the
way they're interacting
with devices are actually
in a form of shift work now,
where the days are
certainly not nine to five,
the so-called banker's hours,
and then the lights are out at nine
and they're asleep until 5:00 AM.
Some people have that
schedule, most people do not.
So episode four, we will go
deeply into shift work, jet lag
age dependent changes in
sleep alertness and cognition
and I will touch back on
a few of your questions
but don't think that
if your question wasn't answered
during these office hours
that we won't get to it, I
absolutely will at some point.
In addition to that, several of you
have graciously asked how you
can help support the podcast.
And we very much appreciate that.
You can support the podcast
by liking it on YouTube,
by subscribing on YouTube,
by recommending the
YouTube videos to others,
as well as subscribing and
downloading the podcast on Apple
where you can also leave
a review and on Spotify,
we're all three, if you like.
you can also help us by
supporting our sponsors.
So check out some of the sponsor
links that were described
at the beginning of the episode.
And in general, recommending the podcast
to people that you know and
that you think would benefit
from the information would be terrific.
As always I will be continuing
to post on Instagram.
You can expect another podcast
episode out next Monday
about the topics that we've
been discussing this month
and above all,
[upbeat music]
thank you for your interest in science.