- Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
[upbeat music]
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of
neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford,
it is, however, part
of my desire and effort
to bring zero-cost-to-consumer information
about science and science-related tools
to the general public.
Before we begin today,
just want to acknowledge
that if you're watching this on YouTube,
yes, I have a bandage on
the left side of my face,
I was trying to cook
something for Costello and I
and I got burned, burned myself,
it was a cooking accident.
I'm fine, no need to dwell
on it, we can move on,
but I just wanted to let you know
everybody's going to be okay,
he got a great meal, I got
a burn and a great meal.
Today's episode is brought
to us by Four Sigmatic.
Four Sigmatic is a wellness company
that makes mushroom coffee.
For those of you that haven't heard
of mushroom coffee before,
I just want to make clear,
these are not psychedelic mushrooms,
and no, the coffee does not
taste like mushrooms at all.
It tastes amazing and
it tastes like coffee.
I started using Four Sigmatic
coffee a few years ago
and then we actually stocked it in my lab,
we still stock it in my lab
because it tastes really good
and it also happens to have
two types of mushrooms in it
that I particularly like
because of their supplement
and medicinal qualities,
and those two are lion's mane mushroom,
which has been shown in
several research studies
to have a mild anxiolytic,
meaning anti-anxiety effect,
and mood-elevating effect,
those are from research
studies done independently,
as well, it has Chaga mushroom,
Chaga mushroom has been shown
to increase growth factors
that impact the nervous system,
like nerve growth factor,
so that's the reason I drink it,
and that's the reason
we stock it in the lab,
why I drink it at home.
If you'd like to try Four Sigmatic,
you can go to foursigmatic.com/huberman,
that's F-O-U-R-S-I-G-M-A-T-I-C,
.com/huberman,
and you'll get up to 40% off your order
plus free shipping on
their mushroom coffees,
that's foursigmatic.com/huberman
for up to 40% off and free shipping.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Blinkist.
Blinkist is an app that has
thousands of nonfiction books
condensed down to just 15
minutes of key takeaways
that you can read or listen to.
For me, I really like
listening to books on Blinkist,
even books that I've already read.
Typically, the way I consume information
is, unless it's fiction, I'll
listen to a nonfiction book
or I'll read the actual,
physical hard copy
of a nonfiction book,
and then at the end, I
like to take some notes
about things that really stuck with me
or key takeaways that I'd like to teach
or share with other people.
With Blinkist, it allows me
to go back to those books
and get all the essential items,
some of which I might have missed
in the course of listening to or reading
the full-length version,
and if I haven't read a book before,
it also gives me a sense of whether or not
I'd like to read the book.
Blinkist has some terrific
science category books,
for example, my colleague and
friend David Eagleman's book,
"Livewired," which came out recently,
is all about neuroplasticity,
it's a fantastic book, I
read the full-length book,
and I've listened to it on Blinkist,
and it's a terrific
synopsis of "Livewired,"
that's in there.
David Sinclair's book, "Lifespan,"
many of you probably
know that David Sinclair,
professor of genetics at
Harvard Medical School,
is a real pioneer in the
aging and longevity field,
his book "Lifespan" is terrific,
I've read the full-length
book, I've listened to it,
and I've listened to it on Blinkist,
and so it really captures a
lot of the essential elements
that you would want to get from that book.
Blinkist is also just a great way
to get through many books on the bookshelf
that you've been meaning to get
to but you haven't had time.
With Blinkist, you can
get unlimited access
to read or listen to a
massive library of books,
not just science books,
and they're all condensed in
this way of just 15 minutes
will allow you to get
all the key information,
so right now, for a limited time,
Blinkist has a special offer
just for "Huberman Lab Podcast" audiences,
you go to blinkist.com/huberman
and you can try Blinkist
free for seven days
and save 25% off your new subscription,
that's Blinkist,
B-L-I-N-K-I-S-T, .com/huberman
to start your free seven-day trial,
and you'll get 25% off,
but only when you sign up
at blinkist.com/huberman.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Theragun.
Theragun is a handheld
percussive therapy device
that releases deep muscle tension.
I was introduced to Theragun
on a dive expedition for my
laboratory a few years ago.
On that expedition, we
were working very hard,
we were diving all day,
we were carrying pelican
cases with equipment,
we were carrying tanks,
very sore, very tired
by the end of the day,
as was everybody else.
Someone brought along a Theragun,
and pretty soon, that thing
was getting passed around
and became the most
coveted device on board
because it really works to relieve
the soreness and deep muscle tension
that accumulates with
physical work, exercise,
even just sitting too
long throughout the day,
so when I got back, I got a Theragun,
I still use the Theragun daily,
it's terrific because it's very quiet
so you can use it while watching a movie
or even while having a conversation
without it feeling intrusive,
it really gets down into the
meat of the muscle if you want,
or you can use it more
superficially if you like.
If you want to try Theragun,
you can go to theragun.com/huberman,
they have several models available,
the first one starts at $190,
which if you think about it,
is comparable to the price
of a professional massage
except that unlike a professional massage,
you can use the Theragun
for as long as you want
throughout the day and for
as many days as you like,
that's theragun.com/huberman,
and I should mention that there's
also a 30-day money-back guarantee,
so if you don't like the
product, you send it back,
you get your money back.
This month on the "Huberman Lab Podcast,"
we're talking all about hormones,
these incredible chemicals
that can impact our mood,
our behavior, our feelings
of optimism or pessimism.
The amazing thing about hormones
is that hormones impact all those things,
but all those things,
how we feel and what
we do and what we think
also can impact our hormones,
and so it's a really
fascinating area of biology
that impacts every single
one of us every day
both in wakefulness and in sleep
and throughout the lifespan.
Today, we're going to be talking
about hormone optimization,
and we're mainly going to be focusing
on estrogen and testosterone
and their derivatives.
Last episode of the
"Huberman Lab Podcast,"
we talked about sexual development,
that is, how the chromosomes,
the gonads, and hormones
impact what we call sexual development,
leading all the way up to puberty.
Today, we're mainly going
to talk about processes
that happen from puberty onward,
although we might talk
a little bit about development as well,
so today, we're going to talk
a lot about basic biology,
but we're going to weave
in a lot of practical tools
along the way for how to optimize
these incredibly powerful
things that we call hormones.
Before we dive into our discussion
about hormone optimization,
I want to raise what I think
is a very important point
that at least I hadn't
heard of until recently,
which is the concept of salutogenesis.
Many of us are familiar with
the concept of pathogenesis,
the idea that there are
all these scary diseases
like dementia and heart
disease and stroke,
and all these things that await us
if we don't take good care of ourselves
and that might await us even if we do,
that's the pathogenic model,
salutogenesis is something I learned about
from one of my Stanford
Medicine colleagues,
which is a different orientation
toward health and well-being
where you're taking on
particular behaviors,
you're taking on a particular stance
towards nutrition and exercise,
supplementation, et cetera,
in order to promote well-being
above where you would be
if you were not doing those behaviors.
Now, if you think about
it, these two things,
salutogenesis and the pathogenic model,
are really two sides of the same coin,
but I'll just give an example
of how this might affect
you in a real way.
If you like exercise because
it feels good, great,
but many people exercise, or
eat well, for that matter,
in order to avoid heart
disease or to avoid dementia,
to avoid negative changes
in body composition,
and while that's powerful
and certainly is the case that exercise
will help you move away
from all those things,
the salutogenesis model differs
in that it involves a
mindset and an orientation
towards doing those things
in order to feels good,
in order to enhance your level of energy,
in order to improve endocrine function
and metabolic function,
so it's really part of
the pathogenic model,
and yet, salutogenesis is
really more of a mindset
toward why you would do
these particular behaviors,
and really, the most powerful mindset
is going to be one where you are thinking
about the pathogenic model,
doing things so that you
don't end up sick, et cetera,
and to move away from sickness,
as well as the salutogenic
model where you're doing things
in order to move towards
health and well-being.
We think of health and wellness nowadays,
or the wellness community
or wellness practices,
and in many ways,
that is the essence of
the salutogenic model,
but I found it very interesting
to know that within the
field of allopathic medicine,
these two models exist
but we don't hear about
the salutogenic model
quite as often,
so it's just something to keep in mind,
especially because of some
of the mindset effects
that were discussed in previous episodes,
I'm not going to go into these
in detail again right now,
but if you might recall from
the episode on food and mood,
we talked about some of
these incredible studies
that were done by Alia Crum's
group at Stanford and others
showing that if you tell people
that the behavior that
they're about to do,
in this case, it was people
cleaning up hotel rooms
because that was their job,
if you tell them that it's good for them,
then you see much greater
positive health effects
than if they aren't
aware of that information
that it's good for them,
so we should really be thinking
about not just moving away from
disease and negative things,
but also why certain
things are good for us
because it's well-established now
from really good scientific studies
that keeping in mind the
positive effects of things
can really have an outsized
effect on well-being,
right down to the level of our physiology.
So let's talk about hormone optimization,
today we're going to talk
about hormone optimization
in reference to estrogen and testosterone
and their derivatives,
now, estrogen and testosterone
and their derivatives
are what we call sex steroids,
now, the sex steroids
immediately call to mind sex,
for obvious reasons,
and steroids, meaning anabolic steroids,
but I just want to emphasize
that estrogen and testosterone
are present in everybody,
it's their ratios that
determine their effects,
and so today we're going to talk
about how you can optimize their ratios
depending on your particular life goals
because the ratio of
estrogen and testosterone
in every individual has profound influence
on feelings of well-being,
feelings of optimism,
feelings of anxiety or lack
of anxiety, on reproduction,
on sexual behavior
independent of reproduction,
they are profoundly powerful molecules,
and we all make these molecules,
to some degree or another,
but there are also
important behavioral tools,
supplementation tools,
as well as prescription drugs
that can impact the ratios
of testosterone and estrogen
in really powerful ways,
so we're going to cover all of that.
I want to emphasize that when you hear
sex steroids or steroid hormones,
most people think about anabolic steroids,
and of course, anabolic steroids
are derivatives of testosterone
or testosterone itself,
and they are heavily used and
abused in the sports community
as well as outside the sports community,
but there, of course, are many steroids
that are not anabolic steroids
that are also abused in sports.
Today, we're not talking
about drugs in sports,
but I think that it
carries such a heavy weight
when people hear the word steroids,
they think about anabolic steroids,
so while today's discussion
will certainly be relevant
to physical performance,
in fact, we're going to talk
about how specific types of exercise,
particular patterns of cold exposure,
as well as particular
patterns, believe it or not,
of breathing can impact
sex steroid hormones,
both estrogen and testosterone,
the discussion isn't really geared
towards performance enhancement in sport,
although we will do an entire episode,
perhaps even an entire month
related to performance enhancement
in physical enterprises.
So one of the first things to understand
if you want to optimize your hormones
is where they come from.
There are a lot of
different glands in the body
that produce hormones,
there's the pineal gland,
some hormones are made
in the hypothalamus,
hormones are made by the gonads,
the ovaries or the testes,
you've got the thyroid gland,
there are a bunch of different glands
that make these different hormones,
but when we're talking about
the sex steroid hormones,
estrogen and testosterone,
the major sources are ovaries for estrogen
and the testes for testosterone,
although the adrenals can
also make testosterone.
Now, there are also some enzymes,
enzymes are things that can
change chemical composition,
and the enzymes that we're
going to talk about today
are the aromatases mainly,
the aromatases convert
testosterone into estrogen,
so in a male, for instance,
that has very high testosterone,
some of that is going to be
converted into estrogen by aromatase,
and aromatase is made by body fat,
it's also made in the testes themselves,
a lot of people don't realize this,
but the testes actually have the capacity
to manufacture estrogen and
aromatase, albeit at low levels,
but this turns out to be important
for optimizing hormone levels
in males at later points,
and we'll discuss that.
It's important to note
that there's a huge range
in terms of the levels of hormones,
testosterone and estrogen,
between individuals,
and it actually occurs within individuals
across the lifespan,
I'm not going to throw
out specific numbers
of X picograms per
deciliter, et cetera today
because that's going to vary a lot,
it's going to depend on
whether or not you're measuring
in picograms or nanograms
and that sort of thing,
if you want to examine your hormones,
you should do that in conjunction
with a medical doctor,
ideally, an endocrinologist can help you
sort out that information,
but the important thing to know
is that prepubescent females
make very little estrogen,
and when we talk about estrogen,
we mainly talk about estradiol,
which is the most active form of estrogen
in both males and females.
So prepubescent females,
very low levels of estrogen,
during puberty, levels of estrogen,
AKA estradiol, basically skyrocket,
and then across the lifespan,
estrogen is going to vary
depending on the stage
of the menstrual cycle,
but as one heads into menopause,
which typically takes place nowadays
somewhere between age 45 and 60,
levels of estrogen are going to drop
and then post-menopause levels
of estrogen are very low.
As well, testosterone will
fluctuate across the lifespan,
testosterone is going to be
relatively low prepuberty in males,
during puberty, it's going to skyrocket,
and then the current numbers
are that it drops off at
about a rate of 1% per year,
although we're going
to talk about some data
that show that there's
actually tremendous variation
in testosterone levels,
there's actually a lot of examples
of men in their 90s, their 90s,
who still have testosterone levels
that mimic pubertal levels,
which is remarkable and
speaks to the huge variation
in testosterone levels across individuals.
So let's talk about other
sources of these hormones,
and then it will make clear
what avenues you might want to take
in order to optimize these hormones.
The other glands and tissues in the body
that make these hormones,
testosterone and estrogen,
as I mentioned briefly, are the adrenals,
so the adrenals right
on top of the kidneys,
and the release of these steroid
hormones from the adrenals,
in particular testosterone
and some of its related derivatives,
are mainly activated by competition,
so let's talk about competition
because it turns out that competition
is a powerful influence on
the sex steroid hormones,
and the sex steroid hormones
powerfully influence competition.
So most people don't realize this,
but most males of a
given mammalian species
never get to reproduce,
in fact, they never even
get to have sex at all,
and we don't often think about that,
but testosterone plays a powerful role
in determining which
members of a given species
will get to reproduce,
which ones of that species
will actually get access to females,
and so here I'm not talking
about humans specifically,
but it's well known in
species like elephant seals,
in species like antlered
animals and rams, for instance,
that the higher levels of testosterone
correlate with access to females.
Now, one interpretation of
this is that the females
are detecting which males
have high testosterone
and selecting them,
they're more receptive to them,
we're going to talk about
receptivity for mating in a moment,
but it's actually more so that the males
that have higher
testosterone forage further
and will fight harder for the females,
and this is really interesting
because there's very good evidence now
that testosterone can reduce anxiety,
promote novelty-seeking,
and promote competitive interactions,
and so before you leap too
far with this in your mind
and think about all these human
behaviors, just stay with me
because there's a little
bit of biology here
that makes it all make sense
and it turns out to be pretty simple.
We have a brain region
called the amygdala,
in Latin, that just means almond,
but the amygdala is most
famous for its role in fear,
we hear a lot about fear and the amygdala,
but that the amygdala
is really involved in threat detection,
it sets our thresholds for anxiety
and what we consider scary or too much,
testosterone secreted from the gonads
and elsewhere in the body
binds to the amygdala
and changes the threshold for stress,
so I've said before on previous
versions of this podcast
and on other podcasts
that testosterone has
this incredible effect
of making effort feel good,
but what I was really
referring to is the fact
that testosterone lowers
stress and anxiety,
in particular, in males
in a given species.
Now, this is important
because we often think of
testosterone as creating,
whatever, masculinization
or it's, you know, virilization,
or all these terms are thrown around,
but what's it really doing
when it comes to mate
choice and competition?
What it's doing is it's reducing
the threshold for anxiety,
and in doing so, it selects individuals
of a given species to push further,
being willing to suffer more,
although it also reduces pain,
so maybe they also suffer less,
in pursuit of reproduction and females.
Now, it's well known in humans
that both males and females
who have elevated levels of testosterone
will engage in more novelty-seeking,
and I do want to point out
that even individuals without
testes have testosterone,
and peaks in testosterone
have similar effects
regardless of whether or not
someone has ovaries or testes,
testosterone increases
generally lead to more foraging,
more novelty-seeking, increases in libido,
and increases in desire to mate,
so it is the case that
increases in testosterone
promote competitive and
foraging-type behaviors
in humans and in nonhuman mammals,
but it's also true that competition itself
can increase androgens,
such as testosterone,
I want to repeat that, competitive
environments themselves
can increase testosterone.
Now, some people have
come to the conclusion
that if you win, your
testosterone goes up,
and if you lose, your
testosterone goes down,
and to some extent, that's true,
but that's not a direct
effect on the gonads,
that's actually mediated by
the neuromodulator dopamine,
we talked about dopamine
in the episode on motivation and drive,
and dopamine and testosterone
have a remarkable interplay in the body,
dopamine is actually released in the brain
in ways that has the pituitary,
this gland that sits over
the roof of your mouth,
release certain hormones
that then go on to promote the
release of more testosterone,
and indeed, winning
promotes more dopamine,
and later, more testosterone,
however, in the short term,
just competing increases testosterone
independent of whether
or not you win or lose,
so the short version of this
is that competition
increases testosterone,
and this may be an ancient
mechanism whereby the androgens,
such as testosterone, are feeding back
to encourage more
competitive-type behaviors
because every species,
whether or not you're
talking about reproduction
or other resource allocation,
is involved in competition,
not every individual of a species
gets access to the same number of mates
or the same quality of mates,
and this is true in both directions,
for males and females and
everything in between.
So I just want to emphasize once more
in case I went through it too quickly
that increases in testosterone in females
are also going to lead to
increase in reproductive behavior
or seeking out reproductive
behavior, they increase libido,
in fact, there's a particular
phase of the menstrual cycle
where testosterone peaks
just before ovulation
that, on average, leads
female humans to seek out sex
more than they would
otherwise during their cycle,
and this is all by self-report,
but this is also while measuring
things like testosterone-estrogen
ratios, and so forth,
so it's really interesting
that a single molecule,
regardless of chromosomal
or gonadal background,
is increasing seeking of
mates across individuals,
increasing desire to compete
or willingness to compete,
and lowering the threshold
for stress and anxiety.
It's important to point out
that while increases in testosterone
promote seeking of mates and reproduction
in both males and females,
in females, it's actually
increases in estrogen
that promote receptivity to mating,
so testosterone is
driving the seeking of sex
and estrogen is promoting
the actual act of sex from females,
so-called receptivity,
consensual receptivity.
In males, it's interesting to
point out that testosterone
is promoting seeking of sex,
but it's also estrogen in males
that's important for libido,
if estrogen levels are brought too low,
then men will completely
lose their libido,
this is often not discussed or overlooked
in the discussion about
testosterone therapy
and performance-enhancing drugs,
people think that
hyperandrogenized individuals,
meaning people that have
very high levels of androgen
will have very high levels
of libido, and they will,
provided estrogen is available
in sufficient ratios to
match that testosterone,
so it's not simply the case
that high levels of testosterone
produce a lot of sex and mating behavior
and low levels of estrogen
are good across the board,
you actually need both in
both males and females,
it's just that in females,
the testosterone levels
are always going to be lower
than the estrogen levels,
and in males, the estrogen levels
are always going to be lower
than testosterone levels,
so testosterone promotes
sex-seeking behavior,
and the real question then is,
does sex itself promote testosterone?
And the answer is somewhat complicated,
but the short version is yes,
and as you recall, sex
has multiple stages,
so there's the physical act of sex,
there's the seeking of sex,
and then there's orgasm and ejaculation.
Now, it's important to
distinguish between these
because whether or not sex
itself increases testosterone
depends on whether or
not the male ejaculates,
and this is very important to understand
because on a previous episode,
I mentioned how dopamine
increases with sexual activity,
remember, dopamine and testosterone
tend to increase linearly
with one another,
but then after ejaculation,
there's a release of prolactin,
and prolactin actually sets
the refractory period in males
during which he can't have sex again,
and the duration of the refractory period
will vary tremendously depending
on how much and how long
that prolactin release occurs.
I also described in a previous episode
how some people take vitamin B6,
I'm not suggesting anyone do this,
but take vitamin B6 in order
to reduce prolactin levels
and thereby reduce the duration
of the refractory period,
but getting at this question
about testosterone and sexual behavior,
it's important to distinguish
between these different
phases of reproduction
or reproductive behaviors,
so there are studies showing
that sexual behavior itself
can increase testosterone,
there was a study published in 2011
from Escasa et al., E-S-C-A-S-A,
this is the stuff of
textbooks, this is on PubMed,
these are quality studies,
showing that men who observe sex,
so I guess this would be
observing pornography,
will have slight increases in testosterone
during the observation,
these people actually were
willing to have blood draws taken
while watching pornography,
they had increases in testosterone
that were very modest,
of about 10%,
whereas when people participated in sex,
so they actually did this study
where people had blood draws
and they had real sex with their partners,
and they had 70%
increases in testosterone,
so there are increases in testosterone
that are quite significant
during the physical act of sex
and far less so during observing sex.
Now, the question that I often get,
in fact, it's one of the
questions I get most often
in the comments on YouTube,
I don't know why that is,
is whether or not ejaculation
adjusts testosterone levels,
and it turns out, there are
two studies that I could find
that were quality studies
on PubMed that address this,
that sex and ejaculation itself
does not reduce testosterone levels
although it will increase prolactin levels
for the reasons I described a moment ago,
however, abstinence or
sex without ejaculation
for a week or more
will increase testosterone
levels up to 400%,
so the answer is actually complicated,
it's not straightforward,
what it means is that sex
itself increases testosterone,
however, abstinence also
increases testosterone
even further,
so it's a nuanced answer,
and I hope this is
satisfactory, no pun intended,
to those of you that have been asking me,
what is the relationship
between sex and ejaculation
and testosterone and dopamine?
It is nuanced, and you have
to understand that nuance
if you want to understand
how certain behaviors impact hormones
and how hormones impact those behaviors.
As I mentioned before, in females,
testosterone also primes the
motivation to seek out sex,
and sex itself also
increases testosterone,
but it also increases prolactin,
so in both men and women,
sex increases prolactin post-sex,
it's just the way that the system works,
it's that testosterone
and dopamine increase
in the seeking-out and
the behavior of sex,
and then after sex,
prolactin levels go up,
there's kind of a quiescence,
the whole nervous system
is promoted towards calm,
and this may actually have
something to do with pair-bonding
and the encouragement of individuals
to spend more time together
to exchange different smells and hormones,
and maybe even pheromones,
and we're going to talk
about pheromones in a moment.
A few years ago, there
was a lot of excitement
about the hormone DHEA,
which is mainly made by the adrenals,
DHEA has been promoted
as kind of a catch-all
for increasing testosterone and estrogen
in males and females,
and indeed, DHEA will increase
both testosterone and estrogen,
this is something to be mindful of
if you're thinking about taking DHEA
or you're taking DHEA already.
DHEA will increase both
testosterone and estrogen,
and the extent to which it
increases one or the other
will depend on whether or
not you're starting off
with more estrogen than testosterone
or whether or not you're starting off
with more testosterone than estrogen
and whether or not you
have a lot of aromatase,
so for individuals that
have a lot of aromatase
being made by the testes or by body fat,
if you take DHEA, there's a good chance
that a fair portion of that
is going to be shuttled
towards estrogen production
and not towards testosterone production,
whereas in individuals that have
low levels of testosterone to begin with,
high levels of estrogen,
there's a good chance that the DHEA
is going to promote mainly
estrogen production,
at least that's what I could find
from the research studies that I examined.
So the way to think about DHEA,
it's a kind of global promoter
of the sex steroid hormones,
and its specific effects
are going to depend
a little bit on where you started
and whether or not you
have ovaries or testes.
So just as there are behaviors
that can increase testosterone,
there are behaviors that
can decrease testosterone,
and one of the most
well-characterized ones in humans
is becoming a parent.
So expecting fathers have
an almost 50% decrease
in testosterone levels, both
free and bound testosterone,
as well, their cortisol
levels, a stress hormone,
drop by almost three-fold,
which is incredible,
and their estradiol levels double,
so their estrogen levels double,
so expecting fathers
many people have known
put on additional body weight,
everyone always thought that
it's because they're eating
in parallel with their pregnant wife,
but it turns out that these
effects of reduced testosterone,
increased estradiol, and reduced cortisol
can all be explained by
an increase in prolactin,
so not just in humans, but
in other species as well,
when the male and female of that species
are expecting young,
they lay down more body fat,
the assumption is that this is to prepare
for long nights of no sleep,
which occurs in many
species, not just in humans,
so it's really interesting
that this hormone, prolactin,
can start suppressing whole
categories of hormones,
sex steroid hormones,
and can start increasing whole
categories of other ones,
so we hear about the dad bod,
there are a lot of
explanations for the dad bod
that extend well beyond
this podcast episode,
but it is a well-known phenomenon
that testosterone is going to drop,
prolactin's going to increase,
estradiol's going to
increase in males and females
that are expecting children.
Now, how long that lasts
is very interesting,
it actually has to do
with how much contact
and how much contact with smells
of the baby, of the offspring,
the father happens to have,
so how available or unavailable he is
will actually impact
his level of hormones,
now, I'm definitely not promoting the idea
that fathers or mothers take
time away from their offspring
in order to keep their
testosterone levels high
or to restore them,
that's not what I'm saying at all,
it's just interesting to point out
that these evolutionary
mechanisms push us toward
or bias us toward particular
categories of behaviors
by influencing our hormones,
which then feed back
and promote more of
that particular behavior
because as I mentioned before,
peaks in testosterone in males and females
cause individuals to seek
sex, not promote parenting,
whereas reductions in testosterone,
increases in prolactin,
and decreases in cortisol
move individuals of both sexes
toward parenting behavior
and less toward reproductive behavior.
The other behavior that
markedly reduces testosterone
in both males and females
and markedly reduces the desire
for seeking sex and sex itself is illness,
and many of you might say,
"Well, duh, when people feel sick,
"they don't feel like seeking out mates,
"they don't feel like having sex,"
but have you ever wondered
why that actually is?
Well, it turns out that
it can be explained
by the release of what are
called inflammatory cytokines,
so cytokines are related
to the immune system,
they travel in the lymph and in the blood,
and they attack invader cells
like bacteria and viruses,
and under conditions of illness,
we make a lot of different cytokines,
some of them are anti-inflammatory,
but some of them are pro-inflammatory,
and the best-known example
of a pro-inflammatory cytokine is IL-6,
and it's known that IL-6, when
injected into individuals,
will decrease the desire for sex
and eventually will reduce
levels of testosterone and estrogen
independent of feeling lousy,
so the reason why people don't
want sex when they're sick
is because levels of IL-6 are increased.
Now, this is important
because as we start to think
about the different ways
to modulate the sex steroid hormones,
so-called optimize the hormones,
keeping levels of IL-6 low
is going to be important for
them to exert their effects,
now, IL-6 doesn't just
travel to the gonads
and shut down the gonads,
it actually has ways to interact
with some of the receptors
that the steroid hormones,
estrogen and testosterone, bind to,
and impact those receptors
so that the sex steroid hormones
can't have their effect.
In short and put simply,
inflammatory cytokines like IL-6
are bad for sex steroid hormones,
and so we're going to talk
about how to modulate IL-6
in the direction that you would want
and how to increase another
cytokine called IL-10,
which is anti-inflammatory
in ways that can help
promote, or at least support,
the sex steroid hormones.
So as we move forward,
we're going to now start to consider
what sorts of behavioral practices,
as well as other things,
can modulate the sex steroid hormones
in the directions that
you want them to go,
but before we do that,
and in order to set the stage for that,
you should be asking yourself,
how is it, or why is it,
at a mechanistic level,
that behaviors can
modulate hormones at all?
If you think about it,
it's kind of strange
that just the mere act of
being a parent or parenting
can change testosterone
levels so dramatically
or estradiol levels so
dramatically, what is it?
Is it the sweat of the baby?
Is it their saliva?
Is it the sight of the baby?
Is it holding the baby,
or is it all those things?
It turns out that many of those effects
are because of smell,
or in some cases, even
possibly pheromones.
Now, I talked about hormones,
hormones, again, are a
chemical, travels in the body,
impacts tissues and cells
elsewhere in the body,
a pheromone is a chemical that's released
by one member of a species
that goes and impacts members elsewhere,
but of the same species,
or even of other species.
Now, pheromone effects are
absolutely well-established
in lots of animal species,
but they are very controversial in humans.
Today, I'm going to talk
about some of the
well-established ones in animals,
I've mentioned one or two of these before
on previous podcasts,
but I haven't mentioned several of them,
and I'm going to talk about the evidence
for pheromones in humans
that are well-established.
So the main ones in
animals that are discussed
are called the Lee-Boot
effect, the Whitten effect,
the Bruce effect, and
the Vandenbergh effect,
named after the people
that discovered them.
The Lee-Boot effect is when
you house females of a given
species together with no males,
they start displaying longer,
what are called estrus cycles,
in many species, they don't
have menstrual cycles,
which are 28 days,
they have estrus cycles
which tend to be four days
or some variant thereof.
It's an interesting phenomenon
because what it means
is that the presence of the male itself
is changing the ovulation cycle.
Now, many people out there,
I imagine mostly the people
that are ovulating out there
will say, "Of course, I
notice I ovulate differently,
"or my cycle changes when I'm
in the presence of my partner
"or I'm not,"
but the pheromone effect
that mirrors this
Lee-Boot effect in humans
has still not really been identified,
nobody knows what the exact chemical is,
but nonetheless, this is a
strong effect in some animals.
The other one is the Bruce effect,
and this is a very dramatic effect
whereby a pregnant animal will
abort or reabsorb her fetus
if the dad of those animals,
the father that sired the litter,
because these are
animals, they're litters,
is removed and a novel male
is placed in her vicinity
for about 48 hours,
and what's interesting is
the way that this happens
is a pheromone that comes from male urine
activates the gonadotropin-releasing
hormone system
and causes a reintroduction
of the estrus cycle
and a spontaneous abortion of the fetus.
Now, a lot of people have
taken the Bruce effect
kind of to its extreme
and asked whether or not in humans,
miscarriages are caused by
detecting the pheromones
or odors of novel males,
meaning the non-dad male,
and that's still an open question,
nobody knows if that's true or not,
so I want to emphasize that.
The other one is the Vandenbergh effect,
and this is one I alluded to
in a previous episode of the podcast,
which is that puberty in
females can be accelerated
by placing a novel sexually competent male
in with a young female who
has not undergone puberty.
There's also a version of this,
which I haven't described,
which is delay of puberty
where you take juvenile female animals
that have not undergone puberty
and you put them with more mature females
of the same species,
and that introduction of more
females will cause a delay,
a significant delay in
the onset of puberty.
So these are all pheromone effects,
and we know they're pheromone effects
because they're not conscious,
they also don't require actual contact
with the other members of a given species,
these are all effects that can be mediated
by the urine from a given species
or by the sweat of a given species,
and speaking of sweat,
the one pheromone effect
that I'm very aware of from
the published literature
is a paper that was published in 1998
by Stern and McClintock
which was getting at this question
of synchronization of menstrual cycles.
Now, the whole idea of
synchronization of menstrual cycles
is pretty controversial,
for a long time, people said,
"Oh, this is absolutely a
well-characterized phenomenon,"
people in dormitories,
their menstrual cycles would synchronize,
people living in environments together,
and then some studies came out
that kind of undercut those data
and said no, this actually doesn't happen,
and it was kind of controversial,
but there is a very clear effect
that was described by
Stern and McClintock,
what they did actually
was they took females,
they charted their cycles,
and then they had other females
wear pads in their armpits
and they collected sweat
from those females,
and then they took the
sweat from those pads
in those female's armpits,
and they introduced them to women
who had never had contact with
the people who had sweated,
they only had contact with their sweat,
in fact, they swabbed it
underneath their nose,
and if that sounds gross,
they dilute it in alcohol,
so much so that they can't actually detect
the odor of the sweat,
that's actually very important
because it's not the smell,
it's the pheromone chemical itself,
and it turns out the
pheromone chemical itself
can modulate the menstrual cycle,
although it doesn't
necessarily synchronize it
with the sweater,
what it does is it changes
the duration and the pattern of ovulation
relative to the so-called
follicular phase,
long and short of this
is that the sweat and
pheromones of females
can modulate the menstrual cycle patterns
of other adult females,
it's just a question of whether
or not they synchronize,
and if you're kind of
rolling your eyes now
and saying, "Well, of course they do,
"and this is really detailed,"
this is how the science is done,
and the reason why people are so skeptical
about the presence of
pheromone effects in humans
is that there's no
well-identified pheromone organ,
you know, we have an area of our nose
that's responsible for smelling,
that's well-established,
it's been observed in
MRIs many, many times,
in cadavers many, many times,
in pretty much all individuals,
but the vomeronasal organ,
which is the pheromone-detecting organ,
hasn't really been found in humans,
there's something called Jacobson's organ,
which is thought to be
the organ in the nose,
it's actually on the top
of the roof of the mouth
and in the kind of back of the nose,
this is for you wine tasters,
I never can pronounce this,
what are they called,
sommelier, whatevers,
the people that are excellent at drinking
and detecting the essences of wine
that you have to go
through all these tests
in order to get certified as one of them,
somebody tell me,
they are using probably
a similar mechanism
of mixing taste and smell,
and Jacobson's organ, if it exists,
the vomeronasal equivalent in humans,
is thought to be a combination
of smell and taste.
Now, it gets even weirder and cooler
when you think about a given
study that was done in humans
where if you take hundreds
of t-shirts from boyfriends,
keep them separate,
you take those t-shirts,
you wash them many times separately,
and then you offer them
to the girlfriends,
the long-time partners of those guys,
and what you'll find
is that the girlfriend
can pick out her boyfriend's t-shirt
among hundreds of other t-shirts,
not because it smells different,
but because something
about it seems different,
it might smell different to her
in some way that's kind of
imperceptible even to her,
and the level of accuracy
in detecting that t-shirt,
her partner's t-shirt,
is way above statistical
significant thresholds,
so much so that you almost have to say
there's something about these effects
that are real pheromone effects,
although people still argue
that there are no pheromone
effects in humans,
that it's all through olfaction,
I think these are interesting
and important to understand
because it means that a lot of things
coming through our nose,
whether or not it's pheromones or smells,
are impacting hormones and
our ability to attach memories
and kind of recognition
of mates and other people,
including our children,
not just our mates,
and of course, perfume manufacturers
have really picked up on
the idea of pheromones
and have entire laboratories set up
to build chemical compounds into perfumes
that are designed to attract other mates,
this is a well-established and
well-documented phenomenon.
And the last point I'll
make about pheromones
is that this combination
of taste and smell
is such a real thing in the animal world
that there's something
called the flehmen response,
during the mating seasons
for different animals,
you can actually even see this in horses,
but for animals that are seasonal maters,
they'll do something
called the flehmen response
where they actually open
their lips and their mouth
and they expose their gums
so that they can capture pheromones
that are floating in the
wind in the environment,
they actually are looking for mates
using their mouth and
kind of sniffing around.
If you own a dog
and you watch the way that
the dog will sniff around
selecting where they want to
urinate, males and females,
they're bringing
molecules into their nose,
I know it sounds kind of
gross, sniffing urine,
but there are a lot of
pheromones in urine of animals,
a lot of pheromones that
are traveling in the wind,
again, whether or not this
is happening in humans,
I don't know, but then you
think about the perfume thing,
and here people are putting
these scents on themselves
that contain putative
pheromones, human pheromones,
and walking around
hoping that their scents
are going to evoke mate-seeking behavior
from other individuals of
the same human species,
so we are among the
animals in this behavior,
independent of whether or not you believe
pheromone effects exist.
So let's get back to behaviors
that can help optimize hormone levels.
One of the main behaviors
that's been shown
to be associated with
poor levels of estrogen
relative to age-match controls
for people with ovaries
or lower levels of testosterone
compared to age-match controls
for people with testes, is apnea,
apnea has everything to
do with under-breathing
and the buildup of too much
carbon dioxide in the body,
there are other effects of apnea as well,
but if there's a consistent
literature in this whole story
about aging and reductions in hormones
and general health and reductions
in hormones, it's apnea.
I went deep into the literature
on advanced menopause,
or when menopausal
symptoms are exacerbated,
and I went into the
literature on andropause,
or early-onset andropause,
or levels of testosterone
that are far lower than they
should be for a given age,
and in every case, you
could find multiple papers
that show that apnea, or
poor efficiency of breathing
and buildup of too much
carbon dioxide in the body
was a problem,
mostly sleep apnea,
although apnea in general
was shown to be an issue
negatively impacting hormones.
Now, the directionality of this
effect isn't entirely clear,
it could be that reductions
in estrogen cause apnea,
and actually, there's some reason
to believe that might be the case,
I found at least one paper
showing that there are estrogen receptors
on some of the neurons that
actually innervate the lungs
and allow for the perception
of how full or empty the lungs are,
in other words, reductions in
estrogen may adjust breathing
by changing our sensitivity
to our own lungs,
now, that was true for males and females,
remember, estrogen is
both males and females,
but as well, I found papers in
which testosterone reductions
were associated with apnea,
and testosterone receptors are also found
on a lot of cells in
the so-called viscera,
including the lungs,
so again, the directionality
of the effect isn't clear,
but what's really interesting
is that there are very clear ways
in which patterns of breathing,
especially patterns of breathing in sleep,
can modulate hormones
in ways that are immediately actionable
and can serve to optimize
both estrogen and testosterone
regardless of whether or not
you have ovaries or testes.
So what is apnea?
Apnea is under-breathing,
or mainly, cessation of
breathing during sleep,
so people are holding their breath,
and then they'll suddenly wake up,
and actually I've talked
about the physiological sigh
on previous episodes of this podcast,
of this pattern of double
inhales followed by exhales
that one can do consciously
to reduce stress and anxiety
and offload carbon dioxide,
that pattern of breathing
is actually what kicks in spontaneously
anytime we have an apnea episode in sleep,
although in many people who have apnea,
they don't engage the physiological sigh.
People who are dramatically overweight
also suffer a lot from apnea during sleep,
there's actually a lot of buildup
of carbon dioxide in the body,
and that can lead to excessive
sleepiness during the day,
inability to access the
deeper phases of sleep,
and it's well-established
that going into deep sleep
and getting the proper patterns
of slow-wave sleep and REM sleep
are important for hormone optimization.
I talked about how to modulate
sleep and optimize sleep
in the first month of the
"Huberman Lab Podcast,"
so please check out those
episodes if you have sleep issues
or you want to work on your sleep,
also check out Matt Walker's
terrific book, "Why We Sleep,"
and that will help you
find various protocols
to help you optimize your sleep,
but the issue of breathing itself
can be adjusted in the
daytime waking hours
in ways that can powerfully
impact both sleep,
reduce incidents of sleep apnea,
and apparently from some
emerging literature,
can also help to optimize various hormones
even just by breathing in
particular ways while awake.
So here's how this works,
there's now a lot of literature
showing that breathing through the nose,
not through the mouth,
is powerful for improving lots of things,
first of all, it improves
cosmetic features
of the jaw and face,
this was first well-established
by my colleagues at Stanford
in a book called "Jaws: The
Story of a Hidden Epidemic,"
this is by Sandra Kahn and Paul Ehrlich,
who are both faculty at Stanford,
has a forward by Robert Sapolsky,
the great Robert Sapolsky,
and it also has a heavy
endorsement upfront
by Jared Diamond, the author
of "Guns, Germs, and Steel,"
the Pulitzer winner,
so a lot of heavy hitters
on this book, "Jaws."
It's not a book that a lot of people
know about, unfortunately,
but it really describes the
benefits of nasal breathing
and the terrible things
that happen when people,
in particular children, but adults also,
are heavy mouth-breathers,
so mouth-breathers have changes
in the cosmetics of their face and jaw
that are really bad in
terms of attractiveness,
and this was done in twin studies,
you can look in the book
and see some of this,
it's really dramatic how
being a mouth-breather
tends to make the chin drop
back behind the upper mandible,
there's a lengthening in the
face, a drooping of the eyes,
it can be quite dramatic or modest
depending on how much mouth-breathing.
Now, sometimes we have to
breathe with our mouths,
but there's also a lot of data and studies
described in this book, "Jaws,"
that describe how nose-breathing
in wakefulness and in sleep
promotes all sorts of positive things
related to not just cosmetics,
but also the improvement of gas exchange
of carbon dioxide and oxygen in the body,
and as well, it can modify levels
of different neurotransmitters
and neuromodulators
in ways that positively
can impact hormones,
so believe it or not,
being a nasal-breather
and avoiding being a mouth-breather
can actually positively impact hormones,
and in particular, the hormones
testosterone and estrogen,
although the way that it does that
is by making you a better sleeper,
which allows you to
produce more testosterone
and the appropriate amounts
of testosterone and estrogen,
but it does that in part
through indirect mechanisms
because deep sleep supports the gonads,
the ovaries and the testicles
and their turnover of cells
and the production of cells,
remember, in the ovary, particular cells
and the egg follicles
themselves make estrogen,
and in the testicle,
that the sertoli cells
and the Leydig cells
are important for the formation of sperm
and for testosterone, respectively.
So what does this all mean?
This means we have to
be breathing properly,
it almost sounds kind of
like, kind of new-agey,
like, oh, you have to breathe properly
to get your hormones right,
but no, you have to breathe properly
to get your breathing and sleep right
so that your sleep can
actually be deep enough
and you're not entering apnea states,
and then that will support gonad function,
and I wouldn't be putting this out
as one of the main
behavioral tools upfront
if it weren't for the fact
that the effects of
apnea on these hormones
are dramatic and terrible,
and the positive effects
of getting breathing right
on these hormones,
testosterone and estrogen,
are dramatic and wonderful,
so let's talk about a few
of those studies briefly
so I can underscore the
value of proper breathing
in order to optimize hormones.
So I was able to find at
least four quality studies
showing that when apnea is
reduced in sleep, or eliminated,
there are significant increases
in testosterone in males
and in proper estrogen to
testosterone ratios in females,
and the way that it works
is very interesting,
apparently, it works by
reductions in cortisol,
now, cortisol is a stress hormone
that is released early
in the day as we wake up
and serves healthy roles in
protecting us against infection,
reducing inflammation, et cetera,
but you don't want
cortisol to be too high,
and you certainly don't
want it elevated too long
throughout the day and night,
and so we all know,
because now we've been told a
lot in the last decade or so,
that getting proper sleep is important
for all these aspects of health,
getting proper sleep can really offset
all the reductions in
testosterone and estrogen
and reductions in fertility that occur
if we don't get enough sleep,
but seldom is it discussed how sleep
actually adjusts things like
testosterone and estrogen,
and it does it by modifying cortisol,
so the molecule cholesterol
can be converted into
testosterone or estrogen,
but there's a competition
whereby the cholesterol
will turn into cortisol
and not testosterone,
or it'll turn into
cortisol and not estrogen
if stress levels are too high,
so the simple version of this
is getting your breathing
right during the waking hours,
meaning primarily, unless
you're working out really hard
or there's some other reason why,
you're maybe eating or speaking,
that you need to be
breathing through your mouth,
you should be a nose-breather,
there's really good evidence for that now,
and in sleep, you also
want to be a nose-breather
because that's going to
increase the amount of oxygen
that you're bringing into your system
and the amount of carbon
dioxide that you're offloading,
there are other positive
effects of it as well,
but you're basically reducing apnea,
breath-holding in sleep leads
to buildup of carbon dioxide
and leads to increases in cortisol,
which then decrease testosterone
and decrease estrogen
in negative ways across all sexes, okay?
So the simple version of this
is get your breathing right,
so how do you do that, how do
you get your breathing right?
Well, for some people that
have severe sleep apnea,
they are going to need the CPAP machine,
this is a machine that you
actually put on your face
and it helps you breathe
properly in sleep.
Many people, however, are
starting to do this thing
of taping their mouths shut,
now, this sounds a little bit extreme,
and you certainly don't want to do this
in any way that's dangerous.
James Nestor talked
about this in his book,
"Breath: The New Science of a Lost Art,"
that simply taping shut the mouth,
with some tape that will allow you
to open your mouth if you really need to,
during sleep can allow
people to shift over
from being mouth-breathers
and snorers to nose-breathers.
In the daytime, the best way
to get good at nasal-breathing
is to dilate the nasal passages,
'cause a lot of people have a hard time
breathing through their nose,
and one way to do this
is to just breathe through your nose more,
and one way to do that
is when you exercise,
in particular, cardiovascular exercise,
most of the time, provided
you're not in maximum effort,
you should be nasal-breathing.
Now, for a lot of people,
nasal-breathing during
exercise is hard at first,
but as you do it,
because the sinuses have a
capacity to dilate over time,
you'll get better at it,
the sinuses, if you haven't
ever held a skull for,
because of my job as a neuroscientist,
I've held a lot of skulls,
taken a lot of brains
out of a lot of skulls,
I teach neuroanatomy,
and I've done that for,
goodness, god knows how many species
I've done that for, including human,
but what the sinuses
are is they're actually,
what you've got are you
got these little portals
in the bone that run, you
know, up here and down here,
behind the nose and into the jaw,
if you ever had a cold and
your sinuses are stuffed up,
you feel like you have
congestion here and here
and around your ears and in
your cheeks and in your face,
and that's because the sinuses
are actually portals where
the bones are fused together
and interdigitated like this,
but they're lined, of
course, with mucus membranes,
and as you start to nasal-breathe more,
the nasal passages will
start to dilate more,
don't worry, you're not
going to get giant nostrils,
but what's going to end up happening
is you're going to have an easier time
breathing through your
nose just from waking,
so my advice would be
breathe through your nose while exercising
unless you're in maximum effort,
pretty soon, what you'll find
is you actually can create more output
than you would if you were
breathing through your mouth,
and of course, there
are exceptions to this,
if you're swimming, follow
that breath protocol,
for fighters and martial artists,
there's reason to do
the kind of exhale
breathing through the mouth,
that shh kind of thing,
you know, there are reasons
to do that sort of thing
for particular sports,
but for most people who are
kind of recreational
athletes or exercisers,
learn to be a nasal-breather,
it has positive cosmetic effects,
it reduces apnea, it
offloads more carbon dioxide,
it increases lung capacity,
it dilates the sinuses,
and it prevents apnea in sleep,
so unless you have severe
apnea and you need the CPAP,
becoming a nasal-breather
can have all sorts of positive effects
by reducing cortisol, reducing apnea,
and indirectly, raising
testosterone and estrogen
in the proper ratios,
so this might seem kind of
foundational and indirect,
but when you go into the
scientific literature,
it comes through as one of
the most powerful things
that you can do that is zero cost,
takes a little effort but it's zero cost,
and it has all of these positive
effects across the board,
you know, both cosmetic
and in sleep and hormonal, et cetera,
so that's the first piece
of behavioral advice.
The second piece of behavioral advice
relates to the viewing of light,
and many of you have heard
me talk about this before,
and I'm not going to belabor the point
that viewing bright light
within the first hour of waking,
whether or not it's from artificial light
or ideally, from sunlight,
has these powerful effects
on sleep and wakefulness,
but we have to return to this
if you want to understand
how light can impact hormones
because hormones, light, and dopamine
have a very close-knit relationship,
so much so that your
light-viewing behavior
can actually have a direct effect
on hormone levels and fertility,
it can have a direct effect
on hormone levels and libido,
it can have a direct
effect on hormone levels
and your ability to heal quickly,
and I'm not talking about shining light
on particular injuries,
that may or may not have positive effects,
we can argue about that on a
subsequent episode, it may,
but what I'm talking about is
viewing light with your eyes,
so let's talk about that now
because the scientific
literature on this are robust
and they extend back several decades,
and yet, I think most people
don't really understand
how powerful this relationship is
between light, dopamine, hormones,
and all the great things that
the sex steroid hormones do
when they're available in your
body in the proper ratios.
In order to understand
the powerful effects
that light can have on
the sex steroid hormones,
we need to understand
seasonal breeding animals,
now, humans are not seasonal breeders,
but if you understand the biology
of how light impacts various
neurotransmitters and hormones,
you'll set yourself up
for a deep understanding
of what you should do with
your light-viewing behavior.
So several species of animals,
many species of animals, in
fact, like rabbits and fox,
and various mustelids,
like ferrets and ermines,
change their pellage
color across the seasons,
this might be kind of a duh,
but fox in winter are
often white or light gray,
and those same animals will
be brown or darker-colored
in the summertime and spring months.
Now, those same animals
breed in the spring,
and they shut down breeding,
they actually shut down ovulation,
they often shut down
testosterone production
in the winter months,
so right now I'm just
correlating color of fur
with tendency to breed,
tendency to breed, as we
know, is going to be related
to the levels of sex steroid hormones,
estrogen and testosterone.
Now, why would these two things be linked?
Well, it turns out that dopamine
is the link between them,
so dopamine has a precursor,
that precursor is tyrosine,
which is amino acid, comes from food,
and when dopamine levels are
high, as I mentioned before,
there's a tendency for more
gonadotropin-releasing hormone,
luteinizing hormone,
follicle-stimulating hormone,
all the hormones that come
from the hypothalamic-pituitary axis
and stimulate estrogen
and testosterone release
from the ovary and testes,
dopamine basically increases all of that.
The precursor to dopamine is tyrosine,
but the precursor to a lot
of the melanin-producing elements of cells
that give pigmentation,
including for the hair,
is tyrosine and tyrosinase, an enzyme,
so yes, the same amino acid-based pathway,
and many of the same enzymes
that are devoted to dopamine
and dopamine increasing
the sex steroid hormones
are devoted to giving
pigmentation to the hair and skin,
and this is why in the summer
months, when days are longer,
animals are breeding more,
and this is also why in the winter months
when days are shorter,
animals are breeding less,
this is also why in humans,
many people, not all,
feel an elevation in mood in
the spring and summer months
because of the amount of
sunlight they're getting
is increased relative
to the winter months.
Now, some of you may be saying,
"I love the fall, I love the winter,"
sensitivity to light in
these dopamine systems
has a strong genetic component,
so you go to some areas of the world,
I have relatives who are Scandinavian,
and in some areas of Scandinavia,
people know that there's
a kind of seasonal affective disorder,
there's kind of a seasonal depression
and people get sadder and
more quiescent in the winter,
there's actually less going out,
and therefore, there's
less sexual behavior,
there's less partying
and things of that sort,
but other people will say,
"No, during the winter
months, I feel great
"and I love the holidays
around winter," et cetera,
so there's a lot of variation,
but in general, the
pathway is the following,
increased viewing of sunlight,
and it has to be to the eyes,
it's not to the skin,
increased viewing of sunlight
increases dopamine levels in the brain,
increased dopamine levels
in animals and humans
increases the amount of these melanocytes
and the activity of these
melanin-producing cells,
which give pigmentation
to the skin and hair,
and indirectly, increase the amount
of testosterone and estrogen,
and thereby, reproductive behavior,
feelings of well-being,
social interactions,
reductions in anxiety, et cetera,
all of which should make sense
based on what we've talked about already
in terms of the biology
and the impact of these steroid hormones
on various aspects of the mind and body.
So how does this translate to a protocol?
This translates to the protocol of,
if you want to optimize
testosterone and estrogen,
you need to get your
light-viewing behavior correct,
it's not just about optimizing your sleep,
which is also important,
it's about getting sufficient
amount of light in your eyes
so you have sufficient levels of dopamine,
so the simple protocols for
that I've reviewed before,
but it means getting
anywhere from 2 to 10 minutes
of bright light exposure in
your eyes early in the day,
it is not sufficient to
do this with sunglasses
unless you have to do
that for safety reasons,
it's fine to wear prescription
lenses and contacts,
if you can't get sunlight
for whatever reason,
you want to use bright artificial light,
but that is absolutely critical
for timing the cortisol release properly,
limiting cortisol release to
the early part of the day,
getting increases in dopamine
that are going to promote
the production of
testosterone and estrogen
to healthy levels,
the other aspect of light-viewing behavior
that's extremely important
is to avoid bright light
exposure to your eyes
in the middle of the night,
if you're viewing bright light
you are suppressing dopamine release,
if you're suppressing dopamine release,
you are suppressing testosterone levels
so much so that I would wager
that a major effect of sleep deprivation
on reducing testosterone and estrogen
is not necessarily because
of the lack of sleep per se,
it's because usually when people
are not getting enough sleep,
they're getting too
much light in their eyes
in the middle of the night as well,
a study on this has
not been completed yet,
but there are two studies
published in "Cell" and "Neuron,"
both Cell Press journals,
excellent journals,
showing that viewing
bright light with the eyes
in the middle of the circadian night
has a detrimental effect on dopamine,
and therefore has a detrimental effect
on things like testosterone and estrogen,
so you can't even begin
to talk about supplements
and other ways to optimize testosterone,
diet and its effects on
testosterone and estrogen
and fertility and reproductive
behavior, et cetera,
until you get your breathing right,
until you get things like your
light-viewing behavior right,
so bright light early in the day
and throughout the day is great,
view as much bright light,
ideally sunlight, as you can,
as much as you safely can,
you obviously don't want
to burn your retinas
or damage your retinas,
so never look at any light
that's so bright it's painful to look at,
but getting a lot of light in your eyes
is not just about adjusting
your sleep-wake rhythms,
it's also about optimizing
your sex steroid hormones,
and avoiding bright light
in the middle of the night
is not just about not
disrupting your sleep,
it's also about optimizing
the sex steroid hormones,
and now that you understand
a bit of how the sex steroid hormones work
and how powerful they
are for reducing anxiety
and all these other effects,
this should be straightforward to do,
or hopefully it's inspired you
to get your light-viewing behavior
and your breathing behavior correct.
In fact, in thinking about tools,
for many people that are suffering
from low levels of estrogen
if they want higher levels
or low levels of testosterone
if they want higher levels,
just getting the breathing
and light-viewing behavior,
which will indirectly
support sleep behavior,
can be a huge and positive effect
on levels of sex steroid hormones.
I can already anticipate
that in hearing this,
you might wonder whether
or not viewing light
is going to, for instance,
increase your testosterone a lot
when in fact you want
your estrogen increased,
or it's going to increase
your estrogen a lot
when you want your testosterone increased,
everything I'm describing
here is for people,
regardless of chromosomal
or gonadal background,
so I'm trying to basically
offer all this information
in one swoop,
but basically, if you're somebody
who naturally has ovaries
and has higher levels of
estrogen than testosterone,
then viewing bright
light early in the day,
because of dopamine's effects,
is going to promote more estrogen
and subtle increases in testosterone,
whereas if you're somebody who starts off
with more testosterone and lower estrogen,
so somebody presumably who has testes
or maybe you're supplementing
with testosterone
through other sources for whatever reason,
bright-light viewing
is going to increase testosterone
and estrogen in parallel,
but you're still going to maintain
the ratio of testosterone to estrogen,
in short, you don't have to worry
that you're going to
increase the wrong hormone,
this is all about optimizing
the ratios of hormones
that you already have.
Okay, so we've talked about breathing,
we've talked about light,
let's talk about a third element
that there seems to be some
excitement about lately
for other reasons
but that can actually have
some pretty profound
influences on hormone levels,
and that's heat and cold,
so as always, rather
than just offer a tool,
I'm going to tell you
the underlying science
as it relates to naturally
occurring phenomena
because, in understanding that
and understanding the mechanism,
you're going to be in
a far better position
to understand the tools and mechanisms
and how you might want to
adjust them for your own life.
So now you understand the relationship
between light, day length,
dopamine, and hormone levels,
and everyone should realize
that temperature and
day length are linked,
and I'm sure as I say that,
you're probably thinking, "Oh, of course."
In summer, when there's more sunlight,
days are longer, nights are shorter,
in general, it tends to be warmer out,
and in winter, when nights
are longer, days are shorter,
it tends to be colder out,
and in the winter months,
testosterone and estrogen tend to be lower
in many animals and in humans,
and in the summer months,
because of the role of dopamine
in promoting the sex steroid hormones,
when days are longer and it's warmer,
humans tend to make more
estrogen and testosterone
relative to the other months of the year.
Now, these effects can be
somewhat weak and modulated
as opposed to in
seasonally breeding animals
where they're really dramatic, okay?
But the point is that temperature
and day length and sunlight,
those are all intimately related
because of the systems
that we evolved in, right?
So before we had artificial light
and artificial heating
and artificial cooling,
our biology evolved under systems
where temperature, day
length, and the hormones
were correlated with one another,
so nowadays, there's a lot
of interest in using cold
as a way to stimulate testosterone,
this is mainly because
in the sports community,
in particular, in the
bodybuilding community,
they are always seeking ways
to maximize testosterone,
dihydrotestosterone,
keep estrogen to its minimum required
to still have a libido and
still have skin elasticity
but also walk around with Saran-wrap skin,
then all this kind of extreme
stuff that happens there
has led to a recent movement
where, believe it or not,
I heard this and I couldn't
believe it, I went and checked,
but although I didn't buy them,
that on Amazon, you can actually find,
they're literally underwear
that have ice packs,
so I think they are ice pack underwear,
so that people are making themselves cold
at the level of the gonads
in order to try and increase
testosterone and libido,
sounds pretty crazy,
but believe it or not,
that and things like ice
baths and cold showers
can have positive effects
on the sex steroid hormones,
both testosterone, mainly in males,
and estrogen, mainly in females,
and you might say, "Wait, I thought cold
"makes the reproductive
axis kind of shut down a bit
"or reduces testosterone and estrogen,"
but it turns out it's
not actually the cold
that's having these effects in people,
things like the ice bath, cold
showers, cold-water swims,
these ice underwear or whatever they are,
can't believe that these actually
exist, but they do exist,
what happens is there's
a rebound in vasodilation
after cooling, so cooling
causes vasoconstriction,
and then after the cooling,
there's a rebound vasodilation
and there's more infusion
of blood into the gonads.
There's also an effect that's neural,
so let me explain how this works
because there are only
a few studies on this,
none of which looking
at the frozen underwear,
but that have looked at cold exposure
and levels of androgens and estrogens,
and it's kind of interesting,
so you have to remember that the gonad,
the ovaries and the testes
are heavily vascularized.
Remember, even at the level of the brain,
GnRH, gonadotropin-releasing hormone,
comes from neurons
that, believe it or not,
start off in your nose
early in development,
migrate into the hypothalamus.
I'm not making that up, they
started off in your nose
and migrated to the hypothalamus.
Those neurons extend
processes, we call them axons,
into the pituitary and release
GnRH into the pituitary.
There's a lot of vascularization
within the pituitary,
so now those hormones, or GnRH,
can stimulate
follicle-stimulating hormone,
luteinizing hormone,
which then are released and
travel into the bloodstream.
Then those hormones reach
the ovary or testes,
and they have to get into
the ovary and testes,
and the way they do that is
through the vascular system,
and people forget, but the vascular system
and how constricted or dilated vessels are
is controlled by neurons, all right?
We discussed this during
the discussion about stress
in the stress episode,
but it's well-known to neuroscientists
that the best way to shut
down neurons is to cool them,
so there are a lot of examples of this
in the scientific literature,
but most people aren't aware of it
because you're not digging around
in the method section of these papers,
but when we want to shut down neurons,
we can do things like inject
drugs that will do that,
like lidocaine, you know,
the stuff that makes you numb
at the dentist,
or you can use different inhibitors,
but one of the best ways
to do it experimentally
is to just cool neurons,
when you make neurons cold,
because there's a temperature dependence
of when neurons can be
active and when they can't,
the neurons shut down,
so the most plausible explanation
for why cold exposure,
either through 1 to 10-minute
ice bath or cold shower
or the ice underpants thing,
would increase testosterone
or increase estrogen
is that you're cooling the neurons
that control vasoconstriction
and vasodilation
and shutting down the entry of blood,
or at least reducing it,
and hormones into the gonad,
and then when the gonad
and the surrounding area
heats up again,
you're getting a rebound
hyper-vasodilation
that delivers excessive
levels of, not excessive,
but increased levels of
GnRH and other hormones
and carriers and carrier
proteins and so forth
that would then stimulate the gonad
to release more testosterone
or would stimulate the gonad
to release more estrogen,
that's the most plausible
explanation I can come up with,
there aren't a lot of studies
looking at direct effects
of temperature on the gonad,
and it's going to be a
difficult study to carry out
in any case because unless it
were done in vitro in a dish,
it's very hard to eliminate
all the other things
like vasoconstriction and vasodilation,
put simply, we don't know
whether or not cold and heat
directly affect the production
of testosterone and estrogen,
we only know that cold and
heat can modulate those,
probably through indirect mechanisms
like controlling the amount of blood flow
by way of shutting down
or activating the neurons.
Now, there's a lot of lore
around heating up the gonads too much,
there's actually a whole set
of pseudoscience webpages
out there saying,
"Well, if you want a girl,
"you should conceive the child
at this room temperature,
"and if you want a boy,
"you should conceive the child
at this room temperature."
I don't think there's really
any firm scientific evidence
for that, for either one,
but there's some interesting literature
about temperature dependence
of production of hormones,
and I think that it probably relates
to these mechanisms of vasodilation
and neural control over vasodilation,
and of course, excessively high heat
is not good for the testes,
for sperm production, or for sperm health,
sperm have all sorts
of proteins in the cap,
things like pentraxins and other things
that cause them to swim faster
when they're expressed properly
and in the right locations,
and heat actually alters the
location and the function
of a lot of those proteins,
they're very heat sensitive,
and so that's why excessive heat
is truly not good for fertility,
which may be independent of heat's roles
in promoting estrogen or testosterone.
Okay, so now we've talked about breathing,
light, and temperature,
we talked about parenthood,
we talked about competition,
and we talked about
some pheromone effects,
now let's talk about
particular forms of exercise
and how they modulate
the steroid hormones,
and then we're going to talk
about various supplements,
both in reference to testosterone
and in reference to estrogen.
So now let's talk about how
exercise in its various forms,
weight training, endurance work,
weight training to failure, or
less intense weight training
can impact testosterone levels,
but I want to remind you that
we're talking about testosterone
both in males and females,
and based on what you know
from earlier in the episode,
testosterone can have
numerous positive effects
in both males and females
provided they're in optimal range.
So if you look on the web,
people will say, "Oh, you know,
"testosterone is increased
by weight training,
"you want to do these big,
heavy compound movements,"
squats and deadlifts and
chins and things of that sort,
but what about the scientific studies?
Like, what's the actual basis for this?
Because if you just take a step back
and look at this from the
perspective of a scientist,
you'd say, okay, what is a squat?
A squat is loading up a
bunch of weights on a bar
and then, you know,
sitting down, essentially,
and standing up over and over again.
What's a deadlift?
It's lifting heavy
weights from the ground.
Why would that increase
testosterone, right?
This is what's often not
discussed in the weight training
or even the exercise science community,
what would actually stimulate
the release of testosterone
from the adrenals and/or testes,
and which one is it,
adrenals or testes or both?
And that's often not discussed,
but as a neuroscientist,
these are the kinds of
things we think about
because we think always that
genes don't create behavior,
immune systems don't know
when to be activated,
lungs don't know when to inhale or exhale,
hearts don't know when to beat
except for the information
that it gets from neurons,
the nervous system controls all of that,
and so really the answer has
to be in the neural system
that's related to these particular types
of weight-bearing exercises.
So when you go into this literature,
it's kind of hard to find real mechanism,
you see a lot of effects,
you'll hear things like,
androgen receptor content,
meaning testosterone and its derivatives,
receptor content following
heavy-resistance exercise,
and you'll find some examples
that, for instance, you know,
they do muscle biopsies,
they can actually see receptor increases,
looking at either high-volume
or low-volume really intense exercise,
and you can find a lot of that
but not a lot of mechanism
about how the nervous
system would do this,
and the reason you'd want
to know how it can do it
is that you could potentially
build better protocols
or figure out exactly
what about these movements
is triggering increases
in androgen receptors and testosterone.
So what's interesting is
when you start digging
into the more mechanistic studies,
what you find is that
heavy weight training,
so this is weight training where the sets
are done with anywhere from
kind of one to eight rep range,
and this translates differently
depending on ratio of muscle
fiber type and so forth,
but where basically people are
working at anywhere from like,
70% to 95% of their maximum,
or sometimes even going
right down to their
one-repetition maximum,
really kind of max effort,
what you find is that
using the nervous system
in a way in which they're
moving heavy loads,
so that I would translate to recruitment
of high-threshold motor units,
for you muscle physiologists,
and there's a rule in muscle physiology
about the neuron recruitment
for moving muscles
where you basically use
the minimum number of
motor units of neurons
to activate muscle as you possibly can,
as loads increase, you have to recruit
more and more neurons,
you always hear about
recruiting muscle fibers,
but really, it's recruiting more neurons
to recruit more muscle fibers,
and what you find is that
heavy weight training,
but not weight training to failure
where completion of a
repetition is impossible,
leads to the greatest
increases in testosterone.
Now, I'm sure there are a bunch
of exercise jockeys out there
that are going to come at
me with a bunch of things
where, oh, yeah, but high volume and this,
and training to failure and that, sure,
if you're willing to kind
of put things side by side,
adjust for exogenous
testosterone treatment
and all the rest,
which was done in these studies,
what you find in general
is that weight training with heavy loads,
so anywhere from one-rep maximum
to somewhere in the six
to eight repetition range,
in males or females,
increases testosterone significantly,
and it does it for about a
day, sometimes up to 48 hours,
and the studies that I found
which seem to hold the
most rigor or weight
based on where they're published
as opposed to being published
in the journal of "Never Heard of It,"
they're published in good-quality
exercise physiology journals,
for instance, the paper by Ratamess,
R-A-T-A-M-E-S-S et al.,
which was published in 2005,
which talks about modulations
in androgen receptor content
after heavy resistance exercise,
looks at going to failure
and not to failure,
the work of Izquierdo et
al. published in 2006,
"Differential Effects of Strength Training
"Leading to Failure Versus Not Failure
"on Hormonal Responses,
Strength, and Power Gains,"
you know, there are a lot of studies here
and I will certainly put the
links to these in the caption,
many of these actually
include Duncan French,
who runs the UFC training center
who I've had the privilege of meeting
and discussing some of this with before,
as well as other authors, of course,
but they all point to the fact
that there's something about
the engagement of the neurons
that recruit high-threshold
motor units in muscle
when moving heavy loads,
but not to failure,
that has to provide some
sort of feedback signal,
either to the gonad to
produce more testosterone,
or is increasing the activity
of receptors in the body.
Now, why do I say that?
Well, this is the puzzle, right?
How is it that a particular movement,
just like how is it that
interacting with your child,
is increasing or decreasing testosterone?
This is the kind of fundamental question
at the mechanistic level,
and we answered the
question for child-rearing,
it has probably something to
do with smell and pheromones,
although I'm sure there
are other cues as well,
but there's clearly a influence
of hard work at the neural level
and then at the muscular level
for increasing testosterone,
and there's also clearly an
effect of working too hard
and presumably increasing
cortisol too much,
although I'm speculating there,
in terms of reducing testosterone,
and so the reason we're
getting nitty-gritty about this
is because ultimately, we'd
really like to understand,
what are the optimal protocols?
You know, out there in the literature,
you hear, move heavy objects
to increase testosterone,
some of that will be converted
to the more powerful androgen, DHT,
by 5-alpha reductase et cetera,
but we really don't understand yet
how these particular behaviors
increase testosterone
and whether or not it's doing that
by modulating the receptors
or it's modulating
testosterone release directly,
presumably, testosterone release directly
and sensitivity of the receptors,
that what most of the
muscle physiology studies
that I was able to find point to,
but this basically boils down
to a particular set of protocols
where if you want to
increase testosterone,
for whatever reason,
that weight training with
heavy loads but not to failure
seems to be the best-supported,
at least scientifically
supported, solution to that,
now, it may not raise
your testosterone levels
as high as you want,
but it's definitely taking
things in the correct direction.
Now, many of you might
be endurance athletes
or also enjoy exercise
besides heavy-weight-bearing exercise,
and there are several studies
exploring whether or
not endurance activity
can increase or decrease androgen levels
and whether or not you combine
endurance activity and weight training,
whether or not that has any effect
if you do the endurance
activity first or second,
and the takeaway from all of this
was that endurance activity,
if performed first,
leads to decreases in testosterone
during the weight training session
as compared to the same weight
training session done first
followed by endurance activity,
in other words, if you want to
optimize testosterone levels,
it seems to be the case
that weight training first
and doing cardio-type
endurance activity afterward
is the right order of business.
Now, when these are done on separate days,
it doesn't seem to have an effect,
they showed no statistical interaction,
but it seems that if
you're going to do these
in the same workout episode
that it's move heavy loads first,
then do cardiovascular exercise,
so there's a little bit of data
looking specifically at
how endurance exercise
impacts testosterone and its derivatives,
and it's very clear that
high-intensity interval training,
sprinting et cetera,
which somewhat mimics the neural activity
that occurs while moving
heavy weight loads,
is going to increase testosterone
and there's ample evidence
for that in the literature,
and that endurance exercise
that extends beyond 75 minutes
is going to start to lead to
reductions in testosterone,
presumably by increases in cortisol,
but of course, the
intensity of the exercise
is going to be important too,
you know, I don't think
anyone really believes
that hiking for three hours
is going to reduce your testosterone,
whereas I think if one were to go out
and run hard for three hours
that you can imagine there'd
be reductions in testosterone
by way of increases in cortisol,
and so while this area
certainly needs more research,
it's pretty clear that
limiting the endurance exercise
to 75 minutes or less,
not making it too intense,
is one way to keep cortisol
from going through the roof,
but I've talked on previous episodes,
and there are a lot of others
who have talked out there
about how to clamp cortisol,
how to keep cortisol more reduced,
this is also one of the
reasons why, you can imagine,
that various individuals,
either for competition or
just for their own purposes,
rely on testosterone therapy,
exogenous testosterone,
not just for weight training,
but for endurance exercise,
so this is one of the reasons
why every once in a while,
professional cyclists will get popped
for performance-enhancing drugs,
meaning they'll get caught,
and it's not just that they're
increasing red blood cells
through EPO and things of that sort,
oftentimes they're also
taking testosterone
not because they want to be large
or have massively hypertrophied muscles,
but because they're
injecting testosterone,
they don't have to worry
about cortisol-induced
reductions in testosterone,
and they can just clamp,
or keep their testosterone levels high,
not something I'm recommending,
but I'm just justifying the rationale
for why an endurance athlete
would want to do that at all.
So now let's switch over
to talking about estrogen,
so there are many people
who are trying to optimize
their estrogen levels,
and one of the places
where this shows up a lot
and I get a lot of questions
about is menopause,
so menopause, as I mentioned earlier,
is this fairly massive reduction
in the amount of estrogen
that is circulating in one's blood
mainly because the ovary
is now depleted of some
estrogen production of its own,
the eggs are not being produced,
they've been depleted, et cetera.
So menopause is characterized
by a variety of symptoms,
and it's multifaceted,
probably deserves an
entire episode on its own,
but things like hot flashes,
things like mood swings,
things like headaches, in
particular migraine headaches,
there can be a lot of brain fog,
it can be very, very
disruptive for people.
Now, you sometimes hear about andropause,
which is thought to be the
kind of analog to menopause,
but menopause has certain characteristics
that make it a very robust
phenomenon for most women,
whereas for men,
andropause is going to sometimes
happen, sometimes won't,
in fact, without going into the details
of the graphs and the data,
it's very clear, as I mentioned earlier,
that some men maintain levels
of circulating androgens
that are quite high,
even as similar as they were in puberty
and their teen years and 20s,
well into their 60s, 70s, and 80s
if they're optimizing
a lot of other things,
and probably genetics
plays a role as well,
whereas some males won't,
but within the female population,
or population of individuals
that have ovaries,
there's a very stereotyped
and characteristic
reduction in estrogen levels
as the number of eggs becomes depleted,
and that's what we think of as menopause.
So what are the various things
that one can do for menopause?
Well, one of the most common ones
is that physicians will
prescribe supplemental estrogen,
so this is hormone therapy
where somebody takes
either their oral estrogen
or they'll use a patch or a pellet,
some way to secrete
estradiol into the system,
and that has varying success
depending on the individual,
some people respond very well to it,
other people really
have challenges with it,
and there are a lot of side
effects associated with it
for some people, not others,
in addition, there's a concern always
about supplementing estrogen
when there's a breast cancer
background in the family
or there's concern about
breast cancer for any reason
because a lot of those cancers
are estrogen-dependent,
and that's why drugs like
tamoxifen and anastrozole
and drugs that block either aromatase
or block, excuse me,
estrogen receptors directly
were initially developed,
you see them a lot on the internet,
again, for all the sports folks
who are trying to increase
testosterone, reduce estrogen,
but remember, those drugs
were initially developed
as ways to prevent estrogen
binding to the estrogen receptor
as cancer treatments,
so I want to be very clear
and I've said this many times,
we always put it in the caption
of each episode, of course,
that I'm not a physician, I'm not an M.D.,
I don't prescribe anything,
I'm a professor and I profess things,
I'm here to translate
the scientific literature
and point to what might be
some useful avenues for exploration,
but this is just for information purposes,
you should definitely talk to your doctor
about anything that I'm talking about now
or in any episode, for that matter.
So if you look at the
literature on menopause
outside of just standard estrogen therapy,
there are some very
interesting compounds out there
that have been used
and that are supported by
quality peer-reviewed studies,
and again, I'll refer you once again
to this amazing website, examine.com,
where you can put in
essentially any condition
or any supplement,
and it will point you to
the human effect matrix,
not animal studies,
but human studies that
have explored these things.
Now, there are a huge variety of them here
so I won't go into all of them,
but some of the pro-estrogenic compounds
that have been shown to be powerful
in the context of menopause,
as well as other conditions
where estrogen is lower
than one would like,
include a description in
some of the literature,
I'll get into this in a moment,
of something like black cohosh,
I think that's the correct pronunciation,
it's literally the word
black and then C-O-H-O-S-H,
and it's very interesting,
there are 13 peer-reviewed studies
that have reached prominence
in the kind of commercial landscape
where this substance, black cohosh,
has been promoted as a
way to increase estrogen,
turns out that the effects are consistent
but are fairly minor,
fairly minor increases in estrogen,
so it does seem to be a real effect,
it is significant over the placebo effect,
but there's also a
significant placebo effect
in some of these studies as well,
so what's interesting when
you look at these studies
is that many of them were carried out
over a period of six-plus months,
they're double-blind studies, et cetera,
and almost all of them lead to
modest increases in estrogen
and modest decreases in
menopause-related symptoms.
Now, a few additional
details about these studies,
they were generally carried
out on women age 45 to 64,
in some cases, they look
specifically at women
that were clinically obese or overweight,
although not always,
the subject size pools are pretty big,
you know, anywhere from 50 to 87,
these are decent size,
132 subjects, et cetera,
so these look to be like quality studies,
and they basically point to
the fact that black cohosh
can have a modest effect in
improving menopause symptoms.
The other one is Panax ginseng,
so P-N-A-A-X ginseng,
has been shown to decrease some symptoms
associated with menopause,
mostly related to libido,
although the other
effects were unreliable.
Other things, like maca,
which is known to increase
dopamine actually,
had minor effects,
things like, the names here
are a little hard to
pronounce, so forgive me,
things like Valeriana officinalis
has shown that there
can be some improvement
in the hot flash symptoms
and some of the insomnia
associated with that,
so that might be worth exploring,
again, discuss with your doctor,
but these were both 100-subject plus,
age 45 to 64 individuals,
double-blind placebo-controlled studies
that showed significant
but modest effects.
There was one substance
in the gallery of the
compounds that was looked at
that turns out to be
particularly interesting,
and this one is also particularly
difficult to pronounce,
and it's Pueraria mirifica,
so I'm going to spell this out for you,
it's P-U-E-R-A-R-I-A, Pueraria,
mirifica, M-I-R-I-F-I-C-A,
and there are four
studies on this compound
that show, in every case,
it to be very potent,
in fact, comparable to estrogen therapy,
estrogen replacement therapy,
in reducing the symptoms of menopause,
so this was pretty striking
because when you go through these studies
and you look again
that they seem to be
pretty well controlled,
as far as I could tell,
and they explored a
pretty wide subject pool,
and it seems that every
single one of these studies,
when looking side by side
at Pueraria mirifica,
which is also called,
now this is really hard to
pronounce, Kwao Krua Kao,
I guess that's the name that
they use in various countries,
that it was comparable to
estrogen replacement therapy,
so I mentioned this because
a lot of people contacted me
and said, "What about the
insomnia in menopause?
"What about the headaches in menopause?"
Now, I'm not suggesting you run out
and immediately start taking
any of these compounds,
please talk to your doctor,
you know, any hormone-related compound
is a serious consideration
because of the relationship
to breast cancers,
but just in general, these compounds are,
estrogen and testosterone,
are exceedingly powerful
in terms of controlling our
mental and physical states,
and so you want to
approach them with caution,
but I thought that that one
in particular was interesting
and for which there are quite
a few PubMed-documented,
peer-reviewed studies in quality journals.
Okay, so now let's talk
about the role of specific compounds,
some of which, many of which can be taken
in supplementation form or
extracted from diet and nutrition
in order to optimize sex steroid hormones,
and again, I just want to emphasize
that I'm not suggesting
anyone take anything
or stop taking anything,
this is purely for informational purposes,
but some of the data on these
is quite striking and impressive.
It's very clear
that certain collections
of nutrients are useful
for promoting testosterone
and estrogen production
in their proper ratios,
and those things are what I would call
the sort of usual suspects,
vitamin D, which is important
for so many biological functions,
including endocrine functions,
zinc, magnesium, et cetera,
and if you want to look
into this more deeply
and you want to understand
exactly what the negative effects are
of not having sufficient
zinc and magnesium,
and what those levels might actually be,
there's a paper that's
available, you can go on PubMed,
I can't pronounce this
last name, I'm sorry,
it looks to me like Wrzosek,
but it's W-R-Z-O-S-E-K,
I hope I didn't butcher that
too badly, Wrzosek et al. 2020
in "Endocrinology and Metabolism Review,"
so this is a recent paper in
a good, peer-reviewed journal
that talks mainly about
how the
hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis
and the sex steroid hormones
are negatively impacted by
deficiencies in magnesium,
deficiencies in vitamin D,
and deficiencies in zinc,
however, that doesn't point to the levels
that one should take in order to optimize,
so it doesn't say take X amount of zinc
or X amount of magnesium
or X amount of vitamin D,
for that information,
because it's so context-dependent
and individual-dependent,
I highly recommend you go to examine.com,
you can put in zinc or
magnesium or vitamin D,
and they will give you ranges of dosages
that are supported by specific studies,
again, that information
is completely free to you,
and it's very useful in figuring that out.
I personally have supplemented
with zinc, magnesium,
and vitamin D for years,
but many other people do that as well,
and the question is always, how much?
And that's why I'm a proponent
of getting blood work done
because that's how you know
whether or not your androgen levels,
as well as things like
vitamin D levels, et cetera,
are sufficiently high,
so the takeaway from these studies
looking at what deficiencies cause
in terms of deficits in
testosterone and estrogen
really point in the direction of,
make sure you're getting
adequate zinc, magnesium, and D3
unless you want these steroid
hormone levels to be reduced
for whatever reason.
One of the things that's been
shown time and time again
to have very negative effects
on sex steroid hormones,
testosterone mainly men,
estrogen mainly in women,
is opioids.
There's this whole issue, of course,
of the opioid epidemic, it's
deserving of an entire episode,
we are going to talk about
that with experts in addiction
and people that treat pain and so forth,
but the opioids dramatically reduce
levels of testosterone and estrogen,
and they do that mainly by
disrupting the receptors
on gonadotropin-releasing hormone neurons,
these neurons within the hypothalamus
that communicate to the pituitary,
and in fact, people that take
large amounts of opioids,
or even take low levels of
opioids for long periods of time,
will develop all sorts
of endocrine syndromes,
that's been shown over and over again,
gynecomastia, or male
breast development in males,
disruptions to the ovary in females,
it's really a quite terrible situation,
so excessive opioids are very problematic
for sex steroid hormones,
I don't think anyone will have any trouble
finding any literature on that,
you can just go into PubMed,
you can put opioids, testosterone,
or opioids, estrogen,
but the major effect is actually
way up in the hypothalamus
to shut down the production of GnRH,
the very hormone that stimulates
testosterone and estrogen release.
Now, there's an entire
industry devoted to supplements
and various things that people can take
to increase testosterone,
some of which have scientific
data to support them,
some of which do not,
and some of which have anecdotal support
and some of which do not.
This ranges so broadly,
I mean, things like the
material off deer antlers,
which is high in, supposedly, IGF1,
which is in the growth hormone pathway,
all the way to actual
consumption of bull testes,
you can go on Amazon right now,
I certainly don't
suggest that you do this,
and you can actually buy
ground up testes from cows,
and you can consume those,
now, a lot of that's going
to be broken down in the gut,
I'm certainly not suggesting you do that,
but just the point out this
is a huge and vast literature,
and it actually dates
back hundreds of years
even though testosterone
wasn't discovered that long ago
as a specific hormone molecule
and characterized and then resynthesized,
it has a huge industry
because of the powerful
effects that it has,
likewise with estrogen,
the development of the birth control pill
was only made possible by
understanding the structure
of estrogen and estradiol,
and we're going to talk
all about birth control
and how it works and its influence
on various other pathways
in a future episode,
but there are these supplement compounds
that are supported by
the scientific literature
in terms of their ability
to adjust androgens,
things like testosterone
and dihydrotestosterone.
One of the ones that has
really good evidence for it is creatine,
it's very clear that
something about creatine,
although the mechanism
isn't exactly clear,
either increases 5-alpha reductase
or makes the testosterone
molecule more susceptible
to certain enzymatic reactions
that leads to increases in DHT,
DHT, dihydrotestosterone,
as I mentioned in the previous episode,
has this dramatic role in creating
a kind of masculinization
of the brain prenatally,
it also defines the
primary sex characteristic
of the growth of the penis, et cetera,
and beyond infancy and early
childhood and later in life,
it has powerful effects
in creating balding,
in beard growth, et cetera,
and it has a much higher affinity
for the androgen receptor
than does testosterone,
so creatine can increase DHT,
which means that if you take creatine
and you're very DHT-susceptible,
then you might experience some hair loss,
this has been heavily debated,
does creatine cause baldness?
It's going to depend,
it's going to depend on how
much 5-alpha reductase you have
and how prone to hair loss you are,
some people can take
creatine without any problem
in terms of hair loss,
some people cannot, they
start losing their hair
to levels that, at least for
them, aren't comfortable.
There are a few other things
that can increase testosterone
and it has to do with the way
that testosterone exists in
its free and its bound form,
so testosterone, the molecule
is kind of total testosterone,
that's usually what's measured,
this is the kind of levels that
are typically thrown around
of anywhere from 300 to 900
being the kind of natural range,
and then supraphysiological,
getting up into 1,200, 1,600 range,
but testosterone isn't
just roaming around free in the blood,
at least most of it isn't,
most of it is bound
to either sex hormone binding
globulin, SHBG, or to albumin,
they're needed as transporters
to get testosterone into cells
so that testosterone can have
its effects on gene expression
as well as other pathways
within the cells,
so people talk about that the
level of free testosterone
is really what's important
and that you want to
optimize free testosterone,
that's a little bit of a tricky statement,
that's kind of like, it's true,
and yet, it's not really reflective
of a thorough understanding
of how these binding globulins work,
remember, these binding globulins
aren't there to soak up
all your testosterone
just to make it hard for
you to free up testosterone
and you know, make gains in
the gym or whatever it is,
or have increases in libido,
they're there to actually
transport testosterone
to specific tissues, to shuttle
them to specific tissues
and to set the rate of bound
and unbound testosterone
so that's it's not all unbound at once,
and you know, it's always interesting
to look in the literature
and see how everyone wants
to free up their testosterone
so that it can work,
but sex hormone binding globulin
can bind up too much testosterone
to the point where it's having
negative effects on libido
or on muscle growth and fat
loss and things of that sort,
this is true in males and females,
or it can be doing exactly
what it's supposed to do,
which is shuttling testosterone
to the proper tissues and organs
where it has all these
effects, including the brain.
So there are supplements,
in particular, tongkat ali,
which is, it has this other name,
it's something called tongkat ali,
sometimes it's called,
and forgive me that
it's hard to pronounce,
but Eurycoma longifolia Jack,
they always seem to have these names
that kind of allude to
androgenic features,
like I don't know why, longifolia Jack,
I don't know, I think it's kind of obvious
why that sounds sort of androgenic.
This has been shown in several studies,
and you can find these on examine.com,
or you can go to PubMed if you
like, I've looked at these,
that it does seem to
have some pro-fertility,
pro-free testosterone, and
subtle aphrodisiac effects,
it does also seem to be
a slight anti-estrogen,
so the reports of this are,
people take this anywhere from
400 to 800 milligrams a day,
again, I'm not suggesting you do that,
but that's kind of what's out there,
and there is some decent
scientific literature
to support the fact that it liberates
some of the bound testosterone
and allows more free
testosterone to be available,
some of the reported
quote-unquote side effects
are things like excessive
alertness and insomnia
if it's taken too late
in the day and so forth,
but I encourage you to explore
that further if that's,
if increasing free testosterone
is something that you're
interested in doing.
Examine.com includes a lot of other things
that can increase testosterone,
one of the things that's been
purported to free up
testosterone in the blood
are things like nettles, stinging nettles,
although I should point
out that the literature
points to stinging nettle
also having some fairly potent effects
on the prostate and on the liver,
and so it might be a tricky molecule
and maybe not an attractive
one for people to take.
So we talked about creatine,
we talked about tongkat ali,
it's clear that boron,
which is really interesting,
believe it or not, I
think boron comes from,
I think these were like,
meteors that landed on Earth
and now they extract boron,
it's one of these crazy stories
that, when you look at it,
you go like, "How could that possibly be?"
but there's actually, that's how it works,
that boron, there's
some scientific support
for it freeing up more testosterone,
and again, freeing up testosterone
may be exactly what you want,
I just don't think that we should
demonize these carrier
proteins like albumin and SHBG,
in fact, albumin is very important
for testosterone to be able
to make it into the brain
to have some of the pro-androgenic effects
on the cognitive effects of testosterone
because in both males and females,
testosterone can shift these
behaviors, like mate-seeking,
reductions in anxiety, and so forth,
that we talked about before,
only by making it into the brain,
and there is this thing called
the blood-brain barrier,
which is fascinating
and deserving of an entire episode also,
and getting molecules across
the blood-brain barrier,
even if they're sex steroid
hormones, which are lipophilic
and can pass through cell
membranes, requires carriers,
and those carriers often are
bound to or include albumin,
and so it's not the goal to
free up all your testosterone,
but getting free testosterone into a range
that works for your
particular goals and needs
is an attractive one,
and that's why we're discussing
these particular tools.
The amounts of boron that people take,
and you can find this,
again, on PubMed or Examine,
but people take a couple
grams of it a day,
I'm not aware of any
specific side effects,
but you always, always,
always want to examine
for the particular side effects
and people with different
backgrounds and conditions,
as we talked about for
menopause and estrogen,
have to be careful
because when you're starting
to modulate hormones,
you're starting to modulate
not just the tissues
that thrive on binding of those hormones,
but remember, the reason why
there's so much breast cancer
and there's a reason why there's
so much testicular cancer
is that any tissue that
undergoes rapid reproduction
of particular cells,
so there's a lot of reproduction of cells
in shedding of uterine lining
and the reproduction of
cells and eggs in the ovary,
and in the testes, there's the production
of Leydig and sertoli cells,
and there's this kind of
ongoing production of sperm,
that's why those tissues
are particularly vulnerable
to the development of cancers,
and many of those cancers
are androgen-sensitive,
that's why one of the major treatments
for prostate overgrowth or prostate cancer
is to give anti-androgenic drugs, okay?
It's not just to shut down all things
related to being androgenized,
it's really about trying
to prevent testosterone
from encouraging growth of tumors,
so I want to really
emphasize the caution there
because it's easy when thinking
about optimizing estrogen and testosterone
to just think, oh, more is better,
more is definitely not better,
and it's not just because
they can aromatize
or convert into other things,
it's because cancers,
or any tissue that has a
lot of turnover of cells,
is going to thrive on androgen,
anything that promotes growth
is going to thrive on estrogen,
remember, brain tissue
doesn't turn over that much,
there isn't really much
production of new neurons,
brain cancers happen but
they're kind of rare,
and when they do happen,
they tend to be glial cells,
which have a lot of proliferation,
glial cells can proliferate,
adult neurons don't
create more of themselves,
they don't create more neurons,
in general, except in a few
places in the brain and body,
so any tissue that recycles
itself is prone to cancers,
and those tissues thrive
on androgens and estrogens
to create more tumor,
so you have to be careful
anytime you're modulating hormones,
especially androgens and estrogens,
and in my scouring of the literature
and looking at kind of what's out there
and what people are talking about,
and I also mean in the
scientific literature,
one of the things that
is new to me, anyway,
probably not new to a lot
of the gym rats out there,
or the people that spend a
lot of time on YouTube videos
talking about androgens,
are these, forgive me for
butchering the name again,
are these ecdysteroids,
so ecdysteroids are molecules
that come from things like
spinach, believe it or not,
that have a lot of similarity
to the cholesterol molecule,
the one that's being discussed
a lot out there right now
is something called turkesterone,
I wish I knew why it
was called turkesterone,
someone tell me why it's
called turkesterone,
does it have anything to do with turkeys?
I don't know why it's called turkesterone,
perhaps someone will know.
In any case, these ecdysteroids
are similar enough to cholesterol,
and remember, cholesterol is the precursor
to testosterone, cortisol, and estrogen,
and it appears that some
of these ecdysteroids
do have bioavailability,
or their metabolites are bioavailable,
and this was something
that, for many years,
people talked about whether
or not insect hormones
or hormones from other species
could actually be used by humans
or whether or not it would
have any effect at all,
and it's pretty clear based on a study
that I was able to find,
there's a paper that came out in 2019,
it's a comparative study in
the "Archives of Toxicology,"
this is Isenmann et al.,
I-S-E-N-M-A-N-N et al.,
that talks about the ecdysteroids
and it was given in conjunction
with strength training
or no strength training,
this was a 10-week intervention,
and their conclusion is
that these ecdysteroids
had a fairly significant,
above placebo controls,
increases in muscle mass,
strength, hypertrophy effects,
all the sorts of things
that one would expect
with increases in androgen,
their conclusion of this
study is not my conclusion,
although I may or may not agree with them,
this isn't about my opinions,
it's just, I want to be clear,
these are their words, not mine,
but they say that, in their words,
quote, "Our results strongly suggest
"the inclusion of ecdysteroid
"in the list of prohibited substances."
So they're saying these
things are so powerful
that they should be on the
list of banned substances,
which might be upsetting to some,
or some of you might be
thinking, well, who cares?
The whole issue of
augmenting hormones in sports
is a very interesting issue,
in fact, if you just want a
little anecdote about that,
I can't reveal names here, of course,
but what I learned recently
was very surprising to me
which is that many athletes in pro sports
are taking testosterone,
and they are able to do that legally
not just because it's
available by prescription,
but they are allowed to do that
under the rules of their sport
in the fine print that no one,
including me, had ever seen,
if they've had an injury,
so if athletes are injured,
then it opens up the door
for certain forms of
testosterone augmentation
and other types of augmentations
that are not available to
them if they're not injured,
which always makes me wonder now
when I see them getting injured
whether or not that's an attempt
to get some of the support
because there's absolutely no question
that estrogens and testosterones
modulate gene expression,
modulate strength, modulate
the way the brain works,
modulates our relationship to
effort and anxiety, et cetera,
and while we're talking
about supplementation,
the effects of supplementation,
I would say, in some individuals
can be quite dramatic,
but they're always, always, always,
except in extreme cases,
going to be far subtler,
excuse me, far more subtle,
to use the proper English,
far more subtle than would be,
for instance, just in
injecting testosterone
or injecting estrogen, et cetera,
so I think we should just be
honest and upfront about that.
So thus far in terms of talking
about optimizing hormones
and in the discussion of supplementation,
I haven't really talked about things
that actually affect the brain directly,
that increase the pituitary
output and things of that sort,
we've mainly been talking about things
that free up testosterone
or that increase estrogen
at the level of the periphery,
but if you remember way back
to the beginning of this episode,
hormones are made in different
locations in the body
and there are hormones
that promote the release and
the production of hormones
from other tissues in the body,
and one of the main hormones for that
is luteinizing hormone,
luteinizing hormone, again,
comes from the pituitary,
circulates and either goes to the ovary
to promote various
aspects of egg maturation
as well as production of estrogen,
and to the testes to promote
testosterone and sperm production,
and the prescription version
of increasing luteinizing hormone
is something called hCG, or
human chorionic gonadotropin,
which has been synthesized
and is now available
as a prescription drug,
it's taken in various contexts
for increasing fertility
both by males and by females,
it can increase, for all the
reasons that now make sense,
it can increase sperm production,
it can produce ovulation frequency,
it can produce the number of eggs, even,
that are deployed in a given ovulation,
although that's not always a good thing,
it basically is pro-fertility,
pro-testosterone, pro-estrogen
depending on your background,
and what's interesting is
hCG was initially synthesized,
collected and synthesized
from pregnant women's urine,
and believe it or not, before
it was synthetically made
and sold as a prescription drug,
there was actually a black
market for pregnant women's urine
where people would buy the urine,
I don't know, I'm guessing
that they probably
just consumed it, which is weird,
but in any case, human
chorionic gonadotropin
is now available as a prescription drug
and it's one of the things
that many people use
to increase testosterone or estrogen
for increasing fertility,
in some cases I think it's used
to increase sports performance
or when people have shut down their gonads
for whatever reason because
of excessive hormone therapies
or they have some sort of,
sometimes there are actually
lesions to the pituitary,
sometimes people have a
tumor in the pituitary,
it's actually not common,
but among brain tumors and neural tumors,
it's one of the more common ones,
and then you get
deficiencies in LH and FSH,
and so people will take hCG
to stimulate the gonads,
so there are a variety of reasons
why these drugs were created,
but there are certain
supplements, not many,
that apparently can
increase luteinizing hormone
and thereby can increase
testosterone and estrogen,
and one of the more well-documented
one is Fadogia agrestis,
that's F-A-D-O-G-I-A,
separate word, A-G-R-E-S-T-I-S,
which, at least according
to the literature
that I was able to find,
can increase levels of luteinizing hormone
and thereby levels of testosterone
or levels of estrogen,
and again, if an individual
were to take Fadogia agrestis,
what they would probably find
is that testosterone and
estrogen would increase
in anyone of any chromosomal
or gonadal background,
but remember, it's the ratio of both,
if someone has low estrogen
and high testosterone,
let's say they have testes
just by way of example,
then both of those would
be expected to increase,
and if someone has high
estrogen and low testosterone,
and let's just say has ovaries,
then both of those would increase
by taking Fadogia agrestis.
The side effect profile
of Fadogia agrestis
hasn't really been documented,
so it's a little unclear,
I just want to emphasize
that anytime someone's going
to start taking supplements,
or modifying sex steroid hormones,
getting blood work done
is extremely important
for safety reasons,
and also just to know whether
or not things are working,
and because all of these things
are subject to negative feedback,
talked about this previously
on a previous episode,
but if testosterone
goes high, or too high,
it can feed back and shut
down luteinizing hormone,
which will then shut down
further testosterone production,
likewise, if estrogens are going too high
or they're going too high at
various phases of the cycle,
that can start to throw
off various other hormones,
including FSH, progesterone, LH,
the menstrual cycle itself
is a just absolutely exquisite balance
of feedback of luteinizing
hormone kept low and constant,
at least for the first
14 days of the cycle,
then mid cycle, there's a peak,
and that's typically
when ovulation occurs,
that's why pregnancy is most likely
during the middle of the 28-day cycle,
FSH kind of goes up and then
down across the first 14 days,
so taking anything or really modifying
one's estrogens or testosterone
on that background of the menstrual cycle
is really going to disrupt
the way those things interact,
and it's just such an
exquisite feedback loop,
so I'm not saying don't do that,
but you definitely want to be
aware of what you're doing,
and blood draws are one way to do that,
monitoring cycles for ovulating females
is another way to do that,
and in males, having a good window
into what's going on
with testosterone, DHT,
aromatase, estradiol, LH, et cetera,
is just vital,
and it's really part and
parcel with the practice
of thinking about optimizing
these incredible things
that we call sex steroid hormones,
estrogen and testosterone
and their derivatives.
The list of supplements and molecules
that can adjust estrogen
and testosterone is vast,
and I only touched on a few of these,
I really tried to emphasize the ones
for which there are human studies
or that have mostly human studies,
or maybe even just one human study,
there are other things out there
for which there are scientific data,
things like Bulbine natalensis,
which definitely has support
for increasing testosterone
but all the studies were in rats,
I think there is some evidence in humans
but the evidence mainly comes in the form
of what we call sponsored research,
so companies paying for research,
which is different than
independent research
by people who are not biased
in terms of the outcome,
and the reason I didn't
throw out things like Bulbine natalensis
is they seem to have liver toxicity
similar to high levels of
anabolic exogenous steroids,
there's some problems associated with them
that make them, you know,
important to think about
if you're curious about this
area and the endocrinology,
but also somewhat precarious,
and you know, that's one category,
so stuff that doesn't have
a lot of evidence in humans,
might actually be dangerous,
the other category of things
that has been shown to improve levels of,
or increase, I should say,
I don't want to say improve
because it's up to you whether or not
you want to increase or decrease
estrogen and testosterone,
that's highly individual,
how could I know,
are the things that are
kind of housekeeping
for production of
estrogen and testosterone,
things like magnesium, things
like D3, things like zinc,
you know, those are the things
that are going to create an overall milieu
of opportunity to produce
normal endogenous levels
rather than increasing
endogenous levels further,
and so I really want to highlight
that there's a difference
between taking something
to create a kind of
backdrop of general support
and taking something that's
going to create a big inflection
in the levels of a given hormone.
So once again, we covered
a tremendous amount of information,
we covered some basic science
of hormones and pheromones,
estrogen and testosterone
and their derivatives,
we talked about
supplementation and behaviors,
competition and parenting,
and how all these things interact,
and I hope that you'll come away from this
with a deeper mechanistic understanding
of how the brain and body are interacting
to control the output
and the ways in which
these incredible things
that we call sex steroid
hormones work and influence us,
I hope you'll also come
away with some ideas
of things that you can do,
in particular, behavioral
practices that can improve sleep
and your relationship to light, et cetera,
because those things
really set the foundation
not just for healthy
steroid hormone output,
but for all sorts of health effects
and for both the
psychology and the biology
of your nervous system,
so I'm sure there'll be many questions,
there are many things that
I couldn't get to today,
I do try and limit these
episodes to about 90 minutes,
which is the optimal
ultradian cycle for learning,
it's a lot of information,
but we've timestamped everything for you,
so feel free to look over it in parts
or circle back where you might
want deeper understanding,
and please put your questions
in the comments section below,
please put suggestions for future episodes
and things that relate to hormones
in the comments section
below, we do look at those
and we do use them to inform the content
for subsequent episodes.
If you're enjoying and
learning from this podcast,
please subscribe on YouTube,
or if you prefer, please
subscribe on Apple and/or Spotify.
At Apple, you have the opportunity
also to leave us up to a five-star review
and to leave a comment
in the review section.
Please also inform your
friends, family, coworkers,
anyone that you think might also benefit
from the information that we're covering,
that really helps us grow our audience
and bring more information to you.
As well, please check out our sponsors
mentioned at the
beginning of each episode,
and we also have a Patreon,
that's patreon.com/andrewhuberman.
At the Patreon, you can
help support the podcast
at any level that you like.
As well, we've partnered
with Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E,
which is a supplement company,
the reason we partner with Thorne
is that they have the
highest levels of stringency
in terms of the quality of
the supplements that they make
and the quantity of the
individual ingredients,
something that's not always the case
with various supplement companies,
but Thorne is exquisitely good
about the stringency of their products,
they partner with the Mayo Clinic
and all the major sports teams.
If you want to check out Thorne
and see the supplements that I take,
you can go to thorne.com/u/huberman,
and if you do that, you can
see the supplements I take,
but as well, it will
allow you to get 20% off
any of those supplements
or any of the other
supplements that Thorne makes,
that's Thorne, T-H-O-R-N-E,
.com/u/huberman
to get 20% off any Thorne supplements.
In closing, I hope you'll
leave today's episode
with a much richer
understanding of the mechanisms
that control the endocrine
and nervous system
in the context of
estrogen and testosterone,
as well as take away various tools
that you might choose to apply,
and next week, we'll be
back with another episode
about the role of hormones
and its important interactions
with the nervous system,
and that will, of course,
include both mechanisms and tools as well,
and as always, thank you for
your interest in science.
[upbeat music]