- [Andrew Huberman] Welcome
to the Huberman Lab Podcast
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
[upbeat music]
- I'm Andrew Huberman, and I'm
a professor of neurobiology
and ophthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine.
This podcast is separate
from my teaching and
research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of
my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer
information about science
and science related tools
to the general public.
In keeping with that theme
I'd like to thank the
sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a
personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and reach your health goals.
I've long been a fan of doing blood tests
and more recently as they've
been developed also DNA tests.
And the reason for that is
that so many of the factors
that impact our immediate
and longterm health
and that inform our health choices
can only be analyzed by
way of blood or DNA tests.
The great thing about InsideTracker
is they make getting the blood
and DNA test extremely easy.
They'll come to your home if you like,
or you can go to a place where you can
get your blood drawn and
your DNA swab taken there.
As well once you get the information back
from InsideTracker, it's
very easy to understand
what to do with that information,
how to interpret it.
And that's really what
sets InsideTracker apart
I believe from other blood and DNA
testing tools and companies.
Most sources and companies
will give you information back
about what your levels of hormones are,
and metabolic factors, et cetera,
but no clear directives about what to do
with that information to get those markers
in the ranges that you want
in order to optimize your health.
InsideTracker makes that all very easy.
It gives you directives about exercise,
about nutrition,
about various supplements you
may or may not want to take.
And once again, only
through blood and DNA tests
can you access that information?
If you want to try InsideTracker
you can visit insidetracker.com/huberman
And if you do that
you'll get 25% off any
of InsideTracker plans.
That's insidetracker.com/huberman
to get 25% off
and enter Huberman at checkout.
Today's episode is also brought
to us by Athletic Greens.
Athletic Greens is an all-in-one
vitamin mineral probiotic drink.
I've been taking Athletic
Greens since 2012.
And so I'm delighted that
they're sponsoring the podcast.
I started taking Athletic Greens
and I still take Athletic
Greens once or twice a day
because it covers all my
nutritional, vitamin, mineral
and probiotic basis.
Of course, you can get
vitamins, and minerals,
and probiotics from food,
but many of us including
me find it hard to do that
on a consistent basis.
Especially when I'm working a lot,
when stress and sleep
aren't optimized, et cetera.
With Athletic Greens
I make sure to get all the things I need
and then all the other
supplements I take or what I eat
I can consider additional insurance.
The great thing about Athletic
Greens is it tastes great.
I like to mix mine with water
and a little bit of lemon juice.
I take it once early in the day
and then sometimes again in the afternoon.
The fact that it includes probiotics
is really important to me.
There are so many data
now pointing to the fact
that probiotics and gut brain health,
and gut health generally are
very important for metabolism,
for hormone output, for
neurotransmitter production,
so many vital things
related to our health,
Athletic Greens makes it easy to make sure
that I'm getting everything that I need
in the vitamin mineral
and probiotic department.
If you'd like to try Athletic Greens,
you can go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and claim a special offer.
They'll give you five free travel packs,
plus a year supply of
vitamin D three K two.
There's now a ton of data as well,
pointing to the fact that
vitamin D three and K2
are important for a huge number
of health related factors,
including hormones, metabolic factors,
neuro-transmitters et cetera.
So they have the year
supply of vitamin D three
completely free along with
your Athletic Greens offer,
and you get the five free travel packs.
So if you'd like to try that
you go to athleticgreens.com/huberman
and claim this special offer.
Today's episode is also
brought to us by Headspace.
Headspace is a meditation app
that makes meditation easy.
I started meditating many years ago,
but I found it was
difficult to stay consistent
with my meditation practice.
In fact when I would get
stressed or really busy
that's when I probably needed
the meditation practice the most.
And that's when I tended to
drop the meditation practice
and run around doing other things.
So it was really a kind of catch 22.
I learned about Headspace a few years ago
on Jet Blue Flights when
they had them included
as an option of whether
or not to watch a movie,
or a television show, or do meditation.
I tried the meditation
and I really liked it.
Very easy to follow along
with a Headspace meditation.
The meditations that they
include on the Headspace app,
are also backed by dozens of peer reviewed
quality independent studies.
And of course there are now thousands
of peer reviewed quality studies
pointing to the fact that
a meditation practice
is beneficial for sake of improved sleep,
for reducing stress,
and a number of other health metrics,
cardiovascular disease, risk, et cetera.
The great thing about Headspace
is it's allowed me to
stay really consistent
with my meditation practice.
They have meditations
of different duration
and different type, so
you never get bored.
I actually look forward
to my meditation practice
and it continues to benefit me.
In fact, since starting Headspace,
I've been consistent with
meditation for much longer
than I ever had previously.
If you want to try Headspace
you can go to headspace.com/specialoffer
and you'll get a free one month trial
with Headspace's full
library of meditations
for every situation.
That's headspace.com/specialoffer
to get one month free trial,
that's their best offer
out there right now.
And then you can try their
full library of meditations
for every situation.
Today, we're going to continue
our discussion about hormones
and we're going to focus
on how particular hormones
influence our energy levels
and our immune system.
Now, last episode I mentioned at the end
that we were concluding
our month on hormones,
but we decide to include
this additional episodes,
so this would be the fifth episode
in the sequence of
episodes about hormones.
Because there are two hormones
which are vitally important
for a huge number of biological functions
that we will talk about today,
but that are particularly
important for energy levels
and your immune system.
This is something that
I get asked about a lot.
So rather than skip to
the next general topic,
today we're going to
talk about the hormones
cortisol and epinephrine
also called adrenaline.
You do not have to have heard
the previous episodes on hormones
in order to understand
and digest the material
from today's podcast.
If I mentioned anything
related to previous episodes,
I promise to give a little
bit of quick background
to get everyone up to speed.
Today, we're going to talk
about the biology of cortisol.
We're going to talk about
the biology of epinephrine.
As always we'll talk mechanism
and there are going to be a lot of tools.
If you're somebody who
struggles with stress
and energy levels,
and balancing stress and energy levels,
today's episode is going
to be vital for you.
If you're somebody who
has challenges with sleep
or you're somebody who has challenges
getting your energy level
up throughout the day,
and getting your energy level
down when you want to sleep
today's episode is also for you.
And we're going to talk
about the immune system
and how to enhance the
function of your immune system.
We're also going to get
into some fun topics
related to learning and memory
and how you can leverage cortisol
and epinephrine in particular,
in order to learn faster.
we're going to talk about
so-called nootropics,
smart drugs and how they work,
because there's several of them
that tap into the epinephrine system
that aren't often discussed
and that you have access to.
We're going to talk about how caffeine
can actually rewire your
brain for better or for worse.
And we're going to talk about
the biology of comfort foods
and why they work so well,
and what they're doing.
And in understanding that
you'll be able to better
understand your food choices
as they relate to short-term
and long-term energy.
So we have a lot to cover,
everything will be timestamped.
I want to just remind people
that we caption every episode
in English and in Spanish.
The captions take a day or
two to pop up on YouTube.
So if you're not seeing those
within the first couple of days,
please be patient with us,
in order to get captions
that actually read
similarly to what I'm saying.
we go through a captioning service,
and so we have them done by experts
and that takes a little
bit of additional time.
Meanwhile if you have any questions
as the episode evolves
please write them down.
Please put them in the comment section.
Please subscribe to the
channel if you haven't already,
and let's get started talking about
how to increase your energy,
and improve and increase your immunity
by leveraging the biology
of cortisol and adrenaline.
Before we dive into the biology
of increasing energy
and your immune system,
I want to cover three topics
that I promised I would
mention from previous episodes.
The first one relates
to intermittent fasting.
The second one relates to
why your stomach grumbles.
I forgot to mention the
biology of that last time.
And the third is a powerful
way to increase growth hormone,
which is powerful for
increasing metabolism,
fat burning, and tissue repair, et cetera.
That doesn't involve a sauna
or wrapping yourself in plastic bags
and going for a jog.
So first intermittent fasting.
Last episode I talked a
lot about growth hormone
and thyroid hormone,
and I mentioned things like
sauna and exercise, and sleep,
and how they can increase
levels of growth hormone
within the healthy ranges.
And why increasing growth
hormone can be very beneficial
because it can burn off body fat,
it can improve muscle and
general tissue health,
cartilage, et cetera.
And we tend to lose,
or our levels of growth
hormone are reduced as we age.
Many people asked me,
"well, what about fasting?"
Everyone's been promised on the internet
that intermittent fasting
leads to these big
increases in growth hormone.
The reason I didn't mention it
is that I couldn't find a study
that actually pointed to
the underlying mechanism.
I saw lots of claims, lots of podcasts.
Lots of degrees behind people's names,
sometimes biologists,
sometimes entirely different
fields talking about this,
but very few studies.
And then I found what I
would consider the study.
We will link to this study.
Turns out that fasting does
increase growth hormone levels
and the way that it
does it is fascinating.
I mentioned in a previous podcast
about hunger and timing of
meals and timing of hunger,
that when you're hungry
you release a hormone in
your body called ghrelin,
sometimes actually called ghrelin.
Thanks for all of you
ghrelinisters, or ghrelinisters
that corrected my pronunciation,
it's both ghrelin or
ghrelin, either one works.
Ghrelin makes you hungry,
when blood glucose,
your blood sugar is low,
ghrelin is secreted and makes you hungry.
And it turns out that ghrelin,
this hunger hormone actually binds
to the receptor in the brain
that normally binds what's called
growth hormone releasing hormone.
So believe it or not the hunger hormone
can act like growth
hormone releasing hormone
and thereby stimulate growth hormone.
Now the levels of growth hormone
that fasting promotes
through this ghrelin system
are pretty substantial.
It's about a doubling
of growth hormone levels
in the waking state.
So we know that you can release
growth hormone in sleep,
intermittent fasting it turns out
can increase growth hormone
by binding ghrelin to the growth hormone,
releasing hormone receptor
and it does it also during the daytime.
So yes indeed fasting can
increase growth hormone,
not to the super levels
that taking growth
hormone would increase it,
or that a sauna could increase it,
but it does seem to
increase growth hormone.
Later in today's episode
we're going to talk a lot about
different patterns of fasting and eating
that can control epinephrine.
And so we will turn to
specifics about how long a fast.
Do you need to fast for two
or three days, or 23 hours?
Fortunately for people
like me who love to eat,
that's not the case.
So we'll talk specific fasting protocols
later in the episode.
We also said, we're going
to talk about tummy grumble,
when your stomach growls
it is not because of fluid
sifting around in there.
A lot of people think,
Oh, you know it's fluid sifting around.
Turns out that your stomach
has smooth muscle that lines it sides
and when you eat something or you don't
every once in a while
your stomach cinches off
at the two ends like a bag
with a hose on either end,
'cause that's essentially
what your digestive system is.
And if there's nothing
in there what happens is
the muscles that line
the sides of your stomach
they kind of extend around the stomach
and these cables,
those are always there and if
you have food in your stomach,
what they do is they churn your stomach.
They literally turn the
muscles of your stomach
like a tumbler to help break up the food
that presumably you
didn't chew well enough
'cause you were eating too fast.
When you don't have any
food in your stomach
that churning continues.
And that contraction of the muscle,
the turning, literally
turning over of your muscles
they don't flip over completely,
but the turning over the muscles,
that's what causes the stomach growling.
If you don't want to be
the person in the meeting,
or sitting there at a in a quiet theater
whose stomach is growling,
chew your food better.
That's the simple solution.
And last episode, I talked
a lot about how sauna,
controlled safe hyperthermia
can cause huge increases
in growth hormone release
anywhere from 300 to 500,
even 1600% increases in
growth hormone release.
Really staggeringly high increases.
I pointed out that many people
don't have saunas in their
yard or in their homes,
and they would go through
some other measures
to increase safely their body heat.
You know, creating a steam
room in their bathroom,
or jogging with extra sweats
on this kind of thing.
Many of you asked about hot baths,
hot bags will increase growth hormone,
however the temperatures that you need
in order to increase growth hormone
are high enough that you
run the risk of burn.
And so I really can't
make any recommendations
about hot bath,
but if you can tolerate a nice hot bath
you are going to get some
growth hormone release.
However, the sauna has this advantage of
you being able to enter 175 degree,
or 200 degree environment,
provided you're not pregnant,
you're not a young child, et cetera.
You can do that safely.
And getting big increases
in growth hormone.
The hot bath will lead to
lesser increases in growth hormone.
We're going to talk a lot about
temperature regulation
in a future episode,
but as always if you're ever going to
start playing with
hyperthermia or hypothermia,
cold baths, ice baths,
hot showers, hot baths
that are beyond the kind of
norm of what's comfortable,
you have to be extremely careful
and please consult a doctor.
I think it's fair to say
that most people would like to have
a lot of energy during the day,
if you work during the day.
And they'd like their energy
to taper off at night.
And I think it's fair to say
that most people don't enjoy being sick.
Nobody wants to get sick.
In other words, you want to have energy,
and you want your immune
system to function well,
to ward off infections of various kinds,
bacterial infections, viral
infections, et cetera.
And it turns out that the two hormones
that dominate those processes
of having enough energy and
having a healthy immune system
are cortisol and epinephrine.
Epinephrine is the same
thing as adrenaline.
In the body we tend to
call adrenaline adrenaline,
and in the brain we tend to
call adrenaline epinephrine.
And I'm sorry for that
I didn't create this naming system.
And the story behind it is uninteresting
and not worth our time.
I will use the words
adrenaline and epinephrine
interchangeably today.
Cortisol is cortisol.
And I just want to
cover a little bit about
what cortisol and epinephrine are?
Where they are released
in the body and brain?
Because if you can understand that
you will understand better
how to control them.
First of all, cortisol
is a steroid hormone
much like estrogen and testosterone
in that it is derived from cholesterol.
Now that could be
cholesterol that you eat,
it could be cholesterol
that's produced by the liver.
As many of you probably know
the relationship between
dietary cholesterol,
the fats that you eat
and blood cholesterol,
and liver cholesterol is
a very controversial one.
It's a barbed wire topic.
There are people that claim
that dietary cholesterol has zero impact
on circulating cholesterol
coming from the liver,
and there are people who
argue the exact opposite,
both with good data in hand I would say.
There are some problems for the idea
that all your cholesterol levels
are determined by dietary intake.
Namely, that anorexics
often have very high levels of cholesterol
that their liver produces,
even though they are eating very little
and sometimes not eating at all.
So understand that cholesterol
is a precursor molecule,
meaning it's the substrate
from which a lot of things
like testosterone and estrogen are made.
Please also understand that cholesterol
can be made into estrogen,
or testosterone, or cortisol.
And that cortisol is sort
of the competitive partner
to estrogen and testosterone.
What this means is,
no matter how much cholesterol
you're eating or you produce,
whether or not it's low or it's high,
if you are stressed
more of that cholesterol
is going to be devoted
toward creating cortisol,
which is indeed a stress hormone.
However, the word stress
shouldn't stress you out,
because you need cortisol,
cortisol is vital.
You don't want your cortisol
levels to be too low.
It's very important for
immune system function,
for memory, for not getting depressed.
You just don't want your
cortisol levels to be too high
and you don't want them to be elevated
even to normal levels at
the wrong time of day.
So we're going to talk how to control
the timing and level of your cortisol.
Epinephrine or adrenaline has
also been demonized a bit.
We think of it as the stress hormone,
this thing that makes us
anxious, fight or flight.
You know, we used to get chased by lions
and tigers, and bears, and now we don't.
and it's this ancient
hangover, that's all wrong.
The fact of the matter is the epinephrine
is your best friend when
it comes to your immunity,
when it comes to protecting
you from infection.
And we're going to talk about why,
and epinephrine adrenaline
is your best friend
when it comes to remembering things
and learning and
activating neuroplasticity.
We're going to talk about that as well.
Once again, it's a question
of how much and how long
and the specific timing of release
of cortisol and epinephrine,
as opposed to cortisol and
adrenaline being good or bad.
They're terrific when they're regulated,
they are terrible when
they're misregulated.
And we will give you lots of
tools to regulate them better.
Cortisol biology 101 in
less than two minutes.
Your brain makes what we
call releasing hormones
and in this case, there's
corticotropin releasing hormone.
CRH is made by neurons in your brain,
it causes the pituitary,
this gland that sits about
an inch in front of the roof of your mouth
and the base of your
brain to release ACTH.
ACTH then goes and causes your adrenals,
which sit above your
kidneys in your lower back
to release cortisol.
A so-called stress hormone,
but I would like you
to think about cortisol
not as a stress hormone
but as a hormone of energy.
It produces a situation
in the brain and body
whereby you want to move,
and whereby you don't want to rest,
and whereby you don't want
to eat at least at first.
Epinephrine or adrenaline
101 in less than two minutes.
When you sense a stressor with your mind
or your body senses a stressor
from a wound or something of that sort.
A signal is sent to neurons
that are in the middle of your body.
They are called the
sympathetic chain ganglia.
The name doesn't necessarily matter.
They release Norepinephrine very quickly.
It's almost like a sprinkler system
that just hoses your
body with epinephrine.
That will increase heart rate,
will increase breathing rate.
In some cases it will
constrict your blood vessels,
it will also increase the
size of vessels and arteries
that are giving blood
flow to your vital organs.
This is why your extremities
get cold when you're stressed
and your heart is beating faster.
More of that energy is being
devoted toward your core.
You also release adrenaline
from your adrenals,
again riding on top of your kidneys.
Those are second system
whereby your system gets flooded
with adrenaline in pulses.
So you can get one pulse,
you can get 10 pulses.
We'll talk about how to
regulate the number of pulses
and you release it from
an area of your brain
called locus coeruleus,
and that creates alertness in your brain.
If you want to learn more
about the stress response
and all the details of that,
including some protocols
of how to regulate stress
please see our episode about stress.
I go into a lot of detail there.
I will touch on some of
the same themes today,
but I really want to cover
energy and the immune system.
And if you're very much interested
in stress per say and stress regulation,
please see the episode on stress.
Okay. So we have cortisol
and we have epinephrine,
and their net effect
is to increase energy.
So first of all, I want to give you a tool
that will help you regulate cortisol
and can also help stave off
certain patterns of mental illness.
Now of course it's not going to
cure mental illness on its own,
but it can support healthy state of mind,
and can help reduce
unhealthy states of mind,
including depression.
So the first tool is to make sure
that your highest levels of cortisol
are first thing in the
morning when you wake up.
One way or another every 24 hours
you will get an increase in cortisol.
That is non-negotiable that
is written into your genome.
That increasing cortisol
is there to wake you up
and to make you alert,
it's to stimulate
movement from being sleep,
presumably horizontal,
to getting up and starting
to move about your day.
And I've said it before,
but I will say it again
the best way to stimulate that
increase in cortisol
at the appropriate time
is that very soon after waking
within 30 minutes or so after waking,
get outside view some sunlight,
even if it's overcast,
get outside view some
sunlight, no sunglasses.
Never look at any light so bright
that it could damage your eyes,
but do that for two to 10 minutes.
If it's very bright two minutes,
if it's not so bright 10 minutes.
Do that, because in the
early part of the day
you have the opportunity to
time that cortisol release
to the early part of the day,
which will improve,
this has been backed by
peer reviewed studies,
it will improve your focus,
it will improve your energy levels,
and it will improve your
learning throughout the day.
It will also prevent a late
shift in cortisol increase.
And late shifted cortisol,
meaning cortisol that increases
around 8:00 or 9:00 PM
is a signature feature of
many depressive disorders,
including major depression, anxiety.
And that of course correlates
with things like insomnia, et cetera.
So that's a key tool,
and I don't know how many of
you are already doing that,
but it is vital to do.
Now I mentioned sunlight
even on cloudy days
and there are specific reasons for that.
So I want to just briefly cover the data
because in the episodes on sleep,
I talked about brightness of light
in regulating cortisol and sleep.
And I talked about how to
measure lux, brightness,
but I was not specific enough I realized
based on the questions that I've received
since that episode.
So here's how it works,
going outside and getting some sunlight
requires that I also tell you how long
and under what conditions.
I've said looking through
a window is not as good,
it takes 50 times longer
to get as much light,
et cetera, et cetera.
Many, many questions have told me
that I'm not being specific enough.
So I'm going to give you the data
and from the data you will understand
exactly how long you
need to do this each day.
On a sunny day, so no cloud cover,
provided that the sun is not yet overhead.
It's somewhere low in the sky
could have just crossed the horizon,
or if you wake up a little bit later
it could be somewhat low in the sky.
Basically the intensity
of light, the brightness,
is somewhere around 100,000 Lux.
Lux is just a measurement of brightness.
If you want to download
the app Light Meter,
that is a free app that
will allow you to do that.
You can hold your finger down
on the little button there
and you can move it around,
and it will continuously
give you a Lux read out.
It's not perfect, it's not
exact, but it's pretty good.
and it is zero cost.
I have no relationship to
Light Meter the company.
On a cloudy day it's about 10,000 Lux.
Okay. So tenfold reduction.
But bright artificial light,
very bright artificial light
is somewhere around 1000 lux.
And ordinary room light is
somewhere around 100-200 lux.
And it has to do with how
much light scatter there is.
So even if you have a very bright bulb
sitting right next to you,
that's not going to do the job.
Your phone will not do the
job not early in the day
to get the cortisol released
at the appropriate time
you need to get outside.
So let's just set a
couple general parameters.
If it's bright outside and no cloud cover
that light can be indirect.
You don't have to be staring into the sun,
please don't damage your eyes.
We can't regenerate those neurons yet
and restore vision that's lost,
but if you have to blink,
that means it's too bright.
It's fine to blink of course,
please do if you need to.
Get outside for 10 minutes,
or five minutes should suffice,
but 10 minutes is sure to suffice.
If it's a cloudy day, dense overcast,
you're probably going to
need about 30 minutes.
If it's light cloud broken cloud cover
it's probably going to be somewhere
between 10 and 20 minutes.
And if you can't get outside
or you're on an airplane
and it's bright overhead,
artificial lights or ordinary room lights
it's going to take you
about six hours of light.
And by time you reach the middle of your
sort of wakeful period, it's too late.
You won't be able to shift your clock
and your cortisol will start
drifting later and later.
This is why it's vital to get
this light on a regular basis,
to get that cortisol
released early in the day.
That sets you up for
optimal levels of energy,
it sets you up for great sleep.
But today's not really about sleep
it's more about energy that cortisol pulse
and the stress that you
might feel early in the day
from having a little bit extra energy.
That is the energy that you want
in order to move about and
learn, and do various things.
That is a healthy level of energy.
So please try and get that sunlight.
If it's within your protocols to do that,
and try and get sufficient sunlight
first thing in the morning,
again within the first hour.
That's the best way to make sure
that you time your cortisol appropriately.
Now throughout the day
you're going to experience
different things.
Most of you are not
spending your entire day
trying to optimize your health.
Some of you might be,
but most of you have jobs
and you have families,
and you have commitments.
Life enters the picture
and provides you stressors,
and those stressors, whatever
they may happen to be,
a difficult coworker,
some disappointment about something,
you didn't get the raise you expected,
or you didn't get the
vacation that you expected.
Those will cause increases
in cortisol and epinephrine.
This is important to understand,
you don't have the luxury
of just having this morning cortisol
and then having a taper off.
You want that major
cortisol early in the day
but then you can expect,
you should expect increases
in cortisol and adrenaline
throughout the day
based on events that
are unpleasant to you.
So for me, the events that
are most unpleasant to me
are things like traffic,
emails that ask me to fill out a form
for which I can't find the link.
These kinds of things stress me out,
I'm a human being.
I don't lose my cool over them
but I can feel my level of alertness
and kind of frustration increased.
The normal kind of things
that go with stress
tense up a little bit.
The key is these blips in
cortisol and epinephrine
need to be brief.
You can't have them so
often or lasting so long
that you are in a state of
chronic cortisol elevation
or chronic epinephrine elevation.
This system of stress was designed
to increase your alertness and
mobilize you towards things,
get you frustrated,
and provide the opportunity
to change behavior.
That's what they were designed to do.
So if you find yourself getting stressed
and staying stressed,
there are great tools that we
provide in the stress episode
that relate to things like
the double inhale exhale,
the so-called physiological sigh.
You can incorporate NSDR,
in non sleep deep rest
protocol, et cetera.
But understand that the energy
that you experienced during stress,
that sudden increase in
alertness and attention
that comes from seeing
something difficult.
That is a healthy hormonal system
and neural system that's working.
And the reason it works is that cortisol
when it's released into the bloodstream
it actually can bind to
receptors in the brain.
It can bind receptors in the amygdala,
fear centers and threat detection centers,
but also areas of the
brain that are involved
in learning, and memory,
and neuroplasticity.
And this is why I say
that neuroplasticity,
the brain's ability to change itself
in response to experience
is first stimulated by attention and focus
and often a low-level state of agitation.
So understand that,
and you won't be quite so troubled about
the little stress increases
that you experience throughout the day.
Now, there are ways to leverage stress,
epinephrine and cortisol
in ways that serve you
and to do it in a deliberate way.
There are also ways to do that
that increase your level
of stress threshold,
meaning they make it less likely
that epinephrine and
cortisol will be released.
So I want to talk about the
science of those practices,
'cause I get asked about
these practices a lot.
Things like Wim Hof breathing
which is also called tummo breathing.
Things like ice baths.
Things like high intensity
interval training.
All of those things have utility.
The question is how you use them
and how often you use them.
Those tools just like
stress from a life event
can either enhance your
immunity or deplete it.
That's right those same practices
of ice baths, tummo breathing,
high intensity interval
training, or training of any kind
can deplete your immune
system or it can improve them.
Excuse me, they can improve it,
meaning they can improve
your immune system.
The key is how often
you use them and when,
and so I want to review that now
in light of the scientific literature,
because in doing that
you can build practices
into your daily or maybe
every other day routine
that can really help buffer you
against unhealthy levels of
cortisol and epinephrine.
Meaning cortisol increases
that are much too great,
or that lasts much too long.
Epinephrine increases
that are much too great,
or that last much too long.
And of course we'll talk
about all the negatives
that go along with
having too much cortisol,
too much epinephrine for too long.
But you hear about those a lot.
You hear about Cushing syndrome,
you hear about abdominal fat accumulation.
You hear about sleep disturbances.
I want to arm you with the tools first
and then we can talk about the dark side,
and all the things that hopefully
you'll be able to avoid entirely,
or that you can get yourself out of
once you have the tools in hand.
Let's say somebody tells you
something very troubling,
or you look at your phone
and you see a text message
that's really upsetting to you.
That will cause an immediate increase in
epinephrine adrenaline
in your brain and body.
And chances are it's going to increase
your levels of cortisol as well.
Let's say you get into an
ice bath or a cold shower,
even if you love the cold,
or if you hate the cold,
that will cause an equivalent increase
in epinephrine and cortisol.
We don't know the exact levels
but it's probably about the same.
Let's say you go out for high
intensity interval training,
you decide you're going
to run some sprints,
you do some repeats,
or you're going to do some
weightlifting in the gym
and you love lifting weights in the gym.
Maybe you like the power lifting thing,
or you decide that you
want to do some hot yoga,
or some thing that you
really enjoy, or you hate,
you're going to increase your
epinephrine and cortisol levels.
There's simply no way around this.
Let's say you decide to sit down
and you're going to do
some deep breathing.
We all hear about the
benefits of deep breathing.
So inhale, exhale, inhale, exhale.
You're going to get big increases
in epinephrine and cortisol.
The data from multiple
studies support this.
All of those are stressors in air quotes.
Now there is a way that
you can cognitively reframe
what those are.
You can tell yourself
I love high intensity
interval training, or
I love weight training.
I personally love exercise.
I'm not crazy about the cold,
I do some cold exposure
stuff now and again,
and we're going to talk a
lot about how to do that
in the optimal way in an upcoming episode.
But you know, getting into the
cold doesn't feel good to me.
I tell myself it's good for me
and I enjoy it at some point
usually when I'm getting out.
All of those increase
epinephrine and guess what,
they increase your levels
of energy and alertness.
So if you're somebody who struggles
with energy and alertness
it can be beneficial,
provided you get
clearance from your doctor
to have some sort of
protocol built into your day
where you deliberately increase
your levels of epinephrine
and your levels of cortisol.
And I want to put the
emphasis on deliberately.
So how would you do that?
Well, it's quite easy
to turn the shower cold
and get into that,
that will wake you up.
And it literally wakes you up
because of increases in epinephrine.
You can do deep breathing of the sort
where you inhale and exhale
repeatedly 25 or 30 times,
maybe hold your breath for a few seconds
on an exhale and then repeat,
so-called Wim Hoff, or
tummo type breathing.
Lots of adrenaline is
released into your system
when you do that.
You will have more energy afterwards.
So it's really important to understand
that the body doesn't distinguish
between a troubling text
message, ice, tummo breathing,
or high intensity interval training,
or any other kind of
exercise, it's all stress.
Cognitively reframing
that and telling yourself
I like this, I enjoy it.
Is not going to change
the way that that molecule
impacts your body and brain.
I sort of chuckle because
people would love to tell you
that all you have to do is say,
"Oh, this is good for me." No.
What it does to tell yourself
that it's good for you
or that you enjoy it.
Is that it liberates other molecules
like dopamine and serotonin
that help buffer the epinephrine response.
Now, the way that it does that,
I've talked about in previous episode,
but I'll just mention
that dopamine is the
precursor to epinephrine.
Epinephrine, adrenaline is
made from dopamine, okay?
Cortisol is made from cholesterol.
Epinephrine is made from dopamine.
And that's why if you tell yourself
you're enjoying something,
and because dopamine is so subjective
that you can in some ways,
as long as you're not
completely lying to yourself,
you can get more epinephrine,
you get more mileage or more ability
to push through something.
And you can sort of reframe it,
but it's not really cognitive reframing.
The cognitive part is the trigger,
but it's a chemical substance
that's actually occurring there.
It's dopamine giving you more epinephrine,
A bigger amplitude epinephrine release,
and it gives you some sense of control.
So here's a protocol that anyone can use.
If you want to increase levels of energy,
if you suffer from low
energy during the daytime,
or whenever it is that
you'd like to be alert.
Pick a practice that you
can do fairly consistently,
maybe every day,
but maybe every third
day or every fourth day,
maybe it's an ice bath or a cold bath.
Maybe it's a cold shower.
Maybe it's the cyclic inhale exhale,
breathing protocol I described,
if that wasn't clear and
people always ask for a demo,
I'm not going to do the
whole thing right now,
but I'm willing to do
a few rounds of this,
or a few cycles I should say.
So it's inhale.
I would do that more deeply, more like.
You do that 25, 30 times repeatedly
you will start to feel warm.
People in the yoga community,
they say you're generating heat.
You're not generating
heat, releasing adrenaline.
Inhale and exhale, inhale
exhale 25 or 30 times,
you will feel agitated and stressed.
That's because you're releasing
adrenaline in your body
and that's because you're releasing
norepinephrine in your brain,
and you'll be more alert.
Then you can follow that
25 or 30 breath cycles
with an exhale hold,
and hold your breath for 15 to 30 seconds.
Always, always, always
do this on dry land.
Never while driving,
operating heavy machinery,
all the standard safety protocols.
Never near water please,
people have passed out and died doing this
with breath holds in water.
There are several deaths
associated with it,
on land it's probably safer,
clear with your doctor,
but 25, 30 breaths exhale hold,
25, 30 breasts again exhale hold,
25 30 breasts again exhale hold.
And then if you like you
can do an inhale and hold
if that's within your margins of safety.
So if all these protocols,
all these activities are just equivalent,
they're just stress.
Then how do we make them good for us?
How do we actually benefit from them?
Now, of course the cold itself
can have some health promoting effects.
It can increase brown fat
thermogenesis and metabolism,
high intensity interval training,
or other forms of exercise
of course has cardiovascular effects
that can be good for us
as does weight training, et cetera.
But what we're talking about here
are ways to increase energy
and to teach our brain and body
to teach ourselves how to
regulate the stress response.
So in addition to the benefits
of the actual practices
what we're talking about
is building a system
so that when you experience
increases in epinephrine and
cortisol from life events
you're able to better buffer those.
And we are also talking about
ways that you can increase energy overall.
'Cause that's what today's
episode is all about,
energy and the immune system.
And indeed, we will talk about
how you can actually
leverage specific protocols
to increase your immune system on demand.
There's great scientific data
to support that one can do that.
So there's a biological
mechanism that's very important
if you want to do those things,
increase energy and your
immune system on demand.
Learn to buffer stress
on demand in real time.
And it means taking these protocols,
these practices whether
or not it's cold water,
or ice bath, or exercise, or any of those
and making one small but
very powerful adjustment
in how you perform them.
But in order to make that adjustment,
I can't just tell you the adjustment.
I have to tell you the mechanism
so that you know if you're
doing it correctly or not.
This is really a case where
if you can understand a
little bit of mechanism,
you will be far better off
than just adopting protocols.
So if you take away nothing
else from this episode
except what I'm about to tell you
please take away the
information I'm about to tell
Cortisol as I mentioned is
released from the adrenals
and it can bind to receptors.
It can have action, both in
the body and in the brain.
In fact, it can bind to the so-called
threat detection center in the brain,
or one of them which is the amygdala,
also called the fear center.
It can do that because cortisol
can cross the blood brain barrier.
It can be released in the body and cross
this biological barrier.
It's like a fence that keeps
things out of the brain
but cortisol has passing
rights, it can go through.
Epinephrine cannot,
epinephrine is polarized,
the shape of it is such that
it can't make it through
the blood brain barrier.
That's one of the reasons
why it's released both
from the adrenals in your body
and released from this brainstem area,
the locus coeruleus in your brain.
That's a powerful thing,
because what it means is that
the body can enter states
of readiness and alertness
while the mind remains calm.
That is biologically possible,
it's not just a psychological trick.
And there are ways that one can do that.
So I'm presuming at this point
that you're getting your morning light
to time your cortisol increase.
I'm presuming that you want more energy
or that you want to
increase your immune system,
its function and its ability
to combat infections of various kinds.
And what I'm suggesting is that
you pick from the pallet of
exercises that are out there,
or tools that are out there
to increase epinephrine.
There are a lot of ways to do that.
You can do that as I
mentioned through cold water,
through exercise.
You can even do that
by having confrontations
with other people.
At a biological level, it is identical.
So if you like to go online
and place the kind of comments
or read the kinds of things,
or look at the kinds of
things that agitate you,
you can if you like look
at that as an opportunity,
I'm not suggesting you do that,
I'd like to see people
taking care of themselves
and each other in much less
destructive ways frankly.
But the prerequisite here
is getting an increase
in adrenaline released from the body.
Now the simplest way to
describe how to do that
would be in the context of cold water
or a breathing protocol,
because then I don't have to deal with the
unknown life circumstances
that get you triggered,
or I could say what gets me triggered
but I'm not going to.
So let's presume cold water.
So let's say you decide you're
going to take a cold shower.
You get into the cold shower
and if it's cold enough,
that will be stressful,
you will experience an
increase in epinephrine,
it will increase your alertness.
Now you're using this as a practice,
as a tool to build you
could call it resilience,
but the ability to stay calm in the mind
while being stressed in the body,
epinephrine is in the body.
And you do that by subjectively
trying to calm yourself.
Now you can do that by telling
yourself it's good for you
by emphasizing your exhales.
Anything that you can
do to try and stay calm
despite the fact that
you are in a heightened
state of alertness.
You do this with exercise,
you can do this with music.
Pretty much anything that will give you
a really heightened state of alertness
offers you the opportunity to
try and stay calm in the mind.
What you're trying to do
at a mechanistic level
is to have adrenaline
released from the adrenals,
but not have adrenaline,
epinephrine released
from the brain stem to the same degree.
So you're not just trying to buffer this,
you're not trying to say,
"Oh, this is good for me,
this is good for me, I'm
going to grind this out."
You're not trying to grind it out,
you're trying to move through this calmly
while maintaining alertness.
You're not trying to zone out necessarily,
although maybe that helps.
You're not trying to distract yourself,
what you're trying to do is
shift cognitively your
relationship to the somatic,
to the body stress response.
Now I'm sure some of you
out there are shouting,
"Yeah, that's exactly like
whatever, whatever, whatever."
I agree.
This is in many ways a self-directed
kind of stress inoculation,
but we're not talking about
this as stress inoculation.
We're talking about this as a way
to increase energy and focus.
And the reason is that epinephrine
when released in the body
has a profound effect
on the immune system.
And when released in the
brain has a profound effect
on the ability to learn
and remember information
and to be alert.
And so we're talking about
splitting the location,
separating the location from which
you have epinephrine, adrenaline released.
Okay. So let's say you
are doing this practice
simply to wake up,
okay, cold shower will do that,
exercise will do that.
The ability to stay calm in mind
while having heightened
levels of adrenaline
and presumably cortisol
as well in the body.
But the cortisol is going
to circulate everywhere.
We'll talk a little bit about
cortisol more in a moment.
You could do that through some
self soothing calming way,
that's going to be highly individual.
You can do it by telling
yourself you enjoy it, et cetera.
But what you need to understand
is that in the immediate
period following that practice
your system, your entire
brain and body are different.
Your body is actually
primed to resist infection,
when you have high levels
of epinephrine in it
for short periods of time.
So the scientific study that explored how
increasing adrenaline in the body
can improve immune resistance is grounded
in a well-known phenomenon
that increases in stress
actually protect you against infection
in the short term.
So I want to look at
the classic data first,
describe what was done.
And then I want to talk
about the more recent study
which is immediately actionable.
There are classic set of
studies that are really based
mainly on the work of
somebody named Bruce McEwen,
who was at the Rockefeller
University in New York.
Bruce passed away a few years ago,
but he had many decades
of incredibly impactful
work under his belt when he did.
The work that I'm going to talk about next
has been done in humans
and has been done in animals,
and has really explored
how inducing stress
can enhance the function
of the immune system
in the short term.
And when, I mean short term,
I mean about one to four days.
I'm not going to go through
all the details of the study,
but essentially what they were
doing was exposing subjects
to some sort of infection,
either bacterial or viral infection,
and inducing stress.
It sounds like a double whammy, right?
You'd think that maybe getting
a little electric foot shock,
or cold water exposure,
or something to increase
your levels of stress
and adrenaline would just make
the effects of the infection worse,
but no, quite the opposite.
Brief bouts of stress,
which now you should be thinking about
in terms of cortisol
and epinephrine release
we're actually able to increase
immune system function.
Now that shouldn't surprise you
if you understand a little bit
about how epinephrine works
in the body and in the brain.
It essentially is the signal
by which the nervous system
can inform immune organs,
things like the spleen and other organs
that make killer cells of various kinds,
B cells and T cells,
to go in combat infections,
bacteria, and viruses.
How else would your immune system know
that there was an infection?
Your immune system can
recognize foreign invaders
but the nervous system
provides the signal,
the sort of alarm signal that
liberates the killer cells,
that tells them there's a problem
and to go seek out the
problem so to speak.
So the duration here is really important
because if stress stayed
too high for too long,
then yes indeed stress can
hinder the immune response.
But for a period of
about one to four days,
it actually can protect you
by way of increasing the immune response.
Now, I can say with certainty
that that effect is
governed by epinephrine,
adrenaline released from the adrenals
and not from the brain,
because they actually explored
whether or not the effect exists
in the presence of what's
called an adrenalectomy,
or removing the adrenals.
So I should just say, without the adrenals
you don't get the effect.
So we know that that effect
comes from adrenaline in the body.
What does that mean for you?
That means if you want to increase
your immune system in the short term
you want to increase your
epinephrine in the short-term.
That's why short bouts
of very intense exercise
probably no more than an hour per day,
provided you're doing
everything else right,
sleeping and nutrition, et cetera,
maybe even shorter bouts
of intense exercise
or exposure to cold water,
or that cyclical breathing
that I talked about before,
because they increase epinephrine
they will bolster the immune system.
And we all hear these reports
every once in a while,
it seems to be the thing that
every once in a while there'll
be an article about how
coffee can improve your immune system,
or something like that.
Indeed caffeine can increase epinephrine
and dopamine to some extent,
but most people are
drinking it chronically.
So its effects are probably
due to increases in epinephrine
and probably whether or
not something like coffee
or other forms of caffeine can improve
or degrade your immune system
will probably depend on whether or not
you're using it in a way
that it increases your
adrenaline as a spike,
that happens rarely,
you know, once every two or three months,
let's say you have an infection coming on,
yes, indeed.
What these data probably mean
is that drinking some hot caffeinated tea
or some hot coffee even
provided you don't get dehydrated from it
because you're also drinking some water
can probably improve your
immune system function,
by way of increasing adrenaline release.
But so can the breathing,
so can cold exposure,
so can exercise.
The mechanism here is what's key,
and I keep saying that
because what it means is that
you don't actually have to
know the specific protocol.
I'm not trying to say, do
this particular protocol.
You have to figure out,
and it should be easy to figure out
what short term adrenaline
increasing behavior
you're willing to do on a
regular basis every day,
or two or three times a week.
Now you could say, well, I'm not sick.
Should I be doing these things often?
I would say, two or three
times a week at a minimum
if your goal is to keep
your immune system tuned up
and you are in the presence of a lot of
children for instance,
which carry a lot of bugs,
because their immune
system isn't developed,
or you work in a healthcare setting,
or you're simply somebody
who's prone to get sick.
I can just say anecdotally,
I guess someone now calls this anecdata
which I don't like that phrase,
because it's sort of...
I don't want anecdotal data to ever be
misunderstood as anything
but anecdotal data.
Anecdotally, I can say that I've had
instances where I've felt
a throat tickle coming on
or some sinus infection,
I will do the cyclic breathing
that I described before.
25, 30 breasts exhale hold,
25 30 breasts exhale hold,
25, 30 breaths exhale hold,
and then big inhale hold.
And most times I didn't
get full blown sick,
but I also take other
precautionary measures
to get sleep, et cetera.
So whether or not it was causal,
or whether or not it's just
correlated I don't know.
However, there's a human study
that I definitely want
to point out to you,
because it was published more recently
than the McEwen work.
It was published in the Proceedings
of the National Academy
of Sciences for the USA,
because there are Proceedings
of the National Academy of Sciences
for many other countries as well.
The title of the paper is
"Voluntary activation of the
sympathetic nervous system."
That's the system that causes
fight or flight AKA stress,
and causes release of adrenaline.
"And attenuation of the innate
immune response in humans."
This is Kox et al. PNAS,
Proceedings to the National
Academy of sciences, 2014.
And they incorporate the
ever famous Wim Hof breathing
Wim Hof breathing is much
like the breathing protocol
that I've described several
times now in this podcast.
It's also called tummo breathing.
Other people from other
cultures and communities
have called it other things.
The naming really isn't important.
Although I do think Wim is a pioneer
in trying to bring these practices
to the general public more broadly
and was involved in this study.
The study was done in the Netherlands.
It was communicated by
Dr. Tamas Horvath at Yale,
I mentioned all that.
Horvath is a terrific scientist,
I'm familiar with his
work over many years.
Here's what they did.
They injected people with E. coli
and they had groups that either
did the sorts of breathing
I've been describing
that increase adrenaline release.
Although I should say,
I don't think you need that breathing
to get adrenaline release.
You could do it with cold exposure,
you could do it with other things,
high intensity interval training as well.
And what they found was that
the response to the E.
coli was quite different
in the people that had a protocol,
in this case breathing
to increase adrenaline.
So this is a remarkable study
because what they found was
that the fever, the vomiting,
the all the negative effects of E. coli,
many of them and some cases all of them
were greatly attenuated
by way of engaging the adrenaline system.
In this case using breathing.
They looked at inflammatory cytokines,
things like IL-6,
which I've mentioned many
times on this podcast.
This are classic inflammatory
cytokine were reduced.
Things like IL-10
which are anti-inflammatory
were increased.
There were some inflammatory
cytokines that were increased.
What's the point here?
The point is you can
control your immune system,
by finding a way that you
can increase adrenaline.
And this runs counter
to what we always hear,
which is don't get too
stressed or you will get sick.
Learn to control adrenaline,
turn it on and turn it off.
Learn to control cortisol,
turn it on with light in the morning,
try and turn it off
and then when it spikes
because of life events
learn to turn it off.
Learning to turn on and off
adrenaline, AKA epinephrine,
and learning to turn on and off cortisol
affords you the ability to
turn on energy and focus
in your immune system.
That's the most important
point from today's podcast
and understanding that it doesn't matter
what protocol you use.
Maybe it's a cup of coffee
and running up a hill five or six times,
that will improve your
immune system function
if you get adrenaline in your system.
You can use an ice bath,
you can use a cold bath,
it really doesn't matter.
You get into an argument,
but I'm not suggesting you do that,
it really doesn't matter.
What's important is that
you're able to then shut off
that response.
And there are ways to do
that we will talk about,
but I want to talk about
some of the other benefits
of epinephrine and cortisol
that occur because of
their actions on the brain.
Because these are many
and they are powerful,
and they relate to energy,
but also the ability to learn.
If I haven't already convinced you
that seeing light early in the day
is good for timing your cortisol.
I should also mention that another hormone
that I discussed last episode
which is thyroid hormone
and is critical for setting
your level of metabolism
is controlled in part by
these circadian mechanisms
and cortisol itself.
The short takeaway on this
is that if you get your cortisol
release early in the day
it will increase your
energy throughout the day,
it will also time your
thyroid release properly.
So there's yet another reason
why you would want to
get that light exposure
early in the day.
For me that's a non-negotiable practice.
If I'm on a plane, I'll try
and get it any way I can.
I'm not shining
flashlights in my eyes yet,
but I really try hard to
get that light exposure
from sunlight early in
the day without fail.
And the thyroid increase
has to do with the fact that
your circadian clock itself
is regulated by cortisol
and the circadian clock times the release
of thyroid hormone.
I don't want to go too
far off in that direction,
but there are a number of studies,
Kalsbeek et al.
Kalsbeek et al. 2012.
If you want to look it up
on PubMed is a great one,
that describes how cortisol secretion
begins to rise during sleep
and peaks shortly after
waking or immediately before.
And that times a set of
neurons in the circadian clock
that then trigger the release of the
releasing and stimulating
hormones for thyroid.
So a really important mechanism,
and thyroid will also tend
to correlate with energy
but mostly metabolism.
Very important to have thyroid in check.
Now let's talk about
epinephrine and cortisol,
and learning and memory.
Everyone has a story
about being so stressed
they couldn't remember something.
You know, sit down to an exam.
I actually had this happen
once sat down to an exam
and just blanked, just blanked.
It only happened once, I
don't know what happened.
I don't think it was sleep deprivation
but I just completely blanked.
And it was very hard for me
to pull myself out of that ditch.
I did manage to do it, but
it was a scary experience.
So I think most people think about stress
and an inability to perform.
However, most of the time
increases in epinephrine
provided they are not through the roof
lead to improved performance.
Now this has been shown over
and over again on memory tests,
on learning new information,
on physical performance.
That when blood levels
of epinephrine are low
you don't perform very well.
When blood levels of
epinephrine are very high
up to about 1500 to 1700 pg/mL.
If anyone's out there, who's
actually measuring this stuff
but I doubt you are,
performance goes way up.
Performance gets better when you are alert
and when you're a little bit stressed.
Absolutely shown again,
and again, and again.
If you get too stressed,
it's the mental side,
it's the epinephrine in the
brain that causes people
to either focus on their
somatic response too much.
Like they feel like they're sweating,
and they're focused on
their bodily response,
they're not focused on what
it is they're trying to do,
or say, or perform, et cetera, or learn.
But epinephrine is a nootropic,
it is a smart drug that
we all make internally,
and cortisol is as well.
Now here's the twist
that does not mean that
you want epinephrine
high during the exam necessarily.
Memory and learning and
performance are actually favored,
they are enhanced by epinephrine increases
immediately after learning.
And that's something
that's rarely discussed,
the timing is vital.
So if you learn some information,
you have a conversation
you're trying to learn a new
language, a new motor skill.
Whatever it is that
you're trying to learn,
the increase in epinephrine
that occurs just afterward
is what's going to
consolidate the information.
It's going to ensure
that the proper circuits
and mechanisms in the
brain for neuroplasticity
are engaged during sleep later that night
or the next night which is
when the real rewiring occurs.
And You might say, "That's
crazy, why would that happen?"
Well, we have to remember,
none of these mechanisms evolved
for us to do what we want and
learn what we want necessarily
although they will allow us to do that.
We've experienced this before,
we might have gotten up,
gone outside get in our car,
drive to work or to somebody's house
you're not thinking about much at all,
and then all of a sudden you
see an accident on the road.
Your alertness is primed
if it happens to be a
particularly gory accident,
there's going to be a lot of
sensory information there.
All of a sudden the
adrenaline, epinephrine
is released into your brain and body.
Guess what?
Not only will you not forget that event,
but you will remember everything
that led up to that event
which has an adaptive function,
because your brain and body's
primary concern is safety, right?
This is the neuro-biological explanation
for Maslow's hierarchy
of needs is safety first.
And so you have heightened
awareness and alertness
for everything that preceded
that spike in adrenaline and cortisol.
So the way to think about this is
if you need to learn something better,
if you're taking Adderall,
or you're taking a lot
of coffee beforehand
you're actually driving the
process in the wrong direction.
You're increasing epinephrine
for learning sure,
but past a certain point
you're actually degrading
learning and performance.
The time to do that is toward the end
or immediately after the learning,
because this mechanism
is not simply devoted to
negative events like a
car crash or a trauma,
it works to make sure that the hippocampus
that encodes memories
as part of the memory and
coding mechanisms is primed.
That it's told what you just
experienced is important,
you're going to need
that information later.
And so I've talked many times before about
using non sleep deep rest NSDR,
or ensuring good night's
sleep after learning.
But what we're also talking about
is as the learning event tapers
off, as you're exiting that,
to make sure that your epinephrine levels
are not tapering off as well.
And this may be one of the
reasons why the 90 minute cycle,
the so-called ultradian
cycle for learning works,
because it takes a few minutes
to get into rhythm of learning.
You can maintain that
alertness for about 90 minutes,
it's no coincidence that
these podcasts are typically
about 90 minutes long.
And as you exit that 90 minutes
you're going to start to feel fatigued.
You're not going to be able to continue
to secrete epinephrine at the same level.
So I'm not telling you that
at the end of this podcast
you should give yourself a foot shock,
or that you should jump into an ice bath.
Although I will say,
if you were to increase your epinephrine
at the end of this episode
by breathing or by way of cold shower,
I'm willing to bet based on
numerous published studies
that the memory for the
information would be enhanced.
Because of this retroactive effect
of epinephrine and cortisol.
Put simply you can remember things better
if you increase your alertness,
AKA your level of epinephrine
and cortisol after,
immediately after something
that you want to learn.
So I'm reminded by people here
at the Huberman Lab Podcast
that the optimal strategy
therefore would be
a 90 minute session of focus or learning
then immediately after cold
shower or tummo type breathing,
or ice bath or something of that sort,
maybe a hard run,
or hit training if you can't
get access to the other things.
And then shower up and
do a non sleep deep rest,
and then get a good night's sleep.
Those would be the optimal tools
and the organization of
tools for enhanced learning.
And of course you could use caffeine
to prime the whole process
by drinking the caffeine
towards the tail of the learning episode,
which is counter-intuitive at least to me.
I should mention since
many of you use caffeine
and I use caffeine.
I do drink coffee,
I love mushroom coffee.
I love mate.
I drink caffeine and various forms.
There was a study that came out recently
that is relevant to our
discussion about energy
and alertness, and learning.
And the study came out
just recently March 2021,
it's Maglhaes et al.
So MAGALHAES.
And it was published
in molecular psychiatry
which is a fine journal,
a peer review journal.
And the title pretty much gives it away,
"Habitual coffee drinkers
display a distinct pattern
of brain functional conductivity."
Chronically drinking coffee
changes brain conductivity.
And it does it in a number of ways
but the key takeaways from this study,
as it relates to sort
of what the circuits do
as opposed to me just listing
off a bunch of brain circuits,
which is kind of meaningless
in this conversation
is that people who drank
coffee habitually every day
had changes in their brain circuitry,
such that there was a shift
or a bias toward anxiety
even when they don't ingest caffeine.
So a lot of times we think,
Oh caffeine increases
your levels of anxiety.
And indeed it appears it does
if you use it chronically,
but not just to caffeine,
it doesn't just raise
your baseline of anxiety
because of what circulating
in your bloodstream.
It actually increases connectivity
between the brain areas
that relate to anxiety.
Now that could be a good
thing or a bad thing
depending on how you look at it.
For people that have are
prone to chronic panic attacks
or anxiety attacks that's
not going to be good.
Some people might use
caffeine in healthy ways.
I believe I do in order to
just increase overall levels of alertness.
Although now not only am
I going to start delaying
my caffeine intake till
two hours after I wake up
for reasons I've talked
about in previous episodes,
but I'm also going to start drinking it
later in learning and focus sessions
as a way to enhance plasticity
around those learning and
focus sessions, not before.
So interesting study, it's free online.
You can access the full paper online,
we will put a link as well.
I want to mention this
issue of nootropics,
so-called smart drugs.
Which is not a topic
that I particularly enjoy
because I don't like the name.
I don't like the idea of a nootropic,
because what is a smart drug?
Well, there's different kinds of smart,
there's creativity,
there's task switching,
their strategy building,
their strategy implementation.
And most of the nootropics
that are out there
just cocktails of a
bunch of different things
that aren't tailored to
the individual at all.
They all seem to have some caffeine,
or some culinary trick
stimulation, et cetera.
But there's an important way to frame this
in light of today's conversation.
Nootropics generally
fall into two categories,
one category are nootropics
that increase blood glucose.
So these are compounds that people take
they increased blood glucose
and increasing in blood glucose
will improve performance,
and can enhance learning
in some situations.
I'm not suggesting
people take these things,
but here's just a list of a few of those.
Some of them are legal,
some of them are gray market,
some of them are illegal.
piracetam, oxiracetam,
aniracetam, all the Tams, okay.
Elevate blood glucose
that's how they work.
The neural effects that you
hear are secondary or tertiary
to the fact that they just
increased blood glucose.
We know that because if you
block the blood glucose effect
you block the nootropic effect, okay.
Others include, and definitely
don't take these please,
amphetamine, cocaine.
Those will increase
learning in the short term
in particular dosages,
but because they increase blood glucose.
And then of course, things
like painful stimuli
or stress will improve learning
by way of increasing blood glucose.
Now stress and epinephrine
that's associated with it
not only improve performance
during the learning about,
but as I mentioned before
having epinephrine come up afterward
will increase the retention
of that information
in the longterm.
And then of course,
there's a whole category of
nootropics that don't
impact blood glucose,
that work by increasing the
cholinergic system activity.
And these are things
like choline, lecithin,
Physostigmine, it's a prescription drug,
phosphodiesterase.
So there're ways to increase energy
that don't require
increase in blood glucose,
and this is a vitally important.
The reason we're talking
about epinephrine and cortisol
for increasing energy and
immune system function
is because they are largely
independent of blood glucose.
Of course, they interact with that system,
but we heard so much growing
up you need to eat for energy,
but the energy that
we're talking about today
is actually a much more powerful one
than the one that you derive from food,
We could call it neural energy.
It's neurotransmitters
that create alertness,
and focus, and the willingness
and the ability to move.
And the willingness and
ability for immune system
to move in response to intruders.
So I think we all too often
think about food as energy
which is great because it is,
but there are other sources
of energy that are neural
and they relate to these hormone systems,
cortisol and epinephrine.
And that's why we're focused on today.
So up until now we've been talking about
increasing energy and
increasing the immune system
by way of cortisol and epinephrine,
but I'd be totally
remiss if I didn't cover
how cortisol and epinephrine
if chronically elevated,
or if elevated too high
can have a lot of detrimental effects.
These are the things
we normally hear about.
I'm going to describe some of those things
but I'm also going to talk
about ways to ameliorate them.
Ways that you can adjust
the cortisol levels,
even if you're stressed.
Ways that you can adjust
epinephrine levels
even if you're stressed
so that they have less
of a negative impact.
I don't have to list off all the ways
that stress is terrible and
chronic stress is terrible
I think you know.
Insomnia, your immune system
over time will get battered
and you won't be able to fight
infection off as well, right?
You don't want to be
stressed for too long.
You can start laying down the sort of
classic pattern of
cortisol induced body fat.
In fact, there's a whole
literature related to comfort foods
and why we want to consume comfort foods
under conditions of chronic stress.
And it's quite interesting actually,
because it reveals something
about the biology of chronic stress
that's informative for how to prevent it,
or to down regulate chronic
stress once it's occurred.
So let's talk for a
second about comfort foods
and the work that I'm going to refer to
is work that was done by a
very impressive scientist
by the name of Mary Dallman.
Her work goes back decades.
She was at University of
California San Francisco,
and she asked this question
that on the face of it
seems kind of obvious,
but for which there was no mechanism known
until Mary and her lab
personnel came along.
And the question was,
why do we seek high-fat
and or high sugar foods
when we are stressed for awhile?
Why would that be?
And the reason is that the
so-called glucocorticoids
of which cortisol is a glucocorticoid.
It's caused as we've mentioned before,
by releasing hormones from the brain,
and ACTH from the pituitary, et cetera.
But normally high levels
of glucocorticoid shut off
the releasing hormones in the
brain and in the pituitary,
they shut down in a so-called
negative feedback loop.
So just like if testosterone
or estrogen get too high
that's read out or that
is seen so to speak
by neurons in the pituitary and brain
and then we shut down our production of
estrogen and testosterone.
If cortisol levels get too high,
if there's too much cortisol
floating around in our bloodstream,
there's a negative feedback loop,
and the brain and pituitary
shutdown, CRH and ACTH
which would otherwise
stimulate more cortisol,
so cortisol levels go down.
So it's a beautiful
negative feedback loop.
Chronic stress however,
stress that lasts more
than four to seven days
and there's a way to think about
what chronic stress really
is in an actionable way,
'causes changes in the feedback loop
between the adrenals and
the brain and the pituitary.
Such that now the brain and the pituitary
respond to high levels of
glucocorticoids cortisol
by releasing more of them.
It becomes a positive feedback loop
and that's bad
it actually gets right down
to levels of gene regulation
and transcription and translation.
And so you really don't
want chronic stress,
because it's a cascade of
stress equals more stress
equals more stress.
So this is why it's very important
to learn to turn off the stress response.
You don't want it elevated for too long.
So there's one study that
Dallman and her colleagues did
where they stimulate chronic stress
by increasing corticosteroids, cortisol.
And they found that subjects
would increase their
consumption of sugar and fat.
In fact they would even eat lard
It's sounds disgusting,
but they were willing to just
eat more fat and more sugar.
And that led to all sorts of things
like type two diabetes
that led to dysfunction in
the adrenal output, et cetera.
And so the real key is to learn
to shut off the stress response.
Because the interesting thing is,
is that dominant colleagues
and some studies that followed
up on their work found that
if the system was kicked
into motion for too long,
then there was a tremendous
shift overall towards anxiety,
because it turns out that body fat itself
receives neural innervation.
Neurons actually talked to body fats
so now you have body fat
releasing certain hormones,
you've got the adrenals
releasing cortisol,
and all of that is
feeding back to the brain
to make you want more
sugar and fatty foods.
So that's how the so-called
comfort foods work.
And you should watch yourself
next time you experience stress.
If it's a short-term about of stress,
typically it blocks hunger.
If it's a longer about of stress
typically it triggers hunger,
in particular for these
so-called comfort foods,
sugary and fatty foods.
And it's kind of interesting
how short-term stress can
actually block hunger.
It does that by activating
or interacting with a system
called the bombesin system.
Bombesin is a peptide hormone.
I think it was named after
some sort of reptiles
or amphibians, excuse
me, some sort of toad.
I think it was initially
sequenced from the toad
before it was later discovered in humans.
And I think the Toad's Latin
name is Bombina bombina,
or something of that sort.
And so they decided to
call this thing bombesin,
but it reduces eating and
stress liberates bombesin
and makes you want to eat less.
But chronic stress causes all these
positive feedback changes,
which are not positive.
I'm calling them positive
because they amplify the
stress response over and over
not because they are good for you.
So short-term stress great,
long-term stress really, really bad.
Other bad effects of stress
that we can talk about
and I won't list off
too many more of these,
because you know so many of
them, you hear about them.
You really want to know how
to control them I'm guessing
is that yes indeed stress
can make you go gray.
The rates at which people
go gray, meaning gray hair,
some cases gray body hair as well
depend on some genetic factors.
There are a couple of
ways that we can go gray.
There's actually a STEM cell,
what they call niche in every follicle.
So you have STEM cells in the follicle
that can produce more and
more of the given hair cell.
And they're actually peroxide groups.
You know we hear about
bleaching hair with peroxide,
at least in the 80s that was a thing,
but you can use hydrogen
peroxide to bleach things,
and you can produce your own
peroxide in the hair follicle,
that will cause the hairs to go gray.
In addition pigmentation of hair,
just like pigmentation of skin
is controlled by melanocytes,
our old friends, the melanocytes.
And I say old friends
'cause on previous episodes
I talked about why sunlight
and getting ample sunlight
can increase levels of certain things
like melanocytes stimulating hormone
which reduce hunger.
It can improve testosterone
and estrogen levels
and all the reasons for that.
Well, it turns out that activation
of the so-called
sympathetic nervous system,
which is really just another name for
the system that liberates
adrenaline from the adrenals
and epinephrine in the brain
drives depletion of
melanocytes in hair stem cells.
So indeed there's a rate of aging
that we will undergo
based on our genetics,
but stress will make us go gray.
And the paper that you should look to
if you want to read more about this
came out very recently.
This is Zang et al, Z
H A N G et al. Nature.
Fabulous journal, definitely
one of the apex journals, 2020.
So this paper showed that
the activation of stress
in various forms will deplete
these melanocytes stem cells.
You do not have to
worry about an ice bath,
or hard exercise or breathing,
increasing your levels of stress
to the point where it's
going to make you go gray.
We're talking again about chronic stress.
And if you want to
offset the stress effects
on graying of hair you can do that
by either having a practice
that helps you regulate
stress on a consistent basis.
So something like non sleep
deep breath, or meditation.
You can get access to massages
or vacations those are great,
but having a practice
to keep stress clamps
so that it's not chronically elevated,
that will be great as well.
This is another case where sunlight
we know stimulates melanocytes,
not just in skin, but in hair.
And so getting ample sunlight,
having a practice to regulate stress
will offset the stressed
induced grain of hairs
by way of stress induced
depletion of melanocytes.
And if melanocytes sounds a
lot like melanin you're right.
That's because anything
involved with pigmentation
in the brain and body
generally has "melano"
up in the front of the word
in some way or another.
So if chronic stress is so bad
because of its effects on
epinephrine and cortisol
being elevated for too long
then the question becomes of course,
well, what's chronic stress?
How do I know the
difference between chronic
and acute stress?
And how do I keep chronic stress at bay?
Because of all these negative effects,
I didn't even list out
the number of other ones,
the effects on depression,
which certainly has a correlate
with elevated cortisol.
Thyroid hormone.
Low thyroid hormone is
associated with depression.
Mistimed thyroid, once
again getting your light
and your feeding and your
exercise and your sleep
on a consistent schedule or consistent ish
is going to be the most
powerful thing you can do
in order to buffer yourself
against negative effects on mental health
and physical health for that matter.
There are things that one can take
supplements, prescription
drugs, et cetera.
Some of you out there may have
or may know people that have Cushing's,
which is chronically elevated cortisol.
There are prescription drugs
that we will talk about
that can be used.
But most people are dealing
with a situation where
life gets stressful then less stressful,
stressful then less stressful.
I would say, based on the
data from McEwen and others,
Bob Sapolsky's Lab over many years.
I would say any stress that lasts
more than a day or two days, or three days
is starting to become chronic stress.
There's really no strict cutoff
because we're not measuring
everybody's cortisol
from moment to moment.
My lab has done experiments
where we measure stress
in people over time.
People vary tremendously
in their ability to have a really hard day
and then fall deeply asleep.
That's going to be the ultimate reset
is the ability to sleep well
more or less undisturbed each night,
although one or two wake
ups during the night,
probably not going to be too detrimental
provided they're not too long,
and you're not viewing light
during those wake-ups or your phone.
But the things that you can take,
if you feel like you're
chronically stressed
and you're veering toward
some of the negative
effects of stress are many.
There are some simple
things that people can do
in terms of supplementation.
All supplements of course
have to be checked out for
their safety margins for you,
because there going to
differ from person to person.
You're responsible for making
sure they're safe for you
if you decide to use them.
One of the most common ones is Ashwagandha
and it has a powerful
anxiolytic anti-anxiety effect.
You're welcome to go to
examine.com and for zero cost
you can see their so-called
human effect matrix.
Ashwagandha has many uses,
It's been used to enhance
power output in athletes
it has been shown to modestly
increase testosterone.
It has been shown to
modestly adjust things like
low density lipoprotein cholesterol,
the so-called bad cholesterol in quotes.
It has a profound effect on anxiety
that's been shown in nine studies.
Nine peer reviewed independent studies,
mean funded by organizations
that have no vested interest
in the answer.
It has a very strong
effect on cortisol itself.
How strong?
The decrease in cortisol noted in humans
is 14.5 to 27.9% reduction
in otherwise healthy but stressed humans.
That's great.
Six studies.
And it mentions there's
a significantly larger
than many other supplements.
Now, some people will say
that taking Ashwagandha
chronically may not be good.
If you've heard about that,
or you can point to specific studies
that indicate exactly why it's not good,
please put in the comment
section or let me know.
In the comment section
on YouTube would be best.
The studies that I'm referring
to did explore both genders.
The number of subjects was
reasonably high, 64 or more.
One to six months study,
so these were long-term studies.
That's great, you like to see that
not just in an acute study.
So males and females
lots of different ages
overweight and non overweight.
They did blood draws of cortisol
which is going to end and
as well as saliva test.
Saliva is actually the best
way to measure free cortisol.
You can also measure it
from ear wax it turns out
which sounds pretty gross and kind of is.
But nonetheless that's where
cortisol will accumulate
in earwax and in saliva,
the free cortisol.
But that's six very quality studies,
independently supported
that all points to these
very significant, you know,
14.5 to 27.9% reductions
in otherwise healthy adults.
So if you're somebody who is
dealing with chronic stress,
it's a stressful period in your life
and you want to stave off the
negative effects of stress.
Well then ashwagandha may,
I want to highlight, may be right for you.
It also does tend to lower total cortisol
which is interesting.
It can lower depression to
at somewhat minimal degree,
and can lower as I
mentioned before things like
low density lipoprotein.
I think ashwagandha
comes through is kind of
the heavy hitter in department.
Now what's interesting also
is the other effects of ashwagandha
that are downstream of reducing
chronic stress and cortisol,
'cause cortisol has so many effects,
there're receptors for cortisol
all over the body and brain.
And so I'll just list these off quickly,
I'm not going to list off each study
or talk about how many subjects in detail.
Again, you can go to
examine.com if you want,
and just put it in Ashwagandha.
See reactive protein,
which is a marker of all sorts
of negative health effects.
Cardiovascular health,
even macular degeneration
is notably reduced.
Heart palpitations notably reduced.
serum T3 and T4, our old friends
from the thyroid hormones
from a previous episode are increased.
Symptoms of OCD decreased,
both the obsessions and the compulsion's
right obsessions are of the mind
compulsions are of behavior.
So there are a lot of
things that are downstream
of reducing cortisol.
Lowered heart rate,
lowered rates of insomnia,
slightly improved memory.
Why that would be, I don't know,
because cortisol in the short
term can increase memory,
I'm guessing it's from increased sleep.
Decreased pain, increased
quality of you know...
Decreased reaction times,
things of that sort.
So the list goes on and on,
but all of those things stem downstream
of decreased cortisol.
So if one were to decide
to take ashwagandha
in order to reduce cortisol,
given that you want
cortisol early in the day
to have energy throughout the day,
the time to take it as
probably later in the day
or in the evening.
I've never heard of it preventing sleep
or causing insomnia of any kind.
That certainly wasn't listed
as one of the major
effects on examine.com.
I will take ashwagandha from time to time
if I'm chronically stressed,
or if I'm not sleeping
as well as I ought to.
You might think that with all my knowledge
about sleep and sleep protocols
that I would sleep perfectly every night,
but unfortunately I have a dog that has
a canine form of of
sundowners, of dementia,
so he's up much of the night, these days.
And so there's no way
I'm getting a solid night of sleep lately.
And so I will supplement with ashwagandha
and typically I'll take it before sleep
and maybe also with my
last meal of the day,
which is at least two
hours before I go to sleep.
Again you have to decide
if it's right for you.
The dosages can vary tremendously.
I would just go buy
what's on the bottle
from a reputable brand.
I would also check out examine.com,
because it mentions a range of dosages
that people have used.
And in various studies
to different effects.
Now, there is something out there
that some of you may actually
be taking or ingesting
that can increase cortisol
and not so incidentally
can decrease estrogen and testosterone.
Because remember cortisol
is made from the cholesterol molecule
so is estrogen and testosterone.
So are estrogen and
testosterone, excuse me,
and it's competitive.
So you're either making more cortisol,
or you're making more of
the sex steroid hormones,
estrogen and testosterone.
Believe it or not liquorice,
which I always thought of as a candy,
but liquorice contains a
substance that I can't pronounce.
G L Y C Y R R H I Z I N.
Glycyrrhizin, which is of
the glabra species of plant,
actually because of its chemistry,
this 18-beta-hydroxy-cholenoic acid,
you don't need to know all that.
Liquorice, black liquorice
contains a substance
that increases cortisol,
and it's increases not
huge, but it is significant.
This has been looked at
in females age 18 to 29,
males and females age 18 to 29,
people age 30.
These are separate studies
where I'm listing off the different ages,
ages 30 to 64.
It turns out that you can see
pretty substantial
increases in serum cortisol
and decreases in
testosterone and estrogen.
So that was complete news to me.
Also increases in blood pressure
that are pretty substantial.
That's going to be downstream of cortisol,
increasing cortisol
increase blood pressure
in order to engage the stress response
as part of the stress response.
Increased hormones of other kinds
that are associated with stress.
Who knew?
I didn't know maybe you knew,
previously if you did forgive me
but licorice and some of the
compounds in black licorice
can actually increase stress.
Probably not the thing to be ingesting
during periods of chronic stress.
Whether or not anyone
has had positive effects
of using it to increase
cortisol and other contexts,
let me know,
but very interesting that
the chemistry of licorice
increases stress hormones,
and therefore you would probably want to,
almost certainly we want to avoid it
in conditions of chronic stress.
Also, if you're trying to
optimize testosterone and estrogen
liquorice seems like a bad idea.
I suppose one instance where
you might want to use licorice
would be if you're traveling
and you're trying to wake
up at a particular location,
because licorice has
these effects on cortisol
and cortisol is associated
with the waking phenomenon
and alertness and energy,
you could use it in that regard.
However, I would be careful to time it
so that you're not getting
two cortisol increases
throughout the day, two peaks.
So you're going to want to make sure
that you're doing all the other
things correct for jet lag
and adjusting to jet lag.
And if you want to know
what those things are,
including timing your feeding,
using temperature, using exercise,
using light to adjust
to jet lag more quickly,
please see the episode that we
did on jet lag and shift work
where I cover all those
protocols in detail.
The other compound that I
think deserves attention
is apigenin.
A P I G E N I N, apigenin.
which is what's found in chamomile.
Apigenin I've talked about previously.
It has various effects one
is it is a mild anti-estrogen
that's been shown in various studies,
and it does have a bit
of an anxiolytic effect
of reducing anxiety.
I take it before bedtime, 50 milligrams.
Again, you have to decide
or figure out if that's
safe for you or not.
I'm not suggesting you take it.
The major source of action is
to calm the nervous system.
And it does that primarily
by adjusting things like
GABA and chloride channels
but it also has a mild
effect in reducing cortisol.
So Ashwagandha and Apigenin together,
I would consider the most potent
commercial compounds
that are in supplement
non-prescription form that one could use
if they were interested in
reducing chronic stress,
especially late in the day
by way of reducing
cortisol late in the day.
So you're probably getting
the impression that
cortisol and epinephrine are
a bit of a double-edged sword.
You want them elevated, but
not for too long or too much.
You don't want them up for
days and days, and days,
but you do want to have a practice
in order to increase
them in the short term.
So we should talk about protocols
that can set a foundation
of cortisol and epinephrine
that is headed towards optimal.
Optimization is always
going to be a series
of regular practices
that you do every day.
So sleeping at certain times,
light at specific times,
food at specific times.
Certain foods, et cetera,
and that's highly individual,
but there are some universals
and we've covered a number of
those in the discussion today.
Meal timing, meal schedules
has a profound effect
on energy levels.
And as I mentioned before
the energy I'm referring
to is not glucose energy.
It's not burning carbs
while running or ketones.
What I'm talking about is neural energy,
epinephrine and cortisol.
Fasting and timing one's eating
are two sides of the same coin.
So even if you're on a kind
of standard three meal a day
with a couple of snacks in between diet
or nutrition regimen,
you are fasting whenever you're asleep,
or you're not ingesting any calories.
So unless you're hooked
up to an IV of glucose
you are fasting while you're sleeping.
There are several
different kinds of fasting
that can relate to
epinephrine and cortisol.
I will do an entire episode
on optimizing food intake
for performance in the sports context.
That's coming up but in the meantime,
I'd like to just talk about
fasting as a source of epinephrine.
Anytime when our blood glucose is low
cortisol and epinephrine
are going to go up.
If we fast for too long, that is stress.
There's no way around that.
Now that doesn't mean it doesn't have
other beneficial effects.
Running a marathon is stress,
but it can also have positive
effects if that's your thing.
So stress has been demonized as a term,
but we want to think about
stress mechanistically,
as epinephrine and cortisol.
And then if we do that
we can think about how
to regulate its timing.
So anytime we haven't eaten
for four to six hours,
levels of epinephrine and cortisol
are going to go up pretty substantially.
There's an exception to that,
which is if you are used to eating
on the clock every two hours or every hour
being half hour late,
or being even 10 minutes
late on that schedule
will induce stress.
Most of that psychological stress,
but also the release
of things like ghrelin
that are going to make you hungry,
'cause they're on that eating clock.
So one thing that many
people do to great benefit
is they follow a so-called
circadian eating schedule.
They eat only when the sun is up,
they stop when the sun is down.
More or less.
The another way to think about this
is they stop eating a
couple hours before sleep
and they eat more or less upon waking
assuming that they're waking up
more or less around the
time of the sunrises,
maybe plus or minus two hours.
Okay. So sort of typical schedule.
Now, let's say you decide to do what I do,
which is I skip breakfast.
I drink water,
I delay my caffeine for
90 minutes to two hours,
and then I drink my caffeine.
And then my first meal is
typically around lunchtime,
11:30 or 12:00.
And yes, occasionally I throw back
some almonds or walnuts or
something earlier in the day.
I do do that from time to time
if I get hungry enough,
or if I just happen to see them.
I'm kind of a drive by eater,
if I see blueberries or nuts or something
I'm just going to pick them
up and put them in my mouth.
I try not do that off
other people's plates,
but I just have that habit of
doing that from time to time.
But typically I don't
eat until about noon.
So I've got a cortisol increase
I've got my sunlight in the morning.
So I'm getting a big pulse
and energy early in the day.
And yes, there's a
little bit of agitation,
I am hungry sometimes early
in the day sometimes no,
but my ghrelin system is used to
kicking in right around noon.
At the point where I eat
as long as I don't eat carbohydrate
in my case, I know that
my epinephrine levels
are going to stay pretty high.
So for me, it's usually meat and salad,
or something of that
sort, or fish and salad.
although I don't
particularly like eating fish
because of the taste,
but I'm assuming low carb or ketones ish
throughout the day.
So I'm probably in a
slightly elevated state
of epinephrine and cortisol
throughout the day.
Some of you are fasting even longer.
You're pushing out till
4:00 PM or 8:00 PM,
or maybe you're even
fasting around the clock.
Anytime you're fasting
you're increasing epinephrine
and cortisol release.
You can do all the meditation in the world
to keep your mind calm,
but you are closer to that edge of stress.
And you're closer to
that edge of peak stress.
So that's something that's
just important to understand
the description about
comfort foods and cortisol
was one of kind of an extreme case
where cortisol systems
kick over to a positive feedback loop.
But we all eat to suppress
cortisol and epinephrine.
When we're hungry cortisol and epinephrine
create an agitation so we go seek food.
When we ingest food
typically if it includes carbohydrate,
there's a blunting of cortisol.
There's a blunting of
epinephrine in the bloodstream.
If you've ever had too
much coffee to drink
and you go and have a
couple of pieces of bread,
you will feel the...
You might describe it as the caffeine
getting soaked up out of your system,
but what you're doing is
you're elevating blood glucose
which is more or less saturating
the effect of caffeine in your system.
Not completely, but it's
going to have that effect.
If you're very stressed and
you sit down to eat something
it will calm you down.
Yes. Because some of the blood
that goes to your stomach
but more so because of these effects
in blunting cortisol and epinephrine.
So the important point here is that
if you want to be alert
you can do that by way of not eating.
Of course, please ingest fluids.
I know some people water fast out there.
I am yet to see good
science on water fasting
and why that can stimulate stem cells,
or people love the idea of
after the Nobel prize
was given for autophagy
and this idea that our
cells clean up debris
in senescent cells, yes, that's true.
But the idea that water fasting
is going to promote that,
I find rather amusing.
Please send me the data
if you know of some great
study in a decent journal,
but pretty much this is
something I hear about.
I don't think water
fasting is a good idea,
nor should you be drinking so much water
that you kill yourself.
You can actually drink
enough water that you die.
So I think ingesting
water in healthy amounts
is a good thing, stay hydrated.
But if you want to be alert stay hydrated,
caffeine may or may
not be in your regimen,
but fasting will make sure that
your levels of energy are up
and you will be primed very well for doing
a protocol of the sort
that we talked about
earlier in this episode.
Of breathing, or cold
exposure, or exercise
to get that increase in
the immune system function.
And if you do that after learning
after trying to learn something,
it will increase learning
for that particular set of information,
whether or not it's motor, or language,
or whatever it happens to be.
Mathematics, programming.
So fasting is a tool for many reasons,
it can increase growth hormone, et cetera.
But today I'm talking
about fasting as a tool
to bias your system toward more
epinephrine adrenaline release
and toward more cortisol release
but still low enough that
it's not chronic stress,
that it's not causing
negative health effects.
But please know that if
life is very, very stressful
if you're experiencing lots of stressors
and you're chronically fasting,
you are positioning yourself
toward a greater likelihood
of being chronically stressed
in the ways that are negative.
Negative effects on the
reproductive access,
lower testosterone and estrogen.
Negative effects on you're
hair will turn gray,
there's reasons for that,
Your sleep will suffer.
Your immune system will suffer.
So I think while it's nuanced
our discussion today about
epinephrine and cortisol
increasing energy and immunity
are designed to help you
understand when you should
be doing certain things.
When you should throttle back.
When you might want to kick
up your adrenaline a bit,
if you're suffering from low energy
because you're just kind of feeling down
and a little bit under activated,
well then the practices of ice baths
and intense breathing, et cetera,
could be very beneficial so might fasting.
But if you're feeling
exhausted and burnt out
sort of drained and stressed
well then fasting or doing
a lot of cold exposure,
or doing a lot of intense exercise
is driving you further and
further into chronic stress.
So because I don't have a
saliva test or a blood test,
or God forbid an earwax test
to measure your cortisol
as we're engaging in
this discussion together,
you have to gauge for yourself
whether or not you are in
a state of under activated
and need more epinephrine and cortisol,
or whether or not you are over activated,
in terms of cortisol and epinephrine.
And you need ways to
buffer those ashwagandha,
Maybe it should be a warm
mellow bath not an ice bath.
So one has to learn how
to regulate these hormones
with behavior, with nutrition,
perhaps with supplementation.
And then of course there
are prescription drugs,
and I always leave these to the end
because A, I'm not a medical doctor
I'm not prescribing anything.
I'm a professor,
I'm professing a number of things
that you can decide for
yourselves what to do with or not.
But of course there are prescription drugs
that can increase cortisol
or decrease cortisol
in cases like Cushing's syndrome,
which if you have that diagnosed,
you should talk to a physician.
You should talk ideally
to a endocrinologist
but to a physician of some sort,
board certified physician.
There are drugs that can
be used to treat injury
like corticosteroids,
that you can inject to
reduce inflammation injury,
but they are cortisol.
So they're going to bias
you towards more stress
in other domains.
Remember cortisol can cross
the blood brain barrier
so you're going to be more
prone to psychological stress.
I also want to mention again,
that I think there's great
benefit to having a practice
that perhaps you do every other day,
but if you can't maybe every
third day or every other day
of deliberately increasing
your adrenaline in your body
while learning to stay calm in the mind,
so that you learn to separate
the brain body experience.
You know, we hear so much
about how beneficial it is
to unify the brain and body,
that we're all out of touch
with our brain and bodies.
I particularly dislike claims like that
or statements like that
because there's great
power as we learned today
in having your body activated
by some sort of stimulus,
cold water or even psychological stress,
but learning to stay calm in your mind.
I should just remind you that most of the
negative effects on your life
and on the lives of others
are due to people perhaps you I hope not
being unable to regulate their mind
when they have high levels
of adrenaline in their body,
either 'cause they read
something on a text
or a comment section,
of course that never happens to me,
but it may happen to you.
Of course it happens to me,
but the idea is to stay calm in your mind
so that then you can
regulate your action, right?
And so I think that
there are these practices
that one can develop over time
that are really straight
forward and zero costs, right?
You could find any number of ways
to increase your adrenaline and stay calm.
And we tend to focus
on things like exercise
as the way that we get our energy up.
But today, again I'm talking about
deliberately increasing adrenaline
while staying calm mentally,
because that has great utility
when the adrenaline hits
through unwanted events,
through things that we didn't seek out.
So the ability to regulate
adrenaline cortisol
is about inducing them deliberately
when you want to push back on infection,
potential infection from bacteria viruses.
It's about pulling back on
adrenaline and cortisol,
maybe through the use of supplementation
but certainly through proper
use of light and sleep
and mental tools that
we talked about as well
when they are chronically elevated.
It's about training your system,
not just to be unified at brain and body,
which sounds great until you're stressed
and then that's terrible.
It's really about having
a deliberate dissociation
between the adrenaline
response from the adrenals
and the adrenaline response
from the brainstem.
So once again, we've
covered a ton of material.
I hope right now, you're thinking,
okay, am I in state of chronic stress?
Am I under activated?
Or could I afford to increase my levels
of adrenaline cortisol to
improve my relationship
to my immune system and
to energy, neural energy.
If you like the information
that you heard today
and you want to remember it,
well, then at the end of this episode,
perhaps you go do something
to increase your level of adrenaline.
And now you know what
some of those things are,
because it will help you
retain the information,
or you could apply that to anything else
that you learn or experience of course.
And I hope that you'll think about
some of the ways in which
cortisol and adrenaline
are not good or bad, that
stresses in good or bad
but short-term stress is healthy.
Alertness and energy is healthy
even if it puts you at
the edge of agitation,
that's an opportunity
to learn how to control
these hormones better.
And I hope that if you're
in a state of chronic stress
that you'll do things
to start tamping down some of that stress
and that you realize
that your nervous system
and your hormone system are linked,
but they're linked in
ways that you can control,
that we don't have to be
slaves to our hormones.
And certainly not the
hormones that cause us stress,
we can learn to control those
both to the benefit of our body
and benefit of mind.
If you're learning from this podcast
and you like the information
that you're learning,
please subscribe on YouTube,
that really helps us,
and in addition if you could
hit the notification button,
that will let you know when
we release new episodes.
Now we release them every Monday morning
but in addition to that
we are starting to really
short clips now and again
as well as some special content.
So hit the subscribe button please
and hit the notifications button.
If you haven't already subscribed
on Apple and or Spotify,
please do that.
You can certainly subscribe
to all three if you like,
and on Apple you can give
us a five-star review
as well as leave us a review.
On YouTube is the place to
leave us comments and feedback
as well as suggestions
for future episodes.
We do read all the comments
and I know many of you
are anxiously awaiting
particular topics and episodes,
and we will eventually get to them all,
I'm not going anywhere.
And we do want to be
thorough about every topic.
Today we rounded out the
discussion about hormones.
We aren't going to continue
with that topic any longer,
we are moving to a new topic segment
for an entire month or so.
If you know of other people
that you think could benefit
from the information on this podcast,
or that you think would
enjoy listening to it
please forward it along to them,
we'd really appreciate that.
Another great way to support us
is to check out our sponsors
that we mentioned at the
beginning of the podcast.
We also have a Patreon,
it's patreon.com/andrewhuberman,
there you can support the podcast
at any level that you like.
I should mention that I will
be answering some questions
that come up frequently in
the comment section on YouTube
in Instagram Lives every once in a while.
I am on Twitter @hubermanlab.
I'm on Instagram, also @hubermanlab.
And on Instagram from
time to time coming up
I'm going to be discussing
answers to your common questions
in these Instagram Lives
and I will make sure
that they're recorded.
So you can check those out,
please follow our Instagram.
If you are not already doing that
and check out our Twitter
if you're on Twitter.
I covered a lot of different
types of tools today,
behavioral tools, et cetera.
But I did mention supplements.
For those of you that are
interested in supplements
we've partnered with Thorne, T H O R N E,
because we believe them
to have the highest levels
of stringency and quality
in terms of supplement production,
in terms of amounts of supplements
in their different
formulations, et cetera.
If you want to check out
the supplements that I take
and you want to get a
discount on Thorne supplements
you can go to thorne.com/u/huberman
and you can get 20% off
any of the supplements that I take,
or any of the supplements that
Thorne sells for that matter.
That's thorne.com/u/huberman
to get 20% off anything that Thorne makes.
Thank you for joining me
for what I hope was an
informative discussion
and an actionable discussion
about how to increase
energy and the immune system
by way of cortisol and
adrenaline epinephrine.
I really appreciate your
willingness to learn new topics
as well as to embrace
and think about new tools
and whether or not they're right for you.
And as always, thank you for
your interested in science.
[upbeat music]